十　印度绅士

然而，对埃芒加德和洛蒂来说，到阁楼去拜访自己敬慕的萨拉是件冒险的事儿。她俩搞不清萨拉什么时候会回到那儿，更摸不准艾米丽亚小姐什么时候会在学生睡后去巡视卧室。她俩难得去阁楼看望萨拉一次，因而萨拉过的是奇特而孤单的日子。比起在阁楼上，她在楼下的日子更孤单，没有谁与她说说话。每次被人差遣去干杂差，她就成了个可怜巴巴的小姑娘，挎着篮子或挟着包包，走在街上；遇到刮风的天气她还要拼命地捂紧帽子；遇到下雨天，雨水从鞋子里渗进来；看见行人匆匆擦身而过，她感到越发孤单。想当年，自己被人尊为“萨拉公主”的日子，在玛丽埃塔陪伴、伺候下，坐着四轮马车，或走在大街上，身穿丽装华服，脸上熠熠生辉，喜气洋洋，光彩照人，始终引得路人观望。这样一名幸福而受人精心呵护的漂亮小姑娘能不引人注目吗？而穿得破破烂烂、可怜巴巴的孩子街上多的是，也不好看，哪有人会转过身来搭理她，对她微笑呢？如今再也没人注意萨拉了。当她匆匆从人来人往的人行道上经过时，谁也不理会她了。她开始迅速地长个儿，但能穿的只有剩下的普普通通几件旧衣服。她知道这样的打扮看起来一定会很古怪。那些值钱的衣服已被处理掉了，那些剩下的她得一直穿下去，能穿多久就穿多久。有时候，路过商店有镜子的橱窗时，看到自己现在的模样，她忍不住笑出声来，有时候羞红了脸，咬紧嘴唇，扭头就走。

傍晚时，她路过窗户里亮着灯光的房子，这时候，她都会忍不住偷偷地往里瞟上几眼。在她的想象中，人们坐在温暖的壁炉前或围着饭桌，这时她觉得自己也快乐起来了。在百叶窗尚未拉上之前，能看看房里的情景对她也是一件乐事。明卿小姐居住的广场旁边住了几户人家，萨拉以自己独特的方式已摸清他们的一些情况。其中一家，她最喜欢，被她称为“大家庭”。之所以称“大家庭”倒不是这一家人的个子长得高——他们其实多数是小孩子——而是因为他们的家庭成员多。“大家庭”里的小孩子就有八个，他们的母亲身体壮实，长着一张红润的脸；父亲身体也很壮实，也长着一张红润的脸；他们的祖母身体也很壮实，也有红润的脸。他们家里的佣人也非常多。八个孩子时常由大人们领着散步，要么坐在童车上，由保姆舒舒服服地推着，要么跟妈妈坐着马车出游。傍晚，他们飞奔到门口去迎接爸爸，亲吻他，围着他又蹦又跳，有时候扯下爸爸的大衣，想在口袋里翻点什么礼物出来，要么挤在儿童室的窗口朝外张望，你推我搡，有说有笑——反正他们日子过得快快活活的，一派大家庭其乐融融的氛围。萨拉喜欢他们，还给他们取了书中用过的名字——都是些很浪漫的名字。有时候萨拉不称他们为“大家庭”，就换另一种说法，管他们叫蒙特莫伦西一家。她管那个头戴花边婴儿帽的胖娃娃叫埃塞尔伯塔·比彻姆·蒙特莫伦西，管稍大的叫维奥莱特·乔莫德·蒙特莫伦西，那个刚学会用两条圆滚滚的小腿蹒跚学步的小男孩叫西德尼·塞西尔·维维安·蒙特莫伦西。接下来，依次为利莲·伊万杰琳·莫德·马里恩、罗莎琳德·格拉迪斯、盖伊·克拉伦斯、维罗尼加·尤斯塔西亚和克劳德·哈罗德·赫克托。

一天傍晚，发生了一件有趣的事。不过，从某种意义上说这也许算不得是件十分有趣的事。

那天，蒙特莫伦西家几个孩子显然要去参加一个儿童聚会。萨拉刚要经过他们家门口时，几个小家伙正穿过人行道要登上正在等候他们的马车。维罗尼加·尤斯塔西亚和罗莎琳德·格拉迪斯身着饰有花边的连衣裙，系着漂亮的腰带，刚钻进马车。紧随其后的是五岁的盖伊·克拉伦斯。他长得非常可爱，脸蛋像玫瑰花一般红润，眼睛湛蓝湛蓝的，霎时间，萨拉看得完全忘了自己是个手中拎着篮子、身上穿着破衣烂衫的可怜小姑娘——事实上她彻底忘了形，只想多看他一会儿。于是，她停下脚步看了起来。

那正是圣诞节期间，“大家庭”的孩子们曾听人讲过许多穷孩子的故事，没有爹娘往他们的袜子里塞礼物，不带他们去看圣诞演出的童话剧——他们缺衣少食，饥寒交迫。故事里说，心地善良的人——有些小孩子也有这样的热心肠——总会去探望这些可怜的穷孩子，送给他们钱或许许多多的礼物，带他们回家一起参加热热闹闹的圣诞聚会。那天下午，盖伊·克拉伦斯刚读过这样的故事，感动得快要掉泪了，于是他心里出现一个强烈的愿望，很想找到这么一个穷孩子，把自己的六便士硬币送给她，让她过上好日子。他觉得整整六便士是个不少的数目，完全可以让她过上富足的日子了。他从家门口穿过人行道一直来到马车门，车门前铺着一条红地毯，他从红地毯走过时，在他短短的水兵式裤子的裤兜里就放着六便士硬币。当罗莎琳德·格拉迪斯钻进车厢，在座位上坐下来，美美地享受坐垫的一弹一跳，而盖伊·克拉伦斯看到萨拉站在湿漉漉的人行道上，一身的破衣烂衫，胳膊上挽了个旧篮子，正出神地看着他。

他认为这小姑娘流露出饥饿的眼神，说不定她很久没有吃过东西了。他却不知道那是因为她渴望他家庭的温馨，以及他那张因悉心照料而显得红润的脸所焕发出的幸福神采。萨拉多么想把他搂到怀里亲吻。盖伊·克拉伦斯却不知道她的这些想法，他只看到一个长着大眼睛的小姑娘，脸是那么瘦削，两腿是那么纤细，身上的衣服是那么破烂，手里还提着一只普普通通的篮子。盖伊·克拉伦斯把手伸进口袋，把六便士硬币掏出来，满怀善意走到她的身边。

“可怜的小姑娘，拿着吧。”他说，“这里有六便士，送给你。”

萨拉吃了一惊，但马上就明白这是怎么回事了。想当年自己阔绰时，从四轮马车上下来，人行道上站着的穷孩子也是这样望着自己，现在她跟他们一模一样了。她也经常施舍那些人。想到这里，她的脸一会儿红一会儿白，一时间只觉得自己不该接受这枚数目虽小却很珍贵的六便士硬币。

“啊，不！”她说，“哦！不，谢谢你。可我真的不能要！”

她说话的口气与街头上一般的穷孩子完全不同，她的举止看起来像个很有教养的孩子。维罗尼加·尤斯塔西亚（其实她的真名是珍妮特）和罗莎琳德·格拉迪斯（她的真名为诺拉）便探身车外，听听到底是怎么回事。

可是盖伊·克拉伦斯出于一片好心，他说什么也不会就此罢休，硬是把硬币塞到了萨拉的手里。

“不行，这钱你得拿着！”他语气坚决，“拿它买些吃的。这可是整整六便士哩！”

他的表情非常真诚和善良，要是萨拉仍然固执己见，真不知道让他有多伤心失望。萨拉不忍心再拒绝他了。要是再表现得那么骄傲，对人可就太残酷无情了。说实在的，她收下的不单是钱，装进口袋的是自己的尊严。这里必须要提一句：这时她的脸颊红了起来。

“谢谢你，”她说，“你是个心肠极好极好的小孩子。”当他高高兴兴地钻进马车，她走开去，尽量想笑出来，但只觉得心头堵得慌，眼睛里噙满了泪水。此前她觉得自己古怪，衣衫褴褛，怎么也没有想到在人家眼里自己已成了叫花子了。

“大家庭”的马车走了，车中的孩子们高兴得有说有笑。

“我说，唐纳德（这是盖伊·克拉伦斯的真名），”珍妮特大声提醒道，“干吗把你那六便士给那个小姑娘？我敢肯定她不是叫花子。”

“她说话不像！”诺拉大声道，“脸上的表情也不像叫花子的表情！”

“再说她也没有主动向你讨要，”珍妮特说，“我担心你让她生气了。要知道，人家穷是穷，可不是叫花子，你硬要把他们当成是叫花子，他们一准会生你的气。”

“她没有生气，”唐纳德说，他有点儿沮丧，但还是觉得自己没错，“她冲我笑了，夸我是个心肠极好极好的小孩哩。我本来就是！”唐纳德的口气还是很坚决，“要知道，我全部的钱就那六便士。”

珍妮特和诺拉交换了眼色。

“叫花子是说不出那样的话的，”珍妮特坚持己见，“要是她是叫花子，她只能对你说：‘谢谢你，好心的小少爷——谢谢你，少爷。’说不定她还会行个屈膝礼呢。”

他们的这番议论，萨拉自然是不知情的。但是从那以后，“大家庭”的孩子们对她深深关注起来，同样萨拉也对他们深感兴趣。每次萨拉经过他们的窗下，儿童室的窗口总会探出几个小脑袋。当他们在炉边围坐下来，也时常谈起萨拉。

“她是寄宿学校里的女仆，”珍妮特说，“我相信她没有家，我相信她是孤儿。尽管她穿得破破烂烂，可不是叫花子。”

此后他们都称呼她为“不是叫花子的姑娘”。这自然是个很长的名字，那几个年纪最小的孩子急急忙忙说起来就显得非常可笑。

萨拉在那个六便士的硬币上钻了个孔，用—条旧的细缎带穿起来，挂到了脖子上。她对“大家庭”越来越有好感——事实上，她对自己喜欢的一切的爱心也与日俱增。她更喜欢贝基了。每星期两个早晨到教室里给年龄较小的孩子们上法语课，成了她最盼望的事情。小学生们喜爱她，都争先恐后地挤到她面前，抢着与她握手。孩子们争相偎依在她的身边，充实了她渴望的心。她站在阁楼的桌子上和麻雀交朋友，把脑袋和肩膀探出窗外，学着麻雀发出叽叽喳喳的叫声，很快就可以听到一阵扑打翅膀和叽叽喳喳的回应，接着，就会飞来一大群肮里肮脏的城里小鸟，落在瓦片上，与萨拉对话，享用萨拉撒出去的面包屑。萨拉和梅基塞代克的关系很好，有时候，它甚至带上自己的太太—起来看望萨拉，偶尔，也会带上一两个孩子。她时常与它说话，不知怎的，那老鼠好像能听懂她说的话。

萨拉对爱米丽产生了一种奇怪的感觉。你看爱米丽总是坐在那儿，看着周围的一切。特别是萨拉孤单的时候，这种感觉更加强烈。萨拉乐于相信，或假装相信爱米丽会理解她，同情她。她不愿承认，她唯一的伴侣居然毫无感觉，对一切充耳不闻。有时候，她把爱米丽放在椅子上，自己在那红色的旧矮凳上面对着它坐下来，凝视着它，想象着有关爱米丽的故事，想着，想着，眼睛睁得大大的，流露出类似恐惧的神色——特别是在夜里，万籁俱寂的时刻。这时候，阁楼上能听到的，只有墙壁里梅基塞代克一家时而发出的奔跑声和吱吱声。在萨拉的想象中，爱米丽是—个好心肠的女巫，能保护她。有时候，她一直盯着爱米丽，她的幻想达到了高潮，这时，她就会向爱米丽提问，她觉得爱米丽几乎就要答复她的问题了。可是爱米丽还是没有开口。

“不过，要说回答，”萨拉自我安慰起来，“我也经常不回答别人。能不回答的我也尽量不回答。当别人侮辱你的时候，对付他们的最好办法就是一声不吭——眼睛盯着，只管想自己的事。我也这么对待明卿小姐，每次都会气得她脸色发白。艾米丽亚小姐显得很害怕，其他的女孩子也是这样。面对人家的挑衅，你能做到不动声色，他们就会觉得你比他们强，因为你能压住自己的怒火，可他们不能，他们只能说些蠢话，事后想起来悔恨莫及。大发雷霆算是厉害了吧，可要是能压得住不发火，那才厉害呢。给你的敌人来个不理不睬那是对付他们最好的办法。我有时候就做不到。爱米丽可能做得比我好，甚至连朋友的问话也不回答，有什么全藏在心里不说出来。”

她竭力搬出这些道理来自我安慰，却发现其实这是一件很难做到的事。一天到晚，她总是被差来遣去，干着累活，不管刮风下雨，也不管天寒地冻，出了远差，回来时浑身湿透，又累又饿，却又有差事需要出门，没有人愿意想到她只是个小姑娘，瘦小的双腿已经疲惫不堪，羸弱的身子已经被冻得冰凉，可得到的报酬只是粗暴的话语和冷酷、轻蔑的目光。这时候厨娘粗俗蛮横，明卿小姐正好心情极端恶劣，女孩子们私下里还要不断嘲笑她穿得破破烂烂，而爱米丽直挺挺地端坐在自己的旧椅子上，对她干瞪眼——这种时候她那颗受伤却高傲而又孤寂的心，怎么能够单依靠幻想来安慰呢？

一天深夜，萨拉又冷又饿地回到阁楼上。她那幼小的胸膛里燃烧着怒火，看到爱米丽的目光是那样的空洞，锯末填充的胳膊和腿没有一丝生机，面对这情景她再也按捺不住了。这里除了爱米丽别无其他的人——这世界空无一人。她坐了下来。

“我真的活不了多久了。”开始时她说了这么一句话。

爱米丽只是对她干瞪眼。

“我受不了啦，”可怜的孩子浑身哆嗦，说道，“我知道快要死了。我好冷呀，浑身湿透。我饿得快没命了。天知道我今天去了多少地方，那些人一天到晚只知道骂我。我没能买回厨娘打发我去买的最后一件东西，他们便不让我吃饭。一些人嘲笑我，因为我的鞋子太破了，陷进烂泥里，人滑倒了。我脏得像个泥猴子。他们见了反而哈哈大笑。你听到我说的话了吗？”

不知道怎么回事，这一次她看着那双圆睁的玻璃眼睛和那充满自得的脸，一股撕心裂肺的怒火突然在心底里燃烧起来。她恶狠狠地抬手将爱米丽从椅子上打落下来，她哭了——萨拉从没这样放声哭泣过。

“你什么也不是，只是个洋娃娃！”她哭喊道，“什么也不是，只是个洋娃娃——洋娃娃——洋娃娃！你什么也不在乎。你一肚子只是木屑。你没心没肺，冷酷无情。你只是个洋娃娃！”

爱米丽躺在地板上，不雅观地曲起膝盖，弯在头上，鼻尖上又有一处摔扁了，但她还是显得心平气和，不失尊严。萨拉把脸埋进双臂里。墙洞里的老鼠厮打起来，吱吱尖叫。梅基塞代克正追逐家庭的某个成员。

萨拉哭得没有先前那么厉害了。她一向可不是这样绝望，她为自己的表现感到吃惊。过了—会儿，她扬起脸看着爱米丽，爱米丽也似乎在偷偷地斜着眼打量她，不知怎的，那双玻璃眼中居然流露出了同情。萨拉弯腰把她抱起来。她感到有些后悔，脸上露出一丝自嘲的微笑来。

“你天生就是洋娃娃，做不做洋娃娃由不得你自己，”她说，叹了口气，“你不像拉维尼亚和杰西，她俩是自己要做没感情的人。我们天生就不一样。你满肚子是锯末，做到现在这份儿上已尽力了。”萨拉亲了亲她，把她的衣服理理整齐，重新放回椅子。

她非常希望隔壁那栋空房子有人住。因为那家的阁楼窗子离她的很近。假如有一天看到那扇方窗框里探出一个脑袋、一对肩膀来，那多好呀！

“要是真的探出个可爱的脑袋来，”她想，“我先跟她打招呼：‘早晨好！’接下来什么事都可能发生。不过，当然啰，除了下等佣人还有谁会睡在那儿？”

一天早晨，萨拉先后去了杂货店、副食店和面包铺买了东西，经过广场拐角处时，欣喜地发现，自己离开这么长的一段时间里，有—辆满载家具的大车停在隔壁那栋房子前，前门敞开着，几个男子正忙着搬运沉重的箱包和家具。

“这里有人来住了！”她说，“真的有人来住了！啊，但愿阁楼窗口探出一个可爱的脑袋来！”

人行道上围着一堆闲人看着搬家，萨拉也想停下来看看热闹。她心想，如果能看到一些家具，就可以看出家具的主人是个怎样的人。

“明卿小姐家的桌椅板凳就跟她本人一模一样，”她想，“记得第一次看到她时我就是这么想的，虽然那时候我还是个小孩子。后来我把自己的想法对爸爸说了，爸爸听了直冲我笑，说我说得没错。我相信‘大家庭’一定有柔软、厚实、舒服的安乐椅和沙发，我看到他们的红花壁纸实在像他们本人，温馨、快乐、亲切和幸福。”

那天稍晚一些时候，她又被打发去蔬菜店买芹菜，当她从地下室阶梯走上平台时，她的心跳猛地加快起来，因为她发现了几件似曾相识的东西。几件从车上卸下来的家具摆在人行道上。其中就有一张漂亮的、精心镶拼起来的柚木桌子、几把椅子以及一架屏风，上面绷着华丽的东方刺绣品，这些东西让她油然而生思乡之情。在印度，她曾见过许多类似的东西。明卿小姐从她那儿拿走的东西中有一件就是雕花的柚木书桌，那是父亲送给她的。

“这些东西可真好看，”她说，“这样的家具只有高尚的人家才有。所有的东西看上去好华丽。想来这准是有钱人家了。”

装家具的大车忙了一整天，来了一车，卸下东西，走了，腾出地方让别的车子来。有几次恰好让萨拉碰上了，看到搬来的东西。可不是，她猜得没错：新搬来的人家准非常非常有钱。家具全都漂漂亮亮，十分华贵，很多还是东方式的。大车上搬下来的地毯、壁毯和饰物美极了，还有许许多多的图画。单书籍就足够办个图书馆了。还有一尊精致的佛像，装在华丽的神龛里。

“他们一准在印度待过，”萨拉想，“他们喜欢印度的东西，惯用这些东西。我真高兴。我觉得他们像朋友似的，即使没人从阁楼的天窗探出头来。”

给厨娘取晚上的牛奶时（样样活儿都得差她去干），她亲眼看见了一件事，这就使情况变得更加让她动心了。那位在“大家庭”里做父亲的男子，模样儿英俊，面色红润，一本正经地穿过广场，快步登上隔壁房子的台阶，那模样活像这里就是他的家，看来往后他要多次在这些台阶上上下下了。他在屋内待了好一会儿，后来几次出来指挥那些搬运工，就好像他有权这样做似的。看得出来，他与新来的这家人关系非常密切，在代他们办事。

“要是新来的人家有孩子，”萨拉寻思道，“那‘大家庭’的孩子一定会前来和他们—起玩，那样他们说不准为了好玩会到阁楼上去的。”

夜里，贝基干完了一天的活，进来看望自己的难友，带来一些消息。

“小姐，隔壁新搬来一位印度绅士，”她说，“他的皮肤黑不黑我不知情，可他准是印度人。他非常有钱，可是个病人。‘大家庭’的那位先生是他的律师。印度先生遇到了一大堆麻烦事儿，所以害上了病，情绪坏透了。他爱信那些个菩萨哩，小姐。他是个异教徒，见到木头和石头的菩萨都要下跪。我就见到他家搬进一尊菩萨，供他拜的。得送他一本布道的小册子。花—个便士就可买到的那种。”

萨拉听了，轻轻一笑。

“我不相信他会崇拜那个偶像，”她说，“有的人藏着偶像是为了摆着好看。比如说我爸爸，他就有一尊漂亮的佛像，可是他就不拜。”

贝基的心眼儿就是发死，认定了这个新邻居是个“异教徒”。这也不错，听起来至少要比一位带着祈祷书去教堂的普普通通先生更富有传奇色彩。那天夜里她俩坐着，聊了很久有关那位先生的事儿：新邻居是个怎么样的人？要是他有妻子，那么妻子长得怎么样？要是有孩子，那这些孩子又怎么样？萨拉看出，贝基巴不得这些孩子的皮肤全是黑的，头上缠着头巾，最重要的是——同他们的父母一样——全都是些“异教徒”。

“我压根没跟‘异教徒’做过邻居，小姐，”她说，“我倒想看看他们是怎么过日子的。”

几个星期后，她的好奇心才得到了满足。原来新邻居还没有妻子，也没有孩子。他是个单身汉，光棍一条。显而易见，他的身体很不好，情绪也很糟。

有一天，驶来一辆马车，在那幢屋前停了下来。佣人从驾驶座上下来，打开车门，首先下车的是“大家庭”的父亲。紧随其后的，是—名穿制服的护士。此时从大门台阶上下来两名男佣人，他们是来伺候房子的主人的。当主人被扶下了车，只见那是一个形容憔悴、神情沮丧的男子，瘦得皮包骨头，身上裹着一件毛皮大衣。他被扶上台阶，“大家庭”的家长走在一旁，显得忧心忡忡。不久之后，又一辆马车赶到了，从车上下来的是一名医生，他进入房屋——显然是来为房屋的主人看病的。

“隔壁住着这样一位黄皮肤的绅士，萨拉，”法语课上洛蒂悄悄说，“你认为他是中国人吗？地理书上说中国人的皮肤是黄色的。”

“不，他不是中国人，”萨拉也悄悄回答说，“他得了重病。继续做练习，洛蒂。跟我读：‘Non, monsieur.Je n’ai pas le canif de mon oncle.’”

印度绅士的故事从此开始了。

十一　拉姆·达斯

有时候，即使在广场上也能见到日落的景色，不过，见到的只能是烟囱之间和屋顶上的那部分。从厨房窗子看出去就什么也见不到了，倒是能猜到现在正是日落时分，因为这时墙上的砖短时间内显得暖烘烘的，天空也是一片粉红色或黄色，说不定有的地方的玻璃上反射出一道耀眼的光来。但是，有个地方能看见落日全部壮丽的景象，见到西方一团团云朵，是火红的或金色的，或是四周镶着夺目光华的紫色，也有片片浮云，染成了玫瑰色，宛如一群粉红色的鸽子在风中翻飞，有风时匆匆掠过蓝天。这个看到全部美景同时又能呼吸到更清新空气的地方，自然非阁楼天窗莫属了。尽管有灰迹斑斑的树木和围栏，当广场突然被迷人的光华所照耀，一切都显得灿烂辉煌，这时候萨拉便知道天空正在发生某种变化；这时候，只要可以脱身而不为人所觉察，不被叫回，萨拉就会悄悄离开厨房，爬上阁楼，登上那只旧桌子，尽可能把头和身子探出窗外。到了这时候她便深深地吸了口气，极目四望起来。这时候，她常常觉得，整片天空，整个世界都属于她。别的阁楼没有一个人在探窗眺望。那些天窗通常都是关着的。即使是支起来通风，也见不到一个人影。萨拉站立窗前，有时候抬头仰望蓝天，只觉得蓝天对她异常亲切，近在咫尺——不啻是头顶的天花板，只是呈穹形而已——有时候眼望西天，那边正发生种种奇妙的变幻：朵朵云彩或飘散，或浮游，或随时化成粉红、深红、雪白、绛紫或淡淡的鸽灰色。有时候云团幻成岛屿或群山，围绕其间的是湖泊，湖水是深绿松石色的，琥珀色的，或绿玉髓色的；有时候成了深黑的岬角延伸出去直达奇异的茫茫海洋；有时候一片片狭长的神奇陆地与另一片片神奇的陆地连在一起，有的地方你似乎可以去奔跑、攀登或稍立片刻，等着美景出现——最后，一切消融殆尽，你便飘然而去。至少，这是萨拉的感受。她立在桌上所见到的美丽景象是别的地方不可比拟的——她半个身子探出窗外——麻雀在石板瓦上、在柔和的落日中喳喳欢叫。在她看来，在这良辰美景，麻雀的叽喳声变得不那么刺耳，反而越发动听了。

那位印度绅士搬来几天后，就出现了这样的落日景象。幸运的是，下午厨房的活儿全干完了，没人差她到哪儿去，或交什么活让她去干，萨拉认为这下比平时更容易溜到阁楼去了。

她爬上桌子，张望起来。这真是个绝妙的时刻。西天团团金色浮云，光华夺目，翻翻滚滚，汹涌着要席卷整个世界。天空中闪烁着壮丽的深黄色光芒，屋顶上飞翔而过的鸟儿，在这黄光衬托下，显得影影绰绰。

“这是个辉煌壮丽的时刻，”萨拉低声喃喃道，“看得我几乎害怕起来了——担心会发生什么奇怪的事。每看到壮丽辉煌的景象我无不有这种感觉。”

猛地，她听到离自己只有几码的地方传来一个声音，不禁转过身去。这声音怪怪的。怪异的吱吱声，像是有人在低声絮语。声音从隔壁阁楼的天窗传过来。有人也像她那样来看日落了。从那天窗探出一个人的脑袋和小半个身子。可那不是小姑娘或丫环的脑袋和身子。那人身上披着白袍，脸孔黑黝黝的，眼睛闪闪发亮，头上缠着白头巾，焕发着异国风采，一看就知道是位印度人——“是个拉斯卡。”萨拉一下就看出来，脱口说道——方才她听到的吱吱声则来自那人手中抱着的小猴子。看来他非常喜欢这只猴子。猴子正偎依在他胸前吱吱叫着。

萨拉朝他看时他也朝萨拉看。这一眼给萨拉留下的第一个印象是，觉得这人那张黝黑的脸显得很忧郁，怀有浓厚的思乡之情。她完全肯定，他上楼来是看太阳的，因为在英国难得一见阳光，他太想看到阳光了。她兴致勃勃地瞥了他一眼，又隔着石板瓦朝他微微一笑。她知道，一个笑容，哪怕是陌生人的一笑，对人也是一大安慰。

萨拉这一笑显然令对方感到很高兴。他的整个表情都起了变化，他也回了她一笑，露出洁白的牙齿，亮晶晶的，像一道光，脸上那阴郁的神情随之一扫而光。萨拉友好的目光对疲惫而沮丧的人非常有感染力。

也许，为了对萨拉行额手礼，那人松开了手中的猴子。那是只十分调皮的猴子，随时都要惹些事来。也许是见了小姑娘它兴奋起来了。它突然挣脱开来，跳到石板瓦上，尖声叫着，跑了过来，跳到萨拉的肩膀上，又从肩上窜到阁楼里去。她看到这情景开心得哈哈笑了起来。她知道，猴子得马上归还主人——如果猴子的主人是拉斯卡的话——可就不知道怎么个还法。小猴子能让她抓住吗？它是不是很淘气让她抓不住呢？它是不是躲开，冲到屋顶上，跑得无影无踪？那不就完了吗？也许小猴儿是那印度绅士的，这位不幸的先生非常喜欢它。

她转身面对拉斯卡，还好自己还记得一些印度话，是她与父亲待在一起时学来的。她要让那人明白自己的意思。于是她就用对方熟悉的话说了起来。

“猴子能让我抓吗？”

一听对方说起自己熟悉的话来，那人黝黑的脸上露出又惊又喜的神色来。她觉得，自己从未见过这样的神情。事实上，那个可怜的人简直觉得他的神在显灵了，这样友善可爱的声音无异于来自天堂。萨拉立即看出，他已习惯于跟欧洲孩子相处了。只听得他连连说出大串尊敬感谢的话来。他说自己是尊贵小姐的仆人，猴子是只好猴子，不会咬人，遗憾的是，抓它不容易。它东逃西窜，快得像闪电，它不听话，可心眼儿不坏。拉姆·达斯像对自己的孩子那样了解它，有时候猴子听拉姆·达斯的话，但不总是那样。如果尊敬的小姐允许的话，拉姆·达斯可以从屋顶过来，爬进她的房间，把这只不中用的小畜生抓住。但是他担心，在萨拉看来，自己这样做是太放肆了，也许不允许他进去。

可是萨拉立即表示没意见。

“你过得来吗？”她问。

“这就过去。”他答。

“那就过来吧，”她说，“瞧它这会儿满屋子东窜西跑，像是吓坏了。”

拉姆·达斯钻出自己阁楼的窗子向她这边过来，动作又稳又轻，像是一辈子全在屋背上行走似的。他滑进了天窗，悄无声息地落到地板上，转身对着萨拉，又行了个额手礼。猴子一见他便轻声吱吱尖叫起来。拉姆·达斯赶紧采取了预防措施，把天窗关上，然后再去抓猴子，追了没多久。显然猴子是为了好玩才让他追了几分钟，很快就吱吱叫着，跳到他肩上，坐在那儿，伸出怪怪的、瘦巴巴的手臂抱住拉姆·达斯的脖子。

拉姆·达斯深深地道了谢。萨拉见这印度人的目光迅速地扫了房间一眼，他已看到房间十分简陋，但对萨拉说起话来像面对着的是位印度土邦的女儿，装作什么都没注意到似的。他抓到猴子后只逗留了一小会儿，很快就离开了。在他短暂的逗留期间，对萨拉的大度再次表示了深深的感激和谢意。他边拍着猴子边说，这小坏蛋看起来很调皮，其实并不坏，有时候还逗自己有病在身的主人高兴呢。要是自己的宠物跑掉了，丢失了，那准会让他伤心的。他说罢又行了个额手礼，便钻出天窗，健步如飞地在石板瓦上跑了起来，敏捷得不亚于刚才那猴子在石板瓦上施展出来的功夫。

那人走了后，萨拉立在阁楼中间，细细回味着那人的脸和举动，从而联想起许多事来。见了他一身印度特色的装束和对人恭恭敬敬的举止不由得勾起她对过去的记忆。想来何等的不可思议，不是吗，一小时前，她，一名听人差遣的小苦工，刚挨过厨娘的痛骂，可几年前，她仆从成群，个个都像拉姆·达斯那样对待她；她所过之处，人人都对她行额手礼，听她说话时，他们都垂着头，前额低得快要触地了，他们全都是听她使唤的奴仆佣人。想来也真不可思议，恍如梦中，全成了往事，一去不可返了。现状肯定无法改变。她知道明卿小姐想给她安排一个什么样的未来。只要她还不到当个正式教师的年龄，她只能被当作干杂活的丫头和女仆供人使唤，这不但要求她不可忘了过去学到的知识，还要她以不可思议的方式学到更多的东西。她得把更多的夜晚花在学习上，但是她知道，如果她没有取得进展，达不到要求，就要受到严厉的训斥。实际上，明卿小姐也知道，萨拉渴求知识，学习自觉，用不着教师督促。拿到书本，她就会埋头读起来，并且能牢牢记住书的内容。完全可以指望她在数年之内胜任教师工作，教大量课程。情况肯定就是这样。等她长到一定年龄，她还是和现在一样干苦活，所不同的是不在学校上上下下到处干，而在教室里。到时候只得让她穿得体面一些，但肯定只是些平平常常的衣服，不会漂亮的，看起来跟仆人差不多。前景只能是这样。就这样，萨拉一动不动站了好一会儿，把上面的事细细想了一通。

接着她的心中出现一个想法，禁不住双颊发红，两眼生辉，挺起那纤弱瘦小的身躯，抬起了头。

“任凭发生什么事，”她说，“有一点是不会变的。如果我是位穿着破衣烂衫的公主，那我是个精神上的公主。穿金戴银时当个公主固然轻而易举，但默默无闻时始终保持一颗公主的心，难道这不是更大的胜利吗？想当年玛丽·安托瓦妮特身陷牢笼时，失去了王后的尊位，身上穿的是一件黑布袍，一头白发，受尽百般羞辱，被称为‘卡佩寡妇’。但是比起当年锦衣玉食、显赫风光时，她更像王后。我最爱的是那时候的她。暴民对着她吼叫吓不倒她，即使要砍她的头时，她表现得比他们还要坚强。”

这些不是她刚想到的，之前她已经这样想过了。在众多苦难的日子里，这想法给了她很大的安慰。于是她在学校走动时，脸上挂着的表情，看起来像是这孩子生活在超越世上众人之上的精神世界里，这使得明卿小姐大惑不解，并且十分恼怒。这孩子对人家的粗言恶语似乎充耳不闻，不以为意；有时候萨拉受到严词训斥，明卿小姐发现她仍然若无其事，以一种不是孩子的目光盯着对方，仿佛伴有傲慢的微笑。她并不知道，这时候萨拉正暗自对自己说：

“你不知道你是在对公主说话，如果我高兴，只要我一挥手，就可以处死你。我饶你一命，是因为我是公主，而你是个可怜、愚蠢、恶毒、粗俗的老东西，不识时务。”

这往往给萨拉带来莫大的乐趣和快慰。虽说属于古怪的想象，她却从中得到慰藉，对她很有好处。每当她出现这种心态，任凭什么样的恶言秽语，粗鲁无礼，对她都不起作用。

“做公主的都得有教养。”她暗自说道。

因此，每逢别的奴仆们学着主子的腔调对她吆三喝五时，她始终高高昂起头，十分优雅地回答他们。面对这情景，他们无不惊得目瞪口呆。

“瞧这小家伙那样儿，一本正经的，像是位白金汉宫里的金枝玉叶。”有时候厨娘会咯咯地笑起来，说，“我没少跟她发火，我得说，可她就是不忘摆出有礼有貌的谱子，满嘴的‘对不起，师傅’‘请费心，师傅’‘请原谅，师傅’‘能打扰一下吗，师傅’，满厨房地说，全不当回事儿。”

在与拉姆·达斯和那小猴子邂逅后的第二天上午，萨拉与自己的小女生待在教室里。给她们上完课后，她把法语练习本收上来。收着，收着，不觉想到王公贵族们被派去乔装打扮、微服察访时的情形：就拿阿尔弗烈德大王来说吧，又要烤面饼，又挨牧牛人老婆的耳光。要是她知道自己打的是哪个，还不吓得半死？要是明卿小姐知道她萨拉——这个穿着露出脚趾破鞋的萨拉——果真是位公主，她该如何呢？此时萨拉所露出的目光正是明卿小姐最受不了的。这种目光她可不要看，当时恰好萨拉近在身旁，一气之下扑过去扇了萨拉几记耳光——活像牧牛人老婆扇阿尔弗烈德大王的耳光。这下把萨拉吓了一跳，她立时从梦中惊醒过来，强自定下神来，一动不动立了片刻，接着出人意料没来由地轻声笑了起来。

“你这不要脸的孩子，好放肆，有什么好笑的？”明卿小姐嚷嚷道。

萨拉花了几秒钟好不容易才忍住了笑，想起自己是位公主。她挨了耳光，脸颊火辣辣的，又红又痛。

“我在想事儿。”她答道。

“这就向我道歉。”明卿小姐说。

萨拉犹豫一会儿后，作出了回答。

“我为刚才的笑——要是有什么不礼貌的话——向你道歉，”她说，“不过想事儿没有什么好道歉的。”

“倒是想什么事儿？”明卿小姐逼问道，“你还敢想事儿？你倒是想什么事儿？”

杰西“嗤嗤”地笑了出来。她和拉维尼亚不约而同彼此用胳膊肘顶了顶对方。姑娘们都从书本上抬起头听了起来。每当明卿小姐为难萨拉时，她们都感到挺好玩的。萨拉往往说话古怪，一丁点儿也不害怕的样子。这次也一样，虽然挨了耳光，耳朵通红通红的，眼睛像星星亮闪闪的，但是没丁点儿害怕的样子。

“我在想，”她说得庄重而不失礼貌，“你还不知道自己在干了些什么。”

“你说我不知道自己干了些什么？”明卿小姐喘着大气，问道。

“是的，”萨拉说，“刚才我在想，要是你知道我是位公主，又打了我耳光，那会怎么样——我该怎么办。刚才我在想，要是我是公主，不管我说了什么又做了什么，你就不敢那样干。刚才我在想，你定会吃惊和害怕，要是你发现——”

眼前，她想象中的未来清晰地浮现出来，她说话的口气是那么的真切，连明卿小姐也受到了影响。在明卿小姐这么一个思想狭隘、缺乏想象力的人听来，一时间也觉得，萨拉直率大胆的话语背后必定藏匿着一股真正的力量。

“什么？”她大声嚷道，“你发现什么？”

“发现我原来是位公主，”萨拉说，“我无所不能——我想做的全都能办到。”

教室里的人无不把眼睛睁得溜圆溜圆的，拉维尼亚从座位上探出身子盯着看。

“回自己的房间去！”明卿小姐气急败坏地说，“立刻就走！离开教室！好好上你们的课，小姐们！”

萨拉微微鞠了一躬。

“如果我刚才笑了不礼貌，请原谅。”她说罢离开了教室，撇下明卿小姐待在那里怒气冲冲，又不好发作，女生们则把头俯在书本上，窃窃私语。

“你看见了吗？你倒是看见她那古怪的样子了吗？”杰西忍不住问道，“要是有一天她真的出人头地，我是不感到意外的。我猜她准成！”

十二　墙壁的另一边

你要是住在连片成排的房子里，猜想自己生活的房间墙壁的另一边的人都在干什么，说什么，定是件有意思的事儿。萨拉就爱这么做。她老喜欢试着想象与高等寄宿女校一墙之隔的印度绅士的事儿，乐此不疲。她知道教室紧挨着印度绅士的书房，但愿那堵墙很厚很厚，让有时下课后孩子们的喧闹声打扰不了他。

“我变得越来越喜欢他了，”她对埃芒加德说，“我不愿他受到干扰。我已经把他看成是朋友了。有的人你连话也没跟他们说过一句，就可以把他们看作是朋友。你只需好好观察他们，惦念他们，为他们难过，慢慢地他们差不多就成了你的亲人了。有时候见到大夫一天连来两次，我就为他急得不得了。”

“我的亲戚没几个，”埃芒加德若有所思地说，“我反而高兴。我那几个亲戚我不喜欢。我那两个姨妈老说：‘哎哟哟，埃芒加德！你够胖了，可不能再吃甜食了。’我那个叔叔老问我这样一类问题：‘爱德华三世哪年登的基？’‘哪个因为吃了鳗鱼撑死的？’”

萨拉不禁哈哈笑起来。

“从没跟你说过话的人决不会问你这样问题的，”她说，“我敢肯定，印度绅士即使跟你十分熟悉了，也不会问的。我挺喜欢他。”

她喜欢上“大家庭”是因为他们个个看上去显得很快活；她喜欢印度绅士是因为他看上去显得很不快活。显而易见，他害了什么重病，没有完全康复。厨房里——在那个地方，佣人们挺有能耐，通过种种神秘的途径什么事都能打听得到——对他的情况有很多说法。说他其实不是印度人，而是位在印度待过的英国人。他遭到大难，经过一次打击后一时间几乎害得他倾家荡产。他认为自己这一生算是毁了，再也没脸见人了，受到这么大的打击，又加上害了脑炎，差点把命也送了。从此他的健康彻底垮了，虽然后来时来运转，所有的财产又都回到他的手中。他的灾难和危机都是与开矿相关的。

“说是什么钻石矿哩！”厨娘说，“我存下的几个钱从不往矿山上投——尤其什么钻石矿，”说着瞟了一眼萨拉，“这些个劳什子咱们心中可有数哩。”

“他的遭遇跟我爸爸一个样，”萨拉暗自想道，“跟我爸爸一样，他也害病，还好没死。”

于是她的心跟他贴得更近了。每当夜里差她出去办事，有时候她反而感到很高兴，因为这样就趁隔壁家的窗帘没有放下，总有机会见到那暖和房间内部的情况，看到自己心中认定的朋友。每当身边没人时，她就停下来，抓住铁栏杆，祝他晚安，像是他会听到似的。

“即使你听不到，也感觉得到。”她就这样想象着，“也许善良的愿望甚至能穿过门窗和墙壁，到达人的心灵。当我站在这寒冷地方，祝愿你康复，重新快活起来，你也许因此会感到一丝温暖，得到小小的安慰，虽然不知道为什么。我真为你难过。”说到这里她的语气很真切，声音压得很低很低，“但愿你有个‘小主妇’，她能抚慰你，就像当年在我爸爸头疼时，我抚慰他一样。我甘心做你的‘小主妇’，可怜的人儿！晚安——晚安！上帝保佑你！”

说罢她走了，只觉得心里暖和一些，人也宽慰多了。她怀着非常强烈的同情心，觉得自己的这番心意必定能通过某种途径为他所接受，她觉得此时此刻，他必定孤独地坐在炉火边的安乐椅上，大概始终穿一件宽大的睡袍，始终一手托着脑门，绝望地盯着炉火。在萨拉的眼中，他这个人仍然心事重重，而且不单单是为过去的事而烦恼。

“他看起来老在想什么现在还让他痛苦的事，”她自言自语道，“他已拿回自己的钱，脑病迟早也会好起来的，所以不该这样呀。看来他还有别的烦心事。”

如果他还有什么烦心事——连仆人也不知情的烦心事——那么，她不禁想到“大家庭”的父亲——她管他叫蒙特莫伦西先生，相信他是知道的。蒙特莫伦西先生常常去探望他，蒙特莫伦西夫人和那几个小蒙特莫伦西也都去，只是不常去。印度绅士似乎对两个岁数较大的女孩特别喜欢——就是珍妮特和诺拉，也就是当时小弟弟唐纳德送给萨拉六便士硬币时，显得很担心的那两个小姑娘。事实上，这位先生对所有的孩子都怀有一颗温柔的心，尤其是小女孩。他喜欢珍妮特和诺拉，珍妮特和诺拉同样也喜欢他。她俩兴致勃勃地盼着某几个下午快快到来，到时候她俩就可以穿过广场，规规矩矩地短时间拜访他；拜访时得端庄有礼，时间不能过长，因为对方有病在身。

“他好可怜，”珍妮特说，“他说，见到我们他就高兴起来。我们尽量不吵不闹，变着法儿让他高兴起来。”

珍妮特是这几个孩子的头儿，孩子们都听她的。什么时候该小心地请印度绅士讲印度的故事得由她来定，什么时候印度绅士累了、她们得悄悄离开，并告诉拉姆·达斯过来伺候也得由她来定。她们都喜欢拉姆·达斯。要是他不是只会讲印度话，那准能讲许许多多的故事。那位印度绅士其实有名有姓，他叫卡里斯福特先生。珍妮特曾把遇见一个“不是叫花子的女孩”的事跟卡里斯福特先生讲了。他非常感兴趣，特别是听拉姆·达斯讲起屋顶猴子历险后，兴致更浓了。拉姆·达斯把那阁楼和室内凄凉的图景详详细细给他描述了一番——说到光秃秃的地板没铺地毯，墙上灰泥剥落，锈迹斑斑的空火炉，硬邦邦的狭窄的床。

“卡迈克尔，”听了这番描述后，他对“大家庭”的父亲说，“我真想知道，这广场四周有多少这样的阁楼。有多少遭殃的小使女睡的是这样的床，可我呢，躺在羽绒枕上为那些财富——大部分不属于我的财富，闹得心绪不宁、寝食不安。”

“我亲爱的朋友，”卡迈克尔先生快活地说，“快别为这档子事活活折磨自己了，这对你没好处。即使全印度的财产都归了你，你也解决不了世上所有不公平的现象。你就是着手把这广场上所有的阁楼都装修好，还有多多少少别的广场和街道也需要装修？情况就是这样。”

卡里斯福特先生坐在壁炉前，眼望着熊熊炭火，嘴里啃着指甲。

“你认为，”过了一会儿，他慢慢地开口道，“你认为，那个女孩子——我念念不忘的那个女孩子——她可不可能——我相信完全有可能——也会沦落到隔壁那个可怜女孩子那种悲惨的境地呢？”

卡迈克尔先生不安地看了看他。他知道，无论对这个人自身，还是对他的健康和那件事，最糟的莫过于对这个独特的问题开始用这样独特的方式来思考。

“如果巴黎帕斯卡尔夫人学校的那个孩子就是你要找的那个，”他劝道，“那么看来她完全有可能已得到有能力供养她的人家照顾。他们收养她是因为她是他们已故小女儿最喜欢的伴侣。他们只有这么一个女儿，帕斯卡尔夫人说，他们是很富有的俄国人。”

“可是那个该死的女人居然不知道那俄国人把她弄到哪里去了！”卡里斯福特先生高声喊道。

卡迈克尔先生耸了耸肩。

“她是个精明又世故的法国人。女孩父亲死后什么生活费用也没给她留下，她能轻轻松松地卸掉这包袱，何乐而不为？像她这类女人都一个样，才不为拖累自己的孩子的前途考虑呢。收养她的那对夫妻已不知去向，踪迹全无了。”

“你说‘如果那是我找的女孩子’，你说的是‘如果’，就是说不是百分之百，而且姓名也不同。”

“听帕斯卡尔夫人说起来是卡鲁，而不叫克鲁——也许只是发音稍有差异造成的，情况却惊人的相似。有位在印度服役的英国军官曾把一个没娘的小女孩送进这所学校。他因破产突然死了。”说到这里卡迈克尔先生停了下来，像是临时想起了什么，“你能肯定确实是在巴黎吗？”

“我亲爱的朋友，”卡里斯福特激动地说道，显得不安与痛苦，“我什么也肯定不了。我没见过那孩子，也没见过她母亲。拉尔夫·克鲁和我从小就很要好，但离开学校后就没见过面，后来是在印度相逢的。矿山辉煌的前景深深吸引了我。他也着了迷。整个事业规模宏大且十分诱人，害得我们都失去了理智。我俩碰在一起只说这事，别的什么也不谈。所以我只知道这孩子被送到某地的一所学校去了。现在我甚至想不起我是怎么听来的。”

他开始激动起来。一提到过去的灾难，他那仍然虚弱的心总要激动起来。

卡迈克尔先生焦虑地望着他。有几个问题需要问问他，但是务必小心谨慎，平心静气。

“你说的确在巴黎，有什么根据？”

“有，”他答道，“因为她母亲是法国人，我听说她希望自己的孩子在巴黎接受教育，所以完全有可能送她到巴黎去。”

“是呀，”卡迈克尔先生答道，“看来可能性很大。”

印度绅士身子前倾，那只修长而虚弱的手敲着桌子。

“卡迈克尔，”他说，“我一定要找到她。只要她活在人世，总能找到那个地方。如果她落到无依无靠、穷困潦倒的境地，那完全是我造成的。一个人心里背着这样的包袱，他怎么能心安理得呢？矿山事业突然的大转机使我们时来运转，美梦成真，可克鲁可怜的孩子可能在街上乞讨！”

“别，别！”卡迈克尔说，“别激动。不妨这么想：一旦找到她，你就有机会把财产交给她。这么一想你就心安理得了。”

“为什么在濒临绝境的时候我不像个男子汉挺身而出顶住呢？”卡里斯福特痛苦地呻吟道，“我相信，我要不是不单是为自己，而且也为别人的钱负责，我就会坚持下去的。可怜的克鲁倾其所有投资了这事业。他信任我——他也喜欢我。可是他死时一定认为是我毁了他——我，汤姆·卡里斯福特，伊顿公学时和他玩过板球的卡里斯福特。他肯定把我看成是个恶棍了！”

“别过于自责。”

“我自责，不是因为那项投资有彻底失败的危险——而是因为我丧失了勇气。我像个骗子和小偷临阵脱逃，因为无颜面对自己最要好的朋友，告诉他是我毁了他和他的孩子。”

“大家庭”的心地善良的父亲把一只手放到对方肩上，安慰他。

“你走掉是因为当时你心力交瘁，精神负担过重，”他说，“你变得脑子糊涂了。不然的话，你一定会坚持下去处理好问题的。离开那地方两天后，你一病不起，困在医院里，脑病折磨得你尽说胡话。别忘了当时的实际情况。”

“上帝！确实如此，”他说，“我担惊受怕，惊慌失措，人都要疯了。一连好几星期我睡不着觉。那天晚上，我跌跌撞撞地跑出家门，满天满地像充斥着不怀好意的怪物在嘲笑我、羞辱我。”

“这足以说明问题了，”卡迈克尔先生说，“一个脑炎即将发作的人怎么能作出清醒的判断？”

卡里斯福特摇了摇低垂的头。

“等我清醒过来，可怜的克鲁已经死了——也下葬了。我似乎什么也想不起来。连续好多个月我都没有想到那小孩子。即使后来想起有这么个孩子，记忆中的一切也像是在迷雾中，模糊一片。”他稍停片刻，揉了揉额头，“即使是现在，想起来也还是模糊不清的。克鲁什么时候肯定跟我说起过她被送到哪所学校的事。你看呢？”

“他可能没有说得很具体。你好像从来没听人说起过她叫什么名字吧？”

“他一直用一个古怪小名称呼她，称她是自己的‘小主妇’。都是这该死的矿山害得我们把别的事全撇开不放在心里了。除了矿山我们什么也不谈。就算他提起过那学校，我已忘了——被我忘了。现在怎么也想不起来。”

“得了，得了，”卡迈克尔说，“反正我们会找到她的。我们接着找，把帕斯卡尔夫人说的好心的俄国夫妇找到。她好像还模模糊糊地记得，那两个人住在莫斯科。以此为线索，我去一趟莫斯科。”

“要是我出得了门，就跟你一起去。”卡里斯福特说，“可是我只能裹着皮衣，在炉火前傻看。看着，看着，就像在炉火中看到克鲁那张年轻快活的脸也看着我。他像是在问我一个问题。有时候晚上做梦，梦见他，始终站在我面前，开口问我同样的问题。你可知道，他问什么吗，卡迈克尔？”

卡迈克尔先生用非常轻的声音回答他。

“我说不准。”他道。

“他总是问：‘汤姆，老朋友——汤姆，‘小主妇’在哪里？’”他说罢，抓住卡迈克尔的手，紧紧捏着，“我必须回答他——必须回答！”他说，“帮助我找到她，帮帮我吧！”

※

墙的另一边，萨拉就坐在阁楼里，正同梅基塞代克说着话，它这是出来找寻晚餐的。

“现如今做个公主可真不易啊，梅基塞代克，”她说，“比往常要难得多了。随着天越来越冷，街上越来越泥泞，公主就更难做了。今天我在门厅从拉维尼亚身边经过时，她就笑话我身上的裙子满是泥泞，我猛地闪过一个念头，想回击她——到头来还是忍住了。一想到自己是个公主，可不能用讥笑来回击讥笑。那只好咬紧牙关硬忍下去。我倒是咬紧牙没说出来。梅基塞代克，今儿下午天可冷啦，晚上也很冷。”

说到这里，她猛地把满是黑发的脑袋埋进双臂。每逢她感到孤独时，常常这样。

“哦，爸爸，”她低声道，“我是你的‘小主妇’，那好像是好久好久以前的事了。”

这就是那天在墙壁两边发生的事情。

十三　一个小百姓

这年冬天十分寒冷。有几天萨拉外出办杂差都得踩着雪走。有时候更糟，雪化了和泥泞搅在一起，成了一片稀泥浆。还有些日子，雾很浓很浓，大街上连大白天也得点上灯。整个伦敦就像几年前的那个下午，当时马车驶过大街，萨拉蜷坐在座位上，依偎着父亲的肩膀。遇到这种日子，“大家庭”家的窗子就显得温暖舒适，特别诱人，让人感到愉悦。印度绅士待着的书房透出温暖绚丽的色调。然而，阁楼却一片难言的凄惨。再也见不到日出、日落的美景，萨拉觉得连星星也不露脸了。天窗外低低压着云层，天空不是灰色的，便是黑糊糊的，像是一片泥泞，要不就下起大滴大滴的雨点来。下午四点钟，即使没有浓雾，天也黑了。这时候萨拉要是不得已上阁楼取什么东西，得点上蜡烛。厨房里的那些娘们儿，个个心情不好，脾气坏得不能再坏了。贝基像个小奴隶，被差来遣去，忙得团团转。

“要不是有你，小姐，”有天晚上，贝基爬进阁楼，哑着嗓子，对萨拉说，“要不是有你，有巴士底监狱和隔壁牢房难友这档子故事，我早活不下去了。这儿还真的像监狱一样了，你说是不是？女东家活得越来越像管大牢的头儿，像你说的，我像是看到她带着串大钥匙，那厨娘活像是小牢头。再多讲些听听吧，小姐。给我讲讲咱们在墙根下挖地道的故事吧。”

“我给你讲讲温暖的事吧，”萨拉冷得直哆嗦，“去，把床单拿来，裹在身上。我也裹上，咱俩坐到床上，紧紧挨在一起，我给你讲热带森林的事，那印度绅士的猴子过去就待在那种地方。每当我见那猴子坐在窗前桌子上，一副伤心的模样望着屋面，我敢肯定他的这是在想念热带森林，过去他用尾巴吊住椰子树，一棵棵跳来荡去。不知道逮住他的是哪个人，不知道他离开后，靠他摘回椰子来过活的家人怎么办。”

“这故事听来是暖和些，小姐。”贝基感激地说，“不知咋的，就是巴士底监狱，经你一说，也让人感到暖烘烘的。”

“这是因为你听了想起了别的事，”萨拉说着，把床单往身上裹起来，最后把身子裹得严严实实的，只露出一张黑不溜秋的小脸来，“我早就看出来了。你的身体受苦时，唯一能做的事就是脑子去想别的事儿。”

“你做得到吗，小姐？”贝基疑惑地问，同时用敬佩的目光打量她。

萨拉皱了皱眉毛，但时间不长。

“有时候能做到，有时候做不到。”她答得很坚定，“我做到的时候，心里就舒坦。我相信，咱们都可以做到——只要多试几次就行。最近我就试过好多次了，现在觉得比过去容易多了。每当遇到事儿很可怕——十分可怕的时候——我就尽力去想：我是个公主。我对自己说：‘我是公主，又是小仙女公主，正因为是仙女，什么也伤害不了我，什么也坏不了我的心情。’你不知不觉间就会忘了别的事。”说罢她笑开了。

萨拉有很多时候不得不让自己去想别的事，她也有很多机会证明自己到底是不是公主。不过，有一天，是个非常艰难的日子，她遇到最严峻的考验。事后她每每想起这件事，许多年她也忘不了。

一连下了好几天的雨。街上又冷又滑，寒雾沉沉异常凄凉，到处都是泥泞——黏稠的伦敦泥泞——万物都被细雨和浓雾笼罩起来。自然少不了一些费时又费力的活儿要干——偏又碰上这样的坏天气——萨拉一再被差出去，弄得那一身破旧的衣衫被淋得湿透了。她那顶破帽上插着的几根古怪的旧羽毛显得越发古怪，脚下那双穿烂了的鞋子湿淋淋的，直淌水。这还不算，明卿小姐存心惩罚她，午饭也不让她吃。她饥寒交迫，疲惫不堪，面容憔悴，时不时引得从她身旁路过的好心人突然生起了恻隐之心，忍不住看她一眼。但是她自己没有发觉。她步履匆匆，努力去想别的事儿。这确实很有必要。她用尽了身上的余力去“假装”，去“设想”。但是这一次做起来遇到从未有过的困难。一两次后她发现，这么做事与愿违，反倒感到更冷更饿。但是她顽强地挺着。泥水滋滋地往破鞋子里钻，呼呼的寒风似乎要卷走她身上的薄外衣。她边走边自言自语，声音不高，连嘴唇也没动。

“假设我身上穿的是干燥的衣服，”她想，“假设我脚上穿的是好鞋子，大衣又长又厚，袜子是美利奴羊毛的，还打着大伞。假设——假设，我刚走近卖热面包的铺子时，捡到一枚没主的六便士硬币。假设我真的捡到了，就跑进铺里，买六只热气腾腾的面包，一口气全吃下去。”

在这世界上，有时会发生古里古怪的事。

这古里古怪的事果真让萨拉给撞上了。方才她自言自语时，正要过一条街。街上满是很深的泥水——她得趟过去。她小心翼翼地伸出脚，可还是没少遭罪。不过因为要选路，眼睛得看着脚下，留神别踩着泥浆。就在她低头刚走到人行道时，看到路沟里有样东西在闪闪发亮。分明是一枚银币——一枚被多人踩进沟里的小硬币，而且不失本色，还在闪着银光。不是六便士的，小些，只是四便士的。

眨眼间钱币就到了她那冷冰冰的、冻得又红又紫的小手中。

“哦，”她喘着粗气，说，“真的！是真的！”

你说巧也不巧，接着她抬头看了看正对面的铺子。那居然是间面包铺，只见一个快快活活、壮壮实实、脸蛋红扑扑的慈祥女人正端着一盘刚出炉的圆面包，热气腾腾，香气扑鼻，往橱窗里放——那些面包又大又松，亮光闪闪，上面还缀着一粒粒葡萄干。

精神上的激动，见了面包，加上面包铺地下室窗子飘出来的诱人的香气——凡此种种闹得萨拉一时间几乎要晕过去了。

她知道，这笔钱完全可以心安理得地花掉。显而易见，这枚硬币在泥水浆里肯定躺了有些时间了，街上人来人往，熙熙攘攘，哪里找得到失主？

“不过我得去问问面包铺里那个女人，有没有丢过东西。”她自言自语，有气无力。她过了街，一条湿腿踩到面包铺的台阶上。就在这时候她抬头一看，禁不住停下了脚步。

只见一个小家伙，境况比她还要惨——哪里有人样，简直是一团破布，里面露出一双满是污泥、冻得通红而瘦小的光脚。那小家伙原想把脚也藏进破布里，没奈何，太短了。破布团上是个脑袋，头发乱蓬蓬的，脏脸上凹陷的大眼睛露出饥饿的神色。

萨拉一见这目光就明白对方饿极了，刹那间生出同情心来。

“这孩子，”她叹了口气，说，“是个平民百姓——比我还要饿。”

这孩子——这个平民百姓——抬起头，看了看萨拉，身子朝一旁挪了挪，好让萨拉过去。她已习惯于给人让路了。她知道，一旦被警察发现，就得喝令她：“滚开！”

萨拉手里攥着四便士的钱币，迟疑了数秒钟后，问她：

“你饿了吗？”

小女孩子又挪了挪披着破布的身子。

“咋不饿？”她沙哑着嗓子反问道，“我咋不饿？”

“你吃过中饭没有？”萨拉问。

“啥中饭——”嗓子更哑了，身子又挪了挪，“早饭也没吃——晚饭也是。啥也没吃。”

“多久没吃东西了？”萨拉问。

“不知道——今儿啥也没吃——没处要。要来要去啥也要不到。”

一看她这景况就使萨拉感到越发的饥饿，越发头昏眼花。可是那些古怪的小念头又在她脑子里闹腾开来，虽然她心里非常难受，但还是对自己说起来。

“要是我是公主，”她说道，“要是我是公主，在公主们一贫如洗又被赶下王位——她们也会——跟平民百姓——如果见了比自己更穷更饿的人——她们不会视而不见的。她们总是和别人分享自己的东西。圆面包一便士买一个。如果是枚六便士的硬币，我可以吃上六个。两个人都吃就不够了。不过比起什么都没有要强多了。”

“你等等。”她对小叫花子说。

她进了面包铺。铺内暖和和的，香气扑鼻。老板娘正往橱窗里添热气腾腾的圆面包。

“请问，”萨拉说，“你有没有丢了四便士——四便士的银币？”说罢，她把那枚不起眼的硬币递给了老板娘。

老板娘看了看硬币，又看了看她——看了看那张认真的小脸和那身湿淋淋、原本很讲究的衣衫。

“哦，老天爷，我可没丢！”她答道，“你捡到的？”

“是我捡到的，”萨拉说，“沟里捡到的。”

“那你就留着吧，”老板娘说，“硬币落在那里没准有一个星期了，天知道是哪个丢的。这可没法查。”

“我知道。”萨拉说，“可我寻思得问问你。”

“真不多见。”老板娘脸上同时露出困惑、兴趣和慈祥的神情来。

“你要买些什么？”她一见萨拉在打量圆面包，便问。

“请给四只小圆面包，”萨拉说，“一便士一只的那种。”

老板娘去橱窗，拿了几只面包，装进纸口袋。

萨拉看见她装了六只。

“对不起，我说的是四只。”萨拉解释道，“我只有四便士。”

“加了两只是为了补充分量，”那女的说，露出慈祥的目光，“我敢说，过会儿你准需要吃的。你不是饿了吗？”

萨拉的眼睛湿润了。

“是的，”她说，“我饿了。你这么好心，谢谢你了，再说——”她还想说：“店外还有个孩子比我还要饿。”但是这时候一下子进来两三个顾客，个个都很匆忙似的，她便什么都没说，再次谢了谢老板娘后，出了店门。

那小叫花子还蜷缩着身子待在台阶的一角。她穿着一身又湿又破的衣衫，样子真吓人。她直勾勾地盯着萨拉，目光木然、痛苦。萨拉突然发现自己正用粗糙的脏手背擦着泪水，她似乎挺惊奇的：自己怎么会流起泪来了。她喃喃自语。

萨拉打开纸袋，拿出一只热气腾腾的圆面包。她冰冷的手已被热面包捂暖了些。

“你看，”她说着把面包放到对方裹着破布的膝盖上，“这面包又香又热。吃吧，吃了就不觉得那么饿了。”

那孩子吃了一惊，抬头看了看她，像是想不到有这样的好事让她碰上，令她又惊又怕。接着她一把抓过面包往嘴里塞，饿狼似的大口大口吃了起来。

“哦，老天爷！老天爷！”只听得那孩子欣喜若狂，嘶哑着嗓子喊道，“哦，老天爷！”

萨拉掏出三只面包，递给了她。

她急不可耐地吃着吃着，同时发出嘶哑而怕人的吞咽声。

“她比我饿，”萨拉自言自语道，“她饿坏了。”但是当萨拉递给她第四只面包的时候，手哆嗦起来，“我不算最饿。”她说着——给了她第五只面包。

萨拉临走时，看见那个饿极了的伦敦小野人往嘴里塞面包。她实在饿急了，忙着吃，顾不得说一声“谢谢”。即使她有教养、懂礼貌，到了这地步也顾不上礼貌了，更何况她根本就没受过教育。她只是个可怜的野孩子。

“再见。”萨拉说。

萨拉到了街对面，看见那孩子一手各拿着一只面包。她刚咬了一口，半途停下来，朝萨拉望过去。萨拉轻轻地点了点头，那孩子又盯着她看——神色奇异，盯了好一会儿，接着，那长着乱蓬蓬头发的脑袋晃了一下，算是回礼，直到看不见萨拉后她才重新吃起来，最后把那只咬了一口的面包吃完。

这时候，面包铺老板娘正从橱窗里往外看。

“哎，真想不到！”她高声道，“这小姑娘竟把面包都给了小叫花子！倒不是她不想吃。你瞧瞧，她自己有多饿。我倒是不明白，她这是图个啥。”

她在橱窗后立了好一会儿，寻思着。她很想弄个明白，到底是怎么回事，便来到门口，盘问起小叫花子来。

“面包是哪个给的？”她问。

女孩朝那远去的萨拉背影点了点头。

“她说了什么？”老板娘接着问。

“问我饿不饿？”对方哑着嗓子答道。

“你怎么说？”

“我说咋不饿。”

“后来她进来买了面包，给了你，是不是？”

那孩子点点头。

“给了几只？”

“五只。”

老板娘捉摸了一阵。

“自己只留下一只，”她低声自言自语道，“六只全让她吃也吃得下——从她的眼神看得出。”

她望着那拖着沉重步子远去的身影。她一向活得自自在在，好久不曾烦心过，这时候心里却被搅得不能平静。

“要是她没跑得那么快就好了，”她说，“也真是，当时我怎么就没再给她六只呢？”她说罢转身对着小叫花子。

“你还饿吗？”她问。

“我老觉得饿，”她答道，“可不像刚才那样饿得慌了。”

“进来吧。”老板娘说着推开门。

那孩子站了起来，拖着步子走了进去。被人请进这暖烘烘的地方，里面满是面包，她压根就没想到会有这等好事。她拿不准接着会发生什么事。她也不在乎。

“暖和暖和身子吧。”老板娘指了指里屋狭小房间里的炉火说，“听好了，往后你饿得不行想吃面包时，就上我这儿来要。我这是看在那小姑娘的份上才这么做的，要不就太不像话了。”

吃了剩下的那只面包后，萨拉觉得好过了些。不管怎么说，面包是热的，有吃的比什么没吃强多了。她边走边小块小块地掰下往嘴里送，细嚼慢咽起来，好把时间拖得长些。

“假设这是只有魔法的圆面包，”她说，“一口就抵得上吃一顿美餐，那我这吃法，准要撑死。”

她回到高级女子寄宿学校所在的广场，天已经黑了。家家户户都亮起了灯。她差不多经常能见到“大家庭”一家人的那个房间里，百叶窗还没关上。通常在这时候，她总看到那位被她叫做蒙特莫伦西的先生坐在大椅子里，身边围着一大群小孩子，有说有笑，好不热闹。那些孩子有的坐在椅子两边的扶手上，有的坐在或靠在他的膝盖上。今天晚上，那帮孩子也围着他，可他没坐着。相反，他们个个都很兴奋。看得出来，有人要出远门了。出远门的是蒙特莫伦西先生。门前停着一辆四轮马车，车上捆着旅行用的大皮箱。孩子们围着他蹦蹦跳跳、说说笑笑，闹个不停。那位脸蛋粉红粉红的漂亮母亲立在他身旁说话，像是临别前最后问什么事。萨拉停下脚步，看见他把岁数小的孩子抱起来亲吻一番，然后弯下身吻了吻大点的孩子。

“不知道他外出久不久，”萨拉想道，“皮箱倒是挺大的。啊，他们该多挂念他呀！我也会想念他的，只是他并不知道世上有我这个人。”

大门打开，她就走开了。这时候她想起了那六便士硬币的事。她看见那出远门的人走出来，站在灯光明亮、暖和的大厅前，几个大点的孩子还陪着他。

“莫斯科会是遍地白雪吧？”小姑娘珍妮特问，“是不是到处是冰？”

“你会坐雪橇吗？”另一个孩子问，“你能见到沙皇吗？”

“我全会写信告诉你们的，”他笑着说，“我会寄回一些俄国农夫的画片和别的东西。快进屋。今天晚上又湿又冷。我情愿不去莫斯科，留下来跟你们待在一起。再见了，再见，小宝贝儿！愿上帝保佑你们！”他说罢快步下了台阶，跳进马车。

“找到那个女孩子后，替我们向她问好。”盖伊·克拉伦斯在门前擦鞋垫上又蹦又跳，高声说道。

他们进了屋，关了门。

“看见了吗，”回到房间，珍妮特问诺拉，“那个‘不是叫花子的女孩子’刚走过去？看她又冷又湿的，还扭过头来打量咱们哩。妈妈说，她那衣服像是富人送给她的——人家送给她是因为衣服穿得太破旧了。学校里总在天气最恶劣的时候，不管白天还是黑夜，打发她出去干活。”

且说萨拉，走过广场，到了明卿小姐学校地下室的台阶前，只觉得头昏眼花，浑身哆嗦。

“不知道那姑娘是哪个，”她想道，“那个他们找寻的小姑娘是哪个。”

她拖着篮子走下台阶，只觉得篮子沉甸甸的。这时候，“大家庭”的父亲正匆匆地坐着马车往车站搭乘去莫斯科的火车。到了那里，他要尽全力寻找克鲁上尉失踪的小女儿。

十四　梅基塞代克的所见所闻

萨拉外出办事的那天下午，她的阁楼里发生了件怪事。当时只有梅基塞代克亲眼所见，亲耳所闻，吓得它惊慌失措，大惑不解，忙躲回洞里，不敢出来。它哆哆嗦嗦，胆战心惊，小心翼翼地探出头，想看看到底出了什么事。

大清早萨拉出去后，阁楼里整天是静悄悄的，只有雨点敲打石板瓦和天窗发出的噼啪声才打破了寂静。梅基塞代克觉得很无聊。后来雨声停了，阁楼又恢复了寂静，它决定出来探听探听，虽然凭经验它知道，萨拉一时还回不来。它东溜溜西转转，这儿闻闻，那儿嗅嗅，想不到居然意外地找到一块上顿剩下的面包屑。就在这时候，屋顶有了声响，引起了它的注意。它停下来细听，心头怦怦直跳。这声响说明，窗外屋顶上有什么东西在走动。声响越来越近，快到天窗口了。天窗神秘地打开来，探进一张黝黑的脸，接着后面又露出一张脸。两张脸小小心心、兴致勃勃地朝里面张望。阁楼外屋顶上有两个男人，正准备悄悄爬进来。一个是拉姆·达斯，另一个是年轻人，他是印度绅士的秘书。这些事儿梅基塞代克自然是不知情的。它只知道，这两个人这一来就要打破阁楼的宁静，侵犯人家的隐私。只见长着黑黝黝脸孔的那个人轻巧而敏捷地钻进窗口，悄没声息地落到地板上，梅基塞代克赶忙转身夹着尾巴逃回洞里，吓得它掉了魂儿。跟萨拉一起它已不再害怕了。它知道萨拉除了面包屑，不会朝它扔别的东西，她说起话来始终是低声轻语，和和气气。可这是两个陌生人，跟他们待在一起就危险了。它身子直挺挺地紧贴洞口，一双明亮的眼睛，警惕地透过缝隙朝外张望。那两个人的谈话它到底听懂了多少，我可说不准。不过即使全听懂了，它也许也不明白到底是怎么回事。

那个秘书动作轻巧，年纪轻轻，也像拉姆·达斯一样悄悄地进了天窗，还看到了梅基塞代克奔回洞里来不及藏起的一截尾巴。

“那是老鼠？”他悄声问拉姆·达斯。

“是，是耗子，先生，”拉姆·达斯同样悄声答道，“墙里多着呢。”

“呵！”年轻人大声道，“怪了，这小孩子居然不怕老鼠。”

拉姆·达斯做了个手势。他也轻声地笑了笑。虽然他跟萨拉只说过一次话，但俨然是这里的熟客，对这里了如指掌。

“这孩子小小年纪，跟什么都挺友好，先生。”他说，“她跟别的孩子不一样。我躲在她注意不到我的地方观察了她。好几个晚上，我悄悄溜过石板瓦看她安不安全。我从自己的窗口看她，可她并不知道我就在附近。她常常站在这桌子上，望着窗外的天空，像是天空在跟她说话呢。麻雀听到她的叫唤就飞过来，她寂寞时就喂这耗子，训练它。这家有个可怜的小奴隶经常上她那儿寻求安慰。有个小女娃还悄悄到这儿来。还有一个岁数大点的，可崇拜她了，喜欢听她说话，听了还想听。这都是我悄悄爬过屋顶亲眼看到的。这家的女东家——可是个恶婆娘——拿她当贱民。可她的举止就像是正统的公主！”

“听来你对她很了解。”秘书说。

“她每天怎么过的，我全知情，”拉姆·达斯说，“她什么时候出门，什么时候回来，什么时候高兴，什么时候悲伤，是冷是饿，我全知情。我知道，她孤单时就坐着看书学习；我知道，她的几个秘密朋友什么时候偷偷来看望她，她会变得快活些——小孩子嘛，就是最穷最苦也有快活的时候——因为她们一来，她就跟她们一起低声说说笑笑：要是她病了，我也会知道的，只要办得到，我就过来伺候她。”

“你能肯定，除了她附近不来别的人，能肯定她不会回来撞上我俩。要是被她看见了，会吓坏她，卡里斯福特先生的计划也就完了。”

拉姆·达斯悄无声息地到了门边，紧贴着门站着。

“除了她，没别的人上楼来的，先生，”他说，“她拎着篮子出去了，几小时内回不来。我这就站在这儿，只要有人上来，一踏上最后一段楼梯，我就能听到。”

秘书从胸前口袋里掏出铅笔和记事本。

“注意听着。”他说罢就在小阁楼里轻手轻脚慢慢转起来，一边看东西，一边快速在记事本上记下来。

他先到那只狭小的床前，用手按了按床垫，发出一声惊叹。

“硬得像石头，”他说，“哪天她出门时得换掉，改天得专门过来，今晚来不及了。”他掀开床罩，细看那只单薄的枕头。

“床罩又脏又破，毯子太薄，被单破破烂烂的，满是补丁，”他说，“这样的床怎么让孩子来睡——还是在什么高级女校里！壁炉不知有多少日子没生火了。”他看了看锈迹斑斑的壁炉说。

“我见到它后就没生过火。”拉姆·达斯说，“这里的女东家，除了她自己，从来就想不到别人也会冷的。”

秘书在本本上飞快地写起来。写完了，抬起头，撕下一页，塞回胸前口袋里。

“这事儿做得挺别致，”他说，“哪个想出来的？”

拉姆·达斯谦恭地深深鞠了一躬。

“说实话，最初是我的主意，先生，”他说，“那只是我凭空瞎想一气。我太喜欢这孩子了，我跟她都是孤零零的。她就爱跟自己的朋友说自己的梦想。有天晚上，我心里难受，就躺在开着的天窗边听她讲。在她的想象中，要是这简陋的阁楼里摆上舒适的家具，会是个什么模样。她说着说着，就像真的出现在眼前，她越说越高兴。结果她提到了这么个怪想法。第二天老爷病了，心情也不好，我给他讲了这事好让他开开心。说来只是个梦想，可老爷听了挺高兴。小姑娘的事儿让他心情好起来。他对小姑娘来了兴趣，还问了我一些情况。最后他要让她的梦想成真，也好让自己开开心。”

“你以为在她睡着的时候这事办得成？要是她醒过来怎么办？”秘书提出自己的看法。显而易见，不管这计划具体是什么，这件事激发了他的兴致，并像卡里斯福特先生一样感到快乐。

“我移动起来脚步轻如鹅毛，无声无息，”拉姆·达斯说，“再说小孩子一向睡得熟——即使是苦命的孩子也一样。我可以做到一个晚上来来去去好多次，让她睡得熟熟的，身子一动不动。要是让另一个人把东西从窗口递给我，我可以做到一丝一毫也不惊动她。她醒来后，还以为是魔法师来过呢。”

他微微一笑，像是他那白袍下的心也感到了温暖，秘书也报之一笑。

“这像是《天方夜谭》里的故事，”他说，“这主意只有东方人才想得出来。浓雾下的伦敦人可没这能耐。”

好在他俩没待多久，让梅基塞代克大大舒了口气，它可能听不懂两个人的这番谈话，但是总觉得他们鬼鬼祟祟的举动和窃窃私语不是个好兆头。那年轻的秘书像是对什么事都感兴趣——地板、壁炉、破板凳、旧桌子，还有墙壁什么的，他全记下来——最后还用手在墙壁上摸来摸去，发现上面钉了许多旧钉子，还挺高兴哩。

“上面可以挂东西。”他说。

拉姆·达斯神秘地笑了笑。

“昨天，她出去时，”他说，“我进来，带了一些尖尖的小钉子，不用锤子就能摁到墙上。我在墙上钉了不少，需要时准能派上用场。”

印度绅士的秘书一动不动地站着，朝四周又看了看，把小本本塞回了口袋里。

“看来记下不少了。我们可以走了。”他说，“卡里斯福特先生有副热心肠，千遗憾、万遗憾就是没能把那丢失的孩子找回来。”

“要是找回那孩子，他一准会身强体壮起来。”拉姆·达斯说，“他的上帝早晚会领她回到他身边的。”

接着他们像进来时那样，悄悄地无声无息钻出了天窗。梅基塞代克吃准了他俩真的走了后，心上一块大石头这才落了地。过了几分钟，它觉得已万无一失，便从洞里钻出来，跑来跑去，指望着那两个叫人好不提心吊胆的人没准口袋里装了面包屑，掉落出来，让它碰上一些。

十六　不速之客

请使劲想象一下，那天晚上剩下来的时间是怎么度过的：小壁炉里的炉火在燃烧、闪烁、跳跃，她俩是怎样蹲在炉火旁；她俩又是怎样揭开菜盘上的盖子，发现美味可口浓香的热汤，汤本身就够她俩吃上一顿，何况还有三明治、烤面包片、松糕，多得叫人吃不了。贝基把洗脸台上的水杯当作茶杯，茶香扑鼻，完全没有必要假装成是别的东西。两个小姑娘吃得喝得暖暖和和，心满意足，心花怒放。萨拉发现这奇妙的好运并非梦境，便尽情享用起来，这也是她一贯的做法。她一向生活在想象的世界里，面对发生的所有稀奇古怪的事已习以为常，所以很快便见怪不怪了。

“不知道这事出自世上何人之手，”她说，“反正有这样的人。你看，咱俩就坐在他生的炉火旁，而且——而且——真真切切！不管他是谁——不管人在哪儿——我有了一个朋友。贝基——有个人，他就是我的朋友。”

不可否认，她俩坐在熊熊炉火前，吃着营养丰富、舒心可口的食物，便有一种又喜又敬的感觉，同时又怀着疑惑的神情打量着对方。

“你是不是觉得，”过了一会儿贝基吞吞吐吐地低声问，“是不是觉得这些东西会消失掉呢，小姐？咱俩是不是要抓紧吃呢？”说着她匆匆往嘴里塞三明治。要是这只是一场梦，吃东西时大可不必讲究那些规矩了。

“不，不会消失掉的，”萨拉说，“我嘴里正吃着松糕，有滋有味哩。梦中可吃不到真正的东西，只是以为在吃东西。还有，我不断掐自己，刚刚还摸了摸一块滚烫的煤，我是有意这么做的。”

她俩终于难以抵挡那奇妙、舒适而又懒洋洋的感觉。幸福的儿童吃饱喝足后往往有这种困倦的感觉，她俩坐在炉火前正陶醉在这种感觉之中，最后萨拉的目光转向那变了样的床上。

床上的毯子有好几条，足以分给贝基一条。隔壁房间里那张狭窄的床这天晚上睡上去必然舒服极了，这是床主人梦中也没有享受过的。

贝基走出房间，到了门口转身贪婪地看了看四周。

“即使天亮后全没了，小姐，”她说，“今晚反正让我见识过了，我是永远也忘不了的。”她把每样东西都看了个遍，像是要牢牢装到心里去似的，“你瞧那儿有炉火，”她说着用手指了指，“前面摆着桌子，上面有灯，灯光是粉红色的，像玫瑰。你床上有条缎面被子，地板铺着暖和和的地毯，样样东西都漂漂亮亮的。还有——”她停了一会儿，一只手轻轻按在肚皮上，“——还有汤、三明治、松糕——就在这里面。”至少她已确信，肚子里装的都是真食物，随后走了。

但凡学生中和仆役间，都存在一些神秘的传播通道，所以第二天一大早大家都知道萨拉·克鲁干出件极为丢脸的事，埃芒加德也受到了惩罚。贝基呢，早饭前她得卷铺盖走人，不过她是在厨房里干杂活的，一时还走不了。仆人们都知道，之所以允许贝基待下去是因为明卿小姐一时不容易找到这么一个无亲无故、地位低下的丫头，干的是奴隶的活，拿的是每周寥寥几先令的工钱。学校里年龄大一点的孩子都知道，明卿小姐没撵走萨拉完全出于自身的实际利益。

“她个儿长得高，好歹学到的东西又那么多，”杰西对拉维尼亚说，“很快就让她教课了。明卿小姐心里明白，她得白干活。你够卑鄙的，拉维，告发了人家在阁楼里玩儿的事。你是怎么知道的？”

“我是从洛蒂口中听来的。她还嫩哩，透露给了我，她自己还不知道。告诉明卿小姐有什么卑鄙的？我觉得这是自己的责任——”她还挺自豪哩，“萨拉老哄骗人。可笑的是穿得这么寒酸，还要摆出了不起的架势，眼睛都长在头顶了！”

“给明卿小姐撞见时，她们都在干吗？”

“假装些傻事儿。埃芒加德拿了一篮吃的东西上楼，和萨拉、贝基一起吃。她可从不把东西分给咱们。这我不计较。可她竟把东西分给阁楼里的下人吃，太掉价了。我真不明白明卿小姐怎么不把萨拉撵走——就是真的需要她来教课也不行。”

“要是她给撵走了，你叫她去哪儿？”杰西免不了有点担心地问。

“我怎么知道？”拉维尼亚凶巴巴地答道，“今天上午她进教室时，看上去准要越发怪模怪样了。我想——尤其在出了这种事之后。昨天她没吃上晚饭，今天也别指望吃上一顿。”

杰西有点傻，可心眼并不很坏，一听这话，猛地拿起书。

“不过，我认为这么做太可怕了。”她说，“她们没有权利害得她饿死。”

那天早上，萨拉进厨房时，厨娘斜着眼看她，别的佣人也一样。她急急忙忙从她们身边走过。事实上，她睡得稍稍过头了。贝基也一样，所以两个人没时间相互打照面，各人都是匆匆下楼来的。

萨拉走进洗碗间。贝基在使劲擦水壶，喉咙里还哼着小曲儿。她抬起头，瞧她的脸，很有些喜不自禁的表情。

“我醒过来一看，小姐——毯子还在哩。”她兴奋地低声道，“跟昨晚一个样，全是真的。”

“我的也一样，”萨拉说，“现在东西还在——全在。我边穿衣边吃了些冷的，是咱们吃剩的。”

“哦，老天爷！老天爷！”贝基开心得叽里咕噜起来，但一见厨娘进来，赶紧埋头擦起了水壶。

明卿小姐想看看萨拉进教室时是副什么模样，这跟拉维尼亚倒是不谋而合。在她的眼中，萨拉总是让人恼火，又让人猜不透。任你对她怎么严厉，她就是不哭，也不惊慌。你骂她，她便一声不吭地立着，板着脸恭恭敬敬听着；惩罚她，她就去干分到的活，饭也不吃，不抱怨叫屈，也没露反抗的迹象。她回你的话从不粗暴失礼，但在明卿小姐听来正是粗暴失礼的表示。不过昨天饿了她一天，又经历了昨晚一场暴烈的场面，再加上今天挨饿，她肯定要垮的。要是她下楼时不面色苍白，不两眼通红、神情哀伤，不服服帖帖，那才怪哩。

明卿小姐破天荒第一次进教室听萨拉给小班学生上法语课，听她们朗读，看她辅导做练习。只见萨拉进来时步履轻松，富有弹性，两颊红润，嘴角挂着微笑。明卿小姐从未见过这等奇事，不禁大吃一惊。这孩子是钢打铁铸的不成？倒是怎么回事？她立马把萨拉叫到跟前来。

“你干了丢脸的事，可看上去毫无认识，”她说，“你这是长着榆木脑袋？”

事实是，如果一个人还是个孩子——即使已长大了——只要吃饱、穿暖、睡好、睡够；只要你认为是在童话故事中入睡，醒来后发现这一切又是真实的，那么他不可能不幸福，甚至想装也办不成；任他怎么努力，眼睛不可能不流露出快乐的光辉。当萨拉抬起双眼，完满而彬彬有礼地回答时，她的眼神几乎惊得明卿小姐张口结舌了。

“请你原谅，明卿小姐，”她说，“我知道自己丢了脸。”

“没有忘记就好，可不要装得像是发了大财似的。这是厚颜无耻。别忘了，今天可没有你吃的饭。”

“知道了，明卿小姐，”她说。但是当她转过身走开时，立即想起头天晚上的遭遇，心头怦怦直跳。“要不是魔法及时救我，”她心想，“我的下场就太惨了！”

“她像是不太饿的样子。”拉维尼亚低声道，“瞧她！也许是假装美美吃了早餐——”只听得她恶毒地笑出声来。

“她跟别人就是不一样。”杰西说，看着萨拉跟着自己班里的学生一起学习，“有时候我还怕她三分呢。”

“够荒唐的事儿！”拉维尼亚愤愤地说。

整整一天，萨拉显得喜气洋洋，容光焕发。仆人无不向她投去迷惑不解的目光，窃窃私语，艾米丽亚小姐的蓝色小眼睛也流露出困惑的神情。她实在不明白，人家这样打压萨拉，该是痛不欲生，可她倒好，还是满不在乎，乐呵呵的。不过，这符合萨拉倔强的性子。也许，她已铁了心硬干到底了。

有一件事，萨拉思来想去后，认为非做到不可。那就是必需尽量不让发生的奇迹这一秘密泄露出去。要是明卿小姐再次上阁楼来，秘密免不了全要败露。不过，看起来至少短时期内她来的可能性不大，除非有什么事引起她的怀疑。埃芒加德和洛蒂一定会被严密监视，她俩再也没有胆量偷偷溜出来。倒是可以把这一奇事告诉埃芒加德，相信她会保守秘密的。要是被洛蒂知道了，也可以做到让她不要泄露出去。也许魔法自有法力隐藏住自己的奇迹。

“不管发生什么事，”这天，萨拉整天反复告诉自己，“不管发生什么事，世界上某个地方，有个心地善良的人，他是我的朋友——我的朋友。即使我永远不知道他是谁——即使我永远没有感谢他的机会——我也不会感到自己是个孤苦伶仃的人。哦，魔法对我真仁慈！”

论天气，前天算是坏的了，但是今天更加恶劣——更冷、更潮、更泥泞。要干的活儿更多，厨娘的脾气更坏，她知道萨拉受了罚，越发蛮不讲理了。但是一旦有了魔法师这个朋友，任它发生什么事都算不了什么了。头天晚上萨拉美美地吃了一顿后，只觉得浑身都有力气。她知道，一整天即使免不了要挨饿，晚上定能暖和和地睡个好觉。她认为自己能挨到第二天开早饭，到时候总该让她吃东西吧。天很晚了，她终于回到了阁楼。她被允许在教室里学到十点钟。她对学习有了兴趣，书看得很晚才上楼来。

她上了楼，在阁楼门前站了下来。说实在的，这时候她的心跳得快极了。

“不用说东西没准全被收回去了，”她尽量装得挺勇敢的样子，低声说，“那都是昨晚念我陷入了可怕的境地才暂时借给我的，是借给我的——我也享用过了，都是真的。”

她打开门，走了进去。她再次微微喘着气，关上门，背靠门，满房间打量起来。

魔法又施展了一番。真真切切，法力比上次还要广大。炉火在熊熊烧着，火光欢快地跳着，越发赏心悦目。阁楼里搬进了好多新东西，面貌大为改观，要不是她深信不疑的话，准会惊得去擦自己的眼睛了。低矮的桌子上又摆上了晚餐——这一回不但有归她用的杯盘碗碟，还为贝基准备了一副。破壁炉台上铺了一块鲜亮厚实的毯子，上面还绣着从未见过的花花草草。毯子上放着一些小摆设。原先光秃秃、难看的东西能遮盖的都蒙上了布幔，显得十分美观。墙上用图钉钉着一些色彩绚丽的奇特布料。那些图钉又结实又尖，不用锤子就能用手摁进木头和灰泥里去。墙上还钉上几把色彩缤纷的扇子，地上摆着几只大垫子，又大又结实，完全可以坐人。还有一只木头箱子，上面铺了块毯子，摆着几个坐垫，看起来很有沙发的派头。

萨拉慢慢地一步一步地离开房门，干脆一屁股坐了下去，又前后左右打量起来。“实在像童话成真了。”她说。

“千真万确，丝毫也没区别。我觉得自己这下神通广大了，想什么就有什么——钻石呀，成袋成袋的金子呀，全都会有！天底下还有什么比这更古怪的？这就是我的阁楼？我还是那个破衣烂衫、又冷又湿的萨拉吗？想当初我假装又假装，但愿出现仙女哩！我一向眼巴巴地只有一个愿望，那就是能让童话故事变成现实。这不，现在我就生活在童话故事之中。我觉得自己已经是仙女了，掌握了点石成金的法力。”

她站起来敲了敲墙，叫隔壁牢房的难友过来，不一会儿贝基来了。

难友一进来，差点没跌倒在地，瘫成一团，好一会儿都喘不过气来。

“哦，老天爷！”她上气不接下气地说，“哦，老天爷，小姐！”——那情景跟早上在洗碗间里的表现一模一样。

“你倒是瞧瞧。”萨拉说。

这天晚上贝基就坐在炉前地毯的软垫上，用上了她自己的杯碟。

萨拉来到床前，发现床上铺的是厚厚的新床垫，摆着几只鸭绒大枕头。原先的床垫和枕头都移放到贝基的床上了，结果呢，贝基添了这些东西后，睡起来自有从未有过的舒服。

“全是哪来的？”贝基有一回禁不住问道，“老天爷！哪个干的，小姐！”

“就别问了，”萨拉答道，“要不是我想说‘哦，谢谢你了’，我还是不知道的好。这反而觉得更美好。”

从此生活变得一天比一天更神奇。童话故事从不间断。几乎每天都有新变化。每天晚上萨拉回来打开房门就会看到出现一些新的用具或装饰物，用不了多久，小小的阁楼就成了摆满各种各样稀奇华贵东西的地方了。难看丑陋的墙壁渐渐全挂上图画和挂毯，出现了一件件精致的折叠家具，墙上挂上了满是书的书架，前后添了一件又一件新的家具和用具，最后已是一应俱全，什么也不缺了。早晨，萨拉下了楼，桌子上摆着的是吃剩的饭菜，晚上回到阁楼里，剩饭冷菜已被魔法收拾走了，换上一份小小而可口的晚餐。明卿小姐照样凶相毕露，出口伤人，艾米丽亚小姐还是一个劲儿地怨天尤人，那些女佣改不了粗俗无礼的性子。不管刮风下雨，天寒地冻，萨拉还是被差出去跑腿，挨骂受气，吆来喝去。几乎不允许她与埃芒加德和洛蒂搭话，拉维尼亚对她身上的衣衫越来越横加嘲讽。她来到教室，其他的女孩都怪怪地瞪着她看。但是她既然生活在神奇的故事里，这一切算得了什么？过去她挨饿时想象出种种故事来安慰自己幼小的心灵，使自己免于陷入绝望，相比之下，如今的生活不是更浪漫、更快活吗？有时候，遇到被训斥时，她忍不住快要笑出声来。

“你们哪知道？”她暗自想道，“你们哪里知道？”

她享受到的舒适而快乐的生活使她变得越来越强壮，今后有望也会保持下去。如果她外出办事回来浑身湿透，又累又饿，她知道只要爬到阁楼，很快就能暖和起来，吃得饱饱的。最艰难的日子里，只要想一想，回家打开房门时会看到什么，又有什么样的欢乐等着自己，她就转忧为喜。很快她变得不那么消瘦了。两颊红润起来，双眼也与脸面相称，不显得过于大了。

“萨拉·克鲁的脸色出奇得好。”明卿小姐不怀好意地对妹妹说。

“可不是，”可怜而傻乎乎的艾米丽亚小姐说，“她一准越来越胖了。过去她可是个饿瘪了肚皮的小乌鸦。”

“饿瘪了肚皮？”明卿小姐怒冲冲地嚷道，“她没有理由显得像是挨饿。她一向就吃得饱饱的！”

“还——还用说？”艾米丽亚顺从地附和道，她胆战心惊地发现自己又像通常那样，说错了话。

“看到这种岁数的小孩脸上出现那样的表情总觉得不对劲。”明卿小姐说得傲气十足，可又含含糊糊。

“啥——啥表情？”艾米丽亚壮着胆问。

“完全可以说是挑衅，”明卿小姐恼火极了，因为她知道令她反感的跟挑衅压根不相干，可又想不出更难听的话来，“换了别的孩子遇到这样非得逆来顺受不可的变故，精神和意志就会消沉下去，就会被彻底压垮。可说实话，她丝毫也不受影响，还像个——像个公主似的。”

“你还记得吧，”脑子缺根筋的艾米丽亚小姐插言道，“那天她在教室里对你说什么来着：你会怎么办，要是你发现她是——”

“记不得了，”明卿小姐说，“别尽说废话。”其实她记得一清二楚。

自然啰，甚至连贝基也变得越来越胖，不再老担惊受怕了。她这也不是有意硬要这样。在秘密的童话故事里她也是个受惠者。她有两条褥子，两只枕头，不少的被子，每天晚上吃到热腾腾的晚饭，炉火前坐垫上也有自己的一席之地。巴士底监狱已消融，囚犯已不复存在。只有两个称心如意的小女孩陶醉在欢乐之中。有时候萨拉拿来自己的书朗诵一段，有时候做做功课，有时候坐在壁炉前，眼望着炉火，竭力想象自己的这个朋友可能是哪个，渴望能和他说说心里话。

接着又出了件事。来了个人，在大门口留下几包东西。上面用粗大字体写着：“右边阁楼的小姑娘收。”

萨拉被打发去开了门，把东西拿了进来。她把最大的两包东西放在大厅的桌子上，看了看地址，恰好明卿小姐下楼来，撞见了她。

“这些东西是哪位小姐的就给她送去，”她厉声道，“别傻站着干瞪眼。”

“东西是送给我的。”萨拉轻声道。

“送给你的？”明卿小姐惊问道，“你这是什么意思？”

“我不知道是从哪儿送来的，”萨拉说，“可上面写着是送给我的。我就睡在右面的阁楼里。贝基在左面。”

明卿小姐来到她的身旁，看了看包包，显得十分兴奋。

“里面都有些什么？”她问。

“不知道。”萨拉答。

“打开。”明卿小姐勒令道。

萨拉照吩咐做了。包包一个个被打开，明卿小姐的脸上露出奇特的表情。呈现在她眼前的全是漂亮、舒适的衣物——各种各样全有：鞋子、袜子、手套，还有一件暖暖和和、漂漂亮亮的外衣，甚至还有一顶好看的帽子、一把雨伞，全是昂贵、上好的东西。外衣口袋里别着一张字条，上面写着：“供日常穿戴——需要替换时会送来新的。”

明卿小姐异常激动。这事儿太意外了，她那利欲熏心的头脑里不觉生出一些奇怪的联想。她到底是不是看错人了？这个被遗弃的孩子暗地里还有个朋友，性情虽然古怪，可有权有势——也许是个此前不为人知的亲戚，突然打探出萨拉的下落，便选用这种神秘而古怪的办法来资助她？亲戚的事往往都很古怪——特别是那些有钱的单身老舅、老叔辈，他们不喜欢身边有孩子。这种人宁愿离得远远的，来关心晚辈的福利。这种人肯定都性格古怪、脾气暴躁，得罪不起。要是真的出来这样的人，让他知道真相，知道自己的至亲落得衣衫单薄、褴褛、吃不饱，还要干重活的境地，那可要出乱子了。她觉得事情实在太古怪，心里七上八下，拿不准主意，不禁瞟了萨拉一眼。

“可不是吗，”她说话的口气是自这孩子丧父之后从未有过的，“有人仁慈地对你。既然给你送来东西，以后穿破了还有新的，那就穿上吧，好显得体面些。换好衣服你就下楼到教室学习去。今天你就不必去办事了。”

约摸半小时后，教室的门开了，萨拉走了进去，教室里全体学生都惊得目瞪口呆。

“老天爷！”杰西不由喊出声来，直捅拉维尼亚的胳膊肘，“你瞧萨拉公主！”

大家都在打量她，拉维尼亚一见，脸孔涨得通红。

可不是，正是萨拉公主。至少现在的她比当年被看作是公主的时候更像公主了，和几小时前从后楼梯下来的那个萨拉判若两人。你看萨拉身上的那件连衣裙，正是拉维尼亚向来看着眼红的那种，浓浓的暖色，做工讲究。一双小腿还是过去杰西羡慕不已的那样纤细小巧。一头浓发用缎带挽在脑后，要是任其披散在独特的小脸四周，看起来就像设德兰群岛产的矮种马。

“没准哪个给她留下了一笔财产，”杰西悄声道，“我老想，她一准会遇上怪的事儿。她这人太怪了。”

“也许又突然冒出什么钻石矿来了？”拉维尼亚挖苦地说，“别这样盯着她看，美了她了，你这傻丫头。”

“萨拉，”明卿小姐那低沉的声音响起来，“进来吧，坐在这儿。”

全教室的孩子都睁大眼睛，相互捅胳膊肘，一时难以抑制自己的强烈好奇心。萨拉坐回到自己过去的荣誉席，头伏在书本上。

当天晚上，萨拉回到阁楼，和贝基一起吃过晚饭后，她在壁炉前坐下，严肃地打量着炉火。

“你脑瓜子里又在编什么故事了，小姐？”贝基崇敬地轻声问。每当萨拉一声不吭地坐着，以梦幻般的眼神望着炉火，这意味着她在编新的故事。但是这次她没有在编，她摇了摇头。

“没有，”她说，“我在想，应该怎么办。”

贝基凝视着她——仍然怀着崇敬的神情。她对萨拉的一言一行无不怀着近似崇拜之情。

“我禁不住想到我的那位朋友，”萨拉解释道，“要是他不愿意公开露面，想方设法找出他是哪个就有失礼貌了。我多么想让他知道，是他使我变得这么快活。心地善良的人使别人快活，也想知道对方是如何快活起来的。他们所关心的不是人家的感谢。我想——我真想——”

说到这里，没有说下去，因为这时她看到房角的桌子上有样东西。两天前她就在房子里发现这件东西了。这是只小小的文具盒，里面装着信纸、信封、钢笔和墨水。

“哦，”她喊道，“之前我怎么没想到呢？”

她说罢站起身，来到房角，拿起文具盒，回到壁炉前。

“我可以给他写信，”她高兴地说，“把写好的信留在桌子上。也许来收拾餐具的人会把信也拿走的。信里我不会问什么事的。我对他的一片感谢之意他肯定是不会介意的。”

于是她写了一封短信。信是这样写的：

您不愿意公开自己的身份，而我却要给您写信，希望您不要认为这是不礼貌的行为。请相信，我不想——我真的无意做个不礼貌的人，或试图打探什么事。我只想感谢您对我的关爱——天使般的关爱——使一切变得像童话故事般奇妙。我对您感激不尽，我自己也快乐无比——贝基也一样。贝基对您同样怀着深深的感激之情——和我一样，她也觉得这一切是多么的美好，多么的奇妙。在此之前我俩非常、非常孤单，受冻挨饿，而现在——哦，一想到您为我俩所做的一切，还能说什么呢？请允许我只说这几个字，我非说不可的几个字：谢谢您——谢谢您——谢谢您！

阁楼里的小女孩

第二天早晨，她把短信留在小桌子上。晚上，信与其他东西被拿走了。可见那魔法师已收到信了。萨拉想到此就觉得更高兴了。各自上床前，萨拉给贝基读了一本新收到的书，读着读着，她的注意力被天窗外的一个声音吸引过去。她的眼睛离开书本，抬头一看，贝基也听到那声响了，只见她转过身在看，紧张地听着。

“那边有啥东西，小姐。”她低声道。

“知道了。”萨拉慢慢答道，“听起来——很像猫——想钻进来。”

她离开椅子，来到天窗前。她听到的是挺怪挺轻的声音——像是抓挠声。她猛地想起了什么，不觉笑了起来。想起来了，一个怪东西，有一次闯到阁楼里来。就在那天下午，她看见那东西闷闷不乐地蹲在那印度绅士家窗前的桌子上。

“说不定，”她又高兴又激动地小声说，“说不定就是那只猴子又逃出来了。哦，但愿就是那只猴子！”

她爬上椅子，小心翼翼地拉起天窗，朝外张望。这天整天都下着雪，就在她附近的雪上，蹲着一只瘦小的身影，打着冷战，见到她，那只小黑脸就可怜巴巴地紧缩起来。

“是那猴子，”她失声喊了起来，“从那印度绅士家里跑出来，见到咱们的灯光就过来了。”

贝基急忙奔到她身旁。

“你让它进来，小姐？”她问。

“是的，”萨拉欢快地答道，“天太冷了，不能让猴子待在外面。猴子很娇嫩。让我哄他进来。”

萨拉小小心心伸出一只手，发出哄劝的声音，她往往用这种声音对麻雀和梅基塞代克说话——自己就好像是只友善的小动物，出于爱心，非常理解动物胆怯的天性。

“过来，亲爱的猴子，”她说，“我不会伤害你的。”

猴子知道她不会伤害自己。她把自己软软的小手放在它身上，边抚摸边朝自己拉过来。它就知道她不会伤害自己。它在拉姆·达斯那双细长、棕色的手中就感到人类的爱心，它在萨拉手中也有同样的感受。它让她把自己提起来，抱进天窗。后来它偎依在她胸口，友善地抓住她的一绺头发，抬头打量她。

“乖猴子！乖猴子！”她哼着，亲吻着那好玩的脑袋，“哦，我就喜爱小动物。”

显而易见，这猴子乐于挨近炉火。她坐了下来，把它抱在膝上。这时它看了看萨拉，又看了看贝基，那神情显得既好奇又感激。

“它的模样可不怎么样，小姐，你说是不是？”贝基说。

“看起来像个难看的小娃娃，”萨拉笑着说，“请不要生气，小猴子；你不是娃娃我才高兴哩。你娘，绝不会为你感到骄傲的，也不会有哪个敢说你长得像自己的哪个亲戚。哦，可我就是喜欢你！”

她说罢背靠椅子，陷入了沉思。

“也许他为自己长得丑而伤心吧，”她说，“他老是这么想。不知道他会不会动脑子？小猴子，宝贝，你会不会动脑子？”

可猴子只是举起爪子搔自己的脑袋。

“你打算拿它怎么办？”贝基问。

“今晚我让他跟我一起睡。明天把他送还给印度绅士。我舍不得送走你，小猴子。可你得走。你应该最爱自己的家。可我连一个真正的亲戚也没有。”

她睡前在自己的脚边给猴子做了一个窝。小猴子蜷起了身子，像个小娃娃，睡着了，对自己有这么个安身的地方感到高兴。

十七　“正是这孩子！”

第二天下午，“大家庭”的三个孩子坐在印度绅士书房里，变着法子逗印度绅士开心。他们是受到他的特别邀请，得到许可来执行这项使命的。最近一段时间，他一直在焦虑不安的状态下度过，今天更是急不可耐地等待着一件事。那就是卡迈克尔先生今天要从莫斯科回来了。卡迈克尔先生在那边待了一周又一周，迟迟回不来。他初到那里，找不到他要找的那一家人的踪迹，令他挺失望。最后他终于满有把握地找到了他们，去了他们的家，人家告诉他说，他们不在家，出门旅行去了。此行所作的种种努力眼看着要付诸东流，所以只好决定留在莫斯科，等着他们回来。卡里斯福特先生坐在他的躺椅上，珍妮特坐在他身旁的地板上。他非常喜欢珍妮特。诺拉找到了一条矮凳，唐纳德则骑在一个用来装饰虎皮地毯的虎头上。必须承认，他一摇一晃地骑着，真够野的。

“骑起马来别弄出这么大的声响来，唐纳德，”珍妮特说，“你这是来逗病人开心的，可不能扯着嗓子乱嚷嚷。是不是太闹了，卡里斯福特先生？”——这话是对印度绅士说的。

他拍拍她的肩。

“不闹，”他说，“这倒好，让我免得想得太多。”

“我这就一声不响了，”唐纳德嚷道，“咱们全像耗子，一声不吱。”

“耗子决不会像你那样乱嚷嚷的。”珍妮特说。

唐纳德用手绢当作缰绳，骑在虎头上一高一低地蹦着。

“来一大群耗子就有可能，”他高高兴兴地说，“上千只就有可能。”

“我相信就算来五万只也不行，”珍妮特板着脸说，“咱们都得像一只耗子，安安静静的。”

卡里斯福特先生笑开了，再次拍了拍她的肩。

“用不了多久爸爸就回来了，”她说，“咱们可不可以这就说说那失踪的小女孩？”

“这时候我恐怕不太有心情说别的事。”印度绅士皱起眉头，一脸倦意，说。

“我们都非常喜欢她，”诺拉说，“我们管她叫非童话里的公主。”

“为什么？”印度绅士问，因为“大家庭”的奇思妙想总让他一时不去想一些事。

回答他的是珍妮特。

“这是因为，虽然她现在还不是仙女，可找到她后，她就像童话中的公主，很富有。起初我们管她叫童话中的公主，可觉得不合适。”

“真的吗？”诺拉说，“她爸爸把钱全交给自己的朋友投到有钻石的矿里，后来他朋友以为钱全损失了，便逃跑了，因为他觉得自己简直成了强盗了，真的吗？”

“知道吗，事实上他不是这种人。”珍妮特急忙插言道。

印度绅士马上握住她的手。

“是的，他确实不是这种人。”他说。

“我为这个朋友感到难过，”珍妮特说，“我没法不难过。他没存心这样做，而且使他很伤心。我肯定会使他伤透心的。”

“你这孩子，小小年纪还挺善解人意呢，珍妮特。”印度绅士说着，把她的手握得更紧了。

“你有没有跟卡里斯福特先生说过，”唐纳德再次大声问，“说过那‘不是叫花子的小女孩’的事？有没有说过她已有了漂亮的新衣服？说不定她也丢失过，现在被人找到了。”

“马车来了！”珍妮特喊了起来，“在门前停下来了。是爸爸！”

大家都跑到窗口去看。

“是的，是爸爸，”唐纳德说，“可没见小女孩。”

三个孩子不由自主地跑出房间，争先恐后地涌进了大厅。他们总是以这样的方式来迎接自己父亲的。接着准能听到他们蹦蹦跳跳，拍着手，被抱起来亲吻。

卡里斯福特先生挣扎着想站起来，可还是跌进了椅子里。

“真没用，”他说，“我不成废人了吗？”

卡迈克尔先生的声音已近在门口了。

“不行，孩子们，”只听他说道，“我跟卡里斯福特先生谈过后你们再进来。去跟拉姆·达斯玩会儿。”

门开了，他走了进来。他的脸显得比原先更红润了，带来一股清新和健康的气息。但与病人急切询问的目光相遇时，甚至在他俩紧握手时，他的眼里透出失望和焦急的神色。

“有什么消息？”卡里斯福特先生问，“关于那个被俄国人收养的孩子？”

“她不是我们要找的孩子。”这便是卡迈克尔先生的回答，“她比克鲁上尉的女儿小很多。她叫爱米丽·卡柳。我见过她，跟她谈过话。那俄国夫妇提供出非常详细的材料。”

印度绅士这时候显得那么疲惫和痛苦！他的手从卡迈克尔先生手中滑了下来。

“如此说来还得重新开始寻访，”他说，“就这样吧，请坐。”

卡迈克尔先生坐了下来。不知不觉间他已渐渐喜欢上这不幸的人了。他本人身体健康，生活幸福，生活在欢乐和关爱之中，所以在他看来孤独与病痛越发显得悲惨而难以承受了。房子里只要响起一个孩子尖细、欢乐的嗓音，就不会如此凄凉酸楚；一个人若是心事重重，始终觉得自己做错了事，害得一个孩子无家可归，这确实是一件无法面对的惨事。

“好了，好了，”他用一种愉快的声音说道，“找到她还是有希望的。”

“必须马上动手找，刻不容缓。”卡里斯福特先生焦急地说，“你有什么新的建议吗?——什么样的建议都行。”

卡迈克尔先生显得有些心神不宁，站起来在房间里踱来踱去，脸上显出一副若有所思、犹豫不决的神情。

“这个，也许，”他说，“我拿不准这值不值得。是这么回事，我在从多佛回来的火车上思前想后，突然产生这么一个想法。”

“什么想法？只要她还在人世，她必定在某个地方。”

“不错，她是在某个地方。我们已经找过巴黎的所有学校。巴黎就不去找了，那就开始在伦敦找。我的想法就是——在伦敦找。”

“伦敦有不少这类学校。”卡里斯福特先生说。这时他心头一动，想起了一件事，“可不是，隔壁就有一所。”

“那就从那儿开始。这么做最方便不过了。”

“说的是，”卡里斯福特先生说，“那儿有个孩子引起了我的注意。不过她不是学生，是个肤色黝黑、孤苦无依的孩子。这个可怜的小姑娘跟克鲁一点也不像。”

也许此时此刻魔法又显灵了——可真是魔力无边。看来确实如此。倒是什么让拉姆·达斯在这个时候想到要进房间来——甚至是在东家正和别人说话的时候？只见他进了房间，毕恭毕敬行了个额手礼，乌黑发亮的眼睛闪着无法掩饰的兴奋光芒。

“老爷，”他说，“那孩子本人来了——就是老爷可怜的那个孩子。她是送猴子来的。猴子又跑到她的阁楼里去了。我让她别走。我寻思让她见见老爷，跟你老说说话儿，兴许让你高兴高兴。”

“她是谁？”卡迈克尔先生问。

“天知道，”卡里斯福特先生说，“她就是刚才我说的那个孩子。那个学校里的小苦力。”他向拉姆·达斯摆摆手，对他说，“不错，我是想见见她。让她进来吧。”他转而对卡迈克尔先生说，“你远行时，”他大声道，“我陷入了绝望的境地，只觉得度日如年，眼前一片黑暗。拉姆·达斯对我说起这不幸的孩子，于是我们两人就想出一个颇具浪漫色彩的计划准备帮一帮她。我觉得这虽是件略带孩子气的事情，却让我有所作为，也可分心旁事。不过若没有拉姆·达斯这么一个身手轻捷、机敏灵活的东方人帮助，这事万万办不成。”

说话间，萨拉进了房间。她双手抱着猴子。显然，猴子对她恋恋不舍，紧紧缠着她，叽里咕噜个不停。萨拉有机会置身印度绅士的房间，很是新奇，兴奋得两颊绯红。

“您的猴子又跑出来了，”她说，嗓音甜甜的，“昨晚他到了我阁楼的天窗前，天太冷了，我把他抱了进去。要不是天太晚了，当晚我准送他回来的。我知道您身体有恙，也许不愿有人打扰。”

印度绅士那深陷的眼睛露出好奇的目光，饶有兴趣地打量着她。

“你想得很周到。”他说。

萨拉看了站在门口的拉姆·达斯一眼。

“我这就把猴子交给拉斯卡，好吗？”她问。

“你怎么知道他是拉斯卡？”印度绅士微微一笑，反问道。

“哦，我认得出拉斯卡，”她说着把那只老大不情愿的猴子递过去，“我生在印度。”

冷不防地，印度绅士直直地坐了起来，表情起了很大的变化，把萨拉吓了一跳。

“你生在印度，”他大声道，“是吗？过来。”他说着伸出自己的手。

萨拉到了他跟前，把手放到他的手中，他像是很愿意握她的手。她静静地站着，她那灰绿色的眼睛惊讶地与他的眼睛相遇。他似乎有什么触动。

“你住在隔壁？”他问。

“是的。我待在明卿小姐的寄宿学校里。”

“你不是她的学生？”

萨拉的嘴角露出一丝怪怪的笑意。她犹豫了片刻。

“我不知道自己到底是什么身份。”她答道。

“为什么？”

“最初，我是学生，是个特殊的学生。可现在——”

“过去你是学生！那么现在呢？”

萨拉的嘴角又浮现出怪怪的、忧伤的微笑。

“我睡在阁楼里，与在厨房打杂的小工为邻。”她说，“我为厨娘跑腿——她吩咐的事我全要干。我还要给年龄小的孩子上课。”

“你来问她，卡迈克尔。”卡里斯福特先生又跌坐回椅子，仿佛已精疲力竭了，“你来问。我问不下去了。”

“大家庭”里高大、慈祥的父亲懂得如何来问小姑娘。萨拉听到他那悦耳而鼓励人的声音，便知道他在这方面很有经验。

“你刚才说的‘最初’是什么意思，我的孩子？”他问。

“指的是我爸爸最初带我来学校的时候。”

“你爸爸现在在哪儿？”

“他去世了，”萨拉非常镇静地说，“他的钱全没了，没给我留下一分一毫。再也没人照料我，没人给明卿小姐付我的费用了。”

“卡迈克尔！”印度绅士高声喊了起来，“卡迈克尔！”

“我们不能吓着她。”卡迈克尔先生急忙侧身对印度绅士低声说，然后又大声对萨拉说起来，“因此他们就打发你住在阁楼里，让你去干杂活了。是这样吗？”

“没人照料我，”萨拉说，“我也没钱，是个没人要的孩子。”

“你父亲的钱是怎么失去的？”印度绅士喘着粗气，插言问道。

“不是他自己丢掉的，”萨拉说，她越来越感到好奇了，“他有个非常要好的朋友——他非常喜欢这个朋友。就是这个朋友拿走了他的钱。他太相信这个朋友了。”

印度绅士的呼吸更急促了。

“他的朋友可能不是存心想伤害他，”他说，“也许是出于误会造成的。”

萨拉并不知道，自己那稚气的声音、平静的回答深深地刺痛了对方的心。若是她知道了，肯定会为印度绅士着想，说得柔和一些。

“结果还是带来了苦难，”她说，“害死了我爸爸。”

“你爸爸叫什么名字？”印度绅士问，“告诉我吧。”

“他叫拉尔夫·克鲁，”萨拉答道，她感到很惊讶，“克鲁上尉。他死在印度。”

那张憔悴的面孔抽搐起来，拉姆·达斯赶紧跑到东家身旁。

“卡迈克尔！”病人气喘吁吁道，“正是这孩子——这孩子！”

一时间萨拉以为他快要死了。拉姆·达斯从一只瓶子里倒出几滴药水，送到东家嘴边。萨拉立在附近，身子有些哆嗦。她迷惑地看着卡迈克尔先生。

“我是哪个？”她结结巴巴地问。

“他就是你父亲的那个朋友，”卡迈克尔答道，“别害怕。我们已找了你两年了。”

萨拉把一只手放到额头上，她的嘴巴抖动起来。她像是在梦中，说了起来。

“我一直在明卿小姐寄宿学校里。”她像是在轻声耳语，“就在墙的那一边。”

十九　“安妮”

“大家庭”的儿童室里洋溢着前所未有的欢快气氛。他们做梦也没想到与“不是叫花子的小姑娘”亲密相识，会如此高兴。单是她的苦难和遭遇就使她成了无价之宝。人人都想一而再、再而三地听她讲述自己的经历。当你坐在明亮而宽敞的房间里温暖的炉火旁，听别人讲阁楼里彻骨的寒冷时，肯定是件莫大的乐事。必须承认，这间阁楼已成了大家乐于一去的地方了，每当你想起梅基塞代克，每当你爬上桌子，从天窗探出脑袋和肩膀，就听到麻雀的鸣叫，看到种种景色，阁楼里的寒冷和空荡荡的情景就显得微不足道了。

自然啰，最爱听的就是那次宴会和那梦想成真的故事了。萨拉被找到后的第二天，她第一次讲了这件事。“大家庭”的几名成员过来与她一起用茶。他们在壁炉前的地毯上或坐或蹲，萨拉就以她独特的方式讲了这事，印度绅士静静地听着。讲完后她就抬头看了看他，把自己的一只手放到他的膝盖上。

“这是我的那一部分故事，”她说，“现在你能不能讲讲你这方面呢，汤姆叔叔？”此前他要她一直唤自己“汤姆叔叔”，“我还不知道你是怎么做的呢，一准很好听的。”

于是他讲了，当自己在孤单地独坐时，身体有病，心情烦闷，脾气暴躁，拉姆·达斯给他讲过路人的事，以排遣烦恼，说有个孩子比别人更频繁地从窗前走过，这引起了他的兴趣——部分原因也许是他非常思念一个小女孩，部分是因为拉姆·达斯讲了他追逃跑的猴子到过阁楼的事。拉姆·达斯给他形象地讲了阁楼凄惨的情景和那孩子的举止，说她的身份不像是个做苦工的，可被当成苦力和女仆使唤了。拉姆·达斯慢慢地发现，她生活得十分悲惨。他发现从屋顶爬了几码就很容易到那天窗，从此引发了后来发生的事。

“老爷，”有一次他说，“在女孩子外出办事时，我可以爬过石板瓦，给她把炉子生起来。她回来看到炉火旺旺的，还以为是魔术师干的呢。”

卡里斯福特先生觉得这主意挺新奇，乐得愁云密布的脸上也露出灿烂的笑容来，拉姆·达斯更是心花怒放，进一步告诉东家说，再多做一些其他事也是不费吹灰之力的。他流露出小孩子般的快乐和想象力。他为实现自己的计划做了好几天的准备，原本是枯燥乏味的日子也变得生趣盎然了。就在举行那个惨遭破坏的宴会的晚上，拉姆·达斯始终密切注视着阁楼里的情况，所有准备送去的东西都放在他自己的阁楼里，他的助手也跟他一起等待机会，跟他一样，对这一古怪的历险也很有兴趣。拉姆·达斯身子一直趴在石板瓦上，注意天窗里的情况，直到宴会遭到灾难性的结局；他相信，萨拉已是精疲力竭，睡起来一定很沉。后来他带着遮光灯爬进了阁楼，他的助手则待在外面，把东西递给他。每遇到萨拉身子轻轻动了动，拉姆·达斯就关上遮光灯，身子直直地趴到地板上。以上及其他种种令人激动的情况都是经孩子们千百次的询问后才知道的。

“我太高兴了，”萨拉说，“我实在太高兴了，我的朋友原来就是你！”

从未有过这么好的一对朋友。不知怎么的，两个人出奇地投缘。印度绅士从来没有像喜欢萨拉那样喜欢过别的人。正如卡迈克尔先生预言的那样，不出一个月，卡里斯福特先生就换了个人似的。他整天乐呵呵的，兴致勃勃，过去他把财产看作是烦人的负担，如今发现那也是一大乐趣。他打算为萨拉做很多很多美妙的事。两个人开过小小的玩笑，他说自己是魔术师，为萨拉做些令她感到意外的事也成了他的一大乐趣。从此萨拉发现自己的房间里出现怒放的美丽鲜花，枕头下藏着稀奇古怪的小礼物。有一次傍晚，两个人在一起时，听到门上响起重重的爪子抓挠声，萨拉开门一看，原来外面立着一只大狗——一只漂亮的俄罗斯猎犬——挂着金银项圈，上面有凸起的文字。“我是鲍里斯，”上面写道，“专来伺候萨拉公主。”

印度绅士最爱回忆衣衫褴褛时的那位小公主。与“大家庭”或埃芒加德欢聚的下午往往是非常快乐的。但是萨拉和印度绅士独坐读书、谈天的时光，更有其独特的魅力。随着时光的流逝，发生了许多有趣的事。

一天傍晚，卡里斯福特先生从书本上抬起头来，发现自己的伙伴好一会儿身子一动不动，呆呆地凝视着炉火。

“你在‘假设’什么，萨拉？”他问。

萨拉抬起头，脸颊红通通的。

“我在想，”她说，“我在回忆那些挨饿的日子，想起一个我见过的孩子。”

“可你有过不少挨饿的日子，”印度绅士道，声调相当感伤，“到底是哪一天？”

“我忘了你还不知道呢。”萨拉说，“就是我梦想成真的那一天。”

于是她把面包铺的事说给他听，说到自己如何在泥浆里拾到四便士硬币，说到比自己还要饿的那个孩子。她说得很简单，只是寥寥数语。但是不知怎么的，印度绅士听了不觉用手掩住眼睛，垂下了头。

“我刚设想了一个计划，”讲完了这件事，最后她说，“我想我该做点事了。”

“什么事？”卡里斯福特先生低声问，“你想做什么都可以去做，公主。”

“我想，”萨拉有些拿不定主意，“你说，我有许多钱——我想能不能去见见那面包铺的老板娘，跟她说，如果挨饿的孩子——特别是遇到坏天气——到她家门前台阶上，或眼看着橱窗，她能不能把他们叫进去，给他们些吃的，费用可以由我来支付。我可以这么做吗？”

“明天早晨就可以去做。”印度绅士说。

“谢谢你，”萨拉说，“我懂挨饿的滋味，到了连‘假装’也假装不了时候，那日子真是太难受了。”

“是的，是的，宝贝，”印度绅士说，“是这样，是这样，一定是这样。设法忘了吧。过来，坐在我膝旁的小矮凳上，只记住你是位公主。”

“好，”萨拉笑着说，“我现在可以给平民百姓送各种面包了。”她说罢坐到小矮凳上，印度绅士（有时候他也喜欢她这样称呼自己）拉过她那满头黑发的小脑袋，靠在自己的膝盖上，抚摸着她的黑发。

第二天早晨，明卿小姐朝窗外张望时，看见了一件最不愿意看见的事。几匹高头大马拉着印度绅士的马车驶到隔壁家的大门前停下来，房主人和一个小孩子的身影，穿着暖和、柔软而艳丽的皮大衣，下了台阶，进了车。那小身影挺眼熟，使明卿小姐想起过去的一些日子。这个小孩子的身后还跟着一个人，也是挺眼熟的——一见就叫她生气。那小孩是贝基，看样子是名跟班，高高兴兴地总陪着小主人上下车，帮她拎包包，拿东西。贝基的脸蛋儿早已变得滚圆、红润了。

不一会儿，马车到了那面包铺的门前，车里的人下了车，你道怪不怪，就在这时候面包铺的老板娘正好也端着一盘热腾腾的小圆面包准备放进橱窗。

萨拉进了店，老板娘回头看了她一眼，放下面包，来到柜台后。她细细盯着萨拉看了看，那张善良的面孔容光焕发起来。

“我肯定记得你，小姐。”她说，“可——”

“不错，”萨拉说，“有一次我付了四便士，你给了我六便士的面包，并且——”

“可你把其中的五个给了小叫花子，”女老板打断了萨拉的话头，说，“我一直记得这件事。开始我还不明白到底是怎么一回事。”她转身对印度绅士，说了下面一段话，“我请你原谅，先生，关心挨饿小孩儿的年轻人可不多见。这事儿我想了好久。请不要见怪我说话放肆，小姐——”她转而对萨拉说，“如今您脸蛋儿红润多了——得，健康多了——比起——比起——”

“我是健康多了，谢谢你，”萨拉说，“而且也快活多了——我来是请你为我办件事。”

“要我，小姐！”老板娘开心地笑着，大声道，“老天爷，倒是什么事，小姐？”

萨拉背靠柜台讲了自己有关坏天气为饥饿的流浪儿提供热面包的小小建议。

女老板眼望着她，一脸吃惊的神色。

“唉哟哟，老天爷！”她听罢说道，“这种事要我干没说的。我自己是个干活的，太多的是没那个本钱，要说难处到处都有。不过不怕你笑话，自打那个湿淋淋的下午以后，我施舍了不少面包，都是想到你的缘故——那时瞧你浑身湿透，又冷又饿，可你把自己的热面包给了别人，活像个公主。”

印度绅士听了禁不住笑了，萨拉想起了自己把小圆面包放到饥肠辘辘的小孩裹着破布的膝盖上时说的话，也微微露出了笑容。

“她看上去饿极了，”她说，“甚至比我还饿。”

“她确实饿坏了，”老板娘说，“好多次，风雨天她坐在那儿，跟我说过，像是有条饿狼在撕咬她的幼小的五脏六腑。”

“哦，自那以后你见过她吗？”萨拉大声问，“你知道她在哪儿吗？”

“知道，知道，”女老板笑道，显得越发善良了，“这不，她就在后间，小姐，她来了都一个月了。她会出落成个不错的好孩子的。她可成了我店里厨房的好帮手哩。简直不会相信她以前过的是什么日子。”

她说罢走到后间的门前，说了句什么话，很快一个小女孩走了出来，跟着她到了柜台后。她确是那个小叫花子，穿得干干净净、整整齐齐的，看起来不像是个长期挨过饿的。她有点害羞，可脸蛋儿挺可人的，既然不再过流浪的生活了，眼神里的那股野性也不见了。她一下子就认出萨拉来，站在那儿一个劲朝萨拉看，好像看不够似的。

“你瞧，”老板娘说，“当时我跟她说，要是饿了就上我这儿来，她一来我就让她干点零活。看得出她倒乐意，我也就慢慢喜欢上她了，最后我就让她干点活，给她一个住处。她做了我的帮手，表现得挺不错，小小的年纪，还懂得知恩图报呢。她叫安妮。不知道姓什么。”

两个孩子好一会儿站着你望我、我望你。最后萨拉把手从暖手筒里抽出来，伸过柜台，安妮接住握起来，两双眼睛紧紧地对视起来。

“我太高兴了，”萨拉说，“我刚想到一个主意。也许布朗太太让你负责给小孩子分发面包。也许你喜欢做这件事，因为你懂得挨饿的滋味。”

“是的，小姐。”小姑娘说。

不知怎么的，萨拉觉得小姑娘是了解自己的，虽然对方话没说几句，只是一声不吭站着打量自己，最后看着自己和印度绅士走出店铺，上了马车，离开了。

CHAPTER Ⅵ　THE DIAMOND - MINES

NOT very long after this a very exciting thing happened. Not only Sara, but the entire school, found it exciting, and made it the chief subject of conversation for weeks after it occurred. In one of his letters Captain Crewe told a most interesting story. A friend who had been at school with him when he was a boy had unexpectedly come to see him in India. He was the owner of a large tract of land upon which diamonds had been found, and he was engaged in developing the mines. If all went as was confidently expected, he would become possessed of such wealth as it made one dizzy to think of; and because he was fond of the friend of his school - days, he had given him an opportunity to share in this enormous fortune by becoming a partner in his scheme. This, at least, was what Sara gathered from his letters. It is true that any other business scheme, however magnificent, would have had but small attraction for her or for the schoolroom; but " Diamond - mines " sounded so like the " Arabian Nights " that no one could be indifferent. Sara thought them enchanting, and painted pictures, for Ermengarde and Lottie, of labyrinthine passages in the bowels of the earth, where sparkling stones studded the walls and roofs and ceilings, and strange, dark men dug them out with heavy picks. Ermengarde delighted in the story, and Lottie insisted on its being retold to her every evening. Lavinia was very spiteful about it, and told Jessie that she didn' t believe such things as diamond - mines existed.

" My mamma has a diamond ring which cost forty pounds, " she said. " And it is not a big one, either. If there were mines full of diamonds, people would be so rich it would be ridiculous. "

" Perhaps Sara will be so rich that she will be ridiculous, " giggled Jessie.

" She's ridiculous without being rich, " Lavinia sniffed.

" I believe you hate her, " said Jessie.

" No, I don' t, " snapped Lavinia. " But I don' t believe in mines full of diamonds. "

" Well, people have to get them from somewhere, " said Jessie. " Lavinia, " - with a new giggle - " What do you think Gertrude says? "

" I don' t know, I' m sure; and I don' t care if it's something more about that everlasting Sara. "

" Well, it is. One of her' pretends' is that she is a princess. She plays it all the time - even in school. She says it makes her learn her lessons better. She wants Ermengarde to be one, too, but Ermengarde says she is too fat. "

" She is too fat, " said Lavinia. " And Sara is too thin. "

Naturally, Jessie giggled again.

" She says it has nothing to do with what you look like, or what you have. It has only to do with what you THINK of, and what you DO. "

" I suppose she thinks she could be a princess if she was a beggar, " said Lavinia. " Let us begin to call her Your Royal Highness. "

Lessons for the day were over, and they were sitting before the schoolroom fire, enjoying the time they liked best. It was the time when Miss Minchin and Miss Amelia were taking their tea in the sitting - room sacred to themselves. At this hour a great deal of talking was done, and a great many secrets changed hands, particularly if the younger pupils behaved themselves well, and did not squabble or run about noisily, which it must be confessed they usually did. When they made an uproar the older girls usually interfered with scoldings and shakes. They were expected to keep order, and there was danger that if they did not. Miss Minchin or Miss Amelia would appear and put an end to festivities. Even as Lavinia spoke the door opened and Sara entered with Lottie, whose habit was to trot everywhere after her like a little dog.

" There she is, with that horrid child! " exclaimed Lavinia, in a whisper. " If she's so fond of her, why doesn' t she keep her in her own room? She will begin howling about something in five minutes. "

It happened that Lottie had been seized with a sudden desire to play in the schoolroom, and had begged her adopted parent to come with her. She joined a group of little ones who were playing in a corner. Sara curled herself up in the window - seat, opened a book, and began to read. It was a book about the French Revolution, and she was soon lost in a harrowing picture of the prisoners in the Bastille - men who had spent so many years in dungeons that when they were dragged out by those who rescued them, their long, gray hair and beards almost hid their faces, and they had forgotten that an outside world existed at all, and were like beings in a dream.

She was so far away from the schoolroom that it was not agreeable to be dragged back suddenly by a howl from Lottie. Never did she find anything so difficult as to keep herself from losing her temper when she was suddenly disturbed while absorbed in a book. People who are fond of books know the feeling of irritation which sweeps over them at such a moment. The temptation to be unreasonable and snappish is one not easy to manage.

" It makes me feel as if someone had hit me, " Sara had told Ermengarde once in confidence. " And as if I want to hit back. I have to remember things quickly to keep from saying something ill - tempered. "

She had to remember things quickly when she laid her book on the window - seat and jumped down from her comfortable corner.

Lottie had been sliding across the schoolroom floor, and, having first irritated Lavinia and Jessie by making a noise, had ended by falling down and hurting her fat knee. She was screaming and dancing up and down in the midst of a group of friends and enemies, who were alternately coaxing and scolding her.

" Stop this minute, you cry - baby! Stop this minute! " Lavinia commanded.

" I' m not a cry - baby - I' m not! " wailed Lottie. " Sara, Sa - ra! "

" If she doesn' t stop. Miss Minchin will hear her, " cried Jessie. " Lottie darling, I' ll give you a penny! "

" I don' t want your penny, " sobbed Lottie; and she looked down at the fat knee, and, seeing a drop of blood on it, burst forth again.

Sara flew across the room and, kneeling down, put her arms round her.

" Now, Lottie, " she said. " Now, Lottie, you PROMISED Sara. "

" She said I was a cry - baby, " wept Lottie.

Sara patted her, but spoke in the steady voice Lottie knew.

" But if you cry, you will be one, Lottie pet. You PROMISED. "

Lottie remembered that she had promised, but she preferred to lift up her voice.

" I haven' t any mamma, " she proclaimed. " I haven' t - a bit - of mamma. "

" Yes, you have, " said Sara, cheerfully. " Have you forgotten? Don' t you know that Sara is your mamma? Don' t you want Sara for your mamma? "

Lottie cuddled up to her with a consoled sniff.

" Come and sit in the window - seat with me, " Sara went on, " And I' ll whisper a story to you. "

" Will you? " whimpered Lottie. " Will you - tell me - about the diamond - mines? "

" The diamond - mines? " broke out Lavinia. " Nasty, little spoiled thing, I should like to SLAP her! "

Sara got up quickly on her feet. It must be remembered that she had been very deeply absorbed in the book about the Bastille, and she had had to recall several things rapidly when she realized that she must go and take care of her adopted child. She was not an angel, and she was not fond of Lavinia.

" Well, " she said, with some fire, " I should like to slap YOU - but I don' t want to slap you! " restraining herself. " At least I both want to slap you - and I should LIKE to slap you - but I WON' T slap you. We are not little gutter children. We are both old enough to know better. "

Here was Lavinia's opportunity.

" Ah, yes, your royal highness, " she said. " We are princesses, I believe. At least one of us is. The school ought to be very fashionable now Miss Minchin has a princess for a pupil. "

Sara started toward her. She looked as if she were going to box her ears. Perhaps she was. Her trick of pretending things was the joy of her life. She never spoke of it to girls she was not fond of. Her new " Pretend " about being a princess was very near to her heart, and she was shy and sensitive about it. She had meant it to be rather a secret, and here was Lavinia deriding it before nearly all the school. She felt the blood rush up into her face and tingle in her ears. She only just saved herself. If you were a princess, you did not fly into rages. Her hand dropped, and she stood quite still a moment. When she spoke it was in a quiet, steady voice; she held her head up, and everybody listened to her.

" It's true, " she said. " Sometimes I do pretend I am a princess. I pretend I am a princess, so that I can try and behave like one. "

Lavinia could not think of exactly the right thing to say. Several times she had found that she could not think of a satisfactory reply when she was dealing with Sara. The reason of this was that, somehow, the rest always seemed to be vaguely in sympathy with her opponent. She saw now that they were pricking up their ears interestedly. The truth was, they liked princesses, and they all hoped they might hear something more definite about this one, and drew nearer Sara accordingly.

Lavinia could only invent one remark, and it fell rather flat.

" Dear me! " she said; " I hope, when you ascend the throne, you won' t forget us. "

" I won' t, " said Sara, and she did not utter another word, but stood quite still, and stared at her steadily as she saw her take Jessie's arm and turn away.

After this, the girls who were jealous of her used to speak of her as " Princess Sara " whenever they wished to be particularly disdainful, and those who were fond of her gave her the name among themselves as a term of affection. No one called her " Princess " instead of " Sara, " but her adorers were much pleased with the picturesqueness and grandeur of the title, and Miss Minchin, hearing of it, mentioned it more than once to visiting parents, feeling that it rather suggested a sort of royal boarding - school.

To Becky it seemed the most appropriate thing in the world. The acquaintance begun on the foggy afternoon when she had jumped up terrified from her sleep in the comfortable chair, had ripened and grown, though it must be confessed that Miss Minchin and Miss Amelia knew very little about it. They were aware that Sara was " kind " to the scullery - maid, but they knew nothing of certain delightful moments snatched perilously when, the upstairs rooms being set in order with lightning rapidity, Sara's sitting - room was reached, and the heavy coalbox set down with a sigh of joy. At such times stories were told by installments, things of a satisfying nature were either produced and eaten or hastily tucked into pockets to be disposed of at night, when Becky went upstairs to her attic to bed.

" But I has to eat' em careful, miss, " she said once; " ' cos if I leaves crumbs the rats come out to get' em. "

" Rats! " exclaimed Sara, in horror. " Are there rats there? "

" Lots of' em, miss, " Becky answered in quite a matter - of - fact manner. " There mostly is rats an' mice in attics. You gets used to the noise they makes scuttling about. I' ve got so I don' t mind' em s' long as they don' t run over my piller. "

" Ugh! " Said Sara.

" You gets used to anythin' after a bit, " said Becky. " You have to, miss, if you' re born a scullery - maid. I' d rather have rats than cockroaches. "

" So would I, " said Sara; " I suppose you might make friends with a rat in time, but I don' t believe I should like to make friends with a cockroach. "

Sometimes Becky did not dare to spend more than a few minutes in the bright, warm room, and when this was the case perhaps only a few words could be exchanged, and a small purchase slipped into the old - fashioned pocket Becky carried under her dress skirt, tied round her waist with a band of tape. The search for and discovery of satisfying things to eat which could be packed into small compass, added a new interest to Sara's existence. When she drove or walked out, she used to look into shop windows eagerly. The first time it occurred to her to bring home two or three little meat pies, she felt that she had hit upon a discovery. When she exhibited them, Becky's eyes quite sparkled.

" Oh, miss! " she murmured. " Them will be nice an' fillin' . It's fillin' ness that's best. Sponge - cake's a' evenly thing, but it melts away like - if you understand, miss. These' ll just STAY in yer stummick. "

" Well, " hesitated Sara, " I don' t think it would be good if they stayed always, but I do believe they will be satisfying. "

They were satisfying - and so were beef sandwiches, bought at a cook - shop - and so were rolls and Bologna sausage. In time, Becky began to lose her hungry, tired feeling, and the coalbox did not seem so unbearably heavy.

However heavy it was, and whatsoever the temper of the cook, and the hardness of the work heaped upon her shoulders, she had always the chance of the afternoon to look forward to - the chance that Miss Sara would be able to be in her sitting - room. In fact, the mere seeing of Miss Sara would have been enough without meat pies. If there was time only for a few words, they were always friendly, merry words that put heart into one; and if there was time for more, then there was an installment of a story to be told, or some other thing one remembered afterward and sometimes lay awake in one's bed in the attic to think over. Sara - who was only doing what she unconsciously liked better than anything else, Nature having made her for a giver - had not the least idea what she meant to poor Becky, and how wonderful a benefactor she seemed. If Nature has made you for a giver, your hands are born open, and so is your heart; and though there may be times when your hands are empty, your heart is always full, and you can give things out of that - warm things, kind things, sweet things - help and comfort and laughter - and sometimes gay, kind laughter is the best help of all.

Becky had scarcely known what laughter was through all her poor, little hard - driven life. Sara made her laugh, and laughed with her; and, though neither of them quite knew it, the laughter was as " fillin' " as the meat pies.

A few weeks before Sara's eleventh birthday a letter came to her from her father, which did not seem to be written in such boyish high spirits as usual. He was not very well, and was evidently overweighted by the business connected with the diamond - mines.

" You see, little Sara, " he wrote, " Your daddy is not a businessman at all, and figures and documents bother him. He does not really understand them, and all this seems so enormous. Perhaps, if I was not feverish I should not be awake, tossing about, one half of the night and spend the other half in troublesome dreams. If my little missus were here, I dare say she would give me some solemn, good advice. You would, wouldn' t you, little missus? "

One of his many jokes had been to call her his " little missus " because she had such an old - fashioned air. He had made wonderful preparations for her birthday. Among other things, a new doll had been ordered in Paris, and her wardrobe was to be, indeed, a marvel of splendid perfection. When she had replied to the letter asking her if the doll would be an acceptable present, Sara had been very quaint.

" I am getting very old, " she wrote; " You see, I shall never live to have another doll given me. This will be my last doll. There is something solemn about it. If I could write poetry, I am sure a poem about' A Last Doll' would be very nice. But I cannot write poetry. I have tried, and it made me laugh. It did not sound like Watts or Coleridge or Shakespeare at all. No one could ever take Emily's place, but I should respect the Last Doll very much; and I am sure the school would love it. They all like dolls, though some of the big ones - the almost fifteen ones - pretend they are too grown up. "

Captain Crewe had a splitting headache when he read this letter in his bungalow in India. The table before him was heaped with papers and letters which were alarming him and filling him with anxious dread, but he laughed as he had not laughed for weeks.

" Oh, " he said, " She's better fun every year she lives. God grant this business may right itself and leave me free to run home and see her. What wouldn' t I give to have her little arms round my neck this minute! What WOULDN' T I give! "

The birthday was to be celebrated by great festivities. The schoolroom was to be decorated, and there was to be a party. The boxes containing the presents were to be opened with great ceremony, and there was to be a glittering feast spread in Miss Minchin's sacred room. When the day arrived the whole house was in a whirl of excitement. How the morning passed nobody quite knew, because there seemed such preparations to be made. The schoolroom was being decked with garlands of holly; the desks had been moved away, and red covers had been put on the forms which were arrayed round the room against the wall.

When Sara went into her sitting - room in the morning, she found on the table a small, dumpy package, tied up in a piece of brown paper. She knew it was a present, and she thought she could guess whom it came from. She opened it quite tenderly. It was a square pincushion, made of not quite clean red flannel, and black pins had been stuck carefully into it to form the words, " Menny hapy returns. "

" Oh! " cried Sara, with a warm feeling in her heart. " What pains she has taken! I like it so, it - it makes me feel sorrowful. "

But the next moment she was mystified. On the under side of the pincushion was secured a card, bearing in neat letters the name " Miss Amelia Minchin. "

Sara turned it over and over.

" Miss Amelia! " she said to herself. " How CAN it be! "

And just at that very moment she heard the door being cautiously pushed open and saw Becky peeping round it. There was an affectionate, happy grin on her face, and she shuffled forward and stood nervously pulling at her fingers.

" Do yer like it, Miss Sara? " she said. " Do yer? "

" Like it? " cried Sara. " You darling Becky, you made it all yourself. "

Becky gave a hysteric but joyful sniff, and her eyes looked quite moist with delight.

" It ain' t nothin' but flannin, an' the flannin ain' t new; but I wanted to give yer somethin' an' I made it of nights. I knew yer could PRETEND it was satin with diamond pins in. I tried to when I was makin' it. The card, miss, " rather doubtfully; " ' t warn' t wrong of me to pick it up out o' the dust - bin, was it? Miss' Meliar had throwed it away. I hadn' t no card o' my own, an' I knowed it wouldn' t be a proper presink if I didn' t pin a card on - so I pinned Miss' Meliar's. "

Sara flew at her and hugged her. She could not have told herself or anyone else why there was a lump in her throat.

" Oh, Becky! " she cried out, with a queer little laugh. " I love you, Becky - I do, I do! "

" Oh, miss! " breathed Becky. " Thank yer, miss, kindly; It ain' t good enough for that. The - the flannin wasn' t new. "

CHAPTER ⅩⅢ　ONE OF THE POPULACE

THE winter was a wretched one. There were days on which Sara tramped through snow when she went on her errands; there were worse days when the snow melted and combined itself with mud to form slush; there were others when the fog was so thick that the lamps in the street were lighted all day and London looked as it had looked the afternoon, several years ago, when the cab had driven through the thoroughfares with Sara tucked up on its seat, leaning against her father's shoulder. On such days the windows of the house of the Large Family always looked delightfully cozy and alluring, and the study in which the Indian gentleman sat glowed with warmth and rich color. But the attic was dismal beyond words. There were no longer sunsets or sunrises to look at, and scarcely ever any stars, it seemed to Sara. The clouds hung low over the skylight and were either gray or mud - color, or dropping heavy rain. At four o' clock in the afternoon, even when there was no special fog, the daylight was at an end. If it was necessary to go to her attic for anything, Sara was obliged to light a candle. The women in the kitchen were depressed, and that made them more ill - tempered than ever. Becky was driven like a little slave.

" ' Twarn' t for you, miss, " she said hoarsely to Sara one night when she had crept into the attic - " ' Twarn' t for you, an' the Bastille, an' bein' the prisoner in the next cell, I should die. That there does seem real now, doesn' t it? The missus is more like the head jailer every day she lives. I can jest see them big keys you say she carries. The cook she's like one of the under - jailers. Tell me some more, please, miss - tell me about the subt' ranean passage we' ve dug under the walls. "

" I' ll tell you something warmer, " shivered Sara. " Get your coverlet and wrap it round you, and I' ll get mine, and we will huddle close together on the bed, and I' ll tell you about the tropical forest where the Indian gentleman's monkey used to live. When I see him sitting on the table near the window and looking out into the street with that mournful expression, I always feel sure he is thinking about the tropical forest where he used to swing by his tail from coconut - trees. I wonder who caught him, and if he left a family behind who had depended on him for coconuts. "

" That is warmer, miss, " said Becky, gratefully; " But, someways, even the Bastille is sort of heatin' when you gets to tellin' about it. "

" That is because it makes you think of something else, " said Sara, wrapping the coverlet round her until only her small dark face was to be seen looking out of it. " I' ve noticed this. What you have to do with your mind, when your body is miserable, is to make it think of something else. "

" Can you do it, miss? " faltered Becky, regarding her with admiring eyes.

Sara knitted her brows a moment.

" Sometimes I can and sometimes I can' t, " she said stoutly. " But when I CAN I' m all right. And what I believe is that we always could - if we practised enough. I' ve been practising a good deal lately, and it's beginning to be easier than it used to be. When things are horrible - just horrible - I think as hard as ever I can of being a princess. I say to myself, ' I am a princess, and I am a fairy one, and because I am a fairy nothing can hurt me or make me uncomfortable. ' You don' t know how it makes you forget " - with a laugh.

She had many opportunities of making her mind think of something else, and many opportunities of proving to herself whether or not she was a princess. But one of the strongest tests she was ever put to came on a certain dreadful day which, she often thought afterward, would never quite fade out of her memory even in the years to come.

For several days it had rained continuously; the streets were chilly and sloppy and full of dreary, cold mist; there was mud everywhere - sticky London mud - and over everything the pall of drizzle and fog. Of course there were several long and tiresome errands to be done - there always were on days like this - and Sara was sent out again and again, until her shabby clothes were damp through. The absurd old feathers on her forlorn hat were more draggled and absurd than ever, and her downtrodden shoes were so wet that they could not hold any more water. Added to this, she had been deprived of her dinner, because Miss Minchin had chosen to punish her. She was so cold and hungry and tired that her face began to have a pinched look, and now and then some kind - hearted person passing her in the street glanced at her with sudden sympathy. But she did not know that. She hurried on, trying to make her mind think of something else. It was really very necessary. Her way of doing it was to " Pretend " and " Suppose " with all the strength that was left in her. But really this time it was harder than she had ever found it, and once or twice she thought it almost made her more cold and hungry instead of less so. But she persevered obstinately, and as the muddy water squelched through her broken shoes and the wind seemed trying to drag her thin jacket from her, she talked to herself as she walked, though she did not speak aloud or even move her lips.

" Suppose I had dry clothes on, " she thought. " Suppose I had good shoes and a long, thick coat and merino stockings and a whole umbrella. And suppose - suppose - just when I was near a baker's where they sold hot buns, I should find sixpence - which belonged to nobody. SUPPOSE, if I did, I should go into the shop and buy six of the hottest buns and eat them all without stopping. "

Some very odd things happen in this world sometimes.

It certainly was an odd thing that happened to Sara. She had to cross the street just when she was saying this to herself. The mud was dreadful - she almost had to wade. She picked her way as carefully as she could, but she could not save herself much; only, in picking her way, she had to look down at her feet and the mud, and in looking down - just as she reached the pavement - she saw something shining in the gutter. It was actually a piece of silver - a tiny piece trodden upon by many feet, but still with spirit enough left to shine a little. Not quite a sixpence, but the next thing to it - a fourpenny piece.

In one second it was in her cold little red - and - blue hand.

" Oh, " she gasped, " It is true! It is true! "

And then, if you will believe me, she looked straight at the shop directly facing her. And it was a baker's shop, and a cheerful, stout, motherly woman with rosy cheeks was putting into the window a tray of delicious newly baked hot buns, fresh from the oven - large, plump, shiny buns, with currants in them.

It almost made Sara feel faint for a few seconds - the shock, and the sight of the buns, and the delightful odors of warm bread floating up through the baker's cellar window.

She knew she need not hesitate to use the little piece of money. It had evidently been lying in the mud for some time, and its owner was completely lost in the stream of passing people who crowded and jostled each other all day long.

" But I' ll go and ask the baker woman if she has lost anything, " she said to herself, rather faintly. So she crossed the pavement and put her wet foot on the step. As she did so she saw something that made her stop.

It was a little figure more forlorn even than herself - a little figure which was not much more than a bundle of rags, from which small, bare, red muddy feet peeped out, only because the rags with which their owner was trying to cover them were not long enough. Above the rags appeared a shock head of tangled hair, and a dirty face with big, hollow, hungry eyes.

Sara knew they were hungry eyes the moment she saw them, and she felt a sudden sympathy.

" This, " she said to herself, with a little sigh, " is one of the populace - and she is hungrier than I am. "

The child - this " One of the populace " - stared up at Sara, and shuffled herself aside a little, so as to give her room to pass. She was used to being made to give room to everybody. She knew that if a policeman chanced to see her he would tell her to " Move on. "

Sara clutched her little fourpenny piece and hesitated a few seconds. Then she spoke to her.

" Are you hungry? " she asked.

The child shuffled herself and her rags a little more.

" Ain' t I jist? " she said in a hoarse voice. " Jist ain' t I? "

" Haven' t you had any dinner? " said Sara.

" No dinner, " - more hoarsely still and with more shuffling. " Nor yet no bre' fast - nor yet no supper. No nothin' . "

" Since when? " asked Sara.

" Dunno. Never got nothin' today - nowhere. I' ve axed an' axed. "

Just to look at her made Sara more hungry and faint. But those queer little thoughts were at work in her brain, and she was talking to herself, though she was sick at heart.

" If I' m a princess, " she was saying, " If I' m a princess - when they were poor and driven from their thrones - they always shared - with the populace - if they met one poorer and hungrier than themselves. They always shared. Buns are a penny each. If it had been sixpence I could have eaten six. It won' t be enough for either of us. But it will be better than nothing. "

" Wait a minute, " she said to the beggar child.

She went into the shop. It was warm and smelled deliciously. The woman was just going to put some more hot buns into the window.

" If you please, " said Sara, " Have you lost fourpence - a silver fourpence? " And she held the forlorn little piece of money out to her.

The woman looked at it and then at her - at her intense little face and draggled, once fine clothes.

" Bless us! no, " she answered. " Did you find it? "

" Yes, " said Sara. " In the gutter. "

" Keep it, then, " said the woman. " It may have been there for a week, and goodness knows who lost it. YOU could never find out. "

" I know that, " said Sara, " But I thought I would ask you. "

" Not many would, " said the woman, looking puzzled and interested and good - natured all at once.

" Do you want to buy something? " she added, as she saw Sara glance at the buns.

" Four buns, if you please, " said Sara. " Those at a penny each. "

The woman went to the window and put some in a paper bag.

Sara noticed that she put in six.

" I said four, if you please, " she explained. " I have only four pence. "

" I' ll throw in two for makeweight, " said the woman, with her good - natured look. " I dare say you can eat them sometime. Aren' t you hungry? "

A mist rose before Sara's eyes.

" Yes, " she answered. " I am very hungry, and I am much obliged to you for your kindness; and " - she was going to add - " There is a child outside who is hungrier than I am. " But just at that moment two or three customers came in at once, and each one seemed in a hurry, so she could only thank the woman again and go out.

The beggar girl was still huddled up in the corner of the step. She looked frightful in her wet and dirty rags. She was staring straight before her with a stupid look of suffering, and Sara saw her suddenly draw the back of her roughened black hand across her eyes to rub away the tears which seemed to have surprised her by forcing their way from under her lids. She was muttering to herself.

Sara opened the paper bag and took out one of the hot buns, which had already warmed her own cold hands a little.

" See, " she said, putting the bun in the ragged lap, " This is nice and hot. Eat it, and you will not feel so hungry. "

The child started and stared up at her, as if such sudden, amazing good luck almost frightened her; then she snatched up the bun and began to cram it into her mouth with great wolfish bites.

" Oh, my! Oh, my! " Sara heard her say hoarsely, in wild delight. " OH, my! "

Sara took out three more buns and put them down.

The sound in the hoarse, ravenous voice was awful.

" She is hungrier than I am, " she said to herself. " She's starving. " But her hand trembled when she put down the fourth bun. " I' m not starving, " she said - and she put down the fifth.

The little ravening London savage was still snatching and devouring when she turned away. She was too ravenous to give any thanks, even if she had ever been taught politeness - which she had not. She was only a poor little wild animal.

" Good - bye, " said Sara.

When she reached the other side of the street she looked back. The child had a bun in each hand and had stopped in the middle of a bite to watch her. Sara gave her a little nod, and the child, after another stare - a curious lingering stare - jerked her shaggy head in response, and until Sara was out of sight she did not take another bite or even finish the one she had begun.

At that moment the baker - woman looked out of her shop window.

" Well, I never! " she exclaimed. " If that young un hasn' t given her buns to a beggar child! It wasn' t because she didn' t want them, either. Well, well, she looked hungry enough. I' d give something to know what she did it for. "

She stood behind her window for a few moments and pondered. Then her curiosity got the better of her. She went to the door and spoke to the beggar child.

" Who gave you those buns? " she asked her.

The child nodded her head toward Sara's vanishing figure.

" What did she say? " inquired the woman.

" Axed me if I was' ungry, " replied the hoarse voice.

" What did you say? "

" Said I was jist. "

" And then she came in and got the buns, and gave them to you, did she? "

The child nodded.

" How many? "

" Five. "

The woman thought it over.

" Left just one for herself, " she said in a low voice. " And she could have eaten the whole six - I saw it in her eyes. "

She looked after the little draggled far - away figure and felt more disturbed in her usually comfortable mind than she had felt for many a day.

" I wish she hadn' t gone so quick, " she said. " I' m blest if she shouldn' t have had a dozen. " Then she turned to the child.

" Are you hungry yet? " she said.

" I' m allus hungry, " was the answer, " But' t ain' t as bad as it was. "

" Come in here, " said the woman, and she held open the shop door.

The child got up and shuffled in. To be invited into a warm place full of bread seemed an incredible thing. She did not know what was going to happen. She did not care, even.

" Get yourself warm, " said the woman, pointing to a fire in the tiny back room. " And look here; when you are hard up for a bit of bread, you can come in here and ask for it. I' m blest if I won' t give it to you for that young one's sake. "

Sara found some comfort in her remaining bun. At all events, it was very hot, and it was better than nothing. As she walked along she broke off small pieces and ate them slowly to make them last longer.

" Suppose it was a magic bun, " she said, " and a bite was as much as a whole dinner. I should be overeating myself if I went on like this. "

It was dark when she reached the square where the Select Seminary was situated. The lights in the houses were all lighted. The blinds were not yet drawn in the windows of the room where she nearly always caught glimpses of members of the Large Family. Frequently at this hour she could see the gentleman she called Mr. Montmorency sitting in a big chair, with a small swarm round him, talking, laughing, perching on the arms of his seat or on his knees or leaning against them. This evening the swarm was about him, but he was not seated. On the contrary, there was a good deal of excitement going on. It was evident that a journey was to be taken, and it was Mr. Montmorency who was to take it. A brougham stood before the door, and a big portmanteau had been strapped upon it. The children were dancing about, chattering and hanging on to their father. The pretty rosy mother was standing near him, talking as if she was asking final questions. Sara paused a moment to see the little ones lifted up and kissed and the bigger ones bent over and kissed also.

" I wonder if he will stay away long, " she thought. " The portmanteau is rather big. Oh, dear, how they will miss him! I shall miss him myself - even though he doesn' t know I am alive. "

When the door opened she moved away - remembering the sixpence - but she saw the traveller come out and stand against the background of the warmly - lighted hall, the older children still hovering about him.

" Will Moscow be covered with snow? " said the little girl Janet. " Will there be ice everywhere? "

" Shall you drive in a drosky? " cried another. " Shall you see the Czar? "

" I will write and tell you all about it, " he answered, laughing. " And I will send you pictures of muzhiks and things. Run into the house. It is a hideous damp night. I would rather stay with you than go to Moscow. Good night! Good night, duckies! God bless you! " And he ran down the steps and jumped into the brougham.

" If you find the little girl, give her our love, " shouted Guy Clarence, jumping up and down on the door - mat.

Then they went in and shut the door.

" Did you see, " said Janet to Nora, as they went back to the room - " The little - girl - who - is - not - a - beggar was passing? She looked all cold and wet, and I saw her turn her head over her shoulder and look at us. Mamma says her clothes always look as if they had been given her by someone who was quite rich - someone who only let her have them because they were too shabby to wear. The people at the school always send her out on errands on the horridest days and nights there are. "

Sara crossed the square to Miss Minchin's area steps, feeling faint and shaky.

" I wonder who the little girl is, " she thought - " The little girl he is going to look for. "

And she went down the area steps, lugging her basket and finding it very heavy indeed, as the father of the Large Family drove quickly on his way to the station to take the train which was to carry him to Moscow, where he was to make his best efforts to search for the lost little daughter of Captain Crewe.

CHAPTER ⅩⅤ　THE MAGIC

WHEN Sara had passed the house next door she had seen Ram Dass closing the shutters, and caught her glimpse of this room also.

" It is a long time since I saw a nice place from the inside, " was the thought which crossed her mind.

There was the usual bright fire glowing in the grate, and the Indian gentleman was sitting before it. His head was resting in his hand, and he looked as lonely and unhappy as ever.

" Poor man! " said Sara; " I wonder what you are supposing. "

And this was what he was " Supposing " at that very moment.

" Suppose, " he was thinking, " Suppose - even if Carmichael traces the people to Moscow - the little girl they took from Madame Pascal's school in Paris is NOT the one we are in search of. Suppose she proves to be quite a different child. What steps shall I take next? "

When Sara went into the house she met Miss Minchin, who had come downstairs to scold the cook.

" Where have you wasted your time? " she demanded. " You have been out for hours. "

" It was so wet and muddy, " Sara answered, " It was hard to walk, because my shoes were so bad and slipped about. "

" Make no excuses, " said Miss Minchin, " and tell no falsehoods. "

Sara went in to the cook. The cook had received a severe lecture and was in a fearful temper as a result. She was only too rejoiced to have someone to vent her rage on, and Sara was a convenience, as usual.

" Why didn' t you stay all night? " she snapped.

Sara laid her purchases on the table.

" Here are the things, " she said.

The cook looked them over, grumbling. She was in a very savage humor indeed.

" May I have something to eat? " Sara asked rather faintly.

" Tea's over and done with, " was the answer. " Did you expect me to keep it hot for you? "

Sara stood silent for a second.

" I had no dinner, " she said next, and her voice was quite low. She made it low because she was afraid it would tremble.

" There's some bread in the pantry, " said the cook. " That's all you' ll get at this time of day. "

Sara went and found the bread. It was old and hard and dry. The cook was in too vicious a humor to give her anything to eat with it. It was always safe and easy to vent her spite on Sara. Really, it was hard for the child to climb the three long flights of stairs leading to her attic. She often found them long and steep when she was tired; but tonight it seemed as if she would never reach the top. Several times she was obliged to stop to rest. When she reached the top landing she was glad to see the glimmer of a light coming from under her door. That meant that Ermengarde had managed to creep up to pay her a visit. There was some comfort in that. It was better than to go into the room alone and find it empty and desolate. The mere presence of plump, comfortable Ermengarde, wrapped in her red shawl, would warm it a little.

Yes; there Ermengarde was when she opened the door. She was sitting in the middle of the bed, with her feet tucked safely under her. She had never become intimate with Melchisedec and his family, though they rather fascinated her. When she found herself alone in the attic she always preferred to sit on the bed until Sara arrived. She had, in fact, on this occasion had time to become rather nervous, because Melchisedec had appeared and sniffed about a good deal, and once had made her utter a repressed squeal by sitting up on his hind legs and, while he looked at her, sniffing pointedly in her direction.

" Oh, Sara, " she cried out, " I am glad you have come. Melchy WOULD sniff about so. I tried to coax him to go back, but he wouldn' t for such a long time. I like him, you know; but it does frighten me when he sniffs right at me. Do you think he ever WOULD jump? "

" No, " answered Sara.

Ermengarde crawled forward on the bed to look at her.

" You DO look tired, Sara, " she said; " You are quite pale. "

" I AM tired, " said Sara, dropping on to the lopsided footstool. " Oh, there's Melchisedec, poor thing. He's come to ask for his supper. "

Melchisedec had come out of his hole as if he had been listening for her footstep. Sara was quite sure he knew it. He came forward with an affectionate, expectant expression as Sara put her hand in her pocket and turned it inside out, shaking her head.

" I' m very sorry, " she said. " I haven' t one crumb left. Go home, Melchisedec, and tell your wife there was nothing in my pocket. I' m afraid I forgot because the cook and Miss Minchin were so cross. "

Melchisedec seemed to understand. He shuffled resignedly, if not contentedly, back to his home.

" I did not expect to see you tonight, Ermie, " Sara said.

Ermengarde hugged herself in the red shawl.

" Miss Amelia has gone out to spend the night with her old aunt, " she explained. " No one else ever comes and looks into the bedrooms after we are in bed. I could stay here until morning if I wanted to. "

She pointed toward the table under the skylight. Sara had not looked toward it as she came in. A number of books were piled upon it. Ermengarde's gesture was a dejected one.

" Papa has sent me some more books, Sara, " she said. " There they are. "

Sara looked round and got up at once. She ran to the table, and picking up the top volume, turned over its leaves quickly. For the moment she forgot her discomforts.

" Ah, " she cried out, " how beautiful! Carlyle's French Revolution. I have SO wanted to read that! "

" I haven' t, " said Ermengarde. " And papa will be so cross if I don' t. He' ll expect me to know all about it when I go home for the holidays. What SHALL I do? "

Sara stopped turning over the leaves and looked at her with an excited flush on her cheeks.

" Look here, " she cried, " If you' ll lend me these books, I' ll read them - and tell you everything that's in them afterward - and I' ll tell it so that you will remember it, too. "

" Oh, goodness! " exclaimed Ermengarde. " Do you think you can? "

" I know I can, " Sara answered. " The little ones always remember what I tell them. "

" Sara, " said Ermengarde, hope gleaming in her round face, " If you' ll do that, and make me remember, I' ll - I' ll give you anything. "

" I don' t want you to give me anything, " said Sara. " I want your books - I want them! " And her eyes grew big, and her chest heaved.

" Take them, then, " said Ermengarde. " I wish I wanted them - but I don' t. I' m not clever, and my father is, and he thinks I ought to be. "

Sara was opening one book after the other. " What are you going to tell your father? " she asked, a slight doubt dawning in her mind.

" Oh, he needn' t know, " answered Ermengarde. " He' ll think I' ve read them. "

Sara put down her book and shook her head slowly. " That's almost like telling lies, " she said. " And lies - well, you see, they are not only wicked - they' re VULGAR. Sometimes " - reflectively - " I' ve thought perhaps I might do something wicked - might suddenly fly into a rage and kill Miss Minchin, you know, when she was ill - treating me - but I COULDN' T be vulgar. Why can' t you tell your father I read them? "

" He wants me to read them, " said Ermengarde, a little discouraged by this unexpected turn of affairs.

" He wants you to know what is in them, " said Sara. " And if I can tell it to you in an easy way and make you remember it, I should think he would like that. "

" He' ll like it if I learn anything in ANY way, " said rueful Ermengarde. " You would if you were my father. "

" It's not your fault that - " began Sara. She pulled herself up and stopped rather suddenly. She had been going to say, " It's not your fault that you are stupid. "

" That what? " Ermengarde asked.

" That you can' t learn things quickly, " amended Sara. " If you can' t, you can' t. If I can - why, I can; that's all. "

She always felt very tender of Ermengarde, and tried not to let her feel too strongly the difference between being able to learn anything at once, and not being able to learn anything at all. As she looked at her plump face, one of her wise, old - fashioned thoughts came to her.

" Perhaps, " she said, " to be able to learn things quickly isn' t everything. To be kind is worth a great deal to other people. If Miss Minchin knew everything on earth and was like what she is now, she' d still be a detestable thing, and everybody would hate her. Lots of clever people have done harm and have been wicked. Look at Robespierre - "

She stopped and examined Ermengarde's countenance, which was beginning to look bewildered. " Don' t you remember? " she demanded. " I told you about him not long ago. I believe you' ve forgotten. "

" Well, I don' t remember ALL of it, " admitted Ermengarde.

" Well, you wait a minute, " said Sara, " and I' ll take off my wet things and wrap myself in the coverlet and tell you over again. "

She took off her hat and coat and hung them on a nail against the wall, and she changed her wet shoes for an old pair of slippers. Then she jumped on the bed, and drawing the coverlet about her shoulders, sat with her arms round her knees.

" Now, listen, " she said.

She plunged into the gory records of the French Revolution, and told such stories of it that Ermengarde's eyes grew round with alarm and she held her breath. But though she was rather terrified, there was a delightful thrill in listening, and she was not likely to forget Robespierre again, or to have any doubts about the Princesse de Lamballe.

" You know they put her head on a pike and danced round it, " Sara explained. " And she had beautiful floating blonde hair; and when I think of her, I never see her head on her body, but always on a pike, with those furious people dancing and howling. "

It was agreed that Mr. St. John was to be told the plan they had made, and for the present the books were to be left in the attic.

" Now let's tell each other things, " said Sara. " How are you getting on with your French lessons? "

" Ever so much better since the last time I came up here and you explained the conjugations. Miss Minchin could not understand why I did my exercises so well that first morning. "

Sara laughed a little and hugged her knees.

" She doesn' t understand why Lottie is doing her sums so well, " she said; " but it is because she creeps up here, too, and I help her. " She glanced round the room. " The attic would be rather nice - if it wasn' t so dreadful, " she said, laughing again. " It's a good place to pretend in. "

The truth was that Ermengarde did not know anything of the sometimes almost unbearable side of life in the attic, and she had not a sufficiently vivid imagination to depict it for herself. On the rare occasions that she could reach Sara's room she only saw that side of it which was made exciting by things which were " pretended " and stories which were told. Her visits partook of the character of adventures; and though sometimes Sara looked rather pale, and it was not to be denied that she had grown very thin, her proud little spirit would not admit of complaints. She had never confessed that at times she was almost ravenous with hunger, as she was tonight. She was growing rapidly, and her constant walking and running about would have given her a keen appetite even if she had had abundant and regular meals of a much more nourishing nature than the unappetizing, inferior food snatched at such odd times as suited the kitchen convenience. She was growing used to a certain gnawing feeling in her young stomach.

" I suppose soldiers feel like this when they are on a long and weary march, " she often said to herself. She liked the sound of the phrase, " long and weary march. " It made her feel rather like a soldier. She had also a quaint sense of being a hostess in the attic.

" If I lived in a castle, " she argued, " and Ermengarde was the lady of another castle, and came to see me, with knights and squires and vassals riding with her, and pennons flying; when I heard the clarions sounding outside the drawbridge I should go down to receive her, and I should spread feasts in the banquet - hall and call in minstrels to sing and play and relate romances. When she comes into the attic I can' t spread feasts, but I can tell stories, and not let her know disagreeable things. I dare say poor chatelaine had to do that in times of famine, when their lands had been pillaged. " She was a proud, brave little chatelaine, and dispensed generously the one hospitality she could offer - the dreams she dreamed - the visions she saw - the imaginings which were her joy and comfort.

So, as they sat together, Ermengarde did not know that she was faint as well as ravenous, and that while she talked she now and then wondered if her hunger would let her sleep when she was left alone. She felt as if she had never been quite so hungry before.

" I wish I was as thin as you, Sara, " Ermengarde said suddenly. " I believe you are thinner than you used to be. Your eyes look so big, and look at the sharp little bones sticking out of your elbow! "

Sara pulled down her sleeve, which had pushed itself up. " I always was a thin child, " she said bravely, " and I always had big green eyes. "

" I love your queer eyes, " said Ermengarde, looking into them with affectionate admiration. " They always look as if they saw such a long way. I love them - and I love them to be green - though they look black generally. "

" They are cat's eyes, " laughed Sara; " But I can' t see in the dark with them - because I have tried, and I couldn' t - I wish I could. "

It was just at this minute that something happened at the skylight which neither of them saw. If either of them had chanced to turn and look, she would have been startled by the sight of a dark face which peered cautiously into the room and disappeared as quickly and almost as silently as it had appeared. Not QUITE as silently, however. Sara, who had keen ears, suddenly turned a little and looked up at the roof.

" That didn' t sound like Melchisedec, " she said. " It wasn' t scratchy enough. "

" What? " said Ermengarde, a little startled.

" Didn' t you think you heard something? " asked Sara.

" N - no, " Ermengarde faltered. " Did you? "

" Perhaps I didn' t, " said Sara; " But I thought I did. It sounded as if something was on the slates - something that dragged softly. "

" What could it be? " said Ermengarde. " Could it be - robbers? "

" No, " Sara began cheerfully. " There is nothing to steal - "

She broke off in the middle of her words. They both heard the sound that checked her. It was not on the slates, but on the stairs below, and it was Miss Minchin's angry voice. Sara sprang off the bed, and put out the candle.

" She is scolding Becky, " she whispered, as she stood in the darkness. " She is making her cry. "

" Will she come in here? " Ermengarde whispered back, panic - stricken.

" No. She will think I am in bed. Don' t stir. "

It was very seldom that Miss Minchin mounted the last flight of stairs. Sara could only remember that she had done it once before. But now she was angry enough to be coming at least part of the way up, and it sounded as if she was driving Becky before her.

" You impudent, dishonest child! " they heard her say. " Cook tells me she has missed things repeatedly. "

" ' T warn' t me, mum, " said Becky, sobbing. " I was' ungry enough, but' t war n' t me - never! "

" You deserve to be sent to prison, " said Miss Minchin's voice. " Picking and stealing! Half a meat pie, indeed! "

" ' T warn' t me, " wept Becky. " I could' ave eat a whole un - but I never laid a finger on it. "

Miss Minchin was out of breath between temper and mounting the stairs. The meat pie had been intended for her special late supper. It became apparent that she boxed Becky's ears.

" Don' t tell falsehoods, " she said. " Go to your room this instant. "

Both Sara and Ermengarde heard the slap, and then heard Becky run in her slipshod shoes up the stairs and into her attic. They heard her door shut, and knew that she threw herself upon her bed.

" I could' ave e' t two of' em, " they heard her cry into her pillow. " An' I never took a bite. ' Twas cook give it to her policeman. "

Sara stood in the middle of the room in the darkness. She was clenching her little teeth and opening and shutting fiercely her outstretched hands. She could scarcely stand still, but she dared not move until Miss Minchin had gone down the stairs and all was still.

" The wicked, cruel thing! " she burst forth. " The cook takes things herself and then says Becky steals them. She DOESN' T! She DOESN' T! She's so hungry sometimes that she eats crusts out of the ash barrel! " She pressed her hands hard against her face and burst into passionate little sobs, and Ermengarde, hearing this unusual thing, was overawed by it. Sara was crying! The unconquerable Sara! It seemed to denote something new - some mood she had never known. Suppose - Suppose - A new dread possibility presented itself to her kind, slow, little mind all at once. She crept off the bed in the dark and found her way to the table where the candle stood. She struck a match and lit the candle. When she had lighted it, she bent forward and looked at Sara, with her new thought growing to definite fear in her eyes.

" Sara, " she said in a timid, almost awe - stricken voice, " are - are - you never told me - I don' t want to be rude, but - are YOU ever hungry? "

It was too much just at that moment. The barrier broke down. Sara lifted her face from her hands.

" Yes, " she said in a new passionate way. " Yes, I am. I' m so hungry now that I could almost eat you. And it makes it worse to hear poor Becky. She's hungrier than I am. "

Ermengarde gasped.

" Oh! Oh! " she cried woefully; " And I never knew! "

" I didn' t want you to know, " Sara said. " It would have made me feel like a street beggar. I know I look like a street beggar. "

" No, you don' t - you don' t! " Ermengarde broke in. " Your clothes are a little queer - but you couldn' t look like a street beggar. You haven' t a street - beggar face. "

" A little boy once gave me a sixpence for charity, " said Sara, with a short little laugh in spite of herself. " Here it is. " And she pulled out the thin ribbon from her neck. " He wouldn' t have given me his Christmas sixpence if I hadn' t looked as if I needed it. "

Somehow the sight of the dear little sixpence was good for both of them. It made them laugh a little, though they both had tears in their eyes.

" Who was he? " asked Ermengarde, looking at it quite as if it had not been a mere ordinary silver sixpence.

" He was a darling little thing going to a party, " said Sara. " He was one of the Large Family, the little one with the round legs - the one I call Guy Clarence. I suppose his nursery was crammed with Christmas presents and hampers full of cakes and things, and he could see I had nothing. "

Ermengarde gave a little jump backward. The last sentences had recalled something to her troubled mind and given her a sudden inspiration.

" Oh, Sara! " she cried. " What a silly thing I am not to have thought of it! "

" Of what? "

" Something splendid! " said Ermengarde, in an excited hurry. " This very afternoon my nicest aunt sent me a box. It is full of good things. I never touched it, I had so much pudding at dinner, and I was so bothered about papa's books. " Her words began to tumble over each other. " It's got cake in it, and little meat pies, and jam tarts and buns, and oranges and red - currant wine, and figs and chocolate. I' ll creep back to my room and get it this minute, and we' ll eat it now. "

Sara almost reeled. When one is faint with hunger the mention of food has sometimes a curious effect. She clutched Ermengarde's arm.

" Do you think - you COULD? " she ejaculated.

" I know I could, " answered Ermengarde, and she ran to the door - opened it softly - put her head out into the darkness, and listened. Then she went back to Sara.

" The lights are out. Everybody's in bed. I can creep - and creep - and no one will hear. "

It was so delightful that they caught each other's hands and a sudden light sprang into Sara's eyes.

" Ermie! " she said. " Let us PRETEND! Let us pretend it's a party! And oh, won' t you invite the prisoner in the next cell? "

" Yes! Yes! Let us knock on the wall now. The jailer won' t hear. "

Sara went to the wall. Through it she could hear poor Becky crying more softly. She knocked four times.

" That means, ' Come to me through the secret passage under the wall, ' " she explained. " ' I have something to communicate. ' "

Five quick knocks answered her.

" She is coming, " she said.

Almost immediately the door of the attic opened and Becky appeared. Her eyes were red and her cap was sliding off, and when she caught sight of Ermengarde she began to rub her face nervously with her apron.

" Don' t mind me a bit, Becky! " cried Ermengarde.

" Miss Ermengarde has asked you to come in, " said Sara, " Because she is going to bring a box of good things up here to us. "

Becky's cap almost fell off entirely, she broke in with such excitement.

" To eat, miss? " she said. " Things that's good to eat? "

" Yes, " answered Sara, " and we are going to pretend a party. "

" And you shall have as much as you WANT to eat, " put in Ermengarde. " I' ll go this minute! "

She was in such haste that as she tiptoed out of the attic she dropped her red shawl and did not know it had fallen. No one saw it for a minute or so. Becky was too much overpowered by the good luck which had befallen her.

" Oh, miss! oh, miss! " she gasped; " I know it was you that asked her to let me come. It - it makes me cry to think of it. " And she went to Sara's side and stood and looked at her worshippingly.

But in Sara's hungry eyes the old light had begun to glow and transform her world for her. Here in the attic - with the cold night outside - with the afternoon in the sloppy streets barely passed - with the memory of the awful unfed look in the beggar child's eyes not yet faded - this simple, cheerful thing had happened like a thing of magic.

She caught her breath.

" Somehow, something always happens, " she cried, " just before things get to the very worst. It is as if the Magic did it. If I could only just remember that always. The worst thing never QUITE comes. "

She gave Becky a little cheerful shake.

" No, no! You mustn' t cry! " she said. " We must make haste and set the table. "

" Set the table, miss? " said Becky, gazing round the room. " What' ll we set it with? "

Sara looked round the attic, too.

" There doesn' t seem to be much, " she answered, half laughing.

That moment she saw something and pounced upon it. It was Ermengarde's red shawl which lay upon the floor.

" Here's the shawl, " she cried. " I know she won' t mind it. It will make such a nice red tablecloth. "

They pulled the old table forward, and threw the shawl over it. Red is a wonderfully kind and comfortable color. It began to make the room look furnished directly.

" How nice a red rug would look on the floor! " exclaimed Sara. " We must pretend there is one! "

Her eye swept the bare boards with a swift glance of admiration. The rug was laid down already.

" How soft and thick it is! " she said, with the little laugh which Becky knew the meaning of; and she raised and set her foot down again delicately, as if she felt something under it.

" Yes, miss, " answered Becky, watching her with serious rapture. She was always quite serious.

" What next, now? " said Sara, and she stood still and put her hands over her eyes. " Something will come if I think and wait a little " - in a soft, expectant voice. " The Magic will tell me. "

One of her favorite fancies was that on " the outside, " as she called it, thoughts were waiting for people to call them. Becky had seen her stand and wait many a time before, and knew that in a few seconds she would uncover an enlightened, laughing face.

In a moment she did.

" There! " she cried. " It has come! I know now! I must look among the things in the old trunk I had when I was a princess. "

She flew to its corner and kneeled down. It had not been put in the attic for her benefit, but because there was no room for it elsewhere. Nothing had been left in it but rubbish. But she knew she should find something. The Magic always arranged that kind of thing in one way or another.

In a corner lay a package so insignificant - looking that it had been overlooked, and when she herself had found it she had kept it as a relic. It contained a dozen small white handkerchiefs. She seized them joyfully and ran to the table. She began to arrange them upon the red table - cover, patting and coaxing them into shape with the narrow lace edge curling outward, her Magic working its spells for her as she did it.

" These are the plates, " she said. " They are golden plates. These are the richly embroidered napkins. Nuns worked them in convents in Spain. "

" Did they, miss? " breathed Becky, her very soul uplifted by the information.

" You must pretend it, " said Sara. " If you pretend it enough, you will see them. "

" Yes, miss, " said Becky; and as Sara returned to the trunk she devoted herself to the effort of accomplishing an end so much to be desired.

Sara turned suddenly to find her standing by the table, looking very queer indeed. She had shut her eyes, and was twisting her face in strange, convulsive contortions, her hands hanging stiffly clenched at her sides. She looked as if she was trying to lift some enormous weight.

" What is the matter, Becky? " Sara cried. " What are you doing? "

Becky opened her eyes with a start.

" I was a' pretendin' , miss, " she answered a little sheepishly; " I was tryin' to see it like you do. I almost did, " with a hopeful grin. " But it takes a lot o'stren' th. "

" Perhaps it does if you are not used to it, " said Sara, with friendly sympathy; " But you don' t know how easy it is when you' ve done it often. I wouldn' t try so hard just at first. It will come to you after a while. I' ll just tell you what things are. Look at these. "

She held an old summer hat in her hand which she had fished out of the bottom of the trunk. There was a wreath of flowers on it. She pulled the wreath off.

" These are garlands for the feast, " she said grandly. " They fill all the air with perfume. There's a mug on the wash - stand, Becky. Oh - and bring the soap dish for a centrepiece. "

Becky handed them to her reverently.

" What are they now, miss? " she inquired. " You' d think they was made of crockery - but I know they ain' t. "

" This is a carven flagon, " said Sara, arranging tendrils of the wreath about the mug. " And this " - bending tenderly over the soap dish and heaping it with roses - " is purest alabaster encrusted with gems. "

She touched the things gently, a happy smile hovering about her lips which made her look as if she were a creature in a dream.

" My, ain' t it lovely! " whispered Becky.

" If we just had something for bonbon dishes, " Sara murmured. " There! " - darting to the trunk again. " I remember I saw something this minute. "

It was only a bundle of wool wrapped in red and white tissue paper, but the tissue paper was soon twisted into the form of little dishes, and was combined with the remaining flowers to ornament the candlestick which was to light the feast. Only the Magic could have made it more than an old table covered with a red shawl and set with rubbish from a long - unopened trunk. But Sara drew back and gazed at it, seeing wonders; and Becky, after staring in delight, spoke with bated breath.

" This' ere, " she suggested, with a glance round the attic - " is it the Bastille now - or has it turned into somethin' different? "

" Oh, yes, yes! " said Sara; " Quite different. It is a banquet hall! "

" My eye, miss! " ejaculated Becky. " A blanket' all! " and she turned to view the splendors about her with awed bewilderment.

" A banquet hall, " said Sara. " A vast chamber where feasts are given. It has a vaulted roof, and a minstrels' gallery, and a huge chimney filled with blazing oaken logs, and it is brilliant with waxen tapers twinkling on every side. "

" My eye, Miss Sara! " gasped Becky again.

Then the door opened, and Ermengarde came in, rather staggering under the weight of her hamper. She started back with an exclamation of joy. To enter from the chill darkness outside, and find one's self confronted by a totally unanticipated festal board, draped with red, adorned with white napery, and wreathed with flowers, was to feel that the preparations were brilliant indeed.

" Oh, Sara! " she cried out. " You are the cleverest girl I ever saw! "

" Isn' t it nice? " said Sara. " They are things out of my old trunk. I asked my Magic, and it told me to go and look. "

" But oh, miss, " cried Becky, " Wait till she's told you what they are! They ain' t just - oh, miss, please tell her, " appealing to Sara.

So Sara told her, and because her Magic helped her she made her ALMOST see it all: the golden platters - the vaulted spaces - the blazing logs - the twinkling waxen tapers. As the things were taken out of the hamper - the frosted cakes - the fruits - the bonbons and the wine - the feast became a splendid thing.

" It's like a real party! " cried Ermengarde.

" It's like a queen's table, " sighed Becky.

Then Ermengarde had a sudden brilliant thought.

" I' ll tell you what, Sara, " she said. " Pretend you are a princess now and this is a royal feast. "

" But it's your feast, " said Sara; " You must be the princess, and we will be your maids of honor. "

" Oh, I can' t, " said Ermengarde. " I' m too fat, and I don' t know how. YOU be her. "

" Well, if you want me to, " said Sara.

But suddenly she thought of something else and ran to the rusty grate.

" There is a lot of paper and rubbish stuffed in here! " she exclaimed. " If we light it, there will be a bright blaze for a few minutes, and we shall feel as if it was a real fire. " She struck a match and lighted it up with a great specious glow which illuminated the room.

" By the time it stops blazing, " Sara said, " We shall forget about its not being real. "

She stood in the dancing glow and smiled.

" Doesn' t it LOOK real? " she said. " Now we will begin the party. "

She led the way to the table. She waved her hand graciously to Ermengarde and Becky. She was in the midst of her dream.

" Advance, fair damsels, " she said in her happy dream - voice, " and be seated at the banquet table. My noble father, the king, who is absent on a long journey, has commanded me to feast you. " She turned her head slightly toward the corner of the room. " What, ho! there, minstrels! Strike up with your viols and bassoons. Princesses, " she explained rapidly to Ermengarde and Becky, " always had minstrels to play at their feasts. Pretend there is a minstrel gallery up there in the corner. Now we will begin. "

They had barely had time to take their pieces of cake into their hands - not one of them had time to do more, when - they all three sprang to their feet and turned pale faces toward the door - listening - listening.

Some one was coming up the stairs. There was no mistake about it. Each of them recognized the angry, mounting tread and knew that the end of all things had come.

" It's - the missus! " choked Becky, and dropped her piece of cake upon the floor.

" Yes, " said Sara, her eyes growing shocked and large in her small white face. " Miss Minchin has found us out. "

Miss Minchin struck the door open with a blow of her hand. She was pale herself, but it was with rage. She looked from the frightened faces to the banquet table, and from the banquet table to the last flicker of the burnt paper in the grate.

" I have been suspecting something of this sort, " she exclaimed; " but I did not dream of such audacity. Lavinia was telling the truth. "

So they knew that it was Lavinia who had somehow guessed their secret and had betrayed them. Miss Minchin strode over to Becky and boxed her ears for a second time.

" You impudent creature! " she said. " You leave the house in the morning! "

Sara stood quite still, her eyes growing larger, her face paler. Ermengarde burst into tears.

" Oh, don' t send her away, " she sobbed. " My aunt sent me the hamper. We' re - only - having a party. "

" So I see, " said Miss Minchin, witheringly. " With the Princess Sara at the head of the table. " She turned fiercely on Sara. " It is your doing, I know, " she cried. " Ermengarde would never have thought of such a thing. You decorated the table, I suppose - with this rubbish. " She stamped her foot at Becky. " Go to your attic! " she commanded, and Becky stole away, her face hidden in her apron, her shoulders shaking.

Then it was Sara's turn again.

" I will attend to you tomorrow. You shall have neither breakfast, dinner, nor supper! "

" I have not had either dinner or supper today. Miss Minchin, " said Sara, rather faintly.

" Then all the better. You will have something to remember. Don' t stand there. Put those things into the hamper again. "

She began to sweep them off the table into the hamper herself, and caught sight of Ermengarde's new books. " And you " - to Ermengarde - " have brought your beautiful new books into this dirty attic. Take them up and go back to bed. You will stay there all day tomorrow, and I shall write to your papa. What would HE say if he knew where you are tonight? "

Something she saw in Sara's grave, fixed gaze at this moment made her turn on her fiercely.

" What are you thinking of? " she demanded. " Why do you look at me like that? "

" I was wondering, " answered Sara, as she had answered that notable day in the schoolroom.

" What were you wondering? "

It was very like the scene in the schoolroom. There was no pertness in Sara's manner. It was only sad and quiet.

" I was wondering, " she said in a low voice, " What MY papa would say if he knew where I am tonight. "

Miss Minchin was infuriated just as she had been before, and her anger expressed itself, as before, in an intemperate fashion. She flew at her and shook her.

" You insolent, unmanageable child! " she cried. " How dare you! How dare you! "

She picked up the books, swept the rest of the feast back into the hamper in a jumbled heap, thrust it into Ermengarde's arms, and pushed her before her toward the door.

" I will leave you to wonder, " she said. " Go to bed this instant. " And she shut the door behind herself and poor stumbling Ermengarde, and left Sara standing quite alone.

The dream was quite at an end. The last spark had died out of the paper in the grate and left only black tinder; the table was left bare, the golden plates and richly embroidered napkins, and the garlands were transformed again into old handkerchiefs, scraps of red and white paper, and discarded artificial flowers all scattered on the floor; the minstrels in the minstrel gallery had stolen away, and the viols and bassoons were still. Emily was sitting with her back against the wall, staring very hard. Sara saw her, and went and picked her up with trembling hands.

" There isn' t any banquet left, Emily, " she said. " And there isn' t any princess. There is nothing left but the prisoners in the Bastille. " And she sat down and hid her face.

What would have happened if she had not hidden it just then, and if she had chanced to look up at the skylight at the wrong moment, I do not know - perhaps the end of this chapter might have been quite different - because if she had glanced at the skylight she would certainly have been startled by what she would have seen. She would have seen exactly the same face pressed against the glass and peering in at her as it had peered in earlier in the evening when she had been talking to Ermengarde.

But she did not look up. She sat with her little black head in her arms for some time. She always sat like that when she was trying to bear something in silence. Then she got up and went slowly to the bed.

" I can' t pretend anything else - while I am awake, " she said. " There wouldn' t be any use in trying. If I go to sleep, perhaps a dream will come and pretend for me. "

She suddenly felt so tired - perhaps through want of food - that she sat down on the edge of the bed quite weakly.

" Suppose there was a bright fire in the grate, with lots of little dancing flames, " she murmured. " Suppose there was a comfortable chair before it - and suppose there was a small table near, with a little hot - hot supper on it. And suppose " - as she drew the thin coverings over her - " Suppose this was a beautiful soft bed, with fleecy blankets and large downy pillows. Suppose - suppose - " And her very weariness was good to her, for her eyes closed and she fell fast asleep.

* * * * * *

She did not know how long she slept. But she had been tired enough to sleep deeply and profoundly - too deeply and soundly to be disturbed by anything, even by the squeaks and scamperings of Melchisedec's entire family, if all his sons and daughters had chosen to come out of their hole to fight and tumble and play.

When she awakened it was rather suddenly, and she did not know that any particular thing had called her out of her sleep. The truth was, however, that it was a sound which had called her back - a real sound - the click of the skylight as it fell in closing after a lithe white figure which slipped through it and crouched down close by upon the slates of the roof - just near enough to see what happened in the attic, but not near enough to be seen.

At first she did not open her eyes. She felt too sleepy and - curiously enough - too warm and comfortable. She was so warm and comfortable, indeed, that she did not believe she was really awake. She never was as warm and cozy as this except in some lovely vision.

" What a nice dream! " she murmured. " I feel quite warm. I - don' t - want - to - wake - up. "

Of course it was a dream. She felt as if warm, delightful bedclothes were heaped upon her. She could actually FEEL blankets, and when she put out her hand it touched something exactly like a satin - covered eider - down quilt. She must not awaken from this delight - she must be quite still and make it last.

But she could not - even though she kept her eyes closed tightly, she could not. Something was forcing her to awaken - something in the room. It was a sense of light, and a sound - the sound of a crackling, roaring little fire.

" Oh, I am awakening, " she said mournfully. " I can' t help it - I can' t. "

Her eyes opened in spite of herself. And then she actually smiled - for what she saw she had never seen in the attic before, and knew she never should see.

" Oh, I HAVEN' T awakened, " she whispered, daring to rise on her elbow and look all about her, " I am dreaming yet. " She knew it MUST be a dream, for if she were awake such things could not - could not be.

Do you wonder that she felt sure she had not come back to earth? This is what she saw. In the grate there was a glowing, blazing fire; on the hob was a little brass kettle hissing and boiling; spread upon the floor was a thick, warm crimson rug; before the fire a folding - chair, unfolded, and with cushions on it; by the chair a small folding - table, unfolded, covered with a white cloth, and upon it spread small covered dishes, a cup, a saucer, a tea - pot; on the bed were new warm coverings and a satin - covered down quilt; at the foot a curious wadded silk robe, a pair of quilted slippers, and some books. The room of her dream seemed changed into fairyland - and it was flooded with warm light, for a bright lamp stood on the table covered with a rosy shade.

She sat up, resting on her elbow, and her breathing came short and fast.

" It does not - melt away, " she panted. " Oh, I never had such a dream before. " She scarcely dared to stir; but at last she pushed the bedclothes aside, and put her feet on the floor with a rapturous smile.

" I am dreaming - I am getting out of bed, " she heard her own voice say; and then, as she stood up in the midst of it all, turning slowly from side to side - " I am dreaming it stays - real! I' m dreaming it FEELS real. It's bewitched - or I' m bewitched. I only THINK I see it all. " Her words began to hurry themselves. " If I can only keep on thinking it, " she cried, " I don' t care! I don' t care! "

She stood panting a moment longer, and then cried out again.

" Oh, it isn' t true! " she said. " It CAN' T be true! But oh, how true it seems! "

The blazing fire drew her to it, and she knelt down and held out her hands close to it - so close that the heat made her start back.

" A fire I only dreamed wouldn' t be HOT, " she cried.

She sprang up, touched the table, the dishes, the rug; she went to the bed and touched the blankets. She took up the soft wadded dressing - gown, and suddenly clutched it to her breast and held it to her cheek.

" It's warm. It's soft! " she almost sobbed. " It's real. It must be! "

She threw it over her shoulders, and put her feet into the slippers.

" They are real, too. It's all real! " she cried. " I am NOT - I am NOT dreaming! "

She almost staggered to the books and opened the one which lay upon the top. Something was written on the flyleaf - just a few words, and they were these:

" To the little girl in the attic. From a friend. "

When she saw that - wasn' t it a strange thing for her to do? - she put her face down upon the page and burst into tears.

" I don' t know who it is, " she said; " But somebody cares for me a little. I have a friend. "

She took her candle and stole out of her own room and into Becky's, and stood by her bedside.

" Becky, Becky! " she whispered as loudly as she dared. " Wake up! "

When Becky wakened, and she sat upright staring aghast, her face still smudged with traces of tears, beside her stood a little figure in a luxurious wadded robe of crimson silk. The face she saw was a shining, wonderful thing. The Princess Sara - as she remembered her - stood at her very bedside, holding a candle in her hand.

" Come, " she said. " Oh, Becky, come! "

Becky was too frightened to speak. She simply got up and followed her, with her mouth and eyes open, and without a word.

And when they crossed the threshold, Sara shut the door gently and drew her into the warm, glowing midst of things which made her brain reel and her hungry senses faint.

" It's true! It's true! " she cried. " I' ve touched them all. They are as real as we are. The Magic has come and done it, Becky, while we were asleep - the Magic that won' t let those worst things EVER quite happen. "

CHAPTER ⅩⅧ　" I TRIED NOT TO BE"

IT was pretty, comfortable Mrs. Carmichael who explained everything. She was sent for at once, and came across the square to take Sara into her warm arms and make clear to her all that had happened. The excitement of the totally unexpected discovery had been temporarily almost overpowering to Mr. Carrisford in his weak condition.

" Upon my word, " he said faintly to Mr. Carmichael, when it was suggested that the little girl should go into another room, " I feel as if I do not want to lose sight of her. "

" I will take care of her, " Janet said, " and mamma will come in a few minutes. " And it was Janet who led her away.

" We' re so glad you are found, " she said. " You don' t know how glad we are that you are found. "

Donald stood with his hands in his pockets, and gazed at Sara with reflecting and self - reproachful eyes.

" If I' d just asked what your name was when I gave you my sixpence, " he said, " you would have told me it was Sara Crewe, and then you would have been found in a minute. "

Then Mrs. Carmichael came in. She looked very much moved, and suddenly took Sara in her arms and kissed her.

" You look bewildered, poor child, " she said. " And it is not to be wondered at. "

Sara could only think of one thing.

" Was he, " she said, with a glance toward the closed door of the library - " Was HE the wicked friend? Oh, do tell me! "

Mrs. Carmichael was crying as she kissed her again. She felt as if she ought to be kissed very often because she had not been kissed for so long.

" He was not wicked, my dear, " she answered. " He did not really lose your papa's money. He only thought he had lost it; and because he loved him so much his grief made him so ill that for a time he was not in his right mind. He almost died of brain fever, and long before he began to recover your poor papa was dead. "

" And he did not know where to find me, " murmured Sara. " And I was so near. " Somehow, she could not forget that she had been so near.

" He believed you were in school in France, " Mrs. Carmichael explained. " And he was continually misled by false clues. He has looked for you everywhere. When he saw you pass by, looking so sad and neglected, he did not dream that you were his friend's poor child; but because you were a little girl, too, he was sorry for you, and wanted to make you happier. And he told Ram Dass to climb into your attic window and try to make you comfortable. "

Sara gave a start of joy; her whole look changed.

" Did Ram Dass bring the things? " she cried out; " Did he tell Ram Dass to do it? Did he make the dream that came true! "

" Yes, my dear - yes! He is kind and good, and he was sorry for you, for little lost Sara Crewe's sake. "

The library door opened and Mr. Carmichael appeared, calling Sara to him with a gesture.

" Mr. Carrisford is better already, " he said. " He wants you to come to him. "

Sara did not wait. When the Indian gentleman looked at her as she entered, he saw that her face was all alight.

She went and stood before his chair, with her hands clasped together against her breast.

" You sent the things to me, " she said, in a joyful emotional little voice - " the beautiful, beautiful things? YOU sent them! "

" Yes, poor, dear child, I did, " he answered her. He was weak and broken with long illness and trouble, but he looked at her with the look she remembered in her father's eyes - that look of loving her and wanting to take her in his arms. It made her kneel down by him, just as she used to kneel by her father when they were the dearest friends and lovers in the world.

" Then it is you who are my friend, " she said; " It is you who are my friend! " And she dropped her face on his thin hand and kissed it again and again.

" The man will be himself again in three weeks, " Mr. Carmichael said aside to his wife. " Look at his face already. "

In fact, he did look changed. Here was the " Little missus, " and he had new things to think of and plan for already. In the first place, there was Miss Minchin. She must be interviewed and told of the change which had taken place in the fortunes of her pupil.

Sara was not to return to the seminary at all. The Indian gentleman was very determined upon that point. She must remain where she was, and Mr. Carmichael should go and see Miss Minchin himself.

" I am glad I need not go back, " said Sara. " She will be very angry. She does not like me; though perhaps it is my fault, because I do not like her. "

But, oddly enough. Miss Minchin made it unnecessary for Mr. Carmichael to go to her, by actually coming in search of her pupil herself. She had wanted Sara for something, and on inquiry had heard an astonishing thing. One of the housemaids had seen her steal out of the area with something hidden under her cloak, and had also seen her go up the steps of the next door and enter the house.

" What does she mean! " cried Miss Minchin to Miss Amelia.

" I don' t know, I' m sure, sister, " answered Miss Amelia. " Unless she has made friends with him because he has lived in India. "

" It would be just like her to thrust herself upon him and try to gain his sympathies in some such impertinent fashion, " said Miss Minchin. " She must have been in the house two hours. I will not allow such presumption. I shall go and inquire into the matter, and apologize for her intrusion. "

Sara was sitting on a footstool close to Mr. Carrisford's knee, and listening to some of the many things he felt it necessary to try to explain to her, when Ram Dass announced the visitor's arrival.

Sara rose involuntarily, and became rather pale; but Mr. Carrisford saw that she stood quietly, and showed none of the ordinary signs of child terror.

Miss Minchin entered the room with a sternly dignified manner. She was correctly and well dressed, and rigidly polite.

" I am sorry to disturb Mr. Carrisford, " she said; " but I have explanations to make. I am Miss Minchin, the proprietress of the Young Ladies'seminary next door. "

The Indian gentleman looked at her for a moment in silent scrutiny. He was a man who had naturally a rather hot temper, and he did not wish it to get too much the better of him.

" So you are Miss Minchin? " he said.

" I am, sir. "

" In that case, " the Indian gentleman replied, " You have arrived at the right time. My solicitor, Mr. Carmichael, was just on the point of going to see you. "

Mr. Carmichael bowed slightly, and Miss Minchin looked from him to Mr. Carrisford in amazement.

" Your solicitor! " she said. " I do not understand. I have come here as a matter of duty. I have just discovered that you have been intruded upon through the forwardness of one of my pupils - a charity pupil. I came to explain that she intruded without my knowledge. " She turned upon Sara. " Go home at once, " she commanded indignantly. " You shall be severely punished. Go home at once. "

The Indian gentleman drew Sara to his side and patted her hand.

" She is not going. "

Miss Minchin felt rather as if she must be losing her senses.

" Not going! " she repeated.

" No, " said Mr. Carrisford. " She is not going home - if you give your house that name. Her home for the future will be with me. "

Miss Minchin fell back in amazed indignation.

" With YOU! With YOU, sir! What does this mean? "

" Kindly explain the matter, Carmichael, " said the Indian gentleman; " and get it over as quickly as possible. " And he made Sara sit down again, and held her hands in his - which was another trick of her papa's.

Then Mr. Carmichael explained - in the quiet, level - toned, steady manner of a man who knew his subject, and all its legal significance, which was a thing Miss Minchin understood as a business woman, and did not enjoy.

" Mr. Carrisford, madam, " he said, " was an intimate friend of the late Captain Crewe. He was his partner in certain large investments. The fortune which Captain Crewe supposed he had lost has been recovered, and is now in Mr. Carrisford's hands. "

" The fortune! " cried Miss Minchin; and she really lost color as she uttered the exclamation. " Sara's fortune! "

" It WILL be Sara's fortune, " replied Mr. Carmichael, rather coldly. " It is Sara's fortune now, in fact. Certain events have increased it enormously. The diamond - mines have retrieved themselves. "

" The diamond - mines! " Miss Minchin gasped out. If this was true, nothing so horrible, she felt, had ever happened to her since she was born.

" The diamond - mines, " Mr. Carmichael repeated, and he could not help adding, with a rather sly, unlawyer - like smile: " There are not many princesses, Miss Minchin, who are richer than your little charity pupil, Sara Crewe, will be. Mr. Carrisford has been searching for her for nearly two years; he has found her at last, and he will keep her. "

After which he asked Miss Minchin to sit down while he explained matters to her fully, and went into such detail as was necessary to make it quite clear to her that Sara's future was an assured one, and that what had seemed to be lost was to be restored to her tenfold; also, that she had in Mr. Carrisford a guardian as well as a friend.

Miss Minchin was not a clever woman, and in her excitement she was silly enough to make one desperate effort to regain what she could not help seeing she had lost through her worldly folly.

" He found her under my care, " she protested. " I have done everything for her. But for me she would have starved in the streets. "

Here the Indian gentleman lost his temper.

" As to starving in the streets, " he said, " She might have starved more comfortably there than in your attic. "

" Captain Crewe left her in my charge, " Miss Minchin argued. " She must return to it until she is of age. She can be a parlor boarder again. She must finish her education. The law will interfere in my behalf. "

" Come, come. Miss Minchin, " Mr. Carmichael interposed, " the law will do nothing of the sort. If Sara herself wishes to return to you, I dare say Mr. Carrisford might not refuse to allow it. But that rests with Sara. "

" Then, " said Miss Minchin, " I appeal to Sara. I have not spoiled you, perhaps, " she said awkwardly to the little girl; " But you know that your papa was pleased with your progress. And - ahem! - I have always been fond of you. "

Sara's green - gray eyes fixed themselves on her with the quiet, clear look Miss Minchin particularly disliked.

" Have YOU, Miss Minchin? " she said; " I did not know that. "

Miss Minchin reddened and drew herself up.

" You ought to have known it, " said she; " but children, unfortunately, never know what is best for them. Amelia and I always said you were the cleverest child in the school. Will you not do your duty to your poor papa and come home with me? "

Sara took a step toward her and stood still. She was thinking of the day when she had been told that she belonged to nobody, and was in danger of being turned into the street; she was thinking of the cold, hungry hours she had spent alone with Emily and Melchisedec in the attic. She looked Miss Minchin steadily in the face.

" You know why I will not go home with you, Miss Minchin, " she said; " You know quite well. "

A hot flush showed itself on Miss Minchin's hard, angry face.

" You will never see your companions again, " she began. " I will see that Ermengarde and Lottie are kept away - "

Mr. Carmichael stopped her with polite firmness.

" Excuse me, " he said; " She will see anyone she wishes to see. The parents of Miss Crewe's fellow - pupils are not likely to refuse her invitations to visit her at her guardian's house. Mr. Carrisford will attend to that. "

It must be confessed that even Miss Minchin flinched. This was worse than the eccentric bachelor uncle who might have a peppery temper and be easily offended at the treatment of his niece. A woman of sordid mind could easily believe that most people would not refuse to allow their children to remain friends with a little heiress of diamond - mines. And if Mr. Carrisford chose to tell certain of her patrons how unhappy Sara Crewe had been made, many unpleasant things might happen.

" You have not undertaken an easy charge, " she said to the Indian gentleman, as she turned to leave the room; " You will discover that very soon. The child is neither truthful nor grateful. I suppose " - to Sara - " that you feel now that you are a princess again. "

Sara looked down and flushed a little, because she thought her pet fancy might not be easy for strangers - even nice ones - to understand at first.

" I - TRIED not to be anything else, " she answered in a low voice - " even when I was coldest and hungriest - I tried not to be. "

" Now it will not be necessary to try, " said Miss Minchin, acidly, as Ram Dass salaamed her out of the room.

* * * * * *

She returned home and, going to her sitting - room, sent at once for Miss Amelia. She sat closeted with her all the rest of the afternoon, and it must be admitted that poor Miss Amelia passed through more than one bad quarter of an hour. She shed a good many tears, and mopped her eyes a good deal. One of her unfortunate remarks almost caused her sister to snap her head entirely off, but it resulted in an unusual manner.

" I' m not as clever as you, sister, " she said, " And I am always afraid to say things to you for fear of making you angry. Perhaps if I were not so timid it would be better for the school and for both of us. I must say I' ve often thought it would have been better if you had been less severe on Sara Crewe, and had seen that she was decently dressed and more comfortable. I know she was worked too hard for a child of her age, and I know she was only half fed - "

" How dare you say such a thing! " exclaimed Miss Minchin.

" I don' t know how I dare, " Miss Amelia answered, with a kind of reckless courage; " But now I' ve begun I may as well finish, whatever happens to me. The child was a clever child and a good child - and she would have paid you for any kindness you had shown her. But you didn' t show her any. The fact was, she was too clever for you, and you always disliked her for that reason. She used to see through us both - "

" Amelia! " gasped her infuriated elder, looking as if she would box her ears and knock her cap off, as she had often done to Becky.

But Miss Amelia's disappointment had made her hysterical enough not to care what occurred next.

" She did! She did! " she cried. " She saw through us both. She saw that you were a hard - hearted, worldly woman, and that I was a weak fool, and that we were both of us vulgar and mean enough to grovel on our knees before her money, and behave ill to her because it was taken from her - though she behaved herself like a little princess even when she was a beggar. She did - she did - like a little princess! " and her hysterics got the better of the poor woman, and she began to laugh and cry both at once, and rock herself backward and forward in such a way as made Miss Minchin stare aghast.

" And now you' ve lost her, " she cried wildly; " And some other school will get her and her money; and if she were like any other child she' d tell how she's been treated, and all our pupils would be taken away and we should be ruined. And it serves us right; but it serves you right more than it does me, for you are a hard woman, Maria Minchin - you' re a hard, selfish, worldly woman! "

And she was in danger of making so much noise with her hysterical chokes and gurgles that her sister was obliged to go to her and apply salts and sal volatile to quiet her, instead of pouring forth her indignation at her audacity.

And from that time forward, it may be mentioned, the elder Miss Minchin actually began to stand a little in awe of a sister who, while she looked so foolish, was evidently not quite so foolish as she looked, and might, consequently, break out and speak truths people did not want to hear.

That evening, when the pupils were gathered together before the fire in the schoolroom, as was their custom before going to bed, Ermengarde came in with a letter in her hand and a queer expression on her round face. It was queer because, while it was an expression of delighted excitement, it was combined with such amazement as seemed to belong to a kind of shock just received.

" What IS the matter? " cried two or three voices at once.

" Is it anything to do with the row that has been going on? " said Lavinia, eagerly. " There has been such a row in Miss Minchin's room, Miss Amelia has had something like hysterics and has had to go to bed. "

Ermengarde answered them slowly as if she were half stunned.

" I have just had this letter from Sara, " she said, holding it out to let them see what a long letter it was.

" From Sara! " Every voice joined in that exclamation.

" Where is she? " almost shrieked Jessie.

" Next door, " said Ermengarde, still slowly; " With the Indian gentleman. "

" Where? Where? Has she been sent away? Does Miss Minchin know? Was the row about that? Why did she write? Tell us! Tell us! "

There was a perfect babel, and Lottie began to cry plaintively.

Ermengarde answered them slowly as if she were half plunged out into what, at the moment, seemed the most important and self - explaining thing.

" There WERE diamond - mines, " she said stoutly; " there WERE! "

Open mouths and open eyes confronted her.

" They were real, " she hurried on. " It was all a mistake about them. Something happened for a time, and Mr. Carrisford thought they were ruined - "

" Who is Mr. Carrisford? " shouted Jessie.

" The Indian gentleman. And Captain Crewe thought so, too - and he died; and Mr. Carrisfoird had brain fever and ran away, and HE almost died. And he did not know where Sara was. And it turned out that there were millions and millions of diamonds in the mines; and half of them belong to Sara; and they belonged to her when she was living in the attic with no one but Melchisedec for a friend, and the cook ordering her about. And Mr. Carrisford found her this afternoon, and he has got her in his home - and she will never come back - and she will be more a princess than she ever was - a hundred and fifty thousand times more. And I am going to see her tomorrow afternoon. There! "

Even Miss Minchin herself could scarcely have controlled the uproar after this; and though she heard the noise, she did not try. She was not in the mood to face anything more than she was facing in her room, while Miss Amelia was weeping in bed. She knew that the news had penetrated the walls in some mysterious manner, and that every servant and every child would go to bed talking about it.

So until almost midnight the entire seminary, realizing somehow that all rules were laid aside, crowded round Ermengarde in the schoolroom and heard read and re - read the letter containing a story which was quite as wonderful as any Sara herself had ever invented, and which had the amazing charm of having happened to Sara herself and the mystic Indian gentleman in the very next house.

Becky, who had heard it also, managed to creep upstairs earlier than usual. She wanted to get away from people and go and look at the little magic room once more. She did not know what would happen to it. It was not likely that it would be left to Miss Minchin. It would be taken away, and the attic would be bare and empty again. Glad as she was for Sara's sake, she went up the last flight of stairs with a lump in her throat and tears blurring her sight. There would be no fire tonight, and no rosy lamp; no supper, and no princess sitting in the glow reading or telling stories - no princess!

She choked down a sob as she pushed the attic door open, and then she broke into a low cry.

The lamp was flushing the room, the fire was blazing, the supper was waiting; and Ram Dass was standing smiling into her startled face.

" Missee sahib remembered, " he said. " She told the sahib all. She wished you to know the good fortune which has befallen her. Behold a letter on the tray. She has written. She did not wish that you should go to sleep unhappy. The sahib commands you to come to him tomorrow. You are to be the attendant of missee sahib. Tonight I take these things back over the roof. "

And having said this with a beaming face, he made a little salaam and slipped through the skylight with an agile silentness of movement which showed Becky how easily he had done it before.

译　序

这本童话书是我在2011年春翻译的，此前我只在1997年译过另一本童话书：《水孩子》。在众多经典童话中我选择这两本书是出于同一个原因：它们是那么的美。美丽的故事，美好的情感，诗意的叙述。不同的是，译《水孩子》是为了我自己早年对它的爱，译这本书一开始却是为了朋友和读者的愿望。

大约五年前，先后有几位好友，其中包括两位编辑朋友，表示希望我翻译《柳林风声》。我说：此书已经有了好几个中译本，我再重译是否多余？他们说：《柳林风声》的文字生动美丽，连美国总统罗斯福（二十世纪美国出过两位罗斯福总统，二战时的罗斯福总统是第二位，这里说的是第一位）也非常着迷，他甚至写信告诉作者说自己一口气读了三遍；但是，已有的中译本似乎不太理想，并没有那样的魅力。朋友们希望我抽点空，锤打一个更理想的中译本出来。很巧，那段时间我开始写博客，同时早年所译《水孩子》陆续出了多个版本，有几位《水孩子》的大读者找到我的电邮，写信给我，也是希望我重译《柳林风声》。于是，我把这件事放在了心上。

两年前我重新开始翻译童书。自然而然地，《柳林风声》成了首选。

这本书的作者肯尼斯·格雷厄姆（Kenneth Grahame，1859—1932）是英国苏格兰爱丁堡人，他的童年很不幸，五岁丧母，随后丧父，兄弟几个都由亲戚收养，他本人在母亲病逝后即由外公外婆带到乡间抚养。童年生活使他终生喜爱田野风光，热爱大自然。他喜欢研究动物，喜欢写作，但他没钱上大学，从二十岁开始起一直在银行里工作。1908年他被一个闯进银行的疯汉子开枪打伤，提早退休；就在这同一年，他的代表作《柳林风声》出版。

这本书的来由是他的儿子。他四十岁出头才得了一个儿子，非常疼爱。孩子六岁时，他自己编故事讲给他听；孩子听得入了迷，不肯离开他去外地过暑假，他就答应用写信的办法来继续。他履行了对儿子的诺言，而那些信件……是的，那些信后来经过加工，变成了你正在往下看的这本书。

这是一本有趣又甜美温馨的书。

有趣的是书中的动物和他们的冒险经历。他们是胆小老实又喜欢冒险的鼹鼠莫尔，热情好客并有诗人气质的水鼠兰特，虚荣浮夸、追求时尚的癞蛤蟆托德和持重且侠义的獾子班杰，另外，还有一个贪吃而潇洒豪爽的水獭奥特。他们友爱互助，经历了许多奇妙有趣的事情，最后癞蛤蟆托德靠朋友们一道仗义出手，夺回家园，并终于改掉了自己的坏毛病。

甜美温馨的是书的主题和情调：家园和友情。无论是奢华的家（癞蛤蟆托德的家）还是简朴的家（鼹鼠莫尔的家），无论是规模宏大的家（獾子班杰的家）还是温馨整洁的小家（水鼠兰特的家），都是动物们各自珍爱的；那一带的河岸和树林是他们共同的家园。他们互相探访，结伴同游，生活充满情趣。鼹鼠莫尔同水鼠兰特相依相伴的友情，獾子班杰兄长般的友爱与呵护，他们仨对癞蛤蟆托德的关爱，构成了整个故事的基调。

如果你喜爱大自然，那你就更应该读这本书了。在肯尼斯·格雷厄姆的笔下，田野、河流、道路、树木……是那么的美丽、充满诗意。季节的变化触动心弦，寻找小水獭的整个过程像美梦一样令人迷醉。燕子们对南方的描述，航海鼠对远方大海和港湾的描述，是那么令人向往……

那么美的笔触在叙述癞蛤蟆托德的荒唐冒险时，又带着一种轻轻的嘲讽，使他显得既滑稽又可爱。甚至在描述水鼠兰特的诗意的感伤时，也略带一丝调侃。这又使全书显得非常轻松活泼。

文字本身是那么的生动，那些句子是那么的精致，使我这个译者感觉到，这本给孩子读的书的难译程度甚至不亚于诗歌。但是翻译过程中我感觉到的只有愉悦，因为我发现自己渐渐地也爱上了它。一本真正好的童话书，对孩子和大人来说都是很有吸引力的，《柳林风声》正是这样一本书。希望它没有被我糟蹋了，希望这个译本没有让我的朋友们，还有你──亲爱的小读者或者大读者──感到失望。

杨柳风，春天的风。

张炽恒
2013年春于奉贤海湾

第一章　河岸

整个早晨，鼹鼠莫尔都在十分努力地工作，给他的小家做春季大清扫。先扫地，再掸灰，然后踩着梯子、台阶和椅子，用石灰水刷墙。最后弄得眼睛和喉咙里都是灰土，一身黑皮毛上溅满了石灰水的白点子，胳膊酸疼，腰酸背痛。而他头顶上的空气、脚下的泥土，他的周围，都洋溢着春天的气息；连他那昏暗低矮的小房子，都透进了春天的无比美妙的渴望氛围。所以呀，他突然发飙就没什么可奇怪的了：他把刷子扔在地板上。“讨厌，”他说，“啊，见鬼！”还加上一句：“去他的春季大清扫！”说完外套都没披上，就冲出了家门。上面有什么东西在急切地召唤着他。他沿着陡峭而狭窄的通道向上爬去。对他来说，这通道就相当于那些住宅离太阳和天空更近的动物所拥有的铺石子儿的马车道。他一边忙着用小爪子扒呀、挖呀、抓呀、抠呀，一边自言自语地咕哝着：“我们上去喽！我们上去喽！”终于，噗！大鼻子钻进了阳光里，他发现自己在一片大草甸上，在温暖的草上打滚。

“真棒！”他说，“这可比石灰水好多了！”阳光洒在他的皮毛上，暖洋洋的；柔和的微风抚摸着他晒热的额头。在与世隔绝的地洞里住了那么久，听觉也迟钝了，小鸟快乐的鸣唱一下子灌进耳朵，差不多就像是吼叫。他立刻弹起四条腿，在生活的欢乐中，在春天的喜悦里，把春季大清扫抛到脑后，蹿过大草坪，来到它另一边的树篱前。

“站住！”树篱豁口处，一只上了年纪的兔子喝道，“此路私人所有，留下六便士买路钱！”顷刻间，他就被很不耐烦的莫尔轻蔑地撞翻了。别的兔子急忙从洞口向外窥望，想看看外面究竟在闹腾什么。莫尔沿着树篱内侧一溜小跑，耍弄他们寻开心。“洋葱酱！洋葱酱！”他嘲弄地说。他们还没来得及想出一句十分满意的话来回敬他，他已经跑得没了影。于是他们像惯常那样，一个个互相埋怨起来。“瞧你多笨！你干吗不告诉他……”“哟，你为什么不说……”“你原本可以提醒他……”等等；不过当然啰，这些都是事后聪明，他们照例总是这一套的。

一切都太美好了，仿佛不是真的一样。他很起劲儿地在草地上东跑西颠，沿着灌木丛，翻过坡顶，发现处处小鸟在筑巢，花儿绽开苞蕾，叶子抽出嫩芽──万物都很快乐，都在成长，都没有空闲。可并没有愧疚感因此来刺他，对他嘀咕“石灰水！”不知为什么，他只感觉到，在这一大群忙碌的居民中间，做唯一的一只懒狗狗，有多么快活。说到底，休假这事最好的地方，也许还不是自己在休息，而是看到别的家伙都在忙着干活儿。

他漫无目的地东游西逛，突然在河边停住了脚步：一条盈满水的河。这时他觉得自己幸福到极点了。他生平还从来没见过河──这个光滑、弯曲、身躯庞大的动物，追逐着、轻轻地笑着，抓住什么东西就汩汩地笑，又哗哗大笑着把它们放开，扑向前去抓新的玩伴，它们晃动着挣脱了，又被它追上来抓住。它浑身颤动，亮晶晶，闪着粼粼、熠熠、烁烁的光；它打着漩儿，翻着泡泡，沙沙地响着，不停地唠叨着。鼹鼠莫尔痴了，迷了，着魔了。他沿着河边一路小跑，就像一个小孩子听大人讲动听的故事着了迷，小跑着紧跟在大人左右一样。他终于跑累了，在河岸上坐下来，而河流依然在不停地对他唠叨着；世上最好听的故事，潺潺地鱼贯而来，发自地心深处，最终要去向那永不知足的大海倾诉。

他正坐在那里向河对岸张望，一个黑乎乎的洞吸引住了他的目光。它在对面的河堤上，离水面只有一点点。他像在梦中一样迷迷糊糊地想：对于一个要求不高、又喜欢小巧玲珑的河边住宅的动物来说，那是个多么温暖舒适的住所呀，河水泛滥时淹不到，又远离尘嚣。他正盯着看，忽然，在洞中央，一个亮晶晶的小东西好像闪了一下，很快就消失了，然后又像一颗小星星一样闪了一下。但星星是不会出现在这样一个地方的，要说是萤火虫吧，又太亮太小了。他正望着呢，它冲着他眨了一下，这就宣告了它是一只眼睛。渐渐地，一张小脸在它周围显现出来，就像画儿的周围显现出画框一样。

一张长着胡须的棕色小脸。

圆脸很严肃，眼睛闪着光──就是一开始吸引他注意的那种亮光。

小巧玲珑的耳朵，丝绸一样的浓密毛发。

是水鼠兰特！

于是，两只动物站在那里，谨慎地互相打量着。

“嗨，莫尔！”水鼠兰特说。

“嗨，兰特！”鼹鼠莫尔说。

“你想过来吗？”水鼠兰特就问。

“唉，说说倒是挺容易的呢。”鼹鼠莫尔说。他有点生气，因为自己是第一次见识河流，对于河边的生活方式很陌生。

水鼠兰特什么也没有说，弯下身子，解开一条绳索，往里拽，然后轻轻地跨上鼹鼠莫尔先前没注意到的一条小船。船的外壳漆成蓝色，内侧漆成白色，大小正好能容下两只动物。鼹鼠莫尔的整个心立刻飞到了船上，尽管他还没有完全明白它的用处。

水鼠兰特敏捷地把船划过来，停稳了，然后伸出前爪，搀着战战兢兢的鼹鼠莫尔迈步往下走。“扶好了！”他说，“现在，动作快些跨上来！”鼹鼠莫尔又惊又喜地发现，自己千真万确坐在了一条真船的船尾。

“今天真是太美妙了！”他说，这时水鼠兰特一撑，让船离开河岸，又重新拿起了桨，“你知道吗，这一辈子我还从来没坐过船呢。”

“什么？”水鼠兰特吃惊地张大了嘴，叫道，“从来没坐过──你从来没有──哦哟哟──那你一直在做些什么哟？”

“坐船真那么美吗？”鼹鼠莫尔不好意思地问。其实，他早就已经愿意相信这一点了：在他的背刚靠上座位后背，试试靠垫的时候；在他打量着船桨、桨架和所有迷人的装备，开始感觉到船在身子底下轻轻摇晃的时候。

“美？这可是世上独一无二的哟。”水鼠庄严地说，“相信我，朋友，坐着船就那么闲逛，是最有价值的事。没有第二件事抵得上它的一半，绝对没有。就那么闲逛。”他继续像做梦一样地说着：“坐──着──船──闲──逛──，坐着──”

“看着前面，兰特！”鼹鼠莫尔突然嚷道。

太迟了。全速行驶的小船撞在河岸上。那梦中人，那快乐的桨手，四爪朝天躺在了船底。

“——船——或跟着船——闲逛，”水鼠兰特快活地大笑一声，一个翻身坐了起来，从容地接着说下去，“待在船里面还是外面，无所谓。好像无论怎样都没什么大不了，魅力就在这里呀。出发，还是不走；到达目的地，还是到达别的地方，还是哪里都不去，你都一直在忙着，从来不专门去做一件事。做完一件事，总是会有别的事可以做，喜欢就可以去做，不过，没什么喜欢就不做最好。听我说！今天上午你要是手头没什么大不了的事，我们就一起顺流而下，逛上它一整天，好不好？”

鼹鼠莫尔十分幸福地来回晃动着脚趾，十分满意地叹出一口气，舒展了一下胸口，快乐透顶地往后一靠，陷在柔软的垫子里。“今天我要开心死了！”他说，“立刻出发！”

“那好，稍等一分钟！”水鼠兰特说。他把缆绳穿进小栈桥上的一个圆环里，爬上去走进洞，只一会儿就蹒跚着又出来了，头上顶着一个胖大的、藤条编的午餐篮子。

“把它丢在你脚边。”他把篮子递上船，看着鼹鼠莫尔，说道。然后，他解开缆绳，重新操起了桨。

“篮子里是什么呢？”鼹鼠莫尔好奇地扭动着身子，问道。

“里面有冷鸡肉，”水鼠兰特报起了菜名，“冷舌头冷火腿冷牛肉腌小黄瓜沙拉法式面包卷水芹菜三明治罐装肉姜汁啤酒柠檬汁苏打水……”

“哇，打住，打住，”鼹鼠莫尔欣喜若狂地嚷道，“太多了！”

“你真的认为太多？”水鼠兰特认真地问，“这只是我平时这样小小出游一下时带的东西，别的动物还老说我小气呢，说我太抠门儿！”

这些话鼹鼠莫尔一个字也没听进去。他沉浸在刚刚投入的新生活里，陶醉在波光、涟漪、芳香、水声和阳光中。他把一只爪子伸进水里，做着悠长的白日梦。水鼠本是个好心肠的小家伙，稳稳当当地划着船，忍着不去打扰他。

“你的衣服我喜欢得要命，老伙计，”大约半小时后，他评论说，“哪一天有了钱，我要给自己弄一套黑丝绒吸烟装。”

“对不起，”鼹鼠莫尔好不容易回过神来，说道，“你一定觉得我没礼貌，但是这一切对我来说太新鲜了。这样看来──这──就是一条──河！”

“这就是那条河。”水鼠兰特纠正道。

“你真的住河边？多快乐的生活啊！”

“住河边，靠河过日子，水上漂，水里游，”水鼠兰特说，“对我来说，它就是兄弟姐妹，姑姑姨姨，朋友伙伴，吃的喝的，天然浴盆。它是我的整个世界，别的无论什么世界我都不要。凡是它没有的，都不值得去要；凡是它不了解的，都不值得去想。主啊！我们一起度过的时光多么美好！春夏秋冬一年四季，它都富有情趣，都有让人兴奋的地方。二月里，洪水来了，我的地窖里灌满了喝了没好处的饮料，黄褐色的水在我最好的卧室窗户旁边奔流；水落下去以后，露出一块块气味像葡萄干蛋糕一样的泥巴，灯芯草之类的杂草堵塞了通道，那时我就可以在大部分河床上到处逛逛而不弄湿鞋子了，还能找到新鲜的食物吃，捡到粗心大意的人从船上掉下来的东西！”

“不过，会不会有时也有点无聊啊？”鼹鼠莫尔大着胆子问，“只有你和河，没有别人可以说个话什么的？”

“你说没有别人？──嗨，我可不能对你要求太高喽，”水鼠兰特宽宏大量地说，“你刚认识河，当然不会了解。如今河岸上太拥挤，许多人就都一块儿搬家了。不是的哦，往常的光景根本不是这样的。水獭呀，翠鸟呀，小鸊鷉呀，黑水鸡呀，全都整天没完没了地要你干这干那──好像别人自己没事情要打理似的！”

“那边是什么？”鼹鼠莫尔挥了挥爪子，指着大河一侧的远处问，一片围着草地的黑幽幽的树林。

“那个？哦，那就是野树林，”水鼠兰特简短地说，“我们很少去那里，我们河边居民。”

“他们──住在那边的不是正派人？”鼹鼠莫尔问，有一点紧张。

“嗯……”水鼠兰特答道，“让我想想。松鼠是好人。兔子嘛──有的还好，但是兔子有好有坏。当然，还有獾子班杰。他就住在树林正中央，别处哪里也不肯住，你出钱请他也不去。亲爱的老班杰！没人招惹他。他们最好别招惹他。”他意味深长地加上一句。

“哟，谁会招惹他？”鼹鼠莫尔问。

“嗯，当然……还……住着些别的人，”水鼠兰特解释说，有点吞吞吐吐，“黄鼠狼，白鼬，狐狸什么的。要说呢，他们也不坏……我同他们是很好的朋友，遇上了就一起打发掉一点时间，玩玩……但他们有时会胡来，这个不用否认，还有，嗯，不能真的相信他们，这也是事实。”

鼹鼠莫尔很清楚，老是谈论可能会遇到的麻烦，哪怕不明说只是暗示，都不合动物的礼节。所以，他抛开了这个话题。

“野树林再过去是什么地方呢？”他问，“就是那个一片蓝，模模糊糊，看上去像山又可能不是山的东西，像是镇子里的炊烟，也许只是一片浮云？”

“野树林那边是广阔世界，”水鼠兰特说，“那地方跟你我没什么关系。我从没去过，也永远不会去。如果你头脑没有完全发昏，也不要去。请别再提它了。好啦！终于到回水河汊了，我们开饭。”

离开主河道后，他们驶进了一片美丽的水面。初看上去它像陆地环抱的一个小湖：绿茸茸的草皮从每一面坡岸上披垂到水边，蛇一样的褐色树根在幽静的水面下泛着光，而他们前方是一道拦河坝的银色肩胛，河水泛着泡沫在坝下翻滚。与水坝挽手并肩的，是一个永不休止地滴着水的水车轮，它不停地转动着，带动一座有灰色山墙的磨坊，使空中充满了催眠般的咕哝声，沉闷得让人透不过气来，但磨坊里面却隔一会儿传出一阵轻轻的说话声，清脆而欢快。真是太美了，鼹鼠莫尔不由得举起两只前爪，喘息着说：“哦，天！哦，天！哦，天！”

水鼠兰特把船划到岸边，靠稳了，帮助仍然笨手笨脚的莫尔安全地上了岸，然后把午餐篮甩上去。

鼹鼠莫尔请求恩准他独自打开篮子，水鼠兰特很高兴地批准了。他自己伸开四爪躺在草地上休息，听凭兴奋不已的朋友抖开桌布铺好，把篮子里的神秘小包一个个取出来，解开后一样一样依次摆好。莫尔依然在喘息着，每揭开一个新秘密都叫一声：“哦，天！哦，天！”一切准备就绪后，水鼠兰特说道：“现在开饭。使劲儿吃吧，老伙计！”这样一个吩咐，鼹鼠莫尔可真乐意听从哟。因为当天一大早，他就按习俗开始春季大清扫，没有停下来吃喝过一点点东西；后来他又经历了许多事，但都仿佛跟现在隔了好远，过了好多天似的。

“你在看什么呢？”水鼠兰特就说。这时，他们饥饿难耐的感觉已经多少缓解了一些了，鼹鼠莫尔的眼睛已经能够稍微离开桌布，看看别的地方。

“我在看一串气泡，”鼹鼠莫尔说，“我看见它们在水面上移动，觉得挺好玩儿。”

“水泡？啊哈！”话音刚落，水鼠兰特就开始快活地叭叽嘴，那样子像是在馋什么人。

紧靠岸边的水面上，露出一张闪光的大嘴巴，水獭奥特把身子伸上来，抖掉外套上的水。

“贪吃的叫花子！”他评论道，一边向食物凑过来，“怎么不邀请我呀，鼠仔？”

“这是个临时聚餐，”水鼠兰特解释说，“顺便介绍一下，我朋友莫尔先生。”

“实在很荣幸。”水獭奥特说，两只动物立刻成了朋友。

“到处都是这样吵闹！”水獭奥特接着说道，“今天好像全世界的人都跑出家门，到水上来了。我来到这回水河汊是图个片刻清静，却没想到碰上你们两个家伙！至少──对不起──我不是这个意思，你们知道的。”

后面窸窣一阵响。声音是从一片树篱中间发出来的，那边依然厚厚地积着去年的落叶。一个斑纹脑袋，架在两只高耸的肩膀前面，从落叶上向这边窥望。

“过来，老班杰！”水鼠兰特叫道。

獾子班杰向前小跑了一两步，然后哼了一声：“呣，伙伴们！”就背过身去，从视野中消失了。

“他就是那么一个家伙！”水鼠兰特很失望评论说，“就是讨厌社交！今天我们不会再看到他了。嗳，告诉我们，河上还有些什么人？”

“托德就是一个，他出来了，”水獭奥特答道，“驾着他那条崭新的赛艇，穿着新运动衣，什么都是新的！”

两只动物相视大笑。

“有一阵子，他只迷帆船，”水鼠兰特说，“后来腻歪了，就玩撑船。什么都不喜欢，成天地玩撑船，天天玩，惹了不少乱子。去年改玩房船，我们大家只好跟着他在房船里待着，并且假装很喜欢。他准备下半辈子就在房船里过。无论他玩什么，每回都一样，旧的腻了，又开始玩新的。”

“他这种人倒也是好人，”水獭奥特若有所思地评论道，“可就是没常性，特别是在船上！”

从他们坐着的地方，目光可以越过中间隔着的小岛，瞥见主河道。就在这时候，一只赛艇刷地映入了眼帘，那个桨手──一个又矮又胖的身影──在艇中前后滚动着，搅得水花四溅，可是他已经是划得不能再卖力了。水鼠兰特站起身来向他打招呼，但是癞蛤蟆托德，没错正是他，他摇摇头，坚定不移地继续划他的船。

“如果他老这样前后滚动，一分钟就会从船里滚出来。”水鼠兰特坐下来，说道。

“肯定的，”水獭奥特咯咯地笑道，“我有没有给你讲过那件好玩的事，就是托德和运河水闸管理员的故事？事情是这样的。托德……”

一只迷路的蜉蝣逆水而来，忽东忽西地改变着方向，那副喝醉了的样子，正是血气方刚、对生活无知无畏的蜉蝣才有的。水上起了一个漩涡，噗哧一声，蜉蝣没影了。

水獭奥特也没影了。

鼹鼠莫尔望过去。奥特的声音犹在耳边，可他趴过的那片草皮上却明明白白已是空空如也。一直望到天边，也不见一只水獭。

但是河面上又起了一串水泡。

水鼠兰特哼起了小曲儿。鼹鼠莫尔想起来了，动物界有个规矩：朋友任何时候突然消失，无论是什么原因，或者根本没有原因，都是不许评论的。

“嗨，嗨，”水鼠兰特说，“我觉得我们该挪挪地方了。不知道我们俩谁来收拾午餐篮比较好？”听他的口气，他好像并不非常渴望得到这个差事。

“哦，我来吧。”鼹鼠莫尔说。既然如此，水鼠兰特当然就让他来了。

收拾午餐篮这件事，是比不上打开它那样令人愉快的。从来都是这样。可鼹鼠莫尔能专心享受每一件事。他刚收拾好，用带子把篮子系紧，又看见一只盘子在草地上瞪着他；他刚把篮子打开再系好，水鼠兰特又指给他看一只任何人都不会看不见的叉子。最最最后，瞧！还有那只他一直坐在上面却毫无知觉的芥末瓶──不过，这件事终于还是完成了，并不让他感到非常生气。

下午的太阳已经在往下沉了，水鼠兰特像做梦一样往回家的方向轻轻地划着船，一边还自顾自地咕哝着什么诗，不怎么理会莫尔。可鼹鼠莫尔午餐吃得饱饱的，心满意足，坐船已经十分在行（他自己这么认为），而且还有点坐不住了，他就说：“鼠仔！我想划划船好吗，现在！”

水鼠兰特微笑着摇摇头。“现在还不行，我年轻的朋友，”他说，“等你训练过几回再说吧。这事不像看起来那么容易。”

鼹鼠莫尔安静了一两分钟，但他心里越来越羡慕兰特。看人家一直划得那么有力，那么轻而易举，他的自尊心开始嘀咕着，他能划得一样好。他跳起来，一把抓住桨。水鼠兰特正出神地望着远处的水面，嘴巴里依然在自言自语地念诗，这突然的一下子吓了他一大跳，一个后仰从座位上摔下来，第二次四爪朝天。这时得胜的莫尔占了他的位置，信心十足地把桨攥在手里。

“住手，你这头蠢驴！”水鼠兰特躺在船底嚷道，“你干不了！你会把船弄翻的！”

鼹鼠莫尔动作有些夸张地把双桨向后一挥，深深地插进水里。他一点都没有划到水面，两条腿一下子甩到空中，整个身子压在躺着的兰特身上。他慌了神，一把抓住船沿，说时迟那时快──噗通！

船翻了，他发现自己在河水中挣扎。

哦，天，水多冷啊，哇，感觉湿得要命。他往下沉，沉，沉，水在耳朵里唱的那是什么歌呀！他浮上水面了，咳着呛着扑腾得水花四溅，这时的太阳多么明亮可亲啊！他感觉到自己又在往下沉，这时他心里一片漆黑，多么绝望哟！接着，一只强有力的爪子抓住了他的脖梗子。──是水鼠兰特，他显然在笑──鼹鼠莫尔能感觉到他在笑，那笑从他的胳膊传下来，通过爪子，传到了他──鼹鼠莫尔的脖子上。

水鼠兰特抓住一支桨，把它塞到鼹鼠莫尔胳膊下面，然后把另一支桨塞到他另一只胳膊下面，自己在后面游着。他把那无助的动物推向岸边，捞出水，在岸上安置好，嚯，那就是一个水淋淋、软塌塌、惨兮兮的包包。

水鼠兰特把他的身子揉搓了一遍，挤掉一些水，然后说道：“得啦，老伙计！现在沿着纤路[1]来回跑，使足了劲儿跑，直到身上干了暖和了为止，我要下水去捞午餐篮了。”

那凄凄惨惨的莫尔，身上透湿，心里面羞愧，开始跑起来，身上差不多干了才停下。这段时间水鼠兰特重新又扎回到水里，把船找回来，翻正，拴牢，把漂浮在水面上的杂物渐渐捞回到岸上，最后潜下水去，找到午餐篮，带着它吃力地上了岸。

一切准备就绪，可以重新出发了。鼹鼠莫尔垂头丧气、一瘸一拐地到船尾坐了下来。开船时，他控制不住激动的情绪，声音低低地说：“鼠仔，我宽宏大量的朋友！真的非常对不起，我的行为太愚蠢、太不知好歹了。刚才想着我可能把漂亮的午餐篮弄丢了，我十分灰心。我知道，我真就是一头十足的蠢驴。你能不能不计前嫌，原谅我，让我们还像以前一样吗？”

“没问题的，上帝保佑你！”水鼠兰特爽快地答应，“沾一点点水，对一只水鼠来说算什么？多数日子，我待在水里的时间比不在水里的时间还要长。别再想它了，听我说！我真的觉得，你最好过来，和我一起待一段时间。我的家很普通很简陋，根本没法和托德家相比，但你还没有去过呢，再怎样我还是能让你住得很舒服的。我可以教你划船、游泳，很快你就会同我们一样，在水上行动自如。”

他这一番厚道诚挚的话，让鼹鼠莫尔感动得说不出话来，只好用爪子背去擦脸上的一两滴泪。水鼠兰特懂得体谅人，眼睛看着别处。鼹鼠莫尔的心情很快就好转了，当两只黑水鸡窃笑着议论他那副狼狈相时，他居然已经能直截了当地回敬他们。

回到家后，水鼠兰特在客厅里生了一炉旺火，在炉子前面摆上一把扶手椅，把鼹鼠莫尔安置在椅子里，替他拿来晨衣和拖鞋，给他讲河上的故事，一直到吃晚饭。对莫尔这样一个住在土里的动物来说，那些故事听起来也是非常惊险有趣的。故事说到了拦河坝、突然暴发的洪水、跳着朝前的狗鱼，还有扔瓶子的汽船──无论如何，确实有瓶子扔下来，而且是从汽船上扔下来的，所以可以推断扔瓶子的就是船。故事里还说到了鹭鸟，他们自以为很了不起；还说到了冒险钻排水沟，同水獭奥特一起夜里捕鱼，跟獾子班杰一块儿去田野里远足。晚饭吃得开心极了，但是饭后不久莫尔就犯困，殷勤的主人只好护送他上楼，进了最好的那间卧室。他的脑袋很快就搁在枕头上，心里面安宁极了满足极了，因为他知道，他新认识的朋友，大河，在轻轻拍打着窗台。

对解放了的鼹鼠莫尔来说，那一天只是许许多多同样美好的好日子的开端。那些日子充满了情趣，并且白昼一天比一天长，因为，丰润成熟的夏天正在到来。莫尔学会了游泳和划船，真正体会到了流水做伴的乐趣。他把耳朵凑近芦苇秆去听，已经间或能听懂风在芦苇丛中飘游时不断发出的窃窃私语声了。

[1]从前没有机器动力时，内河的船往往靠人力拉纤行驶，纤夫们行走的沿河小泾称为“纤路”。

第二章　大路朝天

一个明媚的夏日早晨，鼹鼠莫尔突然说道：“鼠仔，我想求你件事，不知行不？”

水鼠兰特坐在河岸上，正在唱一支小曲儿。那歌是他自己编的，所以他唱得很投入，对莫尔和别的事就不够关心了。话得从那天一大早说起，他和鸭子朋友们一起在河里游泳。鸭子总是喜欢突然来个倒立，他就趁他们这样做的时候，潜下水去，在他们脖子上挠痒痒，就挠在他们的下巴下面，如果说鸭子有下巴的话。鸭子们只好急急忙忙重新浮上水面，冲着他扑打翅膀，气急败坏地嚷嚷。因为你的脑袋要是在水底下，你是不可能把自己的感受痛痛快快说出来的。最后他们乞求他走开，去干自个儿的事，不要再骚扰他们。于是水鼠兰特走开了，他坐在河岸上晒太阳，编了一首鸭子歌，歌名叫做：

鸭　谣

沿着回水河汊，
在高高的灯芯草中间，
看那戏水群鸭，
全都尾巴朝天！

母鸭公鸭尾巴，
还抖动着黄黄的脚丫，
黄黄鸭嘴皆不见，
全都忙活在水下！

绿水草沾着泥浆，
鳊鱼儿在里面游荡，
好一个食物橱哟，
又冷又暗却丰富。

人都各有所爱！
我们有自己的偏爱：
头朝下尾巴朝上，
戏水自由自在！

蓝天在上高高，
雨燕儿盘旋呼叫──
我们在下面戏水，
尾巴齐齐高翘！

“我真说不上非常非常欣赏这首小曲儿，兰特。”鼹鼠莫尔小心翼翼地评论道。他自己不是诗人，也不在乎让别人知道这一点，而且他生性直率。

“鸭子们也说不上喜欢的，”水鼠兰特爽快地答道，“他们会说：‘干吗不让人家在高兴的时候按他们高兴的方式做他们高兴做的事，旁人却要坐在岸上一直看着他们评头品足，做诗来编排他们？全是胡说八道！’这就是鸭子们会说的话。”

“那就是了，那就是了。”鼹鼠莫尔诚心诚意地说。

“不是，不是胡说八道！”水鼠兰特气呼呼地嚷道。

“嗯，那就不是，不是，”鼹鼠莫尔宽慰他说，“可我想问你的是，可不可以带我去拜访托德先生？我听说过他许多事，特别想和他认识一下。”

“嗯，当然可以啦，”和善的兰特说道，他一跃而起，把诗歌从脑袋里解散了，并且那一天再也没有把他们召回，“把船弄出来，我们立刻就划船去他家。什么时间拜访托德都不会不合时宜的。去得早与晚，他都是那副样子。永远是好脾气，你去他总是高兴，你走他总是难过！”

“他一定是个非常好的人。”鼹鼠莫尔评论道。他已经上了船，正拿起桨，而水鼠兰特已经舒舒服服在船尾的座位上坐好了。

“他真是最最好的动物，”兰特答道，“那么单纯，那么和善，那么重感情。也许他不是很聪明──不可能人人都是天才嘛，可能他喜欢吹牛，而且又骄傲自大，但是他有一些了不起的好品质，这蛤蟆仔。”

绕过一个河湾后，他们眼前出现了一座美观庄严的旧红砖老房子，保养得很好的草坪从房子前面一直延伸到水边。

“那就是蛤蟆府，”水鼠兰特说，“左边那个小河湾，就是告示牌上写着‘私人河湾，不准登岸’的，通到他的停船棚屋，我们就在那里下船。马厩在另一边，靠右。你现在看着的那是宴会厅，要说起来的话，年代很久了。你知道的呀，托德相当有钱，这房子确实是附近一带最好的，不过，在托德面前我们从来不这样说。”

他们沿着小河湾向前划行，驶进一个很大的停船棚屋的阴影中，鼹鼠莫尔迅速地收了桨。他们看见里面有很多漂亮的船，有的吊挂在横梁上，有的收放在滑道上，但没有一条在水里。这地方有一种荒废冷落的气氛。

水鼠兰特看看四周。“我明白啦，”他说，“玩船这事结束喽。他已经玩腻了，玩够了。真想知道他如今又在玩什么新花样。来吧，我们去看看他。很快他就会把家底全亮给我们的。”

他们上了岸，穿过点缀着鲜花的草坪，溜达着寻找托德。很快他们就碰上了他，那位老兄正舒舒服服坐在一张藤条花园椅里，满脸专注的神情，膝盖上铺放着一张大地图。

“万岁！”一见他们，他就跳起来，喊道，“好极了！”没等介绍鼹鼠莫尔，他就热情地和他们俩握爪子。“你们能来真是太好了！”他一边接着往下说，一边围着他们跳舞，“我正要派船到下游去接你们，鼠仔，我会严令他们马上接你过来，无论你正在做什么。我极其需要你──你们俩。想用点什么？进去吃点东西吧！你们来得正是时候，你们想不到这有多巧！”

“让我们安安静静坐一会儿吧，蛤蟆仔！”水鼠兰特说着就一屁股坐在一张安乐椅里。鼹鼠莫尔在他旁边一张椅子里坐下，说了几句客气话，称赞托德那“可爱的住宅”。

“整个大河流域最精美的房子，”托德哇啦哇啦地嚷嚷道，“这么好的房子，任何地方也找不到。”他忍不住又加上了一句。

听到这里，水鼠兰特用胳膊肘捅了捅鼹鼠莫尔。很不幸，癞蛤蟆托德看到了这个动作，脸涨得通红。一阵难堪的静寂。接着托德爆发出一阵大笑。“没什么，鼠仔，”他说，“我就是这德行，你知道的啦。这房子并不是那么差，是不？你知道的呀，你自己也相当喜欢它。得啦，我们都切合实际一些。你们正是我需要的动物。你们得帮我。这至关重要！”

“要我猜，是你划船的事吧，”水鼠兰特做出一副愚钝的样子，说道，“你进步挺快，不过还是溅出来不少水花。好好拿出点耐心，再加上些辅导，就可以……”

“哦，呸！划船！”癞蛤蟆托德非常厌恶地打断了他的话，“愚蠢的活动，小孩子玩的。我早就放弃了。没别的，纯粹浪费时间。你们这些家伙本该是明白人，却把所有精力都这样漫无目标地用掉，看到这个我真是痛心透顶。不，我发现了一件真正有意义的事，唯一一件可以做一辈子的正经工作，我打算把余生都奉献给它。过去那么多岁月都浪费了，用在一些无聊的事情上，想到这个我只感到后悔。跟我来，亲爱的鼠仔，还有你这位和蔼的朋友，希望他能赏光。就在马厩场院那边，你们会看到该看一看的东西！”

于是他领路向马厩场院走去，水鼠兰特跟着，脸上是一副表示最最不信任的神情。可是瞧哦，从马车房里拉出来一辆吉卜赛大篷车，只见它簇新锃亮，漆成金丝雀黄，点缀着绿色花饰，车轮是红的。

“就是它！”癞蛤蟆托德叉开腿，挺起肚皮，嚷道，“这辆小车代表的生活，对你们来说，才是真正的生活。野外大道，尘土飞扬的公路，荒野，公地，树篱，起伏的丘陵！野营地，村庄，小镇，城市！今天在这里，明天就动身去别的地方！旅行，改变环境，趣味，刺激！整个世界在你们面前，还有永远在变化的地平线！请注意！在所有已经制造出来的同类型车子里，这一辆是最最精美的，独一无二。进来瞧瞧里面的装备吧。全是我设计的，我本人！”

鼹鼠莫尔兴致勃勃，兴奋极了，紧跟在托德后面跨上阶梯踏板，急切地来到大篷车里边。水鼠兰特只是从鼻子里哼了一声，把两只手猛地插进口袋深处，站在那里一步也没挪动。

里边确实非常紧凑、舒适。几张小卧铺，一张折叠起来靠壁的小桌子，一只做饭的炉子，几只壁式储物柜和书架，一只鸟笼里有一只小鸟，还有各式各样、大大小小的锅碗瓢盆、瓶瓶罐罐。

“一应俱全！”癞蛤蟆托德一边得意扬扬地说，一边拉开一只储物柜，“你看，饼干，罐装龙虾，沙丁鱼，应有尽有。这是苏打水，那是烟草，还有信纸，熏肉，果酱，纸牌和多米诺骨牌──你会发现，”他一边同莫尔一起走下阶梯踏板，一边接着说道，“你会发现，我们今天下午出发时，什么东西也没忘带。”

“对不起，”水鼠兰特嘴里嚼着一根稻草，慢条斯理地说，“我刚才无意中听到你说什么‘我们’、‘出发’、‘今天下午’？”

“哎哟，亲爱的好鼠仔，”托德哀求他说，“别那样冷冰冰不屑一顾地说话行不，你知道的啦，你们不来可不行。没有你们，我是应付不来的。所以就先把这事定下来吧，别争了──我最受不了的一件事就是争论。你总不会打算一辈子黏着那条沉闷的发霉的老河，老守着岸边一个地洞，还有船，就那样过日子吧？我想让你们看看世界！我要把你变成一个真正的动物，伙计！”

“我不稀罕，”水鼠兰特固执地说，“我不去，说不去就不去。我就要黏着我的老河，就要守着地洞和船过日子，我一直那样过，挺好。还有，莫尔会黏着我，我怎样他就怎样，是不是，莫尔？”

“那是当然，”鼹鼠莫尔忠诚地说，“我会一直黏着你的，兰特，你说怎样就怎样，就一定怎样。可是，听起来那样好像……嗳，挺有趣的，是吧！”他眼巴巴地加上了一句。可怜的莫尔！对他来说，冒险生活是多么新鲜、多么刺激的一件事。这件事的新鲜一面，是那么的诱人。这辆金丝雀黄的车子，它的全套小装备，他第一眼看到时就爱上了。

水鼠兰特看出了鼹鼠莫尔的心思，动摇了。他不喜欢让别人失望，他很喜欢鼹鼠莫尔。为了满足莫尔的愿望，差不多让他做什么都行。托德在一旁仔细地观察着他们俩。

“跟我来，进去吃点午饭吧，”他说，展开了外交手段，“我们慢慢商量，什么事都用不着匆忙做决定。当然啦，我并不是真的很在乎。我只不过想让你们两个家伙快活一下。‘为他人活着！’这是我的人生格言。”

蛤蟆府里的一切都很棒，午餐当然也是。吃饭的时候，癞蛤蟆托德只管信口开河。他把水鼠兰特丢在一边，开始在经验不足的莫尔身上做文章，要把文章做得天花乱坠。他天生就是一只口若悬河的动物，又总是沉浸在自己的想象里，这就把旅行的景象、野外生活的欢乐和路途上的情趣，描绘得五彩缤纷，让鼹鼠莫尔激动得在椅子里坐不住。不知不觉中，三个动物很快就说到了一块儿，仿佛出去旅行已经是一件定下来的事。水鼠兰特虽然心里面仍然没有信服，但他的和善还是压倒了他的反对意见。要让两个朋友失望，他可受不了。那两位已经在深入讨论旅行计划，作出许多预想，把未来几个礼拜里每天的活动，都已经设计好了。

大家准备得差不多了，获得最后胜利的托德就领着同伴们来到养马场，指派他们去捉那匹老灰马。托德事先并没有跟老马商量，现在冷不丁就吩咐他在这次尘土弥漫的远足中干最最尘土弥漫的活儿，这让老马恼怒极了。老实说，他情愿待在养马场，所以那两位为了逮他费了不少事。这时托德又往满满的储物柜里硬塞了些生活必需品，把几袋马粮、几网兜洋葱、几捆干草和几只篮子吊在车厢底下。老马最终被逮住，套上了缰绳。车轮刚一转，这些动物就开始说个不停。他们有的跟在车子旁边走，有的坐在车辕上，各随自己的意。这是一个金色的下午。他们扬起的尘土散发出的浓浓气味，让人心旷神怡。从路两边茂密的果园里，小鸟们快活地向他们打招呼，吹口哨。和善的路人从他们身边经过时，对他们说再见，有时也停下来说几句好话，称赞他们的车子漂亮。兔子们坐在灌木树篱里的家门口，举起爪子，嚷嚷着：“哦，天！哦，天！哦，天！”

天快黑的时候，他们已经离开家好远。他们很累，但很快乐。在远离居民区的一块公地上，他们停住了车，松开马缰让灰马去吃草，他们自己坐在车旁的草地上吃了一顿简单的晚饭。托德大谈将来几天他要干的所有事情，这时候呀，他们四周的星星越来越多，越来越大；一轮黄澄澄的月亮，不知从什么地方突然静悄悄地冒了出来，与他们做伴，听他们说话。最后，他们爬进车子，上了各自的小卧铺。托德蹬开四条腿，睡意蒙眬地说：“嗯，晚安，伙计们！这才是真正的绅士生活！说说你的老河吧！”

“我不说我的河，”沉得住气的兰特答道，“你知道我不说的，托德。可我想它，”他动情地低声加上一句，“我想它──老是在想！”

鼹鼠莫尔从毯子下面伸出爪子，在黑暗中摸到水鼠兰特的爪子，捏了一下。“只要你乐意，我怎样都行，鼠仔，”他悄声说，“明天早晨我们溜走，一大早──很早很早──就溜回河边我们亲爱的老洞子里去，好吗？”

“不，不要，我们坚持到底吧，”水鼠兰特悄声答道，“非常感谢，但我应该守着托德，直到这趟旅行结束。丢下他一个人我不放心。不用很久的。他赶时髦从来都长不了。晚安！”

果然很快就结束了，水鼠兰特也没猜到会那么快。

在野外那么久，加上又兴奋，癞蛤蟆托德睡得很死。第二天早晨，无论怎么摇晃，都没法把他从床上叫醒。于是鼹鼠莫尔和兰特不声不响，很男子气地使劲干起活儿来。水鼠兰特照料老马，生火，清洗昨晚的杯盘，准备早餐。鼹鼠莫尔走了很长的路，去距离最近的村子买牛奶鸡蛋和各种必需品，那些东西当然是癞蛤蟆托德忘了带的。繁重的活儿都已经干完，两只动物筋疲力尽，正在休息。这时托德出场了。他精神饱满，心情舒畅，发议论说：如今他们大家过上了轻松愉快的生活，不用再像在家里时那样耗心费神、操劳家务啦。

那一天，他们翻过长满草的丘陵地，沿着狭窄的林荫小岔路，开开心心到处游逛，然后像以前一样，在一块公地上宿营。不过，这一回两位客人用上了心，定要托德干他分内的活儿。结果，第二天早晨动身的时间来到时，托德对这种原始生活一点也不痴迷了，而是一门心思要回到卧铺上去，他可是刚刚才被硬拽起床的呢。像以前一样，他们沿着狭窄的林荫小路，穿过乡间田野，继续他们的旅程。直到差不多下午的时候，他们才上了公路，这是他们第一次上公路。谁也没想到，就在这条路上，飞来一场横祸，落在他们头顶。对他们这次远足来说，那确实是一个大灾祸。而对托德今后的人生旅程来说，那简直就是一件影响力无法抗拒的事。

当时，他们正悠闲自在地在公路上溜达。鼹鼠莫尔走在马头旁边，跟老马说话，因为他抱怨他们完全冷落他，丝毫不理他。癞蛤蟆托德和水鼠兰特走在车子后面，一块儿说说话──至少托德是在说话。兰特只是隔一会儿插上一句：“是啊，一点也不错，你对他说什么来着？”其实他心里面一直在想着毫不相干的事。这时，在他们后面很远的地方，传来警告似的微弱的嗡嗡声，就像一只蜜蜂在远处嗡嗡叫一样。他们回头瞥了一眼，看见一小团尘雾，雾中间一个活的小黑点，正以令人难以置信的速度向他们逼来，同时，尘雾中间有一个微弱的声音在哀号：“噗——噗！”就像一只不安的动物在痛苦地叫唤。他们几乎没当一回事，又回过头来接着说话，可就在这时，刹那间（感觉上好像是这样），和平景象被打破了，一阵狂风，一片喧响，他们的车子就跳起来，翻到路边的沟里了，是它到了跟前！那噗——噗声在他们耳朵里轰鸣震响，有一瞬间，他们瞥到了闪亮的平板玻璃和华贵的摩洛哥羊皮革。那富丽堂皇的汽车，一个脾气暴躁的庞然大物，吓得人喘不过气来。那开车的人神经紧张，使劲儿抓着他的轮子[1]，在那一秒钟里，把整个地、整个天都占了，掀起一团遮天蔽日的尘雾，把他们团团裹住，让他们成了瞎子。接着它又渐渐缩小，变成远处的一个小黑点，变回了一只嗡嗡叫的蜜蜂。

当时，那匹老灰马正一边慢慢向前走，一边梦想着宁静的养马场。突然碰上这样一种没经历过的情形，他就直接情绪失控，被马的天性压倒了。马先是后腿直立，又扬起后蹄奔窜，然后不断地后退。不管鼹鼠莫尔怎样使劲儿拉他的马头，不管鼹鼠莫尔说了多少动听的话来平稳他的情绪，他还是把车子往后推，直奔路旁那道深沟。它摇晃了片刻，然后，一声撕心裂肺的巨响，那辆金丝雀黄的车子，他们的骄傲和欢乐，就侧翻在沟里，成了一堆不可救药的残骸。

水鼠兰特气坏了，一个劲儿地在路上暴跳。“你们这帮流氓！”他挥舞着双拳吼道，“坏蛋，劫匪，你们──你们──你们这帮飙车狂！我要起诉你们！我要告你们！我要把你们一告到底！”他的思乡病一下子就无影无踪了，此时此刻，他成了金丝雀黄大船的船长。对方水手驾船横冲直撞，把他的船逼上了浅滩。他搜肠刮肚，要把那些尖酸刻薄的骂人话全掏出来。过去有些汽艇开得离岸太近，搅起的水浪常常淹了他家客厅的地毯，他就是用那种话来骂那些船长的。

托德直挺挺地坐在满是尘土的路中央，两条腿向前叉开着，两只眼睛直瞪瞪地朝汽车消失的方向望着。他呼吸急促，脸上露出一种温柔而满足的神情，嘴里时不时轻轻地嘟囔一声：“噗——噗！”

鼹鼠莫尔忙着让老马安静下来，过了一会儿，他成功了。然后他走过去看那辆车。它侧翻在沟里，那景象让人看了真伤心。嵌板和窗户都碎了，车轴弯得不可救药，一只轮子掉了，沙丁鱼罐头散落得满世界都是，鸟笼里的小鸟凄凄戚戚地抽泣着，叫人把他放出去。

水鼠兰特过去帮莫尔，但他俩的力气合在一起也没能把车翻正过来。“喂，托德！”他们喊道，“过来帮一把手，行不！”

癞蛤蟆托德没答理一个字，坐在路上一动也不动。他们俩就走过去，看看他到底怎么了。他们发现他神情恍恍惚惚，脸上挂着幸福的笑容，眼睛依然直瞪瞪地望着那毁灭者留下的烟尘。仍然时不时地听到他嘟囔一声：“噗——噗！”

水鼠兰特摇晃着他的肩膀。“你不过来帮帮我们，托德？”他厉声问道。

“多么辉煌、激动人心的景象！”托德喃喃地说着，一点挪窝的意思也没有。“诗一样的运动！真正的旅行方式！唯一的旅行方式！今天在这里，明天就到了下个礼拜才能到的地方！一个个村庄飞逝如电，一座座城镇一晃而过，永远奔向新的地平线！极乐啊！哇，噗——噗！哦，天！哦，天！”

“哦，别再驴了，托德！”鼹鼠莫尔绝望地嚷道。

“想想看，我竟然一无所知！”癞蛤蟆托德继续像做梦一样单调地说着，“那么多岁月被我虚度了，我一无所知，连做梦也没有梦到过！但是现在──但是现在我知道了，现在我完全明白了！啊，从今以后，在我的前方，是一条铺满鲜花的道路！我要疾驰如飞，横冲直撞，在身后扬起一团团尘雾！在我辉煌壮观的进攻之路上，我要毫不在意地把一辆辆马车抛进路沟！极讨厌的小马车──普通马车──金丝雀黄马车！”

“我们拿他怎么办？”鼹鼠莫尔问水鼠兰特。

“什么也不用办，”水鼠兰特很沉着地答道，“因为实在没法办。你要知道，我一千年前就了解他了。他现在是走火入魔了。他又迷上一样新时尚啦，每一回刚开头时，他总是给折腾成这德行。接下来，他会一连好多天这样魔怔，像一只在美梦中游荡的动物，没一点实际的用处。别去管他。我们去看看，马车有没有什么办法弄一下。”

仔细检查一番之后，他们发现，单凭他们俩，即使能够把车子翻正过来，也不能再乘着它旅行了。车轴的状况已是不可救药，脱落的那只轮子也已经成了碎片。

水鼠兰特把缰绳拴在马背上，牵着马头，另一只手提着鸟笼，笼子里那只小鸟已经歇斯底里。“走吧！”他很坚决地对鼹鼠莫尔说，“去最近的镇子也有五六英里，我们只有步行，所以越早动身越好。”

“托德怎么办？”他们俩一起动身时，鼹鼠莫尔焦急地问，“我们不能丢下他，让他一个人这样神经搭错坐在路中央！不安全的。假如再有一个那种东西开过来怎么办？”

“哦，大麻烦托德，”水鼠兰特狠狠心说道，“我和他一刀两断！”

可他们还没走出去多远，身后就响起了啪嗒啪嗒的脚步声，托德追上他们，伸出爪子，一边一个，插进他们的胳膊下面。他仍然呼吸急促，眼睛发直，茫然地看着前方。

“听着，托德！”水鼠兰特厉声说道，“我们一到镇上，你就得直奔警署，弄清楚他们是否知道那辆汽车，它的主人是谁，并且提出控告。然后你得去铁匠铺或修车铺，安排人把车子弄回来修一修，整一整。这要花一点时间，但车子还没有坏到不能修的地步。同时呢，莫尔和我去客栈，找几间舒服的房间住下，等到车子修好，你碰坏的脑子恢复正常再走。”

“警局！控告！”托德像在梦中一样喃喃地说，“要我去控告那个美丽的，那个天堂一样的天赐图景！修马车！我已经永远和马车一刀两断了。我永远不想再见到，也永远不想再听到那辆车。哇，鼠仔！你想不到我多么感谢你同意跟我一块儿出来旅行！没有你做伴，我就不会出来，就永远看不到那个──那只天鹅，那道阳光，那个惊雷！我就永远听不到那种让人神魂颠倒的声音，闻不到那种让人着迷的气味！这一切全亏了你，我最好的朋友！”

水鼠兰特绝望地扭过脸去，不想看他。“你瞧明白了没有？”他隔着托德的脑袋对鼹鼠莫尔说道：“他已经不可救药。我放弃了──到镇上以后我们就去火车站，运气好的话，今晚也许能搭上火车回我们的河岸去。今后你要是再碰上我同这个讨厌的动物一起玩，那才怪呢！”

他从鼻子里嗤了一声。一路走来很累很闷，在剩下的一段路上，他只跟莫尔一个人说话。

一到镇子，他们直接就去了火车站。他们把托德安置在二等候车室，给了搬运工一个两便士的硬币，托他牢牢地看住托德。然后他们把老马寄存在一家客栈的马厩里，对马车和车子里的物件，尽可能详尽地作了说明。一辆慢车终于把他们载到了离蛤蟆府不远的一个车站，他们把中了邪的梦游郎托德护送到家门口，把他弄进屋，吩咐管家喂他吃饭，给他脱衣，把他弄上床。然后他们从停船的棚屋里把船弄出来，向大河下游的家划去，回到自己河边的家。在温暖舒适的客厅里坐下来吃晚饭时，水鼠兰特才感到十分开心和满足。这时候，已经很晚了。

第二天鼹鼠莫尔起得很晚，整天都非常悠闲。傍晚时分，他正坐在河边钓鱼，出去访友闲聊的水鼠兰特回来了，他一路溜达着找到了他。“听到新闻了吗？”他说，“沿河上下，只谈论着一件事。今天托德乘早班火车去镇上预订了一辆很大很贵的汽车。”

[1]即方向盘。

第三章　野树林

鼹鼠莫尔想认识獾子班杰已经很久了。听大家说，他是一个很重要的人物。虽然班杰很少露面，但这地方人人都能感觉到他的无形的影响。可是鼹鼠莫尔一提起这个愿望，就发现兰特在拖延他。“行啊，”水鼠兰特会说，“班杰迟早会出现的，他总是很意外地出现，到时候我就把你介绍给他。没有比他再好的人了！但不是非得去找才会碰上他，不定什么时候说碰上就碰上了。”

“你不能请他来吃顿饭什么的？”鼹鼠莫尔说。

“他不会来的，”水鼠兰特简短地说道，“搞社交，发请柬，请客吃饭什么的，这种事班杰全都很讨厌。”

“嗯，那我们过去拜访他怎样？”鼹鼠莫尔提议说。

“哦，我肯定他一点也不喜欢的，”水鼠兰特忧心忡忡地说，“他很害羞，肯定会冒犯他。我本人虽然和他很熟，也从来没有冒险去登门拜访他。另外，我们去不了。那是不可能的，因为他住在野树林正中央。”

“哟，就算他住那地方又怎样，”鼹鼠莫尔说，“你告诉过我野树林没什么问题的，你知道的呀。”

“哦，我知道，我知道，是没问题，”水鼠兰特推托道，“可是我想，我们还是不要说去就去。别赶在这一会儿。路很远，而且不管怎么说，每年这个时候他不在家的，总有一天他会出现，你安安静静等着好了。”

鼹鼠莫尔只好就此知足。可是獾子班杰一直没有出现。每一天都有得玩有得乐，不知不觉，夏天就已经过去很久了。天冷啦，下了霜，道路泥泞，他们只好大多时候待在家里不出门。河水涨了，在窗外奔流着。这时候，无论想玩什么船，想怎样玩船，都只能望着湍急的河水叹气。莫尔发现自己心里又开始念叨起孤单的灰獾班杰，想着他在野树林中央的獾子洞里面，独自一个人打发日子。

冬令时节，水鼠兰特很贪睡，每天早早就上床，很晚才起身。在短短的白昼里，他有时胡乱涂几句诗，或者做点零星家务事，整理一下房子什么的。当然，经常有动物来串门聊天，所以他们听说了许多趣闻逸事。他们还就刚刚过去的夏天发生的所有事情，把自己的见闻拿出来和别人对比对比。

现在回想起来，夏季的一切是多么丰富多彩的一个篇章啊！那时节，盛装的河岸游行队伍源源不断地向前行进着，展开成一幅幅风景图，一幅接一幅，排成蔚为壮观的行列。紫色的珍珠菜早早出场，沿着镜子般的河面的边沿，抖开蓬乱茂密的头发，冲着镜子里自己的笑脸发笑。温柔多情的柳兰，像一片粉色晚霞，来得也不慢。聚合草悄悄地上前，紫的和白的手牵手，在队列中就位。最后，在一个早晨，羞怯的野蔷薇姗姗来迟，步态优雅地登上舞台；好像弦乐以庄严的和弦开始，却变了调，演奏起加伏特舞曲一样，她的到来宣告了六月最终来临。但这团队中有一个成员还没有来到，那就是山林水泽的仙女们追求的牧羊少年，贵妇人娇小姐在窗前等待的骑士，把睡梦中的夏的生命和爱情吻醒的王子。当时，只等穿着琥珀色无袖短上衣的绣线菊，愉快而自信，散发着芬芳，优雅地进入队列，演出就可以开始了。

那是多么精彩的演出啊！如今，在温暖舒适的洞中半昏睡的动物们，听着风雨敲打门窗的声音，还在悠悠地回想昔日的情景：那些个清晨，日出前一小时还寒意凛冽，白蒙蒙的雾紧贴着水面不肯散去，突然间太阳就又与万物同在了，灰色变成了金色，缤纷的色彩重新诞生，再一次从大地中喷薄而出。于是，又有了早早下水的刺激，又有了沿着河岸蹦蹦跳跳奔跑的欢愉，又有了大地、空气和水的辉煌的万千变化。还有那些个炎热的正午，他们懒洋洋躲在下层灌木的深深的绿荫里午睡，但阳光的尖细的金箭依然透射进来，留下了一个个金色的斑点。下午呢，他们去划船、游泳，沿着满是尘土的林荫小路，穿过金黄的小麦田，到处游逛。最后，还有那些长长的、凉爽的黄昏，许多的线路交汇在一起，许多的朋友围绕在身边，许多的为第二天准备的冒险计划被商议出来……是啊，在冬季这些短暂的白昼，动物们围着火炉，有好多好多话题可以谈论。不过，鼹鼠莫尔手头仍然有不少空闲时间，所以呀，一天下午，当水鼠兰特坐在炉火前的扶手椅里，不是打瞌睡，就是为了不合韵的诗琢磨韵脚时，他下了决心，要独自出门去野树林探险，说不定还能和班杰先生交上朋友呢。

那是一个寒冷静谧的下午，头顶上是钢一样灰白的天空。他悄悄地溜出温暖的客厅，来到野外。旷野光秃秃地向四周伸展开去，一片叶子也不见。他觉得自己从来没有像这一个冬天一样，看得那么远，看万物的内里那么透彻。因为这时的大自然，在一年一度的深深的冬眠中，仿佛已经蹬掉了所有的衣服。杂树林、小山谷、采石场……所有隐蔽的地方，在枝叶茂密的夏天曾经是他探险的神秘矿藏；现在呢，它们把自己，把它们的秘密，全都可怜巴巴地裸露出来了。它们仿佛在乞求他暂时忽视他们的破败贫瘠，等待一段时间，等它们像往年一样，再度披上华丽的伪装，恣意狂欢，用老一套把戏来把他哄骗引诱。眼前这场面是有点凄凉，可也让人感到心清气爽，甚至令人振奋。他很高兴自己喜欢这粗犷、不加修饰、褪去了华丽衣装的乡野。他真真地看到了它袒露的骨骼：美好、强健、纯朴。温柔的三叶草的舞蹈，结了籽的青草的摇曳，他不想看；绿树篱的荫庇，山毛榉和榆树波浪起伏的帷帘，最好别来遮蔽他的视线。他心情无比愉快，向野树林前进着：它横卧在他前方，低矮而凶险，就像南方寂静的大海上一片黑咕隆咚的暗礁。

刚走进去时，并没有什么东西让他感到惊恐。细树枝在他脚下发出断裂的响声，倒伏的树干把他绊倒，树桩上的菌菇长得像漫画，冷不丁看一眼会吓他一跳，因为它们很像一种熟悉而又遥远的东西。不过这一切很有趣，而且令人兴奋。它们一步步引导他向前，可越往里面走，光线越黯淡，树木蹲伏得越密；左右两边的洞穴，冲他张着丑陋的大嘴。

万籁俱寂。暮色从前后两个方向聚拢来，不断地迅速向他逼近；光线像洪水退走一样退去。

这时鬼脸开始出现。

一开始，他觉得模模糊糊瞥见肩膀后面有一张脸：一张邪恶的楔形小脸，正从一个洞里窥望着他。当他转过脸去面对它时，那东西却消失了。

他加快脚步，打起精神，告诉自己不要胡思乱想，否则那东西就会没完没了地出现。他经过一个一个又一个洞穴，有！──没有！──有！当然，有一张窄窄的小脸，目光很凶，瞬间在一个洞口一闪，又消失了。他犹豫了一下，又壮起胆子硬着头皮大步往前走。突然，仿佛向来就是如此似的，远远近近每一个洞口，一共几百个洞口，好像都有脸在闪现，迅速地出现、消失。它们全都恶狠狠地盯着他：每一张脸都邪恶狡诈，一道道目光都很凶。

他心想，只要能离开斜坡上那些洞，就不会再有脸出现了。他纵身一跃，离开小路，钻进了人迹未至的林中。

但是又出现了哨音。

刚开始时听上去微弱尖细，在他身后很远的地方，可不知为什么，却催他加快脚步向前奔。接着，那声音听起来又好像在前方很远的地方了，仍然很微弱很尖细，弄得他犹豫起来，想往回走。正当他停住脚步拿不定主意时，前面后面哨音同时响起来，仿佛在整个林子里响应着传递着，一直到它最远的边缘。很明显，它们都警觉起来做好准备了，无论它们是谁！可他呢，他只身一人，赤手空拳，孤立无援，而黑夜正在逼近。

接着响起了啪嗒啪嗒的声音。

开始他以为那不过是落叶声，因为那声音很轻很细；然后它慢慢变响了，变得很有节奏，他明白了，那不是别的，正是小脚爪啪啪的脚步声，此刻仍然离他很远。在前面，还是在后面？好像开始在前面，接着在后面，然后前面后面都响起来了。越来越响，越来越多，最后四面八方都是啪嗒啪嗒的声音。他忧心忡忡，听听这边，又听听那边，那些声音似乎正在向他逼近。他正不出声地站在那里倾听着，忽然一只兔子从树丛间穿过，猛地向他冲来。他没有动弹，指望兔子放慢脚步，或者改变方向朝别的地方奔跑。可那动物竟直直地猛冲过来，过去时差一点擦到他；顿时他的脸僵住了，眼睛瞪大了。“别挡道，笨蛋，滚开！”鼹鼠莫尔听到他咕哝了一句，看见他绕过一个树桩，钻进一个共用的洞穴，就不见了。

啪嗒声越来越响，最后听起来就像突然降落的冰雹，砸在他周围厚厚的落叶层上。现在似乎整个林子都在奔跑，在狂奔，在猎杀，在追捕，在包围某个东西──或者某个动物？他一阵恐慌，也开始漫无目的地奔跑起来，却根本不知道要跑去什么地方。他撞到东西，摔倒在东西上，拱进东西里面，扎到东西下面，闪身避过东西。最后他在一棵老山毛榉又深又黑的树洞里找到了避难所，它能给他庇护，让他隐身，也许还能提供安全，但是谁能说得准呢？不过，无论如何，他已经太累了，再也跑不动，只能蜷伏在往日飘进树洞里的枯叶上，希望暂时平安无事。他躺在那里喘息、哆嗦，听着外面的哨音和啪嗒声，终于恍然大悟：田野上和灌木树篱中其他小居民在这里碰上的恐怖事物，他们所谓的最黑暗的时刻，就是野树林的恐怖！水鼠兰特曾经想保护他，不让他遭遇到它，却最终没能阻止。

这时候呀，水鼠兰特正浑身暖洋洋、舒舒服服地在炉火旁打盹。写了一半的诗稿从他膝盖上滑落下来；他脑袋后仰，嘴巴张开着，正在梦中的翠绿河岸上漫游。这时一块煤滑落下来，炉子里噼啪一声，喷出一道火苗，把他惊醒了。他想起刚才做的事，伸手到地板上捡起诗稿，苦思冥想了一分钟，然后转动脑袋寻找鼹鼠莫尔，想问问他知不知道某个地方用什么韵脚好。

但是鼹鼠莫尔不在。

他听了一会儿。屋子里好像很安静。

然后他叫道：“鼹仔！”一连几声，没人回答，于是他站起身来走出去，来到门厅里。

鼹鼠莫尔往常挂帽子的钩子上，帽子不见了。总是放在雨伞旁边的胶套鞋也没了踪影。

水鼠兰特走出屋子，仔细察看着泥泞的地面，希望发现鼹鼠莫尔的脚印。找到了，肯定没错。胶套鞋是新的，新买了过冬用的，鞋底上的小豆豆清晰鲜明。他看得出，泥地上的鞋印去向明确，直直的一串，直奔野树林。

水鼠兰特神情非常严肃，站着沉思了一两分钟。然后他走进屋子，在腰里系上一根皮带，插进去几把手枪，抄起靠在门厅角落的一根很粗的棍棒，撒腿向野树林跑去。

他到达林子第一排树跟前时，天色已经黑下来了。他毫不犹豫地一头冲进林子，边走边焦急地向两边张望，寻找朋友的踪迹。从洞中东一张西一张冒出一张张邪恶的小脸，但一看到这勇武的动物，看到他的手枪，看到他手里那根凶恶的大棒子，它们便立刻消失了。他刚进树林时听得很分明的哨音和啪嗒声，也渐渐消失了，停止了。一片静寂。他勇敢地穿过整个林子，一直走到它最远的边缘；然后，他撇开所有的小径，开始横穿树林，仔细搜索着每一块地方，并且一直很带劲儿地呼喊着：“鼹仔，鼹仔，鼹仔！你在哪里？是我呀，我是老兰特！”

他在林子里耐心地搜寻了一个多小时，终于听到一个细微的哭声在回应他，他好高兴。顺着声音的方向，穿过越来越浓重的黑暗，他摸索着来到一颗老山毛榉的树根前面。树上有一个洞，洞里传出一个有气无力的声音：“鼠仔！真的是你吗？”

水鼠兰特爬进洞里，找到了精疲力竭、仍然在发抖的鼹鼠莫尔。“哇，兰特！”莫尔嚷嚷道，“你想象不到，我被吓死了！”

“哦，我十分理解，”水鼠兰特安慰道，“你真不该这么干，莫尔。我一直尽力阻止你。我们河边居民几乎从不单独来这里。就算非得来，至少也会成双结对，那样一般不会出问题。另外，有上百件事必须了解，我们都懂，现在你还不懂呢。我说的是有用和有效的口令、暗号和暗语，口袋里要带的植物，要背诵的诗，脱逃的计策，哄骗的花招。这些都很简单，等你了解了就一点不难；可如果你是小动物，就得学会，否则就会遇上麻烦。当然，如果你是班杰或奥特，那就是另外一回事了。”

“托德先生肯定不在乎独自来这里吧，是不？”鼹鼠莫尔问。

“老托德？”水鼠兰特开怀大笑，“他不会单独在这里露面的。给托德满满一帽子金币，他也不会来。”

听着水鼠兰特爽朗的笑声，看到他的棍棒和亮闪闪的手枪，鼹鼠莫尔大受鼓舞。他停止了哆嗦，胆子开始大起来，心神渐渐恢复镇定。

“行啦，”水鼠兰特就说，“我们真得打起精神，趁着还有一点光亮，动身回家。在这里过夜是不行的，你明白。第一，太冷了。”

“亲爱的鼠仔，”可怜的莫尔说道，“非常非常抱歉，可我真是累坏了，不带一点假。如果一定得回家，也得让我在这里再歇一歇，恢复恢复力气。”

“哦，好吧，”和善的兰特说道，“反正现在天已经差不多黑透了，而且过一会儿该有一点月光的。”

于是鼹鼠莫尔钻到干树叶里，舒展开身体，就一下子睡着了。不过他时睡时醒，还做噩梦。水鼠兰特为了暖和些，尽量把自己捂紧，他躺在那里耐心等待着，爪子里握着一支手枪。

鼹鼠莫尔一觉醒来，精神好了许多，也恢复了往常的心情。水鼠兰特说道：“行啦！我来瞄一眼外面，看看是不是一切都平静，然后我们就真的必须出发了。”

他来到藏身处的入口，把脑袋伸出去。接着，鼹鼠莫尔听到他平静地自言自语道：“嗬！嗬！糟啦！”

“出什么事啦，鼠仔？”鼹鼠莫尔问。

“出雪啦，”水鼠兰特简短地答道，“或者不如说，下雪啦。雪下得很大。”

鼹鼠莫尔钻过来，趴在他旁边往外看，只见那曾经把他吓个半死的树林，已经完全变了样。地洞、树洞、水坑、陷阱和其他威胁过路人的凶险，都在迅速地消失，一张亮晶晶的仙毯，正从四面八方迅速地长出来，它看上去那么纤弱柔美，容不得粗鲁的脚去践踏。细细的粉末漫天飘洒着，爱抚着人的脸颊，带着一丁点刺痛感。一片仿佛来自下面的光，将一根根黝黑的树干映现了出来。

“咳，咳，没办法的事，”水鼠兰特想了想，说道，“我看，我们得动身，碰碰运气。最糟糕的是，我不十分清楚我们在哪里。现在雪把一切都弄得面目全非了。”

确实如此。鼹鼠莫尔都认不出这就是原先那个树林了。不管怎样，他们还是勇敢地出发了。他们选了一条看上去最有前途的路线，互相紧紧地搀扶着，做出一副所向无敌的神气样子。他们每碰到一棵冷冰冰不言不语的新树，都假装认出了一位老朋友；再就是对着白茫茫一成不变的雪原和黑黝黝千篇一律的树干，假装意外地看到了熟悉的通道出口、豁口或小路。

一两个小时以后──他们已经没法计算时间──他们停了下来，疲倦萎靡，迷惘绝望，在一根倒伏的树干上坐下来，喘口气，想一想下一步怎么办。他们累得腰酸背痛，摔得鼻青脸肿，已经好几次掉进洞里，弄得浑身透湿。雪越积越厚，他们的小腿儿陷进去几乎已经拔不出来；树越来越密，比以往任何时候都显得面目雷同。这林子仿佛没有尽头，没有边际，也没有差别，最糟的是，没有出去的路。

“我们不能在这里坐很久，”水鼠兰特说，“我们得再冲一下，出点别的招。太冷了，没人经得住，雪很快就会深得蹚不过去。”他张望着四周，想了想：“瞧，我是这样想的。前面有一个像小山谷一样的地方，那里全是小土丘，小土包，小土堆一类的地形。我们可以走到那里，找个地方避避，有个洞就行，大小不管，只要地上不湿，落不到雪吹不到风。我们可以在洞里好好歇一歇，然后再想办法出去。我们俩都已经累得要死了，而且，说不定过一阵子雪会停，或者出现别的情况。”

于是他们重新站起来，吃力地向前走，进了小山谷。他们四下里搜寻，要找一个干的洞穴或者角落，抵挡刺骨的风和飞旋的雪。他们正在察看水鼠兰特说的一个小圆丘，鼹鼠莫尔突然被绊倒，一声尖叫，摔了个嘴啃泥。

“哇，我的腿！”他叫喊着，“哇，我可怜的小腿！”他翻身从雪地上坐起来，用两只前爪揉着腿。

“可怜的老莫尔！”水鼠兰特很温和地说，“今天你好像不怎么走运，是不？让我瞧瞧你的腿。是的，你的小腿划破了。”为了看清楚些，他跪了下来，然后说道：“没错。等一下，我把手绢拿出来，帮你包扎好。”

“我一定是绊在看不到的树枝或树桩上了，”鼹鼠莫尔惨兮兮地说，“哦，天！哦，天！”

“伤口很整齐，”水鼠兰特又仔细检查了一遍，说道，“绝对不是树枝或树桩划破的。看上去好像是金属物件的边锋割的。奇怪！”他沉思了一会儿，然后察看着周围的土丘和斜坡。

“嗳，别去管它什么干的，”鼹鼠莫尔说，痛得连语法都顾不上了，“不管是什么割的，反正一样是割伤了。”

但是水鼠兰特用手绢仔细包扎好他的腿后，就丢下他，忙着在雪地里刨起来。他又是刮又是挖又是扒拉，四条腿忙得不亦乐乎。鼹鼠莫尔等得不耐烦了，隔一会儿嚷一句：“哦，算了吧，兰特！”

突然水鼠兰特叫了一声：“万岁！”接着又叫了一声：“万——安——安——安——岁！”然后有气无力地在雪地里表演起快步舞来。

“你发现了什么，鼠仔？”鼹鼠莫尔问，仍然在揉他的腿。

“过来看呀！”兴高采烈的兰特一边说，一边继续跳舞。

鼹鼠莫尔一瘸一拐地走上前去，看了好一会儿。

“嗨，”最后他慢条斯理地说道，“我看得很明白了。以前也见过这种东西，好多次。我叫它常见物品。一块门前刮泥板！哟，这有什么呀？干吗围着一块刮泥板跳快步舞？”

“可你没明白它意味着什么吗，你──你这个木头脑瓜？”水鼠兰特不耐烦地嚷嚷道。

“我当然明白意味着什么，”鼹鼠莫尔答道，“只不过意味着一个非常粗心、记性不好的人，把刮泥板丢在了野树林中央，正好搁在人人都肯定会绊到的地方。要我说，他真是没脑子。回家以后，我要去控告这件事，向……向什么人，看我不告他！”

“天哪，天哪！”水鼠兰特嚷嚷道，对他的迟钝感到绝望，“得啦，别争了，来刨吧！”他又动手挖起来，弄得四周雪花飞溅。

又辛苦了一阵子，他的努力得到了回报，一块很破旧的门前擦鞋垫暴露在眼前。

“瞧，我跟你说什么来着？”水鼠兰特得意扬扬地欢呼。

“绝对什么也算不上，”鼹鼠莫尔十分诚实地答道，“好吧，算你又找到一件家用杂物，没法再用就扔了，我看你十分开心呢。如果你非得围着它跳舞，最好就跳起来吧，跳完了，我们可以接着赶路，不用再为这些垃圾堆浪费时间。一块门前擦鞋垫，能吃吗？还是能盖在身上睡觉？还是能当雪橇，坐在上面滑雪回家？你这个气人的啮齿动物！”

“你……真的……以……为，”兴奋的兰特嚷道，“这擦鞋垫什么也不能告诉你吗？”

“确实，兰特，”鼹鼠莫尔气呼呼地说，“我看，我们这样犯傻也犯够了。有谁听说过擦鞋垫能告诉人什么事？擦鞋垫就是不会说话。擦鞋垫根本就不是会说话的物件。擦鞋垫知道自己的位置在哪里。”

“听着，你这个笨脑瓜动物，”水鼠兰特回敬道，他真的生气了，“别这样没个完。别再多说一句废话，如果你今夜还想干干爽爽、暖暖和和睡一觉的话，只管挖就行了──挖、刨、掘、扒拉，特别是土丘四周，因为这是我们最后的机会！”

水鼠兰特来劲儿地向身旁一面雪坡发起了进攻，他用棍棒到处刺探，然后又发飙似地挖掘。鼹鼠莫尔也在忙着刨，不为别的，只是为水鼠兰特效劳而已。按照他的观点，他的朋友是脑袋发晕了。

苦干了大约十分钟后，水鼠兰特的棍子尖碰到了一样发出空洞声音的东西。他接着挖，终于可以伸进去一只爪子，摸到它了。于是他叫鼹鼠莫尔过去帮他。两只动物使劲儿挖呀挖，终于，他们的劳动成果完全展现在了眼前。到目前为止，一直表示怀疑的莫尔，看了不由得一惊。

就在刚才看上去像是一面雪坡的地方，旁边出现了一道样子很结实的门，门漆成深绿色，一侧悬着一根拉铃铁链，门环下方镶着一块小铜牌，上面整整齐齐地用正方形大写字母刻着几个字，借着月光，他们辨认出来了：

班杰先生

鼹鼠莫尔惊呆了，乐坏了，仰面倒在雪地上。“兰特！”他大声表示悔罪，“你是个奇才！真正的奇才，奇才你就是。现在我全明白了！从我摔倒割伤小腿那一刻开始，你的聪明脑瓜就在一步一步证明这一点。你看着伤口，你那高贵的脑袋就自言自语道：‘是刮泥板！’然后你起劲儿地干起来，找到了割伤我的那块刮泥板！你有没有到此为止？没有。换了别人，就会很满足了，但你没有。你的聪明脑袋继续思考。‘只要找到一块门前擦鞋垫，’你对自己说，‘我的推测就得到证明了！’当然，你找到了那块擦鞋垫。你太聪明了，我相信你想找什么都能找到。‘这样的话，’你对自己说，‘肯定有一扇门，就像已经在我眼前一样明摆着。剩下的事，就是把它找出来了！’嗨，这种事我在书里面读到过，但在真实生活里却从来没有碰见过。你应该到你能够展露才华的地方去。在这里，在我们这样的家伙中间，简直是浪费你的才华。如果我有你那样一个脑瓜，鼠仔……”

“既然你没有，”水鼠兰特有点刻薄地打断了他，“我看你是打算要坐在雪地上说上一整夜啦。快站起来吧，看见那根拉铃铁链没有，去拉，使劲儿，有多大劲儿使多大劲儿，我来擂门！”

水鼠兰特用棍子对着门发起了进攻，鼹鼠莫尔跳起来抓住拉铃铁链，两脚离地吊在上面晃荡。隔着很远的距离，一阵隐约可辨的低沉的铃声回应了他们。

第四章　班杰先生

他们耐心等待着，在雪地上跺着脚，好让脚暖和些。仿佛等了很久，终于，他们听见拖拖沓沓的脚步声从里面向门口来了。正像鼹鼠莫尔对水鼠兰特说的那样，仿佛有个人在穿着毡子拖鞋走路，鞋太大，而且鞋跟磨掉了很多。这一回莫尔很聪明，因为事实正是这样。

响起门闩弹开的声音，门开了几英寸，刚够露出一个长长的嘴，一双睡意惺忪、眨巴眨巴的眼睛。

“嗨，下一回再发生这样的事，”一个粗哑的、带着猜疑的声音传来，“我会非常非常生气的。这一回是谁呀，这么冷的天，半夜三更来吵人家？说话！”

“哦，班杰，”水鼠兰特嚷道，“请让我们进去。是我，兰特，还有我朋友莫尔，我们在雪地里迷路了。”

“哇，鼠仔，我亲爱的小伙子！”獾子班杰欢呼道，完全换了一种声音，“快进来，你们俩，快快。呀，你们一定冻坏了。喔哟哟！在雪地里迷路！还是在野树林里，而且是晚上的这个时候！赶快进来吧。”

两只动物急着进去，互相绊倒了。听到门在身后关上的声音，他们高兴得要命，大大地松了一口气。

獾子班杰穿一件长晨衣，脚上一双拖鞋的鞋跟真的磨掉了许多。他的爪子举着一个扁平的烛台，听到他们敲门时，可能正要上床睡觉呢。他低下头亲切地看着他们，拍了拍他俩的脑袋。“这样的夜晚可不适合小动物出门，”他用长辈一样的口吻说道，“恐怕你又在搞什么恶作剧吧，鼠仔。过来，到厨房里来。里面有一等一的炉火，有晚饭，什么都有。”

班杰举着烛火，在前面拖着脚走。他们俩在后面跟着，互相用胳膊肘捅捅对方，意思是有想不到的好事。他们穿过一条很长很暗，而且说真的，实在很破败的过道，走进了一个中央大厅模样的房间。从这里望出去，可以模模糊糊地看到另外几条幽长的像隧道一样的过道，很神秘，一眼望不到头。但这厅里也有门──很厚重，看上去很舒服的橡木门。獾子班杰打开其中一扇，他们立刻就发现自己来到了一间很大的厨房，里面生着火，亮堂堂，暖融融。

地上铺着红砖，磨损得很旧了。宽敞的壁炉炉床上，木头燃着火苗，两个引人注目的壁炉角陷进墙体，通风肯定不会出问题。炉前两侧面对面放着两张高背长椅，这是为喜爱交际的人增设的座位。厨房中间的一张长桌子，是在支架上搁些木坯板架起来的，两边放着长凳。长桌一头摊着獾子班杰吃剩的晚餐，饭菜简单，却很多，一张扶手椅已经推回去靠着桌子。厨房另一端的碗柜里，一排排洁净的盘子闪着亮光。头顶上的椽子上吊着一根根火腿、一捆捆干草、一兜兜洋葱，还有一篮篮鸡蛋。这地方真棒，仿佛能供英雄凯旋大摆庆功宴；能供一大帮子疲惫的农夫收割归来排坐在桌旁，欢歌笑语庆祝丰收；也能供两三个口味简朴的朋友随意坐坐，舒舒服服、称心如意地吃吃饭，抽抽烟，聊聊天。红润的砖地冲着烟熏的天花板微笑；因用了多年而磨出亮光的橡木长椅互相快乐地交换着眼神；碗柜上的盘子冲着架子上的锅壶咧嘴傻笑，而愉快的炉火摇曳着，一视同仁，朝屋子里的每一样东西闪烁着光亮。

班杰和和气气把他们按到长椅上坐好，让他们烤烤火，吩咐他们脱掉湿外套和靴子。然后，他给他们拿来了晨衣和拖鞋，亲自用热水为鼹鼠莫尔洗小腿，在伤口处贴上膏药──最后，如果说整个感觉并不比原先更好，也已经完好如初了。光和热的拥抱，终于让他们干爽暖和了。他们把疲惫的腿架起来，身后桌子上响着馋人的杯盘叮当声。这两只被暴风雪追逐的动物，此刻已经在安全的港湾里。他们刚刚逃脱的那寒冷无路的野树林，仿佛已经离开好远好远。他们所受的苦，仿佛已经成了一个遗忘了一半的梦。

獾子班杰一直忙着在桌子上摆放饭菜，等他们终于烤干了，就唤他俩坐过去。两个家伙早就感到很饿了，这会儿真的看见晚饭摆在面前，似乎只有一个问题需要解决，就是先进攻哪一盘。因为每一盘都那么诱人，进攻了这一盘，不知道其余的会不会乖乖地等到他们有时间把注意力转移过去。好长时间，说话是根本不可能了；渐渐地重新顾得上时，又因为嘴巴里塞得满满的，说起话来那样子好叫人懊恼。獾子班杰根本不介意这种事，也完全不在意他们把胳膊肘支在桌子上，或者两个人同时说话。他本人不参加社交活动，所以有一个想法，就是这种事无关紧要（当然，我们知道他这样想不对，视野太狭窄。虽然为什么要紧得解释半天，这种事还是很要紧的）。他坐在餐桌主位那张扶手椅上，听两只动物讲他们的经历，不时严肃地点点头。无论听到什么事，他似乎都不感到惊讶或震撼，也决不说什么“我跟你们说过的”或者“我不是一直那样说的吗”，或者发表一点高见，认为他们本该这样不该那样。鼹鼠莫尔开始觉得他非常可亲。

晚餐终于真正结束了，两只动物都感到自己不但脸皮保住了，肚皮也绷紧了，而且现在对任何人任何事都满不在乎。于是他们围坐在那一大堆红光灼灼的木头炭火余烬旁，心想，这么晚、这么饱、这么自由自在地坐着，多么快活。他们东拉西扯地聊了一阵之后，獾子班杰热心地说道：“行啦！说说你们那个天地里的事情吧。老托德怎样啦？”

“哦，越来越糟。”水鼠兰特语气沉重，而鼹鼠莫尔却半躺在长凳上，对着火光取暖，把脚后跟翘得比头还高，努力做出一副应景的沉痛表情。“就在上个礼拜，又出了车祸，很严重。你是知道的，他坚持自己开车，可又无可救药地没那个本事。其实他只要雇个名声好、稳重可靠、训练有素的动物，多付点薪水，把一切交给他，就可以万事大吉。可托德不干，自以为天生会开车，谁也做不了他的老师，后面那些事就免不了喽。”

“有多少？”獾子班杰忧郁地问。

“多少次车祸，还是多少辆车？”水鼠兰特反问道，“哦，嗨，说到底是一回事──对托德来说。这是第七辆了。至于另外那些──你知道他那间马车房吗？咳，里面堆满了──堆到屋顶，一点也不夸张──全是汽车碎片，没有一块大过你的帽子！那就是另外六辆的结果──顶多是这样的结果了。”

“他住过三次医院，”鼹鼠莫尔插言道，“至于他不得不交的罚款数目，简直想想都叫人害怕。”

“事情有一部分就坏在这上头，”水鼠兰特接着说道，“我们都知道，托德有钱，但他并不是百万富翁。他开车的本事烂得无可救药，又完全不把法律和秩序放在眼里。丧命或者破产──只有这两种结果，早晚的事哟。班杰！我们是他的朋友，不该采取一点行动吗？”

獾子班杰冥思苦想了一会儿。“听我说！”最后他相当严肃地说道，“现在我什么都不能做，你们一定知道的吧？”

两位朋友表示同意，他们完全理解他话里的意思。按照动物界的规矩，在冬闲季节，不能指望任何动物，做出任何费力的、英雄式的，甚至不很过分活跃的举动。所有动物都在半眠状态，有的完全入眠了。所有动物多多少少都受到气候的约束。以往辛苦谋生的日日夜夜里，所有动物的每一块肌肉都经受了严格的考验，每一分力气都消耗够了，现在正是休息的时候。

“那就好！”獾子班杰继续往下说，“不过，一旦真的过了年，黑夜变短，人到半夜就醒来，心里面感到躁动，盼着天快亮好起床做事，甚至等不到太阳出来──你们知道的！”

两只动物严肃地点点头。他们知道！

“嗯，到那时候，”獾子班杰接着说道，“我们，就是说，你，我，还有我们这位朋友鼹鼠莫尔──我们要严肃地管教托德，坚决不容许他再胡闹。我们要让他恢复理智，有必要的话，采用武力。我们要把他塑造成一个明智的托德。我们要──你睡着了，兰特！”

“我没有！”水鼠兰特一个激灵醒过来，说道。

“吃完晚饭他已经睡着两三回了。”鼹鼠莫尔笑着说。他自己感觉十分清醒，甚至有些兴奋，尽管他不知道为什么。当然啦，那原因就是，他天生就是一只地下动物，生在地下长在地下，班杰家的环境正适合他，让他感到自在舒心。水鼠兰特却是每晚睡在开着窗户的卧室里，窗外是微风吹拂的河流，自然会感到这里气氛呆滞压抑。

“哟，不早了，我们都去睡吧，”獾子班杰说，拿起扁平烛台，站起身来，“你们二位跟我来，我带你们去住处。明天不用早起，什么时候吃早饭都行！”

他领着两只动物来到一个长长的房间里，它看上去一半像卧室，一半像堆东西的阁楼。确实，獾子班杰的过冬储藏品到处可见，占了差不多半间屋子──成堆成堆的苹果、萝卜、土豆，一篮篮的干果，一罐罐的蜂蜜。不过，房间里剩余的地方安放着的两张白色小床，看上去很柔软、很诱人。亚麻被单床单虽然粗糙，却干干净净，散发着美妙的熏衣草香气。鼹鼠莫尔和水鼠兰特只用三十秒就甩掉了衣服，一骨碌钻进被窝，快活无比，心满意足。

遵照好心班杰的指示，第二天早晨两只疲惫的动物很晚才下去吃早饭。他们看见厨房里生着明亮的火，有两只小刺猬坐在桌旁的长凳上，捧着木碗喝燕麦片粥。他俩一进来，刺猬们就放下小勺，站起身，恭敬地行了个低头礼。

“好啦，坐下，坐下，”水鼠兰特高兴地说，“接着喝你们的粥吧。你们两个小家伙从哪里来？在雪地里迷路了，我没猜错吧？”

“是的，的确，先生，”大一点的那只刺猬恭敬地说，“我和这个小比利，我们找路去上学，妈妈非要我们去上学，说天气总是这样的。我们当然就迷路了，先生。比利年纪小、胆子小，害怕了，吓着了，哭了。最后我们碰巧来到班杰先生家的后门口，大着胆子敲门，先生，因为大家都知道，班杰先生是位好心肠的绅士……”

“我明白。”水鼠兰特说着给自己切了几片熏肉。这时鼹鼠莫尔正往小炖锅里打蛋。“外面天气怎么样？别老是‘先生’‘先生’地叫我好吗？”兰特加上一句。

“哦，糟透了，先生，雪深得要命，”刺猬说，“你们这样的绅士，今天出不了门的。”

“班杰去哪里了？”鼹鼠莫尔一边在炉子上热咖啡，一边问。

“主人去书房了，先生，”刺猬答道，“他说今天上午他特别忙，千万别去打扰他。”

这个解释，在场的人当然心知肚明。其实，就像先前说过的那样，一年里你忙乎了六个月，生活得很紧张，另外六个月里比较犯困或者实在困得很。这时候有人来了，或者有事情要办，你总不能老是说我想睡觉吧。老用这个理由太单调。动物们很清楚，班杰吃了一顿丰盛的早餐后，已经躲进书房，倒在扶手椅里，两条腿搁在另一张扶手椅上，脸上蒙着一块红色棉布手绢，忙他在一年里这个时候通常要“忙”的事情去了。

前门的门铃声大作，水鼠兰特正在吃黄油烤面包，一爪子的油，就派比利，那个年龄小的刺猬，去看看来人是谁。门厅里一阵跺脚声，比利就回来了，后面跟着水獭奥特。奥特扑到水鼠兰特身上，抱住他，亲亲热热地大声问好。

“走开！”水鼠兰特鼓着满满的嘴，发急道。

“就料到会在这里找着你，果然没错，”水獭奥特快活地说，“今天早上我到河岸的时候，那一带的人都万分恐慌。兰特整夜没回家──莫尔也是──他们说，肯定发生了什么可怕的事，当然，雪把你们的踪迹全覆盖了。但我知道，人们在困境中多半会去找班杰，要不然，班杰也一定知道些情况，所以我就穿过野树林和雪地，直接上这里来啦！天！穿过雪地时，红彤彤的太阳刚升起来，阳光照亮了黑黝黝的树干，天气真好！在一片静寂中往前走，时不时一大团雪突然从树枝上滑落下来，噗的一声！吓得你跳起来，赶紧跑开找个地方躲藏。一夜之间，不知从什么地方冒出来许多雪城堡、雪洞穴，还有雪桥、雪台子、雪护墙──我本可以停下来，和它们玩上几个钟头呢。这里那里，粗大的树枝被雪压断了，知更鸟栖在上面，蹦蹦跳跳，神气活现，好像那是它们干的似的。头顶上，高高的灰色天空中，一行大雁参差不齐地飞过去。几只秃鼻乌鸦在树梢上方盘旋、巡察，然后露出厌恶的神情，扑打着翅膀飞回家去。但我就是没遇上一个明事理的能向他打听消息。大约走过一半路时，我碰上一只兔子坐在树桩上，正用爪子洗他那张傻乎乎的脸。我悄悄地来到他身后，把一只前爪重重地搭在他肩上，可把他吓蒙了。我只好在他脑袋上拍了一两下，让他稍微清醒清醒。最后我总算从他那里掏出了一点消息，昨晚他们有一只兔子在野树林见到了莫尔。他说，兔子洞里都在传，说莫尔，兰特先生特要好的那个朋友，遇上大麻烦啦；说他迷了路，‘他们’都跑出去，跑到上面去追赶他，搅得他团团乱转。‘那你们就没有一个人帮他一把？’我问，‘也许老天没赐给你们脑子，但你们这些家伙有成百上千，又粗又壮，肥得像黄油，你们的洞穴四通八达，满可以收留他，让他舒舒服服，平平安安。不管怎样，总可以试一下的。’‘什么，我们？’他只是说，‘帮他一把？我们兔子？’听了这话我只有再拍他一巴掌，然后走路。没别的办法哟。好歹知道了一点消息。要是我有幸遇到‘他们’中的一个，我会多领教一些的──否则就让他们领教领教。”

“你一点都不……呃……紧张？”鼹鼠莫尔问，提起野树林，昨天的恐惧又袭上了他的心头。

“紧张？”水獭奥特露出一排闪亮结实的白牙，笑了，“他们有谁碰我一下试试，看我不让他紧张一下。嗨，莫尔，你一向都是个很乖的小家伙，去给我煎几片火腿吧。我饿坏了，这不还有许多话要和鼠仔说呢。几十年没见他了。”

于是，和善的莫尔切了几片火腿，分派刺猬们去煎，自己回来继续吃早饭。水獭奥特和水鼠兰特两个脑袋凑到一起，起劲儿地谈起河水经来，那些经那些话，就像那潺潺的河水一样，滔滔不绝。

一盘煎火腿刚被清空，拿回去再盛，这时獾子班杰进来了。他打个哈欠，揉揉眼睛，用他那种平静朴素的方式跟大家打个招呼，亲切地向每一个人问了好。“一定快到午饭时间了，”他对水獭奥特说，“最好留下来和我们一起吃。你一定饿了，今天上午真冷。”

“的确！”水獭奥特答道，朝鼹鼠莫尔挤了挤眼睛。“看着这些贪吃的小刺猬往嘴巴里塞煎火腿，让我感到饿极了。”

两只刺猬早上喝过粥，然后辛辛苦苦地煎火腿，这时又饿了。他们怯生生地抬眼望着班杰先生，却不好意思开口。

“那好，你们两个小家伙回去找妈妈吧，”獾子班杰和蔼地说道，“我派人给你们指路。我敢肯定，今天你们用不着吃正餐了。”

他轻轻地拍拍他们的脑袋，给了他们六便士。他们恭恭敬敬地行了挥帽礼，又行了军礼，走了。

大家就坐下来一起吃中饭。鼹鼠莫尔发现自己被安排在班杰先生旁边，另外两位依然十分投入地聊他们的河边闲话，什么也不能让他们分心。他就趁机对班杰说，这里的一切使他感到多么舒适，像在家里一样。“一回到地下，”他说，“你心里就踏实了。麻烦找不到你，坏人逮不着你。你完全是自己的主人，不用征求别人的意见，不用在意别人怎么说。上面的世界原先怎样还怎样，你不用管它，不用为它操心。想上去时就上去看看，一切都在那里呐，在等着你。”

獾子班杰朴实地冲着他绽开了笑脸。“那正是我要说的，”他答道，“除了地下，没有哪里安全太平，让人心定神闲。再说，如果你心气高了，想扩大地盘──喏，只要挖一挖，刨一刨，就好了！如果你觉得屋子大了点，只要堵上一两个洞眼，又好了！用不着建筑工，不用跟商人打交道，没有人爬到墙头上观看，说三道四，最重要的是，没有天气好坏。就拿兰特来说吧。河水上涨一两英尺，他就得租个住处搬家，不舒服，也不方便，租金还贵得吓人。再说托德。对蛤蟆府我无话可讲，要说房子，那是这一带最好的。可是假如突然失火──托德去哪里呢？假如瓦片被风刮掉，或者墙体下沉、开裂，或者窗户打碎了──托德去哪里呢？假如房间里灌风──我本人讨厌灌风──托德去哪里呢？是啊，出个门，到上面去逛逛，买些生活必需品回来，这挺不错，可最后还得回到地下──这就是我对家的观念！”

这番话鼹鼠莫尔衷心赞成。于是乎，獾子班杰和他处得很投缘了。“吃过午饭，”他说，“我带你到处转转，参观一下我这个小地方。我看得出来，你会喜欢它的。你懂得住宅建筑应该是什么样，你懂。”

午饭后，另外两位坐到壁炉角跟前，已经围绕着鳗鱼这个题目热烈地争论起来。獾子班杰点起一盏灯笼，吩咐鼹鼠莫尔跟着他。他们穿过门厅，沿着一条主通道往前走，灯笼摇曳的光映现出两边大大小小的房间。有些只是壁橱，有的却宽敞气派，比得上托德的大宴会厅。一条垂直相交的窄过道引着他们来到另一条走廊，这里的情形和前一条一模一样。这建筑规模宏大、枝杈繁多、通道幽暗冗长，储藏室塞满东西的拱顶坚实牢固，到处是砖石结构、拱门、铺砌过的路面，看得鼹鼠莫尔目瞪口呆。最后他说道：“班杰，你究竟哪来那么多时间和精力做这一切的？真让人吃惊！”

“要是我干的，那确实会让人吃惊，”獾子班杰朴实地说，“可事实上呢，我什么也没干──我只是把通道和房间清理出来，需要多少清理多少。还有很多这样的地方，四周全都是。我知道你不明白，我得给你解释一下。嗯，很久以前，现在野树林起伏的这块地方，在它出现并生长到现在的规模之前，曾经是一座城池──你知道的啰，人类的城池。在这里，在我们现在站立的地方，他们生活、赶路、谈话、睡觉、办事。他们在这里养马、开宴会，他们从这里出发，骑马去打仗，赶车去做生意。他们是强大的人民，很富有，是了不起的建筑师。他们把房子造得非常经久耐用，因为他们以为，他们的城池会永存不灭。”

“后来呢，他们全都去哪里了？”鼹鼠莫尔问。

“谁知道呢？”獾子班杰说，“人们来了，待了一阵子，繁荣兴旺起来，然后又去了。他们就是这样子。可我们留下来了。我听说，在城池出现之前很久，这里就有獾子了。现在獾子还在这里。我们是一个持久的族群，可能会搬走一阵子，可我们能等待，我们有耐心，我们会回来。永远是这样。”

“嗯，那些人，最后他们都走了，后来发生了什么事？”鼹鼠莫尔问。

“他们走后，”獾子班杰接着说道，“大风和连绵不断的雨掌控了时事，长年累月，经久不衰。也许我们獾子也尽到绵薄之力，帮了点小忙──谁知道呢？城池渐渐往下沉，沉，沉──坍塌了，夷平了，消失了。然后一切又渐渐朝上长，长，长，种子长成树苗，树苗长成大树，组成森林。荆棘和蕨类植物蔓延开来，也来帮忙。腐叶土累积起来又被冲刷掉，冬天河水猛涨时挟带来的泥沙淤积起来。时光流逝，我们的家园重又准备好了，我们就搬了进来。在我们上面，在地面上，也发生了同样的事情。动物们来了，喜欢上了这块地方，占了自己的地盘，安顿下来，扩展繁衍。他们不为过去烦恼──从不，他们太忙了。这地方起伏不平，有不少土丘，自然就到处是洞穴。不过这倒是一件好事。他们也不为将来操心──怕将来有一天人类会搬回来──住一段时间──这是很有可能的。野树林现在人丁兴旺，什么样的动物都有，好的、坏的、中不溜丢的──我不指名道姓。世界就是各式各样的动物组成的。不过，我猜想，到如今你对他们有些了解了吧。”

“我算是了解啦。”鼹鼠莫尔说，微微打了个寒战。

“嗨，得啦，”獾子班杰拍拍他的肩膀说道，“你瞧，这是你第一回领教他们。其实他们并不是那么坏。我们都得活，也让别人活。不过明天我会到处放话出去，我想，今后你不会再遇到麻烦了。只要是我的朋友，在这地界都可以随便走动，否则我就得查清楚原因！”

他们回到厨房的时候，发现水鼠兰特正焦躁不安，来回踱步。地下的气氛使他感到压抑，让他精神紧张。他好像真的害怕如果自己不照看着，河流就会跑掉。所以他已经披上外套，把手枪插回到了腰带里。“赶快，莫尔，”一见他们，他就着急地说，“我们得趁着白天，赶快离开。不想在野树林再过一夜了。”

“没问题，好伙计，”水獭奥特说，“我和你们一块儿走，蒙上眼睛我也认识每一条路。如果谁的脑袋欠揍，你们放心，我会好好揍它一顿。”

“你完全不用烦躁，鼠仔，”獾子班杰平静地补充道，“我的通道比你想象的要长。在好几个方向，我有直达树林边缘的逃生出口，只是我不喜欢人人都知道罢了。你真的非走不可时，可以从我这些近道中抄一条离开。走之前，你不如放松一下，再坐一会儿。”

水鼠兰特还是急着要走，要回去照看他的河。于是獾子班杰重新拿起灯笼，领着他们走进一条潮湿憋闷的通道。它曲曲弯弯、水淋淋，一部分是拱廊，一部分是在顽石中凿出来的。他们走了很累人的一段距离，好像有几英里长，终于，透过纠结在一起悬在通道出口处的枝叶藤蔓，见到了迷糊零碎的日光。獾子班杰匆匆地跟他们道了别，急不可待地把他们推出洞口，用藤蔓、灌木和枯叶把它遮好，尽可能让一切看上去很自然，然后退了回去。

他们发现自己正站在野树林的边缘，身后是石头、荆棘和树根零乱地堆积和纠结在一起；前方是一大片宁静的原野，镶着一道道树篱，黑黝黝的与白雪交相辉映；前面更远的地方，那条熟悉的老河闪着光，冬日的太阳红红低低地悬在地平线上。认识每一条路的水獭奥特，充当起这一小群动物的头儿，领着他们沿一条最短的路线疲惫缓慢地向远处一道栅栏门前进。到那里后，他们休息了片刻，回头望去，只见野树林黑压压一大片，密密层层，阴森险恶，嵌在广袤的白色原野中间，面目狰狞。他们不约而同地回过头来，快快地赶路，奔回家去：奔向炉火和炉火映照下的熟悉的物件，奔向窗外那欢快的声响。发出声响的是那条河，他们了解并信任它的所有禀性，它从不作怪搞鬼，让他们害怕。

鼹鼠莫尔一路匆匆地跑，急切地期盼着回到家的一刻，急切地要回到他熟识和喜爱的事物中间。这时他明白过来了，他是一只属于耕地和树篱的动物，同他连接在一起的是犁沟，是他常常光顾的牧场，是他黄昏时分流连不去的林荫小路，是种着庄稼的田园。严寒的天气，顽强的忍耐，真格地同粗犷的大自然冲突交锋，那是别人的事。他得聪明些，他得守着那舒适的地界──他的命运就安排在那里，那地方自有它的刺激和奇遇，足够他消遣一生。

第五章　家园之乐[1]

绵羊杂乱地挤在一起，向羊栏跑去。他们仰着脑袋，喷出薄薄的鼻息，细细的前蹄跺着地面。淡淡的水汽从拥挤的羊圈里升腾起来，弥散在寒冷的空气里。两只动物兴高采烈、有说有笑地匆匆从旁经过。他们正穿过乡间回家去：长长一整天，他们都跟奥特在野外，在水边高地上打猎、探险。他们那条大河的几条支流的细细的源头就在那高地上。冬日短暂的白昼将尽，暮色正合拢来，但他们仍有一段路要赶。刚才脚步沉重、缓慢地穿过无路的耕地时，他们听到羊的声音，就赶了过来。现在，他们发现有一条脚爪踩出来的小径从羊圈通出去，走在上面感觉松快多了。对这个小小的鼓舞，所有小动物的内心都拥有的某种天赋作出了反应，它明白无误地在说：“是的，一点没错，这条路通向家！”

“我们好像来到了一个村庄。”鼹鼠莫尔放慢脚步，稍带迟疑地说。那条脚爪踩出来的小径，没多久变成了小道，然后又扩展成一条林荫小路，现在把他们交付给了一条碎石铺面的大道。两只动物受不了村庄，而他们时常在上面过往的那几条公路自有独立的走向，与教堂、邮局和酒店毫不相干。

“哦，没关系的！”水鼠兰特说，“一年里的这个季节，他们全都太太平平待在家里，坐着烤火。男人、女人、孩子、狗儿、猫儿，全都是。我们悄悄地溜过去就行了，不会招惹麻烦、遇到不快。如果愿意，可以透过窗户瞧他们一眼，看看他们在干什么。”

十二月中旬的夜幕降得那么快，一下子把小小的村庄全笼罩住了。他们踏着初雪的一层薄薄的雪粉，蹑手蹑脚走上前去。除了街道两旁昏暗的橘红色方块以外，几乎什么也看不见。一幢幢村舍的火光或者灯光，透过那些方块窗扉，流溢到外面黑魆魆的世界里。那种低矮的格子窗多半不挂窗帘，窗内的人围坐在茶桌旁，或者专心致志地做手工，或者有说有笑，还做着手势。在窗外的看客眼中，都各有一种给人带来快乐的魅力。这种魅力正是演艺纯熟的演员的终极追求──完全意识不到观众存在，自然而然表现出来的一种魅力。两个离开自己家那么远的观众，随心所欲从一家剧院跑到另一家。当他们看到一只猫儿被人抚摸，一个瞌睡的孩子被人托起来拥在怀里送上床，一个疲倦的男人伸个懒腰，在一根燃烧的木头一端磕空烟斗时，他们的眼睛里流露出了伤感。

但最让人心跳的是一方小小的窗户。窗帘拉上了，夜色中它只是一方透着光的空白。它透出一种家的感觉。四墙围护、帷帘遮屏的一方小天地，把外面自然界那个有压力的大世界隔开了，忘却了。紧靠白色窗帘挂着的一只鸟笼在窗户上映出一个清晰的剪影，笼子的每一根栖木、每一道铁丝、每一样配件，甚至在昨日被舔圆了边角的那块方糖，都清晰可辨。中央那根栖木上，那个毛蓬蓬的占有者，把脑袋塞进了羽毛里。它好像离他们很近很近，仿佛抬起手就能很容易地抚摸到似的。甚至他蓬起的羽毛的细尖尖，都清晰地映画在那块发光的屏幕上。他俩正看着，那瞌睡的小家伙不安地动了一动，醒了。他抖抖身子，抬起头。他们看得见他的张开着的小小的喙。他懒洋洋地打了个哈欠，看看四周，然后又把脑袋扭到背后，埋进翅膀里，竖起的羽毛也渐渐地收拢来，最后完全静止不动了。这时，一阵刺骨的寒风刮进他们的后脖颈，冰凉的雨夹雪刺痛了皮肤，使他们如梦初醒，意识到自己脚趾冰冷，两腿发酸，离家还有很长很累的一段路。

出了村庄，突然一下子就不再有村舍了，透过黑暗，他们又嗅到路两边亲切的田野气息。他们打起精神，踏上最后一段漫长的归途。这是回家的路，这路，我们知道，迟早走到尽头。到时门闩喀嚓一响，炉火突然映入眼帘，各种熟悉的物件迎候着我们，那情景就像迎接久别后从遥远海外归来的游子。他们默默而坚定地行进着，各自想着自己的心事。鼹鼠莫尔满脑子都是晚饭。夜色漆黑一片，在他心目中，这是完全陌生的乡间，他把领路这件事完全交给水鼠兰特，乖乖地尾随着他。水鼠兰特按照习惯走在前头一小段，双肩耸起着，两眼紧盯着前面笔直、灰暗的道路。所以呀，当那个召唤突然触到可怜的莫尔，像电击一样击中他时，兰特没有注意到。

我们这个与众不同的种类，已经失去敏锐的生理感觉很久了，甚至已经没有适当的词汇来表达动物和环境──周围有生命的或无生命的事物──之间息息相通的关系。例如，我们只有“嗅觉”这一个词来概括整个系列的微妙刺激，它们却日日夜夜在动物鼻子里嗡动着，表示召唤、警告、挑逗、排斥。正是这样一个来自虚空的神秘的、仙乐一般的呼唤，突然透过黑暗触动了莫尔。那感召激得他浑身一遍遍地颤栗，多么熟悉哦，虽然他一时还不能清楚地记起那究竟是什么。他一下子就完全定住了，用鼻子使劲儿地向各处搜寻，想捕捉住那根细丝、那道传达信息的电流，它那么强烈地触动了他。只一会儿，他就重新捕捉到了它。这一回，记忆的洪流随着它蜂拥而来了。

家！这就是那信息的含义。那亲切的感召，那从空中飘来的温柔的触摸，那些又拉又拽的看不见的小手，全都来自同一个方向！唔，那一刻，它一定近在咫尺，他的老家：他第一次发现大河那一天就将之匆匆丢下，再没有回过的家！现在，它派探子和信使出来，要捉他回去了。自从在那个欢快明媚的早晨逃离后，他几乎连想也不曾想到过它。他沉浸在新生活里，陶醉在各种乐趣、奇遇、新鲜感和吸引人的体验之中。现在，往日的记忆涌上心头，在黑暗中，家，那么清晰地呈现在他眼前！它确实破旧狭小，陈设简陋，可那是自己的家，他自己动手建造的家，每天工作结束后回到里面那么幸福。很明显，家也喜爱他。它正想念着他，盼他回去。它正通过他的鼻子，对他诉说这一切，带着哀愁，带着责备，但并不怨恨，并不生气。它只是凄楚地提醒他，它就在这里，它想他。

这呼叫清清楚楚，这召唤明白无误。他必须立刻服从，立刻前去。“鼠仔！”他充满了欢乐，激动地喊道，“停下！回来！我需要你，快停下！”

“哦，跟上，莫尔，来呀！”水鼠兰特欢快地答道，继续吃力地向前走。

“求求你停下，鼠仔！”可怜的莫尔央求道，他心里面痛苦极了，“你没明白我的意思！这是我的家，我的老家！我刚刚发现了它的气味，它就在附近，真的非常近。我一定得去，一定，一定！哦，回来，鼠仔！求求你，求求你回来！”

这时水鼠兰特已经在前头好远。太远了，听不清鼹鼠莫尔究竟在喊些什么；太远了，分辨不出他嗓音中那尖利的声调、痛苦的吁求。他的心思在天气上，因为他也嗅出了一点什么，好像快要下雪了。

“莫尔，现在我们不能停，真的！”他回过头来喊道，“我们明天来吧──已经很晚了，而且马上又要下雪，这条路我还拿不准！我需要你的鼻子，莫尔，所以快跟上来吧，你可是个好伙计！”水鼠兰特不等莫尔回答，只管奋力向前赶路。

可怜的莫尔独自一人站在路上，他的心碎了，在他心底里，一汪酸泪正在聚积着，聚积着。他知道它就要一涌而出，尽情宣泄。但即使面临这样的考验，他对朋友的忠诚依然毫不动摇。他片刻也不曾有过抛弃兰特的念头。可同时，老家飘送来的信息在向他嘀咕、恳请、祈求，最后专横地下了拥有他的结论。他不敢再在它们的魔力圈子里停留下去了。他猛地挣断心弦，把脸冲着前方的路，顺从地追随着水鼠兰特的踪迹。可那微弱的淡淡的气味，仍然朝着他那竭力逃避的鼻子穷追不舍，责备他麻木不仁，有了新朋，忘了旧友。

他费了好大劲儿才赶上兰特。兰特一点都没生疑心，开始愉快地唠叨起回家后该干些什么，客厅里生起一炉柴火会多么让人快活，他准备吃一顿怎样的晚饭。他丝毫没留意到同伴心中痛苦，没留意到他沉默不言。不过，最后，当他们走了相当长一段路，经过紧贴着道路的一片杂树林边缘的几个树桩时，他停下来，好心地说：“喂，莫尔老家伙，你好像累坏了。你一声不吭，两只脚拖着走好像灌了铅似的。我们在这里坐一分钟，歇一歇吧。到现在雪还没有落下来，我们已经走了一大半路了。”

鼹鼠莫尔凄凄惨惨地一屁股坐在树桩上，竭力克制着自己，因为他感觉到自己真的要哭出来了。他已经跟那一汪酸泪斗了很久，可它就是不肯认输。它一个劲儿地往上，往上，硬要冒出来，一点一点又一点，其余的一股脑儿飞快地往上涌。最后，可怜的莫尔放弃了抗争，不管不顾、止不住地放声痛哭起来，因为他知道，一切都完了，那个很难说已经找到的东西，他已经失去。

莫尔突然哭得死去活来，让水鼠兰特又惊讶又沮丧，有一会儿竟不敢开口说话。最后，他平心静气、深表同情地说：“怎么啦，老伙计？究竟怎么回事？把你的苦恼说出来吧，看我能不能帮帮你。”

可怜的莫尔说话很困难，他的胸膛不停地剧烈起伏着，阻碍他说话，话到嘴边也被噎住。“我知道它……破旧……脏……地方小，”他终于呜呜咽咽、断断续续地说出来了，“比不上……你的舒服住处……托德的漂亮府第……班杰的大屋子……可那是我自己的小家……我喜欢它……我跑出来，把它忘得一干二净……可我突然嗅到它了……在路上，我叫你，可你不听，兰特……我一下子全想起来了……我想念它！……天哪，天哪！……你不肯往回走，鼠仔……我只好丢下它，可我一直嗅到它的气味……我觉得心要碎了……原本可以过去看一眼的，鼠仔……只看一眼……就在附近……可你不肯往回走，鼠仔，你不肯往回走！天哪，天哪！”

回忆卷起了新的悲伤浪潮，泪水再一次完全占据上风，哽噎得他说不下去了。

水鼠兰特两眼直直地看着前面，一言不发，只是轻轻地拍着莫尔的肩膀。过了一会儿，他忧郁地咕哝道：“现在我全明白了！我是一头多蠢的猪啊！一头猪──就是我！我就是一头猪──十足的一头猪！”

他等着，等莫尔的哭泣渐渐缓和下来，变得有节奏些。他等着，等到最后，莫尔只是在抽鼻子了，哭泣变得断断续续。这时他站起来，漫不经心地说：“嗨，我们最好还是接着走，老家伙！”边说边迈步，沿着他们刚才辛辛苦苦走过来的路，原路往回走。

“你（呃）去哪里（呃），鼠仔？”莫尔吃惊地抬起头来，满脸泪花，喊道。

“我们去找你的家，老伙计，”水鼠兰特愉快地答道，“所以你最好一起来，要费点事呢，需要你的鼻子。”

“哦，回来，鼠仔，快回来！”鼹鼠莫尔嚷道，站起身来急忙追了上去，“没用的，我跟你说！太晚了，天太黑，那地方离这里太远，而且快下雪了！还有──我绝不是有意要让你知道我对它感情那么深──这完全是个意外，一个错误！想想河岸吧，还有你的晚餐！”

“去他的河岸和晚餐！”水鼠兰特诚心诚意地说，“我告诉你，我一定要找到那地方，哪怕在外面待一夜。打起精神来，老家伙，抓住我的胳膊，我们很快就会回到那里的。”

莫尔仍然在抽鼻子，他央求着，不大情愿地让专横的伙伴把自己拽上了回头路。兰特滔滔不绝地给他讲趣闻逸事，好让他恢复情绪，高兴起来，好让令人疲惫的路途显得短些。终于，他们来到了水鼠兰特觉得肯定是莫尔“耽搁下来”的那段路附近，他说：“好了，别说话了。干活儿！用上你的鼻子，用心找。”

他们默默地走了一小段路，突然，水鼠兰特从他挽着莫尔的那条胳膊觉察到一道微弱的电流，它震颤着流过那动物的身体。他立刻松开自己的胳膊，退后一步，聚精会神地等待着。

信号来了！

莫尔僵立了片刻，翘起的鼻子微微颤动着，嗅着空气。

接着他短促地向前跑几步──错了──猛地止步──回头再试；然后慢慢地、稳稳地、充满信心地向前。

水鼠兰特很是兴奋，神态像个梦游者似的，紧跟着鼹鼠莫尔。他们跳过一条干沟，钻过一道树篱，在微弱的星光下，靠鼻子嗅着，越过了一片开阔、无路、光秃秃的田野。

突然，莫尔毫无征兆地一头钻了下去。不过，水鼠兰特一直很警觉，立刻就跟着他下了地道──莫尔那准确无误的鼻子忠实地引领着他，找到了它。

地道又窄又闷，土腥味很重，兰特觉得过了好长时间才到达它的尽头。他们站直了，伸一伸胳膊，抖一抖身子。鼹鼠莫尔划着了一根火柴。借着火光，水鼠兰特看见他们正站在一块打扫得干干净净的空地上，脚下铺着沙子，脸正对着莫尔家那扇小小的前门，门旁悬着拉铃绳，门上方嵌着哥特体字母。

莫尔走到墙跟前，从一根钉子上摘下一盏灯笼，把它点亮。水鼠兰特瞅着四周，看到他们所在的地方像是前院。门的一旁放着一张花园长椅，另一边有一个石滚子。鼹鼠莫尔在家时是个爱干净的动物，不能容忍别的动物在他的地面上踢出一道道痕，堆成一个个小土堆。围墙上挂着铁丝花篮，里面种着些蕨类植物。花篮之间安着托架，托架上放着石膏塑像──加里波第、婴儿撒母耳、维多利亚女王，还有另外一些意大利当代英雄[2]。前院一侧有个九柱戏场子，场子边上有一排长凳，还有一些刻着圆圈圈的小木桌，那些圆圈是放啤酒瓶的位置。院子中间是一个圆形的小池塘，池子边上镶着一圈鸟蛤贝壳，池子里面养着金鱼。池子中央矗立着一座形状新颖奇特的建筑，它四周嵌着更多的鸟蛤贝壳，顶上安着一颗银白色的大玻璃球，映在上面的每一样东西都变了形，很好玩。

这些物件那么亲切，一下子映入眼帘，让莫尔脸上放出光来。他催促着兰特赶快进门，在门厅里点亮一盏灯，扫视了一下他的旧家。只见到处都积了厚厚的灰尘，长时间没人料理的屋子里一片清冷凄凉的景象，房间狭小，陈设破旧──他又一次崩溃了，两只爪子捂着脸，一屁股瘫坐在门厅里的椅子上。“鼠仔呀！”他凄凄惨惨地哭道，“我干吗这样做哟？干吗在这样一个夜晚，带你来到这个又冷又小的破地方，此时此刻你本可以待在河边的家里，在旺旺的炉火前烤你的脚指头，周围尽是你那些讲究的摆设！”

水鼠兰特没理会莫尔的自怨自艾。他在屋子里跑来跑去，打开一扇扇门，检查房间和橱柜，点亮许多灯和蜡烛，各个地方都摆放上一个。“顶顶好的一座小屋！”他兴高采烈地嚷嚷道，“那么紧凑！安排归置得多好！样样都不缺，样样都在合适的位置！今晚我们会过得很快活的。第一件需要做的事是生一炉旺火，这事我来办，我找东西是最内行的。这就是客厅？棒极了！把那些小铺位安在墙上是你自己想出来的吗？顶顶好的主意！嗨，我去搬木柴和煤，你去找个掸子，莫尔──厨房的桌子抽屉里肯定有的──把屋子稍微弄整洁些。快忙起来，老家伙！”

令人振奋的同伴让鼹鼠莫尔受了鼓舞，他站起身，用力又用心地开始掸灰擦垢。水鼠兰特抱来满满一抱柴火，跑前跑后，很快就生着了火，欢乐的火苗呼呼地直蹿烟囱。他招呼鼹鼠莫尔过去暖暖身子。可莫尔立刻又是一阵沮丧，他绝望透顶地跌坐在一张长椅上，把脸埋在掸子里。“兰特，”他呻吟道，“你的晚饭怎么办呢，你这个又冷又饿又累又可怜的动物？我没东西给你吃，什么也没有，面包屑也没有！”

“你这家伙，咋这么容易投降哟！”水鼠兰特责备道，“嗨，就是刚才，我清清楚楚看到厨房碗柜里有一个开沙丁鱼罐头的起子。人人都知道，哪里有起子，哪里附近就有沙丁鱼罐头。振作起来！打起精神，过来和我一起找找。”

他们就照着法子去找，搜遍每一个柜子，拉开每一只抽屉。结果当然没有预料的好，但也不算太让人沮丧──沙丁鱼一罐，船长饼干[3]一盒，差不多是满的，还有包着银纸的德国香肠一根。

“够开宴席了！”水鼠兰特一边摆饭桌，一边评论道，“我敢说，有些动物，如果让他们坐下来和我们一起吃晚饭的话，要他们干什么都行！”

“没有面包！”鼹鼠莫尔忧伤地叹息道，“没有黄油，没有……”

“没有肥鹅肝酱饼，没有香槟！”水鼠兰特咧开嘴笑着，接口说道，“说到这个我想起来了──过道底那扇小门里面是什么？当然是你的酒窖！这屋子里什么奢侈品都有了！等我一分钟。”

他向酒窖门走去，很快就走了回来，身上沾了点灰尘，两只爪子里，两只胳膊下，各夹着一瓶啤酒。“看来你是个挺放纵自己的乞丐，莫尔，”他评论道，“一样也不戒。这小屋子真是我到过的最快活的地方。这些墙画你从哪里弄来的？这么一贴，太有家的气氛了。怪不得你那么喜欢这个家呢，莫尔。说来听听，布置得这么好，你是怎样办到的。”

水鼠兰特忙着去拿盘子和刀叉，还有调和蛋杯要用的芥末。这时候，鼹鼠莫尔开讲了。因为刚才情绪激动的缘故，他的胸脯还在起伏。起先他还稍微有些不好意思，但是越往下说，就越放得开了──这是怎样设计的，那是怎么想出来的。这是从姑姑那里得来的飞来横财，那可是个淘换来的宝贝，而且买的是便宜货。这一件却是“省吃俭用”好些时候，辛辛苦苦攒钱买来的。说到最后，他的情绪完全恢复了，一定要去抚摸一下他的财物。他拿起一盏灯，向客人展示它们的特点，详详细细地解说一遍，完全忘了他们俩都迫切需要的晚餐。兰特饿极了，却努力掩饰着，一会儿严肃地点点头，一会儿皱起眉头仔细端详，有机会插言评说时，还不时说上一句“真棒”、“好不寻常哦”什么的。

水鼠兰特终于把他诱骗到了桌饭旁边。真的要打开沙丁鱼罐头时，他们突然听到前院里有声音，像是一只只小脚在石子儿上扭来扭去的声音，还有一片杂七杂八的细细的嘀咕声。他们能断断续续地听到只言片语──“好啦，站成一排……汤米，把灯笼稍微举高点……先清清你们的嗓子……我报过‘一二三’后不要再咳嗽……小比尔在哪里？……过来，快，我们都在等你……”

“发生什么事了？”水鼠兰特停住手，问道。

“肯定是田鼠，”鼹鼠莫尔答道，神态中有一丝得意，“每年这个时候，他们都会按规矩到处走动，唱圣诞颂歌。在我们这一带，这差不多已经成习俗了。他们从来不漏掉我，最末一个到这里。唱到莫尔家结束。我总是请他们喝热饮料，如果供得起，有时还请他们吃晚饭。如今又听到他们的声音，就好像回到了过去的时光。”

“去看看他们吧！”水鼠兰特嚷道，跳起来，向门口跑去。

门一打开，映入眼帘的是一幅可爱的冬令景象。前院里，一盏牛角灯笼的昏暗光线，照亮了站成半圆形的十来只小田鼠，他们脖子上围着红色精纺羊毛围巾，前爪深深地插在衣兜里，两只脚跳着吉格舞取暖。他们亮晶晶的小圆眼睛羞怯怯地互相瞟着，偷偷地笑几声，吸吸鼻子，又盯着自己的外衣袖子好一阵子。门开的时候，那个年龄大些提着灯笼的，正在喊：“预备，一、二、三！”空中立刻就扬起了他们尖细的声音。他们唱的是一首古时候的颂歌，是他们的祖先在结了冰霜的休耕农田里，或者在大雪封住了烟囱拐角的时候创作的，[4]一代代传下来，每逢圣诞时节，在泥泞的街道上，对着亮灯的窗户歌唱。

圣诞颂歌

众位乡亲，对着冰霜寒潮，
请敞开你们的家门，
虽然有风跟着，有雪沾着，
还是请我们进去烤烤火吧，
欢乐将属于你们，在早晨！

我们跺着脚呵着手指头，
站这里冒雨雪顶寒风，
远道而来向你们致意──
你们在炉边我们在街头──
祝欢乐属于你们，在早晨！

因为在前半夜过去之前，
引导我们来的一颗星
会突降如雨的喜乐福祉──
赐福明朝，赐福来日，
赐欢乐给每一个早晨！

善人约瑟夫[5]跋涉在雪中
看见那颗星低垂马厩上空；
玛丽[6]不用再前行，迎着她
茅草屋顶在上，褥草在下！
欢乐属于她，在那天早晨！

于是他们听见了天使的声音：
“是谁第一个欢呼圣诞？
是所有动物，因为圣婴降临
是在他们所居住的马厩！
欢乐将属于他们，明天早晨！”

歌声停止了，歌手们有些羞怯，但喜气洋洋，和旁边的人交换着眼色。接下来是一片寂静──但只有一会会儿。接着，从上方的地面上，从遥远的地方，透过他们不久前刚经过的地道，一阵嗡嗡嗡的微弱音乐声传到他们耳边，那是远处的钟声在叮叮当当地鸣响着欢乐。

“唱得真好，孩子们！”水鼠兰特热情地喊道，“进来吧，大家都进来，烤烤火暖暖身子，吃点热乎的东西！”

“是啊，快进来，田鼠们，”鼹鼠莫尔急忙喊道，“还像过去一样！随手关上门。把那张高背长椅拖到炉火前面。现在，稍等一分钟，等我们──哦，鼠仔！”他绝望地嚷道，一屁股坐下，眼泪都快掉下来了，“究竟怎么办呢？我们没东西给他们吃！”

“全交给我吧，”兰特说道，好像他才是主人，“喂，那个拿灯笼的！过来，我有话问你。嗯，告诉我，晚上这个时候还有商店开着门吗？”

“嗯，当然有，先生，”田鼠恭敬地答道，“每年这个时候，我们这里的商店任何时候都开门。”

“那好，你听着！”水鼠兰特说，“你立刻出去，带上灯笼，给我……”

接着他们又嘀咕了一阵子，鼹鼠莫尔只零零星星听到几句，比如，“记住，要新鲜的！……不，那个一磅就够了……一定要买布金斯家产的，别的我都不要……不，只要最上等的……如果那一家没有，就换一家试试……对，当然，要自制的，罐装的不要……就这样，你尽力而为吧！”最后是硬币叮叮当当从一只爪子递到另一只爪子里的声音，田鼠接过一只很大的购物篮子，就提着灯笼急匆匆地出门了。

其余田鼠在高背长椅上坐成一排，小腿儿悬空，晃荡着，尽情享受炉火，把他们的冻疮直烤到发痒。鼹鼠莫尔想引着他们轻轻松松地交谈，没成功，就大讲起家史来，要他们逐个儿报出自己众多弟弟的名字。看来那些弟弟们年龄太小，今年还不让出来唱圣诞颂歌，不过呀，料想得到，父母批准的那一天很快就会来到的。

这时水鼠兰特正忙着察看啤酒瓶上的标贴。“我看出来了，这是老伯顿牌的，”他赞许地评论道，“好有见地的莫尔！就要这个牌子的！现在可以来加些调料做热麦芽酒了！把东西准备好，莫尔，我来拔软木塞。”

没多大工夫，就把酒调好了，装在锡壶里，把它深深地塞进炉子中央最红的炭火中间。不一会儿，田鼠们一个个都啜着、咳着、呛着（因为调制的麦芽酒哪怕一点点，劲儿也够大的），一边擦眼睛，一边呵呵地笑，忘了自己这一辈子挨过冷受过冻。

“这些小家伙还会演戏呢，”鼹鼠莫尔向水鼠兰特介绍说，“全是他们自己编，自己演。演得还真不错！去年他们演了一出顶顶好的戏，说一只田鼠在海上被巴巴里海盗[7]抓住了，被强迫在一艘战舰上划桨。他逃脱了。回到家乡时，他的情妹妹已经进了女修道院。嗨，你！当时你参加演出的，我记得。站起来，背一段台词来听听。”

被点到的田鼠站了起来。他羞怯地咯咯直笑，眼睛在屋子里瞟了一圈，舌头却依然像打了结，憋不出一句词儿。同伴们给他加油，莫尔哄他鼓励他，水鼠兰特甚至不惜抓住他的肩膀摇晃他。但无论怎么弄，也克服不了他的怯场心理。大家围着他忙得团团转，就像一群船工，按照皇家溺水者营救会的章程，抢救一个长时间溺水的人一样。正在这时，门栓咔嗒一响，门开了。打灯笼的田鼠出现在门口，沉甸甸的篮子压得他脚步蹒跚。

篮子里实实在在的内容一倒在桌上，演戏的话题马上就被忘到了九霄云外。在兰特指挥下，人人动手，或者干活儿，或者去取东西。短短几分钟，晚饭就准备好了。莫尔像做梦一样在餐桌主位上坐定时，看到刚刚还空荡荡的桌面现在已经排满了美味佳肴；看到小朋友们脸上放光，片刻也不耽误，马上就开始吃了起来。其实他自己已经饿极了，于是也放开肚皮，享受那些魔术般变出来的食物。他边吃边寻思，这次回家，最后居然变成了这么快乐的光景。他们边吃边聊，说些往事，田鼠给莫尔说了些本地最近的小道消息，还尽其所知，回答了他询问的上百个问题。水鼠兰特几乎不说话，只管照料着客人们各自想吃什么吃什么，多吃多喝，让莫尔丝毫不用操心费神。

最后响起了一片杯盘刀叉放下的叮当声，田鼠们要走了。他们说了很多声谢谢，还有像雨点一样的节日祝福；出门时，上衣口袋里塞满了带回家给弟弟妹妹的纪念品。门在最后一个小客人身后关上，灯笼上的叮当声渐渐消失了。莫尔和兰特就把火拨旺，把椅子拉到炉火跟前，给自己斟上最后一杯调制麦芽酒作为睡前饮料，议论几句这长长的一天里发生的事情。最后水鼠兰特打了个大大的哈欠，说道：“莫尔，老家伙，我要倒了。简直不能用犯困这个词儿来形容。那边一张床铺是你自己的吧？好的，我就睡这一张了。这小屋子多妙啊！每一样东西都是伸手就够得着！”

他爬上床铺，把自己裹在毯子里，马上就进入了梦乡，就像一捆大麦被搂进了收割机的怀抱中一样。

疲倦的莫尔也很乐意立刻上床睡觉，他的脑袋很快就挨到了枕头上，一颗心沉浸在无比的快乐和满足之中。但是他在合上两只眼睛之前，让它们在他的老房间里巡视了一遍。在炉火的映照下，这房间那么的温馨柔和；火光停留在每一样物件上，在上面嬉戏。不知不觉中，这些熟悉而亲切的物件早已成了他自身的一部分，现在正微笑着迎接他归来，毫无怨言。他现在的心境，正是机智的兰特想要悄悄地引他进入的那一种。他很清楚，家里的一切有多么平凡简朴，甚至很狭小；但他也明白，家对自己有多么重要，这样一个港湾，对一个人的生存具有何等特殊的价值。没错，他丝毫也不想抛弃新的生活和灿烂广阔的新天地，不想离开阳光、空气和它们呈现给他的一切，爬回来，守在家里；上面的世界吸引力太强大了，即使他目前身处地下，也仍然在召唤他，他知道自己必须回到那个更大的舞台上去。不过，心中知道有这样一个家可以回，这有多好啊。这地方完全属于他自己，这些物件重新见到他时总是喜笑颜开，永远可以指望它们这样率真地欢迎他归来。

[1]原文为拉丁文，dulce domum，意思是“天伦之乐，家庭之乐”。

[2]加里波第，意大利爱国者，将军；撒母耳，《圣经》中的人物，希伯来领袖和先知。

[3]一种优质饼干。

[4]过去英国住宅的烟囱不是我们见到的直通通指向天空的那种，而是大而弯曲，有的甚至是一个像迷宫一样复杂的系统，小孩子能够爬进去清扫。

[5]圣母玛利亚的丈夫，耶稣的养父。

[6]指圣母玛丽亚，玛丽是玛丽亚的昵称。

[7]巴巴里海岸位于埃及以西的北非，曾经是海盗出没的地区。

第六章　托德先生

这是初夏一个晴朗亮丽的早晨。大河两岸已经复原，河水恢复了惯常的流速。热热的太阳，仿佛用千万根金线，把万物从土中拽起来，拽出来，迎向自己；让它们变绿，变茂密，生出尖刺。鼹鼠莫尔和水鼠兰特天刚亮就起床了，忙着干一些与船有关联的活儿，为正在到来的行船季节做些准备。比如上清漆和油漆，修理船桨，修补坐垫靠垫，把不见了的带钩船篙找出来，等等。这时候他们在小客厅里，已经快吃完早饭，正在热烈地讨论当天的计划，忽然门上响了一记很重的敲门声。

“麻烦！”水鼠兰特说，满嘴都是鸡蛋，“看看是谁，莫尔，好小伙子，你已经吃完了。”

鼹鼠莫尔出去应门，水鼠兰特听到他发出一声惊喜的大叫。接着客厅的门猛地打开了，莫尔郑重其事地通报：“班杰先生到！”

獾子班杰来正式拜访他们，或者更确切地说，拜访任何人，都实在是一件了不得的事。如果你非常想见他，一般只有一大清早，或者黄昏将夜时分，在灌木树篱旁等候着，趁他悄没声地溜过去时，同他碰个正着。要不然就得到野树林中央他家里去找他，那可是一件非同小可的事。

獾子班杰脚步很重，他大步走进屋子，然后站在那里，一脸严肃，看着两只动物。水鼠兰特不由自主把蛋勺掉在桌布上，大张着嘴呆坐在那里。

“时间到了！”獾子班杰终于极其庄重地说道。

“什么时间？”水鼠兰特瞟着壁炉台上的钟，很不自在地问。

“你应该问是谁的时间，”獾子班杰答道，“嗨呀，是托德的时间！托德的时间到了！我说过，冬天一过去，我就要接手管教他，今天我就是来管教他的！”

“托德的时间，当然！”鼹鼠莫尔高兴地嚷道，“万岁！我想起来了！我们要把他教导成一个明智的托德！”

“昨晚我从可靠的消息来源获悉，”獾子班杰在扶手椅里坐下，接着说道，“就在今天上午，又有一辆马力特大的新汽车会送到蛤蟆府试用，不满意可退货。也许，此时此刻，托德正忙着打扮自己，穿上他心爱的那套奇丑无比的服装。托德的模样本来还不错（相对而言），一穿上那身行头，就成了个怪物。只要是头脑还好使的动物，不小心遇见他，都会狂晕。我们得趁早忙活起来，不然就太迟了。你们二位马上陪我去蛤蟆府，完成拯救工作。”

“说得对！”水鼠兰特一跃而起，嚷道，“我们去拯救那不幸的可怜动物！我们要把他改变过来！他得彻底洗心革面，要不然我们就跟他一刀两断！”

他们上路了，去完成他们的善举。班杰在前面带路。动物结伴出行时，总是采取一种适当的、合理的方式。他们排成一列纵队，而不是杂乱无序地横在路上，不然的话，如果突然遇到麻烦或危险，就无法互相支援了。

来到蛤蟆府的马车道上时，他们发现，果然像獾子班杰预料的那样，一辆簇新锃亮的汽车，很大的个头，漆成鲜红色（托德最喜爱的颜色），正停在宅子前面。他们走到门口时，大门正好猛地打开来。托德先生鼻子上架一副护目镜，头戴便帽，脚上套着长筒橡胶靴，身披一件奇大无比的外套，一边大摇大摆地走下台阶，一边拽上他那副长长的皮革驾驶手套。

“哈啰！快来，伙计们！”他一眼就看到他们，兴高采烈地嚷道，“你们来得正是时候，同我一起去快快活活地──快快活活地──快……快……呃活……”

注意到朋友们一言不发，一个个脸上冷冰冰的，表情严厉，他原本热情洋溢的语调顿时变得结结巴巴，邀请还没说完就没了声音。

獾子班杰大步走上台阶。“把他弄进去。”他坚决果断地对同伴们说道。托德挣扎着抗议着，被推搡到门里面去了。班杰则转过身来，对着那个把新车开来的司机。

“恐怕今天不需要你了，”他说，“托德先生改变了主意。请你理解，这是最终决定。你不必等了。”说完他随着其他人走进去，关上了门。

“行啦！”他对癞蛤蟆托德说道，这时他们四个都站在大厅里，“首先，把这一身可笑的玩意儿卸了！”

“不行！”托德回嘴道，劲头十足，“你们这样粗暴地对待我，什么意思？我要求你们马上给个解释。”

“那好，你们两个替他脱。”獾子班杰简短地命令道。

托德一个劲儿地踢着踹着，叫骂出各种难听的话。他们不得不把他摁倒在地板上，否则没法好好干活儿。水鼠兰特坐在他身上，鼹鼠莫尔一点一点剥下他那身驾驶服，然后让他重新站直。一身讲究的行头卸下之后，他那股子狂风暴雨式的劲儿好像消失了一大半。现在他只是托德了，不再是公路煞神。他只能无力地咯咯笑着，求饶似的看看这个又看看那个，好像完全明白了自己的处境。

“你知道迟早会有这一天的，托德。”獾子班杰严厉地解释道。

“你把我们的警告都当成了耳旁风，一直不断地挥霍你父亲留下的钱财。你开车狂飙，撞坏多少东西，还跟警察争吵，在这个地区败坏了我们动物的名声。特立独行没什么不好，可我们动物决不允许自己的朋友干蠢事出丑超过一定的底线。你已经触到这个底线。现在，你在许多方面还是个不错的家伙，我不想对你太狠。我将再做一次努力，让你恢复理智。你跟我到吸烟室里去，听我给你讲讲你都干了些什么。我们来瞧瞧，你从里面出来时，是否还是进去之前那个托德。”

他牢牢地抓住托德的胳膊，把他拽进吸烟室，随手关上了门。

“那白费力气！”水鼠兰特不屑地说，“找托德谈话，是治不好他的毛病的。你说什么他都会答应。”

他们舒舒服服地坐在扶手椅里，耐心等待。透过关着的门，他们只能听见獾子班杰嗡嗡的话音长时间响个不停，声浪一会儿高一会儿低。不久，他们就注意到，班杰的说教时不时地被拉长的呜咽声打断，那明显是从托德的心底里发出来的，他是个软心肠、重感情的动物，很容易──眼下，暂时地──被任何观点左右。

大约过了三刻钟，门开了，獾子班杰用爪子牵着一个没精打采的托德很庄重地走了出来。托德浑身的皮像口袋似的耷拉着，两条腿打着颤，腮帮子上挂着一道道泪痕，那是被獾子班杰的动人演说勾出来的。

“坐那里，托德。”獾子班杰指着一张椅子，和蔼地说。“朋友们，”他接着说道，“我很高兴地告诉你们，托德终于认识到自己走错了路。他真诚地为过去的错误思想和行为感到懊悔，答应永远彻底地放弃玩汽车。他向我作出了一个带有这种意思的郑重承诺。”

“这真是个好消息。”鼹鼠莫尔很认真地说。

“确实是个好消息，”水鼠兰特半信半疑地评论道，“只要──只要──”

他这样说的时候，非常严厉地看着托德，心里忍不住觉得，从那只动物仍然悲伤的眼睛里，仿佛看到有一种东西隐约闪了一下。

“只要再做一件事就行了，”欣慰的班杰接下去说道，“托德，我要你当着你这两位朋友的面，把刚才你在吸烟室里对我满口答应的话，再郑重其事地重复一遍。首先，你是不是为过去的所作所为感到懊悔，认识到那完全是一种愚行？”

很长很长的停顿。托德绝望地看看这边又看看那边，其他动物则一言不发，严肃地等待着。他终于开口了。

“不！”他说，语气有些抑郁，但毫不妥协，“我不懊悔。那根本不是愚行！那就是很光荣的！”

“什么？”獾子班杰喊道，非常非常震惊，“你个出尔反尔的动物，刚才在里面你不是对我说……”

“哦，是啊，是啊，在里面，”托德不耐烦地说，“在里面我什么都会说。你那么有口才，亲爱的班杰，那么感人，那么有说服力，把你的大道理摆得头头是道──在里面你对我可以想怎样就怎样，你知道的啦。可事后我绞尽脑汁，把事情全部捋了一遍，发觉自己其实一点都不懊悔或后悔，所以非要说我懊悔可是一点好处也没有的。喏，是不是？”

“那就是说，”獾子班杰说道，“你不答应不再碰汽车？”

“当然不答应！”托德断然地回答道，“正相反，我说话算数，看见一辆汽车，噗——噗！我就上去开走！”

“我不是早就这样跟你说过吗？”水鼠兰特对鼹鼠莫尔说。

“那好吧，”獾子班杰站起身来，斩钉截铁地说，“既然好说好劝你不听，我们就来试试武力管不管用。我一直担心会走到这一步。托德，过去你经常邀请我们三个过来，和你一起住在这所漂亮房子里。好吧，现在我们就照办。哪一天把你的脑筋搞正常了，我们就离开，不到那一天不走。你们二位把他弄上楼去，把他锁在卧室里，然后我们几个把事情安排一下。”

托德又踢又蹬，拼命挣扎着，被两位忠实的朋友拖上楼去。“你知道这是为你好，蛤蟆仔，”水鼠兰特和蔼地说，“想想看，等你熬过这一关，治好这场痛苦的疯病，我们大家又会像以前一样一起玩，那多开心！”

“在你病好以前，我们会好好地为你照管一切，托德，”鼹鼠莫尔说，“我们会好好当心，不让你的钱像以前那样被糟蹋掉。”

“不再发生不幸事件交警方处理，托德。”水鼠兰特说，这时他们正把他塞进卧室。

“不再一连几个礼拜住医院，被女护士呼来喝去，托德。”鼹鼠莫尔一边补上一句，一边转动钥匙把他锁在了里面。

然后他们下楼，任由托德透过锁孔冲着他们高声叫骂。然后三位朋友开会，讨论目前的局势。

“这件事要拖很长时间呢，”獾子班杰说，叹了口气，“我从没见过托德这样死心塌地。但我们无论如何也要坚持下去，把事情完成。得时时刻刻有人看着他。我们轮班陪他，直到他身上的毒自己排完为止。”

他们按照这个办法排好了班。晚上每个动物轮流睡在托德的房间里，白天也分班看守。刚开始时，对这几个小心谨慎的守卫来说，托德的确是个很难对付的家伙。疯劲儿一上来，他就会把卧室里的椅子排成形似汽车的样子，蹲在最前面那张椅子上，向前弓着身子，眼睛直盯着前方，嘴里发着很难听的噪音。最后达到高潮时，他会完整地翻一个筋斗，趴倒在东倒西歪的椅子中间，暂时显得心满意足。不过，随着时间的推移，这种痛苦的发作次数越来越少了。他的朋友们也千方百计让他分心，把注意力转移到新的渠道里去。可他好像就是不能对其他事情产生兴趣，很明显地变得没精打采、萎靡不振了。

一个晴朗的早晨，轮到水鼠兰特值班。他上楼去把班杰换下来的时候，发现班杰烦躁不安，急着要出去。班杰想去树林，到地下洞穴里溜达一大圈，伸展伸展胳膊腿。“托德还赖在床上，”他站在门外，告诉水鼠兰特，“从托德嘴里掏不出几句话，他只说什么‘哦，别理我，我什么也不要，也许过一会儿我就好多了。过一段时间症状会渐渐消失的，不用太着急’之类。哎，你得留神，兰特！托德安安静静，温温顺顺，装出一副主日学校获奖小明星的模样时，就是他最狡猾的时候。肯定会出花招的。我了解他。哟，现在我得走了。”

“今天你还好吗，老家伙？”水鼠兰特走到托德床边，高高兴兴地问道。

他等了好几分钟才听到回答。一个虚弱无力的声音终于回答道：“非常感谢你，亲爱的鼠仔！你真好，想着问问我！可还是先告诉我，你自己好吗，优秀的莫尔好不好？”

“哦，我们都很好。”水鼠兰特答道。“莫尔嘛，”他很不谨慎地多嘴道，“他跟班杰一起出去溜达了。他们俩要到午饭时候才回来，所以，今天上午只有你我两人一起快快乐乐地打发时间，我会尽量让你开心的。快从床上跳起来吧，乖小伙子，这么好的早晨，别愁眉苦脸躺在那里！”

“亲爱的，好心肠的兰特，”托德喃喃地说，“你对我的情况了解得太少，现在我离‘跳起来’还差得远呢──即使有一天真能做得到！不过，别为我费心啦。我不愿成为朋友们的累赘，料想也不会很久了。真的，我希望不会。”

“嗯，我也希望不会，”水鼠兰特诚心诚意地说，“这段时间你害得我们好苦，听到你说就要结束了，我真高兴。这么好的天气，划船季节刚刚开始！你太不像话了，托德！倒不是我们嫌你麻烦，可你弄得我们错失了好多好多机会。”

“不过，恐怕你们还是在嫌麻烦呢，”癞蛤蟆托德有气无力地回应道，“我完全能理解。这很自然，你们为我费心劳神很多，已经厌倦了。我不能要求你们再为我做什么。我是个大麻烦，我知道。”

“是啊，你确实是，”水鼠兰特说，“但我告诉你，只要能让你变成一个明智的动物，再怎么麻烦我也愿意。”

“既然你这样说，鼠仔，”托德比先前更虚弱了，他喃喃地说，“我求你──可能是最后一次了──求你尽快跑个来回，去村子里──即使马上就去也可能已经太迟了──把医生请来。还是别让你费心了吧。不必白白添麻烦了，也许还是听天由命的好。”

“嗨，你要医生做什么？”水鼠兰特问道。他凑到近前，仔细察看着托德。托德当然是一动不动地平躺着，声音比先前更虚弱，模样变了很多。

“最近你一定注意到──”托德喃喃地说，“不──为什么你就该注意到呢？注意到一些事只会找来麻烦。明天，是啊，也许你会对自己说：‘唉，要是我早注意到就好了！要是我当时做点什么就好了！’可是不用了，不必添麻烦。你别介意，把我的请求忘了吧。”

“听着，老哥们儿，”水鼠兰特说，开始有了几分惊慌，“如果你真的需要，我当然会把医生请来。可你还不至于病到那种程度吧。我们来聊聊别的事情。”

“亲爱的朋友，”托德带着悲哀的笑容说道，“对我这样一个病人来说，恐怕‘聊聊’是起不到什么作用的──而且，恐怕医生也不一定有用。不过，就算是一根稻草也要抓住吧。顺便提一下，既然你准备去，不介意同时也请律师过来一趟吧？我不愿另外再给你添麻烦，可我偶然想起来，你会经过律师门口。那样我能省一点事。有一些时刻──也许我该说有一种时刻，人必须面对不愉快的差事，不惜代价，哪怕耗尽生命！”

“要找律师了！哦，他一定病得很重！”受了惊吓的兰特对自己说。不过，他急急忙忙走出房间时，并没有忘记随手把门仔细锁好。

到外面后，他停下来想了想。另外两位都不在旁边，没有人可以商量。

“还是保险一点好，”他沉思着自言自语道，“托德无缘无故凭空想象自己病重得要命，这种事以前倒也碰到过，可从来没听他说要请律师！如果没有大碍，医生会对他说他是头老驴子，让他振作起来，那倒也是个收获。最好还是迁就他一下，去就去吧，花不了很长时间的。”于是他跑向村子，办他的慈善差事去了。

一听到钥匙在锁孔里转动的声音，癞蛤蟆托德就轻轻一跳下了床。他一直在窗口焦急地注视着兰特，直到他在马车道的尽头消失。然后，他一边纵情大笑，一边尽快地行动起来。他把眼下能找到的最漂亮时髦的衣服穿上，又从梳妆台的一个小抽屉里拿了许多现金塞满衣袋，紧接着，将床上的床单、被单系在一起，临时做成一根绳子，一端系在窗子中间那根竖框上──那富丽堂皇的都铎式[1]窗户可是他卧室的一大特色──爬出去，轻轻地滑落到地上。然后他吹起曲调欢快的口哨，朝着与水鼠兰特相反的方向，无忧无虑地扬长而去。

对兰特来说，那一天的午饭时间是黑色的。獾子班杰和鼹鼠莫尔终于回来了，他不得不在餐桌上面对他们，讲他那令人同情却难以置信的故事。獾子班杰的一番刻薄甚至可以说冷酷的评论，那是可以想象的，所以就不提了。可让水鼠兰特痛苦的是，连鼹鼠莫尔也发话了。他虽然尽可能站在朋友一边，也忍不住说道：“这一回你可有点犯浑了，鼠仔！托德也是，没有动物比他再浑了！”

“他装得太邪乎了。”兰特垂头丧气地说。

“他把你骗得太邪乎了！”獾子班杰火气很大地重新加入了谈话，“不过，光动嘴巴是于事无补的。不用说，眼下他肯定已经跑远了。最糟糕的是，他自作聪明，自高自大，什么蠢事都做得出来。唯一感到安慰的是，现在我们自由了，不必再浪费宝贵的时间给他放哨。但我们最好继续在蛤蟆府睡一段时间。托德随时都可能让人给弄回来──放在担架上，或者夹在两个警察中间。”

话虽这么说，獾子班杰并不知道将来会发生什么事，不知道要有多少水，多么混浊的水，从桥下流过，托德才会重新自在安逸地坐在他祖传的府宅里。

此时此刻，轻松愉快、不负责任的托德，正轻快地在公路上走着，已经离家好几英里。起先为了躲避追踪，他走小路，过田野，还换过几次路线。可现在，他觉得已经没有被抓回去的危险了：太阳在欢快地对着他微笑，整个大自然都加入了一支颂歌的合唱，那是他的心正对他自己唱着的一首自我颂扬的歌。他心里面全是满足，脑子里全是自负，几乎是一路走来一路跳舞。

“干得真漂亮！”他咯咯地笑着对自己评论道，“智力和暴力对决，智力更棒，这是必然的。可怜的老鼠仔！啊呀呀！獾子班杰回来时他不得挨一顿骂！一个挺出色的家伙呀，鼠仔，长处不少，可就是没什么智慧，完全没受过教育。将来有一天，我得管教管教他，看看能不能把他教出点名堂。”

他满脑子都是这种自高自大的念头，一路昂首阔步地走来，到了一座小镇。只见主街的半道上，一幅“红狮”幌子，横过街道，飘飘荡荡地悬着。他这才记起来自己没吃早饭，还走了这么长的路，顿时觉得饿到了极点。他大步走进那家客栈[2]，叫了一份招牌名称如此之短的客栈所能提供的最好的午餐，坐在咖啡室里吃起来。

他刚吃一半就听见一个太熟悉太熟悉的声音，正沿着大街由远及近。那声音使他一个激灵，浑身颤抖起来。噗——噗！越来越近。听得出那辆汽车拐进客栈的院子，停了下来。托德不得不抓住桌子腿来掩饰自己控制不住的冲动。不一会儿，那伙人就走进了咖啡室。他们很饿，很健谈，轻松愉快、喋喋不休地谈论着那天上午他们的经历，还说起了一路顺顺当当把他们载过来的那辆车子的优点。托德如饥似渴、全神贯注地听了一阵子，终于再也忍不住了。他悄悄地溜出咖啡室，到柜台上付了账，一出门，就不声不响地转悠到了客栈院子里。“不会有害处的，”他对自己说，“我只是瞧一瞧！”

汽车停在院子中间，根本没人看管，马夫和其他随从们都在里边吃饭。托德慢悠悠地围着它转，审视着、评点着、沉思冥想着。

“不知道，”他就自言自语地说，“不知道这种车子发动起来容易不？”

片刻之后，也不知道是怎么发生的，他发现自己的手握在车门把手上，正在转动它。随着那熟悉的咔嗒一声响，往日的激情一下子攫住托德，主宰了他的身心。像在梦中一样，他发现自己不知怎么就坐在驾驶座上了；像在梦中一样，他拉动操纵杆，绕着院子开了一段，穿过拱门驶了出去；像在梦中一样，对对和错的判断，对明摆着的后果的恐惧，一时间都仿佛飞到了九霄云外。他加快了速度，车子从街上一啸而过，跃上公路，然后便穿行在空旷的乡间了。这时他脑子里只有一个意识，那就是他又做回托德了：处在最佳状态巅峰时刻的托德、煞神托德、大路的霸主、小路的君王，见到他人人都得让路，否则就给你重重一击，让你灰飞烟灭永不再见天日。他一边飞驰，一边哼唱，那车子也嗡嗡地轰鸣着，响应他的歌声。好多英里在他的车轮下消失，他只知疾速向前，不问它驶向何方。他在满足本能，及时行乐，不管它后果如何。

“我看，”首席地方法官兴致勃勃地评述道，“这个案子其他各方面的案情都很清楚，唯一的困难在于，对我们面前这个在被告席上畏缩成一团的疑犯、屡教不改的流氓、顽固不化的恶棍，怎样才能让他充分领略到难受的滋味。让我想一想：现在已经可以认定他有罪，事实清楚，证据确凿──第一，偷盗昂贵的汽车；第二，驾车危害公众；第三，对乡村警察粗野无礼。书记员先生，请告诉我们，对于上述各项犯罪行为，可以判处的最严厉的处罚是什么？当然，不能给犯人任何无罪假定的权利，因为不存在证据不足的问题。”

书记员用钢笔挠了挠鼻子。“有人认为，”他评述道，“偷盗汽车是最严重的犯罪行为，确实如此。但是，对警察言语无礼，无疑可处以最重的处罚，应该如此。假如说对盗窃罪判得轻些十二个月，对野蛮驾驶罪判得宽大些三年，对冒犯警察罪判十三年──根据我们从证人席上得到的证词，即使只相信十分之一的证词，我本人从来最多只相信十分之一，那也是一种十分严重的冒犯──那么上述数字如果正确地加在一起，总共就是十九年……”

“好极了！”首席法官说。

“……所以您最好凑个整数，二十年，这样比较保险。”书记员总结道。

“极好的建议！”首席法官赞许地说，“犯人！打起精神来，站直了。这一次判你二十年。记住，如果下一次你再出现在我们面前，只好重重地判你了！”

紧接着，粗暴的法警们向倒霉的托德扑过去，给他戴上了镣铐。他尖叫着、祷告着、抗议着，被拖出了法庭。他们拖着他穿过市场，市场上那些爱戏弄人的百姓，对只遭到通缉的嫌犯，一向给予同情和帮助，可对已经定罪的罪犯，总是很苛刻的。他们挖苦他，向他扔胡萝卜，高喊流行口号。他们拖着他走过嘘嘘地起哄的学童，学童们看到一位绅士陷入困境，总是能从中得到些快乐，天真的小脸上放出光来。他们拖着他从发着沉闷声响的吊桥上走过，从布满钉刺的吊闸下钻过，从阴森森的古堡中那条凶巴巴的拱道下穿过──那些古老的塔楼可是高耸入云呢。他们经过警卫室，警卫室里挤满了不当班的军士，军士们冲着他咧开嘴直乐。他们经过咳嗽的哨兵，哨兵的咳嗽含讥带讽，让人难受至极，因为值班哨兵顶多只敢这样来表示对罪犯的轻蔑和厌恶。他们拖着他上了几段年久失修的螺旋式阶梯，从穿着钢盔甲的士兵身旁走过，士兵们从面甲后面射来威胁的目光。他们穿过院子，院子里的猛犬绷紧了脖子上的皮带，爪子向空中乱抓，想扑他。他们经过几个老古董看守，那些看守把戟靠在墙上，面前放着一个肉馅饼和一壶棕色麦芽酒，正打瞌睡。他们拖着他走啊走，走过拉肢刑讯室和拇指夹刑讯室，走过通往非公开断头台的岔路口，最后来到这个最幽深的看守所中心这一间最阴森的地牢门口。门前坐着一个老古董狱卒，正用手指转动着一串又大又重的钥匙。在这里，他们终于停了下来。

“他奶奶的！[3]”警官说，他摘下头盔，擦了擦额头，“起来，你个老潜鸟，把这个坏蛋癞蛤蟆接管过去。他可是个罪大恶极、狡猾无比、机敏过人的罪犯。把你的本事都拿出来，把他给看好喽。你可给我听仔细了，白胡子老头，要是出了什么意外，就拿你的老脑袋瓜子抵他的脑袋──两个脑袋都要遭瘟！”

狱卒阴冷地点点头，把他那只干枯的手放在了不幸的托德肩上。生锈的钥匙在锁孔里嘎吱一响，巨大的牢门就在他们身后哐当一声关上了。于是，在欢乐英国从东到西、从南到北最坚固的城堡中，托德成了最偏远、最戒备森严的地牢里一名无助的囚犯。

[1]都铎是英国一王朝的名称，自1485至1603年共存在118年，该时期英国的建筑混合着传统的哥特式风格和文艺复兴风格。

[2]“红狮客栈”是西方文学作品中常出现的名称，就像中国文学作品中的“悦来客栈”一样。

[3]原文oddsbodikins，骂人话，比God damn it温和些，很少见。有外国专家称出自莎士比亚剧作《哈姆雷特》，经译者考证，不实。

第七章　黎明之门前的吹笛人

柳莺躲在河岸那幽黑的镶边里，正唱着他尖细轻柔的歌。虽然已过晚上十点，天空依然把已逝白昼之光的裙边抓在手里，紧扯着不放。在短暂的仲夏之夜那凉凉的手指触摸搅动下，炎炎的午后郁结着的暑气已经破开，翻滚着散尽了。莫尔正伸开四肢躺在河岸上。那一天，从黎明破晓到日落黄昏，没见过一丝云彩，酷热至极，压得他现在仍然气喘吁吁。他在等他的朋友回来：白天他一直跟另外几个伙伴待在河上，放了水鼠兰特一马，让他赴约去见奥特，那是他俩之间一个长期有效的约定。可他回去时，却发现屋子里黑黑的空无一人，不见兰特的影。他肯定是和老伙伴待在一起不想走了。天还是太热，屋子里待不住，所以莫尔躺在凉爽的酸模草叶子上，把这一天经历的事回想了一遍，觉得全都很棒。

不一会儿就听见水鼠兰特的脚轻轻落在热烘烘的草地上，越走越近的声音。“好凉快哦，真舒服！”他说，然后坐下来，若有所思地凝视着河水，一言不发，入了神。

“你肯定在那边吃过晚饭了吧？”鼹鼠莫尔就问。

“简直没办法，”水鼠兰特说，“我要走，可他们听也不想听。你知道他们一向待人很好的。他们使出浑身解数让我高兴，直到我走的那一刻。可我一直觉得不忍心：虽然他们拼命掩饰，可是我看得很清楚，他们很不快乐。莫尔呀，恐怕他们遇上麻烦了呢。小胖又丢了，你知道他父亲心里有多疼他，虽然嘴上从来不说。”

“什么，那孩子？”鼹鼠莫尔轻飘飘地说，“嗨，就算丢了，又有什么可担心的？他老是自个儿跑出去。丢了，又找到了。他太喜欢冒险啦，但是从来不曾出过事。这附近人人都认识他，喜欢他，就跟喜欢老奥特一样。放心吧，说不定哪只动物碰上他，把他送回家，就万事大吉了。嗨，我们自己就遇到过他。离家好几英里，他一点也不慌张，开心得很呢！”

“没错，可这一回比较严重，”水鼠兰特语气沉重地说，“他已经丢失好几天，奥特一家人到处找遍了，没发现一丝一毫的踪迹。他们还问遍了方圆几英里以内的每一只动物，可没人知道一丁点他的消息。奥特明显着急得很，只是不肯承认而已。我从他那里打听到，小胖的游泳学得还不是很好。我看得出来，他是想到拦河坝那地方了。一年中的这个时节，坝那里仍然有许多水往下流，孩子们总是对那地方很着迷。还有，那里有……嗯，陷阱之类的东西──你知道的啦。奥特不是那种没到时候就很紧张儿子的人。可现在他真的很紧张。我走的时候，他出来送我──说是想透透气，还说什么伸展伸展腿脚。但我看得出来，根本不是那么回事。所以我引他开口，把他好一顿盘问，最后把实话套出来了。他要去浅滩，整夜守着。昔日里，桥造起来之前，大家一向都是从老浅滩那里过河的，那地方你知道吗？”

“我很熟悉，”鼹鼠莫尔说，“可奥特为什么偏偏要选那地方守着呢？”

“嗯，好像，他正是在那里给小胖上第一次游泳课的，”水鼠兰特接着说道，“因为那里有个沙嘴，它靠近河岸，水很浅，有很多碎石。那里也是他经常教他捕鱼的地方，小胖的第一条鱼就是在那里捉到的，那是他很自豪的一件事。孩子爱那地方，奥特心想，如果他从不知什么地方游荡回来──如果此时此刻可怜的小家伙还在这世界上的话──可能会直奔他非常喜爱的浅滩。还有，如果他偶然经过那里，想起好多事情，也许会停下来玩。所以奥特每天夜晚去那里守着──抱着一线希望，你知道的哦，只是抱着一线希望！”

他们沉默了一会儿，两人都在想同一件事──漫漫长夜里，那个孤独、伤心的动物，蹲在那边浅滩上，通宵守候着，等待着──抱着一线希望。

“算了，算了，”水鼠兰特就说，“我觉着我们该回去了。”却没有一点动弹的意思。

“兰特，”鼹鼠莫尔说道，“虽然好像没什么可干的，但不干点什么，我实在没法回去，也睡不着。不如把船弄出来，向上游划。再过个把小时月亮就要出来了，那时我们就可以尽力搜索一番。不管怎么说，总比什么也不干就回去睡觉强。”

“我也是这样想的，”水鼠兰特说，“不管怎么说，这样的夜晚睡不睡的无所谓。离天亮也没多久了，到时候我们可以一边找，一边向早起的人打听他的消息。”

他们把船弄了出来，水鼠兰特操桨，小心地划着。河的中流现出一条清亮狭窄的航道，隐隐约约地倒映着天空。但是水中凡是有河岸、灌木和树的影子的地方，那些影子全都像岸上的原物一样，黑糊糊连成一片。所以，鼹鼠莫尔掌舵时必须好好看清楚。夜那么黑，那么寂寥，但黑暗中充满了各种细微的声响：歌声、唠叨声和一些窸窸窣窣的动静。这些声响透露出小不点族群起来活动了，在干他们的营生。他们会通宵达旦地忙碌，直到阳光照到身上，送他们应当应分地去休息。河水本身的声音也比白天更清晰可辨，它的咕噜声和扑哧声更显得突如其来，仿佛近在咫尺。时不时地，突然一声响，吓他们一跳，仿佛是谁清清楚楚叫了他们一声，那声音真的非常清楚。

地平线很清晰，对天空寸步不让。在一个特定的方向，一片银白色的磷光不断升高，渐渐扩展开来，衬得地平线格外黑。终于，在一直期待着的大地边缘，月亮雍容华贵地慢慢升了上来，最后纵身一跃，脱开地平线悬浮在空中，没有了羁绊。他们又开始能看清地面了──宽广的草地、静谧的花园、两岸之间的河面，全都柔柔地展现在视野里。神秘恐怖的气氛一扫而空，夜色明亮如同白昼，但又与白昼大大不同。他们常去的老地方又在迎候着他们，但换了一身打扮，仿佛它们曾悄悄溜走，换上这一身皎洁的新装，又悄没声地溜回来，含羞带笑地等待着他们，想看看他们是否还认得出来。

两个好朋友把船拴在一棵柳树上，上了岸。他们来到这寂静的银色王国，耐心地搜索着树篱、中空的树、一条条小河与河沿上的一个个小涵洞，还有壕沟和干涸的河道。然后他们又上船，划向大河对岸。他们就这样来来回回往上游一路找下去。那一轮宁静安详的月亮悬在无云的空中，虽然离得那么远，也在尽力帮他们搜寻。最后，她的时间到了，只好很不情愿地沉向地平线下方，离开了他们。于是，神秘氛围再一次笼罩住了田野和大河。

然后，一种变化开始慢慢地显露。地平线变得更清晰了，田野和树木变得越来越分明，而且不知为什么变了模样。笼罩它们的神秘气氛开始退去。忽然，一只小鸟尖叫了一声，又寂静无声了；蓦地起了一阵微风，吹得芦苇和香蒲草沙沙作响。莫尔在划桨，待在船尾的兰特突然坐直了身子，聚精会神地倾听着。莫尔一边很轻地划着，只让船不停下来，一边仔细扫视着岸上。这时，他不由得好奇地看着莫尔。

“听不见了！”水鼠兰特叹息道，重新陷进了座位里。“多么美，多么新奇哟。消失得那么快，还不如没让我听见呢。那声音在我心里唤起了一种痛苦的渴望：只要能再听一回，一直永远地听下去，别的什么都好像无所谓了。不！又来了！”他喊道，再一次凝神倾听起来。他听得入了迷，着了魔，很长时间默默不语。

“它在往前移，我快听不见了，”没多会儿，他就说，“莫尔啊！太美了！那么愉快，沸腾着喜悦，那遥远的笛声的呼唤呢，纤细、清晰、快乐！做梦也想不到有这样的音乐，想不到笛声会有那么甜美，更想不到笛声里的召唤有那么强烈！划呀，莫尔，快划！那音乐和召唤一定是为我们而来的。”

鼹鼠莫尔非常非常纳闷，但他服从了。“我什么也没听见，”他说，“只听见风从芦苇、灯芯草和柳树枝条中间吹过的声音。”

水鼠兰特就算听到了他的话，也没有回答。他全神贯注、情不自禁、浑身颤抖，全身心都被这新的神圣事物占有了。它抓住了他不由自主的灵魂，晃悠着、颠动着，像一只强有力的手托着一个无力但幸福的婴儿。

莫尔默默地、平稳地划着，不久，他们来到大河的分流处，一条长长的回水河汊在这里向一侧岔开。兰特早丢下舵索了，这时就轻轻地歪了歪脑袋，示意划桨手让船走回水河汊。曙光之潮悄无声息，不断地推进着，现在他们已经能看清像宝石一样镶嵌在水边的花儿的颜色。

“越来越近，越来越清晰了，”水鼠兰特快乐地嚷道，“现在你肯定听见了吧！啊──终于──看得出来你听见了！”

那欢畅的笛声的清流，向鼹鼠莫尔奔涌过来，像浪涛一样拍打着他，一下子把他卷住，完全占有了他。他透不过气来，呆若木鸡，停止了划桨。他看见了同伴脸颊上的泪水，他低下头来，理解了。好一会儿，他们待在那里一动不动，任凭那流苏一样缀饰着河岸的紫色千屈菜拂弄着。接着，伴随着那醉人的旋律，清晰而不容违逆的召唤来临了。它把自己的意志强加给莫尔，使他又弯下腰，机械地划起桨来。光不断变得更明亮，但是黎明临近时本该唱起来的小鸟一个也不出声，除了那天籁，万物都静得出奇。

他们继续向前划行。那个早晨，两岸丰美的河边草甸，清新翠绿得无与伦比。他们从来不曾发现玫瑰有这样鲜艳，柳兰有这般绚烂缤纷，绣线菊会弥漫出如此沁人的芬芳。这时，正在逼近的拦河坝发出的嗡鸣声渐渐占领上空，他们感觉到自己正在接近终点──无论它是什么，肯定在那里等待着他们结束这次远足。

那巨大的拦河坝，用泡沫和闪光做成一个宽阔的半圆形臂弯；用碧水形成的闪亮的双肩，从左岸到右岸，封住了回水河汊，在平静的水面上搅起一个个飞旋的漩涡，一串串漂浮的泡沫；用它那庄严而抚慰人心的轰鸣，盖住了所有别的声音。在拦河坝波光粼粼的臂抱里，在水流的中央，停泊着一座小岛，岛的边缘密密地缀着一圈柳树、白桦树和桤树。它有些矜持，有点害羞，但蕴含丰富；它把它所拥有的一切都藏在一层面纱后面，等待既定时间的来临。时间到了，才向应召而来的被选中者坦承。

在一种庄严的期待中，两只动物缓慢但毫不迟疑地划过动荡起伏的水面，把船停靠在小岛那鲜花盛开的岸边。他们默默地上了岸，穿过花丛、芳香的草丛和灌木丛，来到平地上，在一片小草坪上面停住了脚。这是一片绿得神奇的草坪，环绕着它的是大自然自己的果园──沙果树、野樱桃树和黑刺李树。

“这是我的梦中曲之乡，是那音乐演奏给我听的地方，”水鼠兰特悄声说道，仿佛在催眠状态中，“如果世上有一个地方我们肯定会找到他，那就是这块圣地！”

鼹鼠莫尔突然感觉到一种非凡的敬畏感袭来，摁下他的头，把他浑身的肌肉变成了水，使他的脚在地上生了根。那不是恐慌──其实他感到出奇的平静和快乐──那是一种把他摄住、攫紧的敬畏感。不用看他就知道，那只能意味着一个令人敬畏的神灵近在咫尺。他艰难地转过身去找他的朋友，看见兰特就在他身边，诚惶诚恐，剧烈地颤抖着。四周栖满小鸟的树枝上依然悄无声息，天光仍然在变得越来越明亮。

也许他本不敢抬起眼睛，此刻，笛声虽已沉寂，召唤却似乎依然居高临下、不容违逆。即使死神本人正等着他，一旦他用肉眼看了那正正当当地隐藏着的事物就立刻把他击倒，他也不会抗拒那召唤。他颤抖着服从了，抬起谦卑的头。这时，大自然的脸上辉映着不可思议的色彩，她仿佛为正在发生的事屏住了呼吸──黎明正在临近，在无比澄澈的曙光里，莫尔看着朋友与救助者的眼睛。他看见那对向后弯曲的犄角在渐渐增强的日光中闪亮；看见一双慈祥的眼睛正诙谐地俯视着他们，中间是一只刚毅的鹰钩鼻，一丝笑意绽放在长胡须的嘴角。他看见一条鼓着一道道肌肉的胳膊搁在宽阔的胸前，修长柔韧的手中仍握着刚从唇边拿开的那支潘神之笛[1]；看见曲线完美、长满绒毛的双腿威严而悠然地摆放在草地上。最后，他看见他的两只蹄子中间依偎着圆滚滚、胖乎乎、年幼、稚气的小水獭──他一副平和安然、心满意足的模样，睡得正酣。在紧张得透不过气来的这一瞬间，莫尔看到了所有这一切，在清晨的天空映衬下，如此生动。他看见了，所以他还活着；他活着，所以他仍然感到惊讶。

“兰特！”他颤抖着，缓过气来，轻轻地问道，“你害怕吗？”

“害怕？”水鼠兰特喃喃地说，眼睛里闪烁着难以形容的爱的光芒，“害怕！怕他？哦，不，决不！不过……不过……哦，莫尔，我还是有点怕！”

两只动物匍匐在地，俯首膜拜。

突然，太阳那辉煌灿烂的大金盘出现在他们对面的地平线上了。最初的光线从浸在水中的平坦草甸子上射过来，晃得两只动物满目阳光。等他们重新能看见时，那幻象已消失了，空中充满了小鸟赞颂黎明的歌声。

他们茫然地凝视着，渐渐意识到刚才看见的一切和所失去的一切，同时越来越深地陷入一种说不出的惆怅之中。这时，一阵变幻莫测的微风，旋舞着从水面上刮起，撩拨着山杨树，摇晃着含露的玫瑰花，轻轻地、爱抚地吹拂着他们的脸；一经它那轻柔的触摸，他们立刻就忘掉了一切。这正是那现身相助的仁慈的半神[2]，心细体贴，最后赠送给他们的最好礼物：遗忘──以免那使人产生敬畏之心的记忆滞留、滋长，给欢笑和愉悦蒙上阴影；以免那异乎寻常的记忆萦绕在心头，损害这些被他救出困境的小动物的后半生。这礼物是要让他们像以往一样幸福快乐、无忧无虑。

莫尔揉揉眼睛，瞪着茫然四顾的兰特。“对不起，刚才你说什么，兰特？”他问。

“我想，我刚才只不过是说，”兰特慢吞吞地说道，“如果有地方能找着他的话，肯定就是这种地方，就在这里。瞧！呵，他就在那边，那小家伙！”他高兴地大喊一声，向沉睡中的小胖奔去。

但莫尔又站在那里发了一会儿呆。恍如一个人突然从美梦中醒来，努力回忆着，却什么也回想不起来，只隐隐约约地感觉到它的美，美极！最后，那一丁点感觉也渐渐消失了，做梦的人只好悲惨地接受冰冷严酷的梦醒，连同它所有的惩罚。莫尔正是这样，他和他的记忆搏斗了一阵子，然后伤心地摇摇头，追随水鼠兰特而去。

小胖醒来了，吱吱地欢叫了一声，一看见父亲的两个朋友，又开心地扭了扭身子──要知道，过去他们经常逗他玩的。可是只一会儿，他就神色茫然，哀哀地啼号着，转圈寻找起来──就像一个孩子在保姆的怀抱里幸福地睡着了，醒来后发现自己孤孤单单躺在一个陌生的地方，搜遍了所有角落和橱柜，跑遍了一个个房间，无言中，心底里越来越绝望。就这样，小胖顽强地、不知疲倦地在岛上找来找去，直到最后完全没有希望的时候才放弃，坐在地上痛哭起来。

鼹鼠莫尔迅速跑过去安慰那小动物，可兰特却徘徊不去，久久地、满腹狐疑地看着草地上几个深深的蹄印。

“有一个……伟大的……动物……来过这里。”他若有所思、慢条斯理地嘀咕道，站在那里冥思苦想，苦想冥思，脑子里着很奇怪地翻腾着。

“快过来，兰特！”鼹鼠莫尔喊道，“想想可怜的奥特吧，他还在浅滩那里守着呐！”

小胖很快就被安抚好了，他们答应他一件乐事──乘坐兰特先生的真船在河上游览。两只动物领着他来到河边，把他妥善地安置在船底，夹在他俩中间，沿回水河汊往外划。现在太阳已经全部升上了地平线，照得他们暖洋洋的。小鸟无拘无束、精力充沛地歌唱着，花在两岸微笑着频频点头。可不知为什么，在两只动物心里，似乎就是刚才，在某一个地方，他们见到的花儿的色彩更加丰富，更加艳丽──在哪里呢？

又来到了主河道。他们掉转船头，逆流而上，向他们的朋友独自守夜的地点划去。离那熟悉的浅滩不远时，鼹鼠莫尔把船划到了岸边。他俩把小胖拎出船外，让他站在纤路上，命令他向前开步走，并亲切地拍了拍他的背道别，然后用桨一撑，把船驶到中流。他们看着那小动物摇摇摆摆、志得意满、煞有介事地沿着纤路往前走；他们一直看着小胖，直到看见他突然抬起鼻子，摇摆的步子一下子变成了笨拙的小跑。他加快了脚步，尖声哼唧着，扭动着身子，像是认出了什么。他们顺着大河向前望去，看见奥特神情紧张、身体僵硬，一跃而起，离开他一直默默地、耐心地蹲守着的浅滩，连蹦带跳从柳枝中间穿过，来到纤路上。他们听见他一路跑，一路又惊又喜地叫着。于是，鼹鼠莫尔重重地划了一桨，把船转过来，任凭满当当的河水载着他们重返下游──去哪里都行，他们的搜寻任务已经圆满完成了。

“奇怪，我觉得好累，兰特，”鼹鼠莫尔说，他疲惫地靠在桨上，任凭船在水上漂着，“也许你会说，我们整夜没睡，可这算什么呀。每年这时候，我们都是一礼拜有三四晚上不睡的。我说的不是这个，我觉得自己好像经历过一件惊心动魄的事，而且事情刚过去不久，可并没有发生过什么特别的事呀。”

“或许是一件惊人的、美丽辉煌的事，”水鼠兰特喃喃地说，闭着眼睛仰靠在船上，“我的感觉和你一模一样，莫尔。简直累得要命，可是身体并不累。真幸运，水流的方向帮着我们，送我们回家。太阳又晒到身上了，阳光透进人的骨头里，感觉真惬意！听，风在芦苇里吹曲呢！”

“像音乐──在很远的地方。”鼹鼠莫尔说，昏昏欲睡地点点头。

“我也正这样想呢，”水鼠兰特喃喃地说，懒洋洋像做梦，“舞曲──那种欢快的音乐，像流水一样没有停顿，但也是有歌词的，一会儿有一会儿没有，隔一会儿听到几句，然后又变成了舞曲，然后什么都没有了，只剩下芦苇在轻声细语地絮叨。”

“你耳朵比我好，”鼹鼠莫尔惋惜地说，“我听不见歌词。”

“让我试试，把歌词念给你听，”水鼠兰特仍然闭着眼睛，说道，“现在又变成有歌词的了，声音很轻，但很清楚──以免敬畏的感觉滞留不去……把快乐的嬉闹变成苦恼……在救助的时刻显我神力……事情过去就把它忘掉！现在轮到芦苇了──它们叹息着唱道：忘掉，忘掉。歌声渐渐消失，变成了沙沙沙、飒飒飒的声音。歌声又回来了──

“以免四肢撕裂被血染红……我松开设下的陷阱和捕机……松开它们时你们见我面容……因为你们一定会忘记！划近些，莫尔，离芦苇近些！很难听清楚，声音每分钟都在减弱。

“我是救助者和治疗者，我鼓励……潮湿林地里的小小流浪者……迷途者我寻回，受伤者我包扎……吩咐他们把这一切都忘记！近些，莫尔，再近些！不，没用了，歌声已经消失，变成了芦苇的低语。”

“可这些歌词是什么意思呢？”纳闷的莫尔问道。

“我不知道，”水鼠兰特简单地答道，“我听到什么，就传给你什么。啊！现在又来了，这一回又完整又清楚！终于，这一回，是实实在在的了，明白无误的了，朴素……热情……完美……”

“嗯，那我们就听听。”鼹鼠莫尔说，他已经耐心地等了好几分钟，被热烘烘的太阳晒得有些瞌睡了。

可是听不到回答。他望了一眼，明白了静默的原因。兰特脸上挂着非常幸福的笑容，仍然保留着倾听的神态，已经睡熟了。

[1]这里等于说莫尔面前的“朋友与救助者”就是潘神本人。潘神为古希腊神话里的山林之神和畜牧神，羊足人身，头上有角，手持芦笛。

[2]潘神在古希腊诸神中地位很低。

第八章　托德的冒险

托德发现自己被监禁在一间阴冷发臭的地牢里，知道一座暗无天日的中世纪堡垒已将他和外面的世界隔开。不久前，他还在那个阳光普照、石子儿大路平坦通达的世界里，快快活活、尽情玩乐，仿佛全英国的每一条路都已经被他买下来似的。现在，他四仰八叉扑倒在地上，流着酸楚的泪，沉溺在悲观绝望之中。“一切都完了，”他说，“至少，托德的毕生事业完了，这反正是一回事。英俊的公众人物托德，富有而殷勤好客的托德，自由自在、无忧无虑、温文有礼的托德！我怎能指望有一天被放出去哟。”他说：“我冒冒失失偷了那么漂亮的一辆汽车，又异想天开、骇人听闻地冒犯了一大帮肥肥胖胖的红脸膛警察，坐牢是我罪有应得！”说到这里，他哽咽住了。“一个动物愚蠢到我这份上，”他说，“只有在这地牢里受苦了，到最后，那些曾经以认识我为荣的人们，连托德这个名字都会想不起来！哦，英明的老班杰呀！”他说：“哦，聪明的兰特和明智的莫尔呀！你们的判断力多么优秀，对人和事多么有见地！哦，不幸的、被遗弃了的托德！”他就这样日夜哀叹着过了好几个礼拜，不吃饭也不吃餐间小点心──虽然那个阴沉沉的老古董狱卒知道托德腰包里满满的，屡屡表示付出点代价就可以从外面弄进来好吃的东西，甚至搞些奢侈品。

却说那狱卒有个女儿，她是个可爱的村姑，心地善良，平时帮父亲在牢里干些比较轻的活儿。她特别喜爱动物，养了一只金丝雀。厚厚的牢墙上有一根钉子，白天她将鸟笼子挂在上面，把睡午觉的犯人吵得烦透了；晚上，她就把它放在接见室的桌子上，用椅子罩布盖住。另外，她还养了几只花斑鼠和一只不停转圈的松鼠。那好心肠的姑娘很同情托德的不幸，有一天，她对父亲说：“父亲！看到那可怜的动物那么不开心，瘦了那么多，我真受不了！你让我来管他吧。我有多么喜爱动物你是知道的。我要让他吃东西，亲手喂他，让他坐起来，做各种各样的事。”

父亲回答说，她想怎么摆弄托德都行。他已经厌烦托德了，厌烦他老是这样生闷气、犯贱，厌烦他那副神态。于是，那一天，她去做善事了，她敲了敲托德的牢门。

“嗨，打起精神来，托德，”她一边走进去，一边用好话哄他，“坐起来，擦干眼泪，做一个明智的动物。试试看，吃点午饭吧。瞧，我给你带来了我自己做的饭菜，热乎乎刚从炉子上端下来的！”

那是卷心菜煎土豆，扣在两个盘子中间。一股子香气，飘满了窄小的牢房。痛苦的托德俯卧在地上，卷心菜的气味直钻他的鼻子，使他一时间觉得生活也许并不像他自己想象的那么单调乏味、令人绝望。但他仍然哀嚎着，蹬着腿，不接受人家的安慰。于是，聪明的姑娘就暂时退了出去。当然，热卷心菜的许多气味留了下来，那是不用说的。在抽泣的间隙，托德嗅着嗅着，有了反应，脑子里渐渐地有了一些新的、鼓舞人心的念头：他想到了骑士精神、诗歌和他尚未完成的功绩；他想到了广阔的草甸子，草甸子上吃草的牛，牛的皮毛被阳光和风梳理着；他想到了菜园子、香草圃、不断被蜜蜂围攻的暖融融的金鱼草；还想到了蛤蟆府餐桌上摆放杯盘时那令人欣慰的叮当声，客人们一个个拉近椅子就餐时椅子脚擦地的声音。狭小的牢房里空气呈现出玫瑰色，他开始想念朋友们，想着他们肯定能做点什么；他想到了律师，想着当时他们一定很乐意接他的案子，自己竟那么驴，没有请上几位；最后，他想到的是他本人非凡的聪明才智，想着只要动动自个儿那伟大的脑袋瓜子，就能干成许多大事情。于是，他的心病差不多医好了。

几小时后，姑娘回来了。她端着一个托盘，托盘里放着一杯热气腾腾的香茶，还有一碟堆得高高的黄油烤面包，热乎乎的，切得很厚，两面都烤成了焦黄；黄油从面包孔里淌出来，滴成一粒粒金色的大珠子，像蜂巢里淌出来的蜜。黄油烤面包的气味简直是在对托德说话，并且声音毫不含糊。它讲述着温暖厨房；讲述着一个个明朗的结霜的清晨、一顿顿早餐；讲述着冬日黄昏漫游归来，穿拖鞋的脚搁在壁炉挡板上时，客厅的炉边有多么舒适；讲述着心满意足的猫儿的咕噜声，昏昏欲睡的金丝雀的啁啾声。托德重新坐直身子，擦干眼泪，开始小口喝茶，大口嚼面包。不久他就无拘无束地开始谈起他自己、他住的房子、他在家里做的事、他是怎样的一个大人物、他的朋友们有多么重视他。

狱卒的女儿看出来，这个话题和香茶一样，对他确实有益，就鼓励他继续往下说。

“给我说说蛤蟆府吧，”她说，“它好像很美呢。”

“蛤蟆府，”癞蛤蟆托德骄傲地说，“是一所称心如意、样样齐全的绅士住宅，出类拔萃。它部分始建于十四世纪，但是配全了各种现代设施。最新式的卫生设备。五分钟就到教堂、邮局、高尔夫球场，适合……”

“上帝保佑你这动物，”姑娘说道，笑了起来，“我又不是想买下它。给我说一些实际情况吧。不过，你先等一下，我再去给你拿点茶和烤面包。”

她轻快地走出去，一会儿就又端着一盘食物回来了。托德埋头猛吃烤面包，他的精神状况完全恢复到了平时那样。他给她讲停船棚屋、鱼塘、年代很久的带围墙的菜园子；给她讲猪圈、马厩、鸽棚和鸡舍；给她讲乳品屋、洗衣房、瓷器柜和放衣物的大壁橱（她特别喜欢这个）；给她讲宴会厅，讲许多动物来聚餐，他托德是又得意又神气，大家唱歌、讲故事、一起胡闹，玩得好开心。然后，她又要他说说他的动物朋友们，他讲了他们怎样生活，怎样消磨时光。他们的一点一滴，她都非常感兴趣。当然，她并没有说自己喜爱动物是把他们当宠物，因为那会把托德得罪到家，这种见识她还是有的。她把托德的水壶灌满，又把他睡觉的稻草抖松，然后说了晚安。这时候的托德，差不多又成了从前那只乐观开朗、沾沾自喜的动物。他唱了一两支过去他常在晚宴派对上表演的那种小曲儿，然后蜷曲身子躺在稻草上，美美地睡了一夜，还做了些最开心的梦。

郁闷的日子在继续，在那以后，他们一起聊天很多次，聊得很投机。渐渐地，狱卒的女儿为托德感到很难过了。她觉得，因为一次在她看来不值得一提的冒犯，就将一只可怜的小动物关进监牢，真是可耻之极。自然啰，在自负的托德心目中，她那么关心他，是出于渐渐对他萌生的柔情，但他们之间社会地位悬殊，他不禁有些惋惜，因为她是个长得挺好看的小姑娘，而且明显很仰慕他。

一天早晨，姑娘心不在焉，答非所问。在托德看来，姑娘对他那些机智的言辞和闪烁着火花的评论没有给予适当的注意。

“托德，”她就说，“请听我说。我有个姑妈，是个洗衣妇。”

“得啦，得啦，”托德很有风度、很殷勤地说，“没关系的，别再想这个了。我有好几个姑妈，本来都该做洗衣妇的。”

“安静一分钟，托德，”姑娘说，“你话太多了，这是你最主要的毛病。我正在动脑筋，你打断我的思路了。刚才我说，我有个姑妈是洗衣妇，她给这城堡里的所有囚犯洗衣服──这种挣钱的活儿我们都留给自家人，这你明白的。她每个礼拜一早晨把要洗的衣服拿走，礼拜五傍晚把洗好的衣服送回来。今天是礼拜四。喏，我想到这样一个主意：你很有钱──至少你自己是经常这样对我说的──而她呢很穷。几个英镑对你来说算不了什么，可对她来说却不是个小事情。嗯，我想呀，如果适当地笼络笼络她──用你们动物的话说，给她一点好处──你们也许能做成一笔交易。她让你穿戴上她的衣服帽子什么的，你就可以冒充官家的洗衣妇，从城堡里面逃出去。你们俩在许多方面挺像──特别是身材。”

“我们俩不像，”癞蛤蟆托德气呼呼地说，“我的身材挺漂亮──就癞蛤蟆而言。”

“我姑妈也是，”姑娘答道，“就洗衣妇而言。随你的便吧。你这只可恶、骄傲、忘恩负义的动物，我干吗要为你难过呢，还想帮你！”

“是是是，好好好。真的非常感谢你，”癞蛤蟆托德连忙说道，“可是听我说！你不会真的要蛤蟆府的托德先生装扮成洗衣妇，满世界乱跑吧！”

“你可以继续在这里做你的癞蛤蟆，不用跑啊，”姑娘很生气地回敬道，“我看呀，你是想乘着四匹马拉的马车离开呢！”

正直的托德一向是乐意认错的。“你是个善良聪明的好女孩，”他说，“我确实是一只骄傲愚蠢的癞蛤蟆。请你费心介绍我认识你可敬的姑妈吧，我确信不疑，那位优秀的女士和我一定能达成双方都满意的协议。”

第二天傍晚，姑娘领着她姑妈来到了托德的牢房。这个礼拜洗好的衣服，她包在毛巾里，用别针别住，也带来了。这次会面，老太太事先有了心理准备。她看到托德故意很显眼地放在桌子上的那些金镑[1]后，事情差不多立刻就成了，没再费什么口舌。托德的现钱所得到的回报是一件印花棉布罩衫、一条围裙、一块披肩和一顶褪了色的黑女帽。老太太提出的唯一条件是，用东西塞住她的嘴，把她捆起来，丢在角落里。她解释说，尽管事情显得可疑，她还是希望凭着这种不是很令人信服的骗术，再加上她本人绘声绘色的故事编排，保住她的饭碗。

托德高兴地接受了这个建议。这能使他离开监狱时有点气派，不至于辱没他铤而走险的亡命徒的名声。他欣欣然帮着狱卒的女儿，尽量把她的姑妈弄成一副惨样，装成一个对局面没有控制能力的受害者。

“现在轮到你了，托德，”姑娘说，“脱掉你的外套和马甲吧，你这样子已经够胖的了。”

她一边笑得身子直颤，一边给他套上印花棉布罩衫，扣上扣子，给披肩弄出符合身份的褶子，把褪色女帽的带子系在他下巴下面。

“你简直就是她在镜子里的模样，”她咯咯地笑道，“只不过我敢肯定，你一辈子从来不曾有过一半这样的体面。好啦，再见吧，托德，祝你好运。顺着你进来时的路直走，如果有人对你胡说些什么，你可以照样回几句玩笑话，很可能有人会那样子的，男人嘛。不过，你要记住，你在世上孤身一人，是个弄不好会丢了名声的寡妇。”

托德揣着一颗打颤的心，尽可能平稳地迈着步子，小心翼翼地开始了一次看起来最轻率、最冒险的行动。但很快他就发现，一切都意想不到的顺畅如意。他心中暗喜。可是这公众亲和力还有造成这亲和力的性别，其实都属于另外一个人。想到这个，他觉得有一点点屈辱。在每一扇闩上的小门、每一道阴森的大门面前，洗衣妇的矮胖身材、棉布罩衫上人人熟悉的印花图样仿佛就是一张通行证。他甚至发现，在他犹豫不决，拿不准向哪边拐才对时，是下一道门的看守帮他摆脱了困境。他们急着要离开门口进去喝茶，唤他快些过去别磨蹭，别让他们在那里等上一整夜。主要的危险倒是在于他们跟他开玩笑，说俏皮话。当然啰，他得迅速地作出适当的反应。可这并不容易，因为托德是个自尊心很强的动物，而那些玩笑大多数（他认为）很低劣很不得体，那些俏皮话一点都没有幽默感。虽说费了好大的劲儿，无论如何，他总算压住了火气。他回敬的言语挺适合对方，跟他的假身份也比较相称，并且尽量没有逾越健康情趣的底线。

他拒绝了最后一间警卫室里的再三邀请，躲开了最后一名张开胳膊、佯装热情地恳求来个告别拥抱的看守，终于穿过了最后一个院子。好像经过了好几个钟头似的，但是终于听到咔嗒一响：最外面那道巨大的门上的小便门在他身后关上了。他充满渴望的前额感觉到了外面世界的新鲜空气，他知道，他自由了！

这大胆的行动轻易就成功了，弄得托德头脑发晕，只管快步向镇子里的灯光走去，丝毫不知道下一步该怎么办。他只明确一件事，那就是必须尽快离开这地方，他不得不扮演的那位女士在附近可是一个大家都认识的公众人物哟。

他正边走边动脑筋，不远处，镇子一侧的一些红绿灯引起了他的注意，火车头喷气的噗噗声和货车车厢转轨的哐啷声也传进了他的耳朵。“啊哈！”他心想，“有点小运气！此时此刻，全世界我最想要的东西就是火车站。而且，我不用穿过镇子就能到那里，不必再靠着机敏的应答来撑住这个丢脸的角色，虽然那样效果好得很，对一个人的自尊心却没有好处。”

于是，他径直走到火车站，查看了一下时刻表，发现半小时后会有一趟车，去的方向肯定和他的家差不离。“运气又不错！”托德说。他一下子来了精神，走到售票处买票。

他报了一个站名，那是他所知道的离他们村子最近的小站，蛤蟆府则是他们村子最主要的标志。然后，他机械地伸手到本该是马甲口袋的地方去掏钱。那件棉布罩衫，到目前为止，一直在高尚地支持着他，却被他忘恩负义忘在脑后的棉布罩衫，这时出来阻挠他了。它挫败了他的企图。他像在噩梦中一样，拼命和那件奇怪的东西搏斗。它仿佛抓着他的手不放，把他浑身肌肉的努力都化成了水，并且一直在嘲笑他。其他旅客在他身后排成一排，不耐烦地等着，这时就向他提出些有用或无用的建议、有道理或没道理的批评。最后──不知怎么──他永远也不曾弄明白是怎么回事──他突破了障碍，到达了目的地，摸到了所有马甲口袋永世常在的地方，却发现──不仅钱没有，装钱的口袋也没有，装口袋的马甲也没有！

让他恐怖的是，他想起来啦，外套和马甲都被他落在了牢房里，连同他的皮夹子、钱、钥匙、手表、火柴、铅笔盒──让生活有价值的一切，让多口袋动物、造物主的骄子区别于一口袋产品或没口袋产品的一切。[2]那些低等动物只会蹦蹦跳跳到处乱跑，他们是没有必要的配备来参加真正的竞争的。[3]

情急苦恼之下，他想出个铤而走险的招数来应对。他重新摆出往日那副优雅的派头──乡绅和名牌大学学监的混合派头──他说：“听着！我发现自己忘带钱包了。请把那张票给我吧，好吗？我明天就把钱送来。我是这一带的知名人士。”

售票员盯着他本人和他那顶褪了色的黑色女帽看了片刻，然后大笑起来。“假如过去你经常玩这套把戏，”他说，“那我倒真该认为你是这一带相当知名的人士了。得啦，请你离开窗口吧，夫人。你妨碍别的旅客了！”

一位老绅士已经在他的背上戳了好一会儿，这时猛地把他推开了。更糟的是，老绅士称呼他“我的好娘儿们”，这比那天晚上发生的任何事情都让托德生气。

碰了钉子，满怀的绝望，他沿着月台盲目地往前走去，泪水从鼻子两边直往下淌。他本来要乘坐的那一列火车就停靠在月台边。他心想，眼看着就要安全了，就要到家了，却因为缺少几个可恨的先令，因为靠工资过日子的办事员吹毛求疵不信任，就转眼成了空，这真叫人受不了。他们很快就会发现他逃跑了，派人来追捕，把他抓住，辱骂他，给他上镣铐，拖他回监狱，让他过面包加白水、稻草当铺盖的日子。他们会加派双倍的警卫，给他加倍的处罚。还有，唉，那姑娘会怎样挖苦他啊！怎么办呢？他的腿跑不快，很不幸，他的体型人家认得出来。挤进车厢座位下面藏着行不行呢？他曾经见到小学生用这个办法，那是因为关怀备至的父母提供的盘缠被他们挪到其他更好的用途上去了。他正琢磨着，却发现自己已经到了火车头跟前。那慈爱的司机，一个魁梧的大汉，一只手提着油罐，另一只手捏着一团废棉纱，正在给它上油、擦拭，深情地抚摸它。

“哈啰，大娘！”火车司机说，“遇到麻烦了？你好像不是很开心。”

“唉，先生！”托德一边说，一边又哭了起来，“我是个不幸的穷洗衣妇，把钱全弄丢了，买不起火车票，可今晚我一定得想办法回家，真不知道该怎么办。哎呀，哎呀！”

“确实挺糟糕的，”火车司机沉思着说，“丢了钱──回不了家──要我说，还有小家伙在等着你回去吧？”

“一大帮小家伙呐，”托德抽泣道，“他们要挨饿了──他们会玩火柴──打翻油灯，那些天真的小家伙！──他们会吵架，全都吵成一团。哎呀，哎呀！”

“嗯，我说个办法你看行不行，”善良的火车司机说，“你说，你是专门帮人家洗衣服的。很好，这就行啦。你看到了，我呢是个火车司机，没法否认，这是个脏得要命的工作。穿脏的衬衣一大堆，总是一大堆，我老婆都洗厌烦了。如果你回家后帮我洗几件衬衣，洗好让人送回来，我就让你搭乘我的火车头。这是违反公司条例的，不过，这地方比较偏远，管得不是特别紧。”

癞蛤蟆托德的苦恼变成了狂喜，他迫不及待地爬上火车头，进了驾驶室。当然，他这一辈子没洗过一件衬衣，就是想洗也不会洗，而且，无论如何他也不打算学。不过，他心想，我平安回到蛤蟆府后，又有了钱和装钱的口袋，就多送些钱给火车司机，够他请人洗好多好多衣服。那不一样吗，说不定还更好呐。

信号员挥动那面受人欢迎的小旗，火车司机鸣响汽笛欢快地作答，火车驶出了车站。车速渐渐加快，癞蛤蟆托德看到了铁轨两侧真实的田野、树木、树篱、母牛和马，[4]它们一一从身旁飞一般地闪过。他心想，现在火车每一分钟都在带着他向蛤蟆府靠近。他想到那些同情他的朋友，想到衣袋里叮当作响的钱，睡在上面舒舒服服的软床，还有各种好吃的东西。他想象着人们听他讲述自己的冒险经历和聪明过人时，纷纷表示赞赏和钦佩。他不由得跳上跳下，大喊大叫，东一句西一句地唱起歌来。火车司机惊讶得不得了，因为以前他隔一段时间也会碰上一个洗衣妇，但从来不曾碰到过一个像这样的洗衣妇。

火车行驶了好多好多英里，托德已经在考虑一旦回到家以后晚饭吃些什么。这时他注意到，火车司机脸上露出迷惑不解的神情，把脑袋探出驾驶室外，正在使劲儿听着什么声音。接着，托德又看见他爬上煤堆，目光越过火车头的车顶，盯着什么东西看。然后，他回到驾驶室，对托德说：“非常奇怪，我们是今晚这个方向的最后一趟列车，可是我敢起誓，我听到有另外一趟车跟在后面！”

托德立刻停下了他那套轻浮愚蠢的滑稽动作。他沉下脸来，蔫了，脊椎末端隐隐作痛。那感觉传到双腿，使他很想坐下来，竭力不去琢磨这里面的各种可能性。

当时，月光非常明亮，火车司机在煤堆上站稳了，能看见后面很远地方的铁轨。

一会儿他就嚷嚷起来了：“现在我看清楚啦！是一个火车头，在我们这条铁轨上，开过来啦，速度快得不得了！好像是在追我们！”

悲惨的托德趴在煤尘里，使劲儿想主意。真沮丧喏，就是想不出来。

“他们很快就会撵上我们了！”火车司机嚷道，“火车头里全是人，那样一群人挤在一起，不能再古怪了！有的像老古董看守，挥着戟，戴头盔的警察挥着警棍，还有些衣衫破烂戴圆顶高帽的人，虽然离这么远，我也不会看错，明显是便衣侦探，挥着左轮手枪和手杖。他们全都挥着家伙，全都在喊同一句话：‘停车！停车！停车！’”

这时托德双膝跪倒在煤上，双爪握着拳头举起来，大声哀求道：“救救我，只求你救救我，亲爱的仁慈的火车司机先生，我向你坦白一切！我不是你所看到的朴实的洗衣妇！没有孩子在等我，天真不天真的都没有！我是一只癞蛤蟆──著名的公众人物托德先生，拥有大量土地的业主。我凭着极大的勇气和了不起的聪明才智，刚从一座可憎的地牢里逃出来。是我的冤家对头把我投进监牢的。如果后面火车头上那些家伙把我抓回去，那么可怜的、不幸的、无辜的托德就会被重新戴上镣铐，过面包加白水、稻草当铺盖的日子，再次陷入悲惨的境地！”

火车司机非常严厉地俯视着他，说道：“还是说实话吧，你犯了什么事关进去的？”

“不是什么大不了的事，”可怜的托德脸涨得通红，说道，“只是趁车主吃午饭的时候借了一辆汽车，当时他们用不着车子。其实，我不是故意要偷车，可是他们──特别是法官们──把无心的过失和一时的冲动看得太严重了。”

火车司机神情严肃，他说：“恐怕你确实是一只坏癞蛤蟆呢，按理我该把你交出去，交给被你冒犯的法庭。但你显然是在危难关头，我不会见死不救的。我受不了汽车，这是其一；我在自己的火车头上时，受不了警察的颐指气使，这是其二。而且一看到动物流泪，我总是感到不舒服，心肠就软下来。所以啊，打起精神来吧，托德！我会尽力而为，也许，我们还是能打败他们的！”

他们操起铲子，发狂似的添煤；炉子怒吼着，火花四溅；火车头上下跳动，左右摇晃。可追捕者们还是慢慢地赶上来了。火车司机叹了口气，用一团废棉纱擦了擦前额，说道：“恐怕这不管用，托德。你看见了，他们跑得很轻松，他们的引擎比我们的好。我们只剩下一个办法了，这是你唯一的机会，所以，下面我说的话你要仔细听好喽。我们前面不远，有一条很长的隧道。在隧道另一头，铁轨从一片密林中穿过。喏，过隧道时我会开足马力全速前进，但后面那些家伙会稍微慢下来一点，自然是因为怕出事故。过隧道之后，我会关掉蒸汽，使出最大的力气按下刹车。一到可以安全跳车的时刻，你就得立马跳下去，趁着他们还在隧道里，看不见你，在林子里藏好。然后我会重新全速前进，他们想追的话就追我好啦，想追多久追多久，想追多远追多远。现在注意了，做好准备，我叫你跳你就跳！”

他们继续添煤，火车射进隧道，火车头怒吼着嘎嘎地响着直往前冲，从隧道另一头射出来，驶进了清新的空气和宁静的月光之中。只见那座林子黑魆魆的，很帮忙地躺在铁轨两侧。司机关掉蒸汽，按下了刹车。癞蛤蟆托德走到阶梯踏板上，当车速减慢到几乎像步行速度一样时，他听见司机大喊一声：“现在，跳！”

托德跳下去，顺势沿着路基向前滚了一小段，拍拍屁股爬起来，没受伤，就飞快地爬进林子，藏了起来。

他向外面窥望，看见他搭乘的火车又加快速度，在远处消失了。然后，追他的火车从隧道里猛冲出来，吼叫着，鸣着汽笛。车上那一帮杂七杂八的人挥舞着各式武器，喊叫着：“停车！停车！停车！”他们过去后，癞蛤蟆托德从心底里笑了出来──自从他被投进监狱以后，他第一回笑得这样舒心。

但很快他就笑不出来了。他意识到，夜已很深，又黑又冷，这是一片陌生的林子，他没钱，也没地方找晚饭吃，朋友和家都还离得很远。火车的吼叫声和嘎嘎声过去之后，一切都归于死一般的寂静，让人不寒而栗。他不敢离开树林的掩蔽，只想着尽量远离铁路，所以一个劲儿地往林子里面钻。

在高墙里面待了好多个礼拜之后，他觉得树林很陌生、很不友好，好像有意要耍弄他似的。欧夜鹰发着呆板的嘎嘎声，使他觉得林子里到处是搜索他的看守，正向他包围过来。一只猫头鹰悄无声息地向他俯冲下来，翅膀擦到了他的肩头，吓得他跳起来，心里面怕怕地满以为那是一只手。然后，那猫头鹰像蛾子一样轻快地飞掠而去，“嗬！嗬！嗬！”地发着粗俗的笑声，让托德觉得趣味非常低级。有一回他遇到一只狐狸，那家伙停下来，摆出一副挖苦人的架势，上下打量着他，说道：“哈啰，洗衣妇！这礼拜少了一只袜子和一个枕套！注意，别再出这种事！”说完就窃笑着，大摇大摆地走开了。托德四处看，想找块石头扔他，可就是一块也找不到，把他恼得不能再恼。他又冷又饿，筋疲力尽，最后找了棵中空的树作为栖身处，用树枝和枯叶，尽可能为自己铺了一张比较舒服的床，呼呼一觉，睡到天亮。

[1]英国旧时金币，面值一英镑。

[2]基督教认为天地万物都是上帝──造物主创造的，所以作者用了“产品”这个词。作者在这里寓以丰富的戏谑成分。其一，对癞蛤蟆托德自视高人一等的戏谑；其二，对人类自视高于其他动物的戏谑：以口袋之有无或多少作为标准来区分高等动物和低等动物，借以戏谑人类区分动物等级之高低的标准，并调侃人类社会的等级标准。另外，“一口袋产品”指的是袋鼠？──也许。

[3]“真正的竞争”，这里指的应该是生存竞争──对生存竞争理论的戏谑。

[4]这里“真实”二字呼应托德在监狱里的情景，那时他只能向往这一切。

第九章　旅行者种种

水鼠兰特烦躁不安，也不知道因为什么。从表面上看，夏季仍然处在全盛期的顶峰。尽管耕地上碧绿已经让位给金黄，尽管花楸浆果正在变红，树林已经零零星星夹杂着烈焰般的黄褐色，但是，光、热和色彩所呈现的度依然不减，并没有季节将更迭、天气要转寒的征兆。不过呢，果园里、树篱间，不停歇的合唱已经冷静下来，成了几个依然不知疲倦的演唱者时有时无的晚祷歌声。知更鸟又开始亮相，空气中有了一种变迁和分离的氛围。当然，布谷鸟已经沉默很久，而许多别的长羽毛的朋友，几个月来一直是这幅熟悉的乡村风景画的一部分，一直是它的小小社交圈子的成员，也渐渐地不露面了。看来，各个队列好像都在每天不断地变稀疏。兰特一直关注着飞禽队列的动向，这时看出它们一天天有了南迁的趋势。甚至黑夜里躺在床上时，他也觉得自己辨认得出，那些急不可耐的翅尖的拍击声和震颤声正从头顶上的夜空掠过，响应那不容违逆的召唤。

大自然的大饭店跟别的大饭店一样，有旺季也有淡季。随着客人们一个个收拾行李、付账、离去，客饭餐厅里每开一次饭，席位就可怜兮兮地缩掉一圈。随着套房一间间被关掉，地毯一块块被卷起，侍者一个个被辞退，那些留下来不走，等待明年重新全面开业的搭伙人和寄宿者，看着大家走的走、散的散，听着别人热切地讨论计划、路线和新居，只见到伙伴们一天天减少，情绪不免受到感染。这时人就会惴惴不安、抑郁消沉、爱发牢骚。干吗要这样急着换地方呢？干吗不安安静静待在这里，像我们一样，快快活活地过日子？你不了解这大饭店淡季里的情形，不知道我们这些留下来的，把一年四季的风光看个遍，自有多少乐趣。毫无疑问，对方总是这样来回答：你说的全是事实，我们很羡慕你，也许改年我们会留下来，但这一回我们约好了，巴士已经到门口，我们到时间了！于是，他们笑一笑，点点头，就出发了。留下来的人对他们是既想念，又怨恨。水鼠兰特属于那种自给自足的动物，扎根在这块土地上，无论谁走，他反正不走。可他还是不由得注意到了气氛的变化，从骨头里感受到了那气氛的影响。

这种迁徙在持续，很难安下心来认认真真做点事。水位低了，水流缓了，水边的灯芯草已经长得又高又密。兰特离开河岸，漫无目的地向乡间走去。他穿过一两片已经被太阳烤干、弥漫着尘土的牧场，一头钻进了麦田。这是一片波浪起伏、沙沙作响的黄色海洋，处处轻柔地运动着、细声地低语着。他经常在这里游逛，在粗壮挺拔的麦秆丛林里穿行。它们在他头顶上支撑起自己的一片金色天空，一片永远在舞蹈、光彩熠熠、细雨绵绵的天空。有时被过路的风刮歪了，但一个打挺、一阵欢快的笑声过后，这天空又恢复了原样。在这里，他还有许多小朋友，那是一个自成一统的社会，过着充实忙碌的生活，但总是有片刻闲暇同来访的客人说几句闲话，交换一点消息。不过今天，尽管田鼠和巢鼠客气得很，却好像一门心思扎在自己的事情上。许多鼠儿在忙着打洞挖地道，另外一些鼠儿一小群一小群地聚在一起，核查小套房的计划书和图纸。要规划得合意、紧凑，还要选便利的位置，靠近大商店。有些鼠儿正在把积满灰尘的衣箱衣篓拖出来，还有些鼠儿已经在埋头打包自己的财物。遍地都是一堆堆一捆捆的小麦、燕麦、大麦、山毛榉坚果和其他各种干果，乱七八糟地放着，等待运走。

“这不是老水鼠仔嘛！”他们一见到他就喊道，“过来搭把手，兰特，别在那里闲站着！”

“你们在搞什么鬼呀？”水鼠兰特凶巴巴地说，“你们也知道的吧，眼下还没到考虑过冬住处的时候，早着呐！”

“是啊，我们知道，”一只田鼠有几分羞怯地解释道，“可提前准备总是好的，是不？我们真的必须得赶在那些可怕的机器来田里到处咔哒咔哒之前，把所有家具、行李和存粮从这里搬走。而且你知道的呀，如今这世道，最好的套房很快就会被挑完的。如果去晚了，就只好随便找个地方住下了。而且新套房还得先好好装修一下，搬进去住才合适。当然啦，现在是早了点，这我们知道，不过，也只是先开始干起来而已。”

“干什么干啊，麻烦，”水鼠兰特说，“今天天气好极了。还不如出去玩玩船啊，到树篱边逛逛啊，或者到树林里搞个野餐什么的。”

“嗯，我看，今天就不去了吧，谢谢你，”田鼠急忙答道，“也许改天能行──等我们稍微有空的时候……”

水鼠兰特轻蔑地从鼻子里哼了一声，转过身去要走，却被一个帽盒绊了一下，摔倒了，嘴里跑出几个有失尊严的词来。

“一个人如果小心些，”一只田鼠有几分尖刻地说道，“走路时看着点，就不会伤着自己──不会失态了。小心那只手提箱，兰特！你最好找个地方坐下来。过一两个小时，我们也许会稍微有空来陪你了。”

“我料想得到，你所谓的‘有空’，圣诞节前是不太会有的。”水鼠兰怒气冲冲地回敬道，择路走出了麦田。

他有些沮丧地回到河边──他忠实安稳的老河，决不会打包迁徙，去过冬的住所。

他窥见一只燕子栖息在流苏一样垂挂在河岸边的柳枝中间。不一会儿就又来了一只，随后第三只也加入进来。燕子们在大树枝上坐立不安，动个不停，认真地低声交谈着。

“怎么，已经要走了？”水鼠兰特溜达到他们跟前，说道，“着什么急呀？要我说，简直就是荒唐可笑。”

“哦，如果你指的是要离开，还没呢，”第一只燕子答道，“我们只是计划计划，把事情安排安排。你知道的呀，好好商量商量今年走哪条路线，在哪里歇脚，等等。说说也开心的嘛！”

“开心？”水鼠兰特说，“我就是不明白这有什么好开心的。如果你们不得不离开这可爱的地方，离开会想念你们的朋友，离开你们刚住进去不久的温暖的家，唉，一旦时候到了，我一点也不怀疑，你们会勇敢地离开，去面对一切的麻烦和困苦，适应新的环境和生活的改变，而且还会假装自己并不是很不快乐。可是，在真正需要离开之前，就很想谈论，哪怕想一想，这就……”

“不，你自然不理解喽，”第二只燕子说，“首先，我们心里面为这事感到激动，那可是一种甜蜜的不安哟。然后，记忆仿佛归巢的鸽子，一个个接踵而来。晚上它们拍着翅膀穿过我们的梦境，白天它们伴随我们在天上盘旋。当遗忘已久的那些地方的气味、声音和名字，一个个渐渐回来向我们示意时，我们就非常渴望互相询问，对比各种信息，好让自己确信那一切都是真真实实的。”

“今年能不能不走，就停一年也不行吗？”水鼠兰特眼巴巴地提议道，“我们大家会尽力让你们感到舒适自在。你们不知道，当你们在远方的时候，我们在这里日子过得有多美。”

“有一年我试着‘停’过，”第三只燕子说，“那时我太喜欢这地方了，该走的时候就犹豫了，没跟别的燕子一块儿走。开始几个礼拜还挺不错，可是到后来，哦哟哟，夜太长、太烦人了！白天不见阳光，直打哆嗦！空气又冷又湿，一亩地都找不到一只虫子！不，这可没什么好的。我的勇气全泄光了。一个暴风雪的寒夜里，我拍拍翅膀起飞了，借着强劲的东风，顺利地飞向内地。过大山口时，雪下得很大，我顽强地拼了一场才飞过去。当我向着下方，向着那么蓝、那么宁静的湖泊快速下滑时，热烘烘的阳光又晒在了背上。那种幸福至极的感觉，还有吃到第一口肥肥的虫子的滋味，我永远都忘不了！过去就像一场噩梦，未来全都是快乐的假日。一个礼拜接一个礼拜，我不断向南飞，轻轻松松、慢慢悠悠地飞，敢停留多久就停留多久，但始终听从着召唤！不，我受过告诫了，再也不敢动违抗的心思了。”

“是啊，南方的召唤，南方的召唤！”另外两只燕子像在梦中一样地呢喃着，“南方的色彩，南方的歌，南方的天空灿烂明媚！哦，你还记得吗……”他们不知不觉沉湎到温情的回忆里，把水鼠兰特忘到了脑后。他在一旁听得入了迷，一颗心跟着燃烧起来。他知道，自己那根一直蛰伏着、潜藏着的心弦，也终于开始震颤了。这几只准备南徙的小鸟的交谈，他们的苍白的间接描述，就已经有足够的力量唤醒这狂野的新感觉，让他浑身激灵灵、颤栗不已。一旦身临其境──让真实的南方阳光温情地触一触，让真真的南方香风拂一拂，那又该怎样的心潮澎湃呢？他闭上眼睛，鼓起勇气放任自己做了一会儿梦。等他睁开眼睛再看时，大河竟仿佛成了钢灰色，透着寒意，绿色的田野也仿佛灰蒙蒙没有了光泽。这时他那颗忠诚的心，仿佛在大叫大喊，责备他那个软弱自我的背叛变节。

“那你们干吗还每一次都回来呢？”他嫉妒地问燕子们，“我们这乡下小地方，又穷又土又乏味，有什么吸引你们的地方？”

第一只燕子说：“你认为，到了当令的季节，我们不会感觉到另一种召唤吗？葱翠的草甸子、湿润的果园、有许多虫子的温暖的池塘、吃草的牛、翻晒的干草、簇拥在屋檐完美之屋[1]周围的所有农家房屋，不会召唤我们吗？”

第二只燕子说：“你以为，生灵中只有你才如饥似渴，盼望再一次听到布谷鸟的歌声吗？”

第三只燕子说：“到了当令的时候，我们又会得思乡病，想念在英国河流的水面上摇曳的幽静睡莲。可是今天，那一切好像都显得苍白、稀薄、遥远。此时此刻，我们的血液在跟着另一种音乐跳舞呢。”

他们又只顾着自己呢呢喃喃地聊了，这一回他们喋喋不休的醉人话题是紫罗兰色的大海、黄褐色的沙滩和有很多蜥蜴的堤坝。

水鼠兰特又烦躁不安起来，漫无目的地走开了。他爬到大河北岸平缓的斜坡上，躺下来，向南边望去。丘陵地在四周远远地围成一个巨大的圆环，把更远的地方挡在了他的视野之外──今日之前，它一直就是他的地平线，他的月球山脉[2]，他的世界尽头，再过去，就没有什么他想看、想知道的了。可是今天，他凝望着南方，心中澎湃起了一种新的需求。他觉得那绵亘着的低矮轮廓的上方，澄澈的天空中仿佛颤动着应许之光。可是今天，没见过的世界成了他的一切，未知的天地成了他生活中的唯一真实。今天，小土丘的这一边成了真正的空白，而另一边却是一幅熙熙攘攘、色彩缤纷的全景图──他内心的眼睛看得清清楚楚：多美啊，碧色的大海，跳跃的浪花，涌起的波峰！多美啊，沐浴着阳光的海岸，白色的海边别墅在橄榄林的映衬下熠熠闪光！多美啊，寂静的港湾里挤满了华丽的船舶，正准备驶向盛产美酒和香料的紫色岛屿，低低地横陈在懒洋洋的海面上的岛屿！

他站起身，重新往下朝水边走去。然后他又改变主意，转向尘土飞扬的林荫小路的路边。小路一侧是低于路面的树篱，乱蓬蓬的，茂密而阴凉。他躺下来，半截身子埋在里边。这样他可以眼睛看着碎石铺面的小路，心里想着它通往的奇妙世界，脑子里想象着可能路过的种种旅行者，还有他们去追寻或不寻自来的好运和奇遇──在外面，在那一边，在远方！

耳朵里传来了脚步声，一个有些疲惫的行路人的身影进入了视野。他看出来，那是一只老鼠，一只风尘仆仆的老鼠。那旅行者走到近前时，很有礼貌地用带着外国味的姿势向他致意，犹豫了片刻，然后带着愉快的笑容，从小路上下来，走进阴凉的草丛中，在他身旁坐下。他好像很累，水鼠兰特听任他休息，没问他什么。兰特明白他脑子里想着些什么，也明白这样一条生活准则：动物们有时只是无言地做伴，放松一下肌肉，让脑子偷个懒。

旅行者很瘦，尖脸，肩背有些驼。他的爪子又细又长，眼角有许多皱纹，戴着一对小小的金耳环，耳朵长得齐整纤巧。他身上的蓝色针织套头毛衣褪了色，蓝底色的裤子上沾了不少泥，屁股上打了补丁。他随身携带的一点点财物，包裹在一块蓝棉布手绢里。

陌生人歇了一会儿之后，叹息一声，嗅了嗅空气，看了看四周。

“风送来的温暖气息，是苜蓿的气味，”他评论道，“我们听到的声音，是母牛在后面吃草，吃几口草，轻轻地喷一口气。远处有收割庄稼的声音，背靠林地的村舍那边升起一缕蓝色的炊烟。大河就在附近流淌，因为我听见了黑水鸡的叫声，而且从你的体型，我看出来，你是个淡水水手。似乎一切都睡着了，但又一直在运行着。你过的是一种上等的日子，朋友。只要足够强壮，肯定能过上天底下最好的日子！”

“是啊，这就是生活，唯一活得值的生活。”水鼠兰特做梦似的回应道，不像平时那么信心十足。

“我说的不完全是那个意思，”陌生人谨慎地说，“但肯定是最好的。我曾经那样生活过，所以我了解。正因为我刚那样生活过──六个月──所以知道是最好的。我走到这里，腿酸了，肚子饿了。我正在远离它，听从古老的召唤，徒步向南走，回到过去的生活中去。属于我的那种生活，我离不开的那种生活。”

“难道，这位又是他们中的一个？”水鼠兰特沉思着。“你刚从哪里来？”他问。他几乎不敢问他准备到哪里去，因为答案他似乎心知肚明。

“一个挺好的小农场，”旅行者简短地答道，“那个方向，”他冲着北边歪歪脑袋，“在什么位置并不重要。在那里我什么都不缺，生活中我有权期望的一切都有，还不止呢。可我到了这里！不过，来这里我同样也很高兴，很高兴来这里！又走完了许多英里的路，离我心中的愿望又近了许多！”

他紧盯着地平线，眼睛里闪着光。他仿佛在倾听某种声音，英国内陆地区虽然充满了欢快的牧场歌声和农家歌声，却缺少那种声音。

“你不是我们中间的一分子，”水鼠兰特说，“连农场主都不是。我敢断定，你甚至不属于这个国家。”

“对，”陌生人答道，“我是一只航海鼠，是啊，我最初起航的港口是君士坦丁堡，不过，在那里，我同样可以说是一个外国人。你一定听说过君士坦丁堡吧，朋友？一个美丽的城市，也是一个古老而光荣的城市。你也许还听说过挪威国王西格德吧，他曾率领六十艘船航海到君士坦丁堡。当他的随从从大街上骑马经过时，沿街都撑着紫色和金色的天篷表示敬意。皇帝和皇后驾临他的船，同他一起饮宴。西格德回国时，他手下的北欧人有许多留下来，加入了皇帝的御林军。我的祖先，一只在挪威出生的老鼠，也随着西格德赠送给皇帝的船留了下来。从那以后，我们家族的人一直做航海家，这就不足为怪了。对我来说，我出生的城市是我的家，但它和伦敦河之间的每一个令人愉快的港口也同样是我的家。我全都熟悉，它们也熟悉我。随便在哪个码头或海滩上把我放下，我都等于回到了家。”

“我猜你常去远洋航行吧，”水鼠兴趣越来越浓，说道，“成年累月看不到陆地，给养短缺，淡水限量供应，心总是同浩瀚的海洋相通，诸如此类？”

“根本不是，”海鼠坦白地说，“你描述的那种生活根本不适合我。我干的是海岸营生，难得看不到陆地。吸引我的是海岸上的快乐时光，那可不下于航海哟。哦，那些南方海港！海港的气息、夜晚的锚泊灯，真令人悠然神往！”

“嗯，也许你选择这种方式更好，”水鼠嘴上这样说，心里面却有些怀疑，“你要是愿意，就给我讲讲海岸上的事吧。说一说，一个有志气的动物可以指望从那里带回什么样的收获，将来有一天在炉火旁，可以用不平凡的回忆来温暖最后的时光。至于我的生活，坦白地说，我如今感到有些狭獈、有些闭塞呢。”

“我最近一次出航以后，”海鼠开讲道，“最终在这个国家上了岸。我怀着很高的期望，想在内陆办个农场。这次航行将成为历次航行中的一个好例证，实际上，将成为我色彩缤纷的人生的缩影。像往常一样，此行也是家庭纠纷促成的。家里刮起了龙卷风，我就搭上一艘小商船，从君士坦丁堡起航，驶向希腊群岛和黎凡特[3]。在我们经过的著名海域，每一个浪头都跳荡着不死的记忆。[4]那是些金色的白昼、芳香的夜晚！船一直在进港、出港，到处都是老朋友。白天天气热，我们就睡在凉爽的神殿或者废弃的蓄水池里。日落后，我们饮宴、唱歌，头顶上那天鹅绒般的夜空镶着非凡的群星！从那里我们折向亚德里亚海，沿海岸航行。亚德里亚海海滨浸泡在琥珀色、玫瑰色和水蓝宝石色的大气中，我们把船停泊在陆地环抱的宽阔港湾里，在古老而高贵的城市中漫游。最后，在一个早晨，当太阳庄严地在我们身后升起时，我们沿着一条金色的航道驶进了威尼斯。啊，威尼斯真是一座美丽的城市，在那里，老鼠可以自在地闲逛，轻松地享乐！逛累了，晚上可以坐在大运河边沿，跟朋友们一起饮宴。空中乐声洋溢，头上繁星满天，锃亮的钢质船头光芒闪烁。那些小艇摇曳着，一只只紧挨在一起，你可以从上面走过去，从运河这一边直走到那一边！要说吃的，你喜欢鲜贝吗？嗳，嗳，还是暂时不要在这个话题上多耽搁吧。”

他沉默了一会儿。水鼠也一言不发，他入了迷，在梦中的运河上漂着，幻觉中听见一支歌像钟声一样，高亢地回荡在水汽蒙蒙、灰蒙蒙、浪涛叠卷的运河大堤之间。

“最后我们重新向南航行，”海鼠接着说道，“沿着意大利海岸一路南下，到巴勒摩才泊岸。我在那里下船，去海滨度过了一段很长的快乐时光。我从不跟随一条船太久，那样会思想狭隘，产生偏见。再说，西西里岛是我常去的快乐好地方之一。我认识那里的每一个人，他们的习俗也正适合我。我在岛上快快活活过了好多个礼拜，同内地的乡村朋友们待在一起。又待得不耐烦了，我就沾光搭上一条驶往撒丁岛和科西嘉岛的商船，很高兴再一次感觉到清新的海风迎面扑来，大海的浪花飞沫溅到脸上。”

“可是下面的……货舱，我想你们是这样叫它来着，那里面是不是又热又闷？”水鼠问。

航海家正眼看着他，眨了一下眼睛表示怀疑。“我是个老手，”他很率直地说，“船长的舱房对我来说够好的啦。”

“根据各种流传的说法，海上生活很苦。”水鼠喃喃地说，陷入了沉思。

“对于水手来说是很苦。”航海家严肃地说，又隐约眨了一下眼睛。

“在科西嘉，”他接着说道，“我搭上了一条运酒去欧洲大陆的船。傍晚，我们赶到阿拉西奥，把船泊好，将酒桶拖上甲板，用一根长绳子串起来，从船舷边扔下大海。然后水手们登上小艇，向岸边划去，一路唱着歌，后面拖着一长串颠簸着的酒桶，像一英里长的一队海豚。沙滩上有马匹在等着。马拉着酒桶，在小镇里，沿着陡峭的街道往上冲，叮叮咚咚好不热闹。最后一桶酒送到后，我们就走人，去给肚子里补充点东西，歇一歇。晚上，和朋友们一起坐坐，喝酒到深夜。第二天早晨，我跑到那个好大好大的橄榄林子里，换换空气，休息休息。我暂时同海岛打够了交道，在港口和船上待了够多时间，所以，我去农夫中间过了一段懒散的日子。我躺在那里看他们干活儿，或者伸开四肢躺在高高的山坡上，遥远的下方是蔚蓝的地中海。就这样，一程一程，有时步行，有时乘船，终于到了马赛，遇到些过去的同船水手，拜访了一些准备出洋的大船，又一次参加聚会饮宴。说到鲜贝了！嗨，我有时梦到鲜贝或马赛，会从梦中哭醒！”

“这话题提醒了我，”懂礼貌的水鼠说道，“你偶尔提起你饿了，我该早点说这话才是：你一定愿意歇个脚，同我一起吃顿中饭吧？我的洞就在附近。时间已经过了中午，非常欢迎你去随便吃点东西。”

“那我就打扰啦，你是个好心人，真够朋友，”海鼠说，“其实，我坐下时已经饿了，无意间提到鲜贝以后，胃里就一直一阵阵难受得厉害。不过，你可以把吃食拿到这里来吗？除非迫不得已，我是不太喜欢受拘束的。在这里无拘无束，我可以一边吃，一边再给你讲讲航海见闻，说说我的愉快生活──至少对我来说很愉快。而且从你专心致志的神态，我断定它给你的印象也是不错的。但如果我们进了屋，百分之九十九我一会儿就睡着。”

“这确实是个极好的建议。”水鼠说。他急匆匆地起身往回赶。到家后他取出午餐篮，往里面装了一份简单的饭菜。他记着陌生人的出身和喜好，特意往里面放了一条一码长的法式面包，一根大蒜在里面唱歌的香肠，一块躺倒了哭叫着的干胳，一个裹着稻草的长颈瓶──里面装着曾在遥远的南方山坡上闪耀并将之收集、贮藏起来的瓶装阳光。[5]他拿起东西，全速赶回海鼠身边。他们俩一起打开篮子，把里面的东西拿出来，摆放在路边草地上。水手对他的口味和判断力大加赞赏，让他高兴得满脸通红。

海鼠的饥饿感刚减缓了些，就马上接着讲他最近一次的航海经历。他引导着他的单纯的听众，在西班牙从一个港口到另一个港口，让他在里斯本、波尔图和波尔多上岸，把他引荐给康沃尔郡和德文郡那些令人愉快的海港，一路驶过来，沿英吉利海峡北上，来到最后一个码头前沿的海上，在那里碰上了长时间的逆风，被暴风雨驱赶，经受日晒雨淋，然后才上了岸。在那里，他领会到又一个春天的神奇暗示和预兆，燃起激情，长途跋涉，奔向内陆，渴望远离令人厌倦的海上颠簸，体验一段平静的农场生活。

水鼠着了魔，激动得浑身颤抖，一里格一里格[6]地跟随着冒险家，穿过暴风雨中的港湾和拥挤的停泊处，乘着奔涌的潮水越过港口的沙洲，驶进蜿蜒的、急湾处隐藏着繁华小镇的河流……最后，在沉闷的内陆农场长住下来。这时，水鼠遗憾地叹口气，从叙述中走了出来：农场里的事他一点都不想听。

这时，他们已经吃完饭，航海家恢复了精神，劲头更足了。他说话的声音响亮起来，眼睛里放着仿佛是从遥远的海中灯塔摄来的亮光。他给自己的玻璃杯里倒满了鲜红透亮的南方葡萄酒，向水鼠倾着身子，嘴里说着话，眼睛迫使水鼠同他对视着，控制住了水鼠的身心。他那双眼睛是灰绿色的，如同动荡的北方海洋，水面上泛着一串串变幻不定的白沫。玻璃杯里的酒灼灼地闪耀着红宝石的光，正仿佛南方的心脏，为了有勇气与它的脉搏合拍的人而跳动着。这两种光，变幻的灰光和安定的红光，主宰了水鼠，使他陷于动弹不得、痴痴迷迷、瘫软无力的状态。那些光芒以外的平静世界渐渐地远去，不复存在了。只听得见话语，奇妙的话语，在不断地向外涌流。不知道那纯粹是说话呢，还是有时渐渐地变成了唱歌──水手们起锚时唱的船歌，帆索在凄厉的东北风中响亮的嗡鸣，日落时分船夫背对杏黄色天空拉网时唱的小调，吉他和曼陀林在意大利凤尾船或者土耳其长划艇上的合奏？不知道那些话语是否变成了风的哭泣──起先只是哀怨的呜咽，渐渐地增强为含怒的尖叫，继而拉高成凄厉的呼啸，最后沉落下来，化作鼓起的风帆所滤出的空气的淅沥？所有这些声音，那着了魔的聆听者仿佛全都听到了──连同海鸥饥饿的悲诉、浪涛拍岸的轻柔轰响、海滩砂石抗议的呼声。它们又渐渐地变回到话语。聆听者揣着一颗怦怦直跳的心，相随着去十几个海港冒险──打仗、逃跑、重整旗鼓、相助同伴、仗义行侠；又去海岛寻宝，在平静的泻湖钓鱼，在温暖的白色沙滩上打瞌睡一整天。他听他讲深海捕鱼，用一英里长的网捞上来银光闪闪的一大网收获。他听他讲险情突至：无月的夜晚忽然间扑来喧腾的浪涛，大雾中头顶上蓦地冒出巨大邮轮的高耸的船艏。他听他讲返回故乡的快乐：船绕过海岬，驶进灯火通明的港口；码头上人影绰绰、欢呼声四起，锚链下浪花飞溅；归来者沿着陡峭的小街攀爬前行，走向透过红窗帘映射出来的温馨灯光。

最后，他在白日梦里依稀觉得冒险家站了起来，但仍然在说话，仍然在用那双海灰色的眼睛牢牢地控制着他。

“现在，”他轻轻地说着，“我要重新上路了，坚持不懈地向西南方走，风尘仆仆地走很多天，直走到那座灰色的海滨小镇为止。它紧贴在陡峭的港湾一侧，我对它太熟悉了。在那里，你从昏暗的门口向下俯望一段一段的石头台阶，看到巨大的粉红色缬草花簇悬垂着，石阶尽头是一汪波光粼粼的蓝色海水。古老海堤的铁环和木桩上拴着一只只小船，它们漆成鲜亮的颜色，跟我童年时爬进爬出的那些船一样。大潮时，鲑鱼在潮头跳跃，一群群的鲭鱼闪着光，从码头边海滩前嬉游而过。日日夜夜都有巨轮从窗前滑过，进港泊岸或者驶向辽阔的大海。所有航海国家的船早晚都会到达那里；在注定的时刻，我选中的船会在那里松开锚链。我会从从容容，逗留等待，直到最后那条为我而来的船，满载着货物，船艏斜桁俯指着港口，被绞船索拽入航道中央。那时我就乘着小船或顺着锚链，悄悄溜上船去。然后，在一天早晨，水手们的歌声和脚步声、起锚机的尖叫声、锚链收上来时欢快的嘎嘎声会把我叫醒。我们扯开船艏的三角小帆和前桅的大帆，船缓缓地转舵，海港一侧的白色房屋慢慢地从我们身边向后滑去，远航就开始了！她稳稳地驶向海岬时身上还披着帆布；一到外海，她就斜对着风，任凭碧色的海浪哗哗地拍打着，直指南方！”[7]

“你呢，你也会来的，小兄弟。因为时光流逝，一去不返，而南方依然在等待着你。听从召唤，在不可逆转的时间逝去之前，踏上冒险的旅途吧！只要门在你身后砰的一声关上，你向前跨出轻快的一步，就走出了旧生活，迈进了新的人生！将来有一天，很久后的一天，杯中酒干了，戏演完了，如果愿意，你可以慢慢地走回家，回到这里，在你的安静的河边坐下，拿出满满一大袋的上等回忆招待伙伴们。一路上你很容易赶上我，因为你年轻，我却上了年纪，腿脚软了。我会走走停停，回头看看，最后肯定能看见你赶上来，步子匆忙，心情轻松愉快，满脸的神情写的是‘南方’两个字！”

他的声音渐渐消失，就像一只昆虫的小喇叭声音很快变小，归于沉寂。水鼠兰特瘫在那里，瞪着眼睛，看见白色的路面上最后只剩下远方一个小黑点。

他机械地站起来，开始收拾午餐篮，仔仔细细，不慌不忙。他机械地回到家里，把几样小件必需品和特别珍爱的宝物归拢来，装进一只小背包里。他慢条斯理地干着，像梦游者一样在屋子里转悠着，始终半张着嘴倾听着。他把小背包甩到肩上，仔细挑了一根行路用的结实棍子，不慌不忙，但也毫不犹豫，一步跨过门槛，正遇上鼹鼠莫尔出现在门前。

“嗨，你要去哪里，鼠仔？”鼹鼠莫尔惊讶至极地问，一把抓住他的胳膊。

“去南方，同别的旅行者一起，”水鼠兰特喃喃地说，声音像说梦话一样的单调，眼睛根本不看着人，“先去海边，再乘船，到那些召唤着我的海岸去！”

他很坚决地往门外挤，仍然不慌不忙，却已经是横下了心。鼹鼠莫尔惊恐至极，用身体堵住他，察看着他的双眼，发现它们呆滞无神，变成了布满条纹、游移不定的灰色眼睛──不是他朋友的，而是别的动物的眼睛！他紧紧地抓着他，把他拽进去，推倒，摁住。

水鼠兰特拼命挣扎了一会儿，然后仿佛一下子就没了劲儿。他精疲力竭、一动不动地躺在地上，闭着眼睛，打着哆嗦。鼹鼠莫尔就扶他站起来，把他安置在椅子里。他瘫坐在里面，缩成一团，浑身剧烈地哆嗦着；一点一点，最后爆发出一阵歇斯底里的干嚎。莫尔把门关紧，将小背包扔进抽屉里锁好，然后静静地在朋友旁边的桌子上坐下，等待这阵奇怪的疯魔病过去。渐渐地，水鼠兰特昏昏沉沉地打起了盹儿。在不安的浅睡中，他惊醒了好几次，嘴巴里含含糊糊地咕哝着。在懵懂的莫尔听来，他说的都是些奇奇怪怪、疯疯傻傻的外国事情。然后，他进入了深深的睡眠。

鼹鼠莫尔心里很着急，走开去忙了一会儿家务事，回到客厅时天已经快黑了。他发现水鼠兰特仍然在原来的地方，实际上已经完全醒了，却无精打采、一言不发、垂头丧气。他匆匆瞄了一眼兰特的眼睛，发现它们又变成了原来的深棕色，清澈明亮。他感到无比满意，在兰特身边坐下来，试着帮助他打起精神，把前面发生的事情想起来、说出来。

可怜的鼠仔尽其所能，一点一点地解释着。可那些事情大多是联想，用冷静的语言怎能表达清楚呢？那曾经对他歌唱、至今萦绕在心头的大海之声，他怎样复述给另一个人听？航海家回忆的上百件往事的魔力，他怎样间接地重现？即使对他本人来说，现在也是魔咒已破，魅力已消失。他发现，几小时前似乎是不可避免要发生、且是唯一可能发生的事，现在想说清楚都已经很难。所以呀，他没能向鼹鼠莫尔说明白那一天的经历就没什么可奇怪的了。

对莫尔来说，至少这一点是明白的：那一场疯魔病大发作虽然使兰特受了惊吓，给他留下了沮丧的副作用，却已经过去了，兰特的神志也已经恢复正常。不过，一时间，他对日常生活中的所有事情全都没有了兴趣。而变化中的季节无疑正带来一天一个样的事务和活动，对此他也没有兴趣开开心心地预作安排了。

后来，在一个偶然的机会，鼹鼠莫尔装作漫不经心地转移了话题，说起正在收割的庄稼、堆得像小山的四轮马车、拉车的马、不断升高的干草垛、收割完毕的田地上空升起的好大一轮月亮，还有月光下星罗棋布的一捆捆庄稼。然后他说起周围苹果在变红，核桃栗子在变成褐色。再后来又说起做果酱，做蜜饯，做果子酒……就这样一步一步，从从容容地，最后说到了仲冬，说起仲冬时节的欢乐开怀和温暖舒适的室内生活。这时，他简直成了抒情诗人。

慢慢地，水鼠兰特开始坐起来，同莫尔一起谈论这些事。他呆滞的眼睛变亮了，脸上少了几分留神倾听着什么的神情。

乖巧的莫尔就悄悄地溜开，回来时拿了一支铅笔和几张半页的纸，放在桌子上朋友的胳膊肘旁边。

“你有好久没有做诗了，”他说，“今晚你就写一点试试，别再──嗯，老想那么多。我觉着呀，你写上几句，哪怕只是几个押韵的词，感觉就会好很多。”

水鼠兰特厌烦地把纸从身边推开，可细心的莫尔趁机离开了客厅。过了一会儿，他从门外向里面偷看，窥见水鼠兰特已经两耳不闻窗外事，一心只在做歪诗了。只见他一会儿草草地写几个字，一会儿吮着铅笔屁股。虽然他吮的时间比写的时间长很多，但是鼹鼠莫尔很高兴地了解到，他的病终于开始见好了。

[1]原文为the House of the perfect Eaves，这里指教堂──House of God。因为燕子在屋檐下做窝，最喜欢屋檐，作者想象“他们”以屋檐为标准来衡量房屋，所以教堂在“他们”口中成了“屋檐完美之屋”。

[2]在非洲国家乌干达境内，尼罗河的源头。

[3]黎凡特，自希腊至埃及的地中海东部各国及岛屿的统称。

[4]指古希腊传说中的故事。

[5]这里是从水鼠兰特的主观角度来描述食物和酒的，最后一样实际上就是下面提到的南方葡萄酒。作者在暗示：诗人气质的兰特已经被航海鼠的叙述弄得神魂颠倒，进入了半现实半幻梦的状态。

[6]长度单位，一里格约等于三英里，一英里等于1609米。

[7]西方人用第三人称来称呼船时，都用女性的“她”，这也许是因为他们对航行情有独钟。

第十章　托德的进一步冒险

那棵中空的树正门朝东，所以时间很早托德就被唤醒了。一是因为阳光泻了进来，照在他身上；二是因为脚指头冻得太厉害，害得他做了个怪梦。他梦见自己在家中，在一个寒冷的冬夜，在那间有都铎式窗户的漂亮卧室里，躺在床上。他的被子、床单、枕头、毯子全都从床上起来了，发牢骚，提抗议，说它们再也受不了这寒冷，就全跑到楼下厨房里，去火炉边取暖。他赤脚跟在后面，在铺着石头的冰冰冷的过道里走了好几英里，跟它们争论，恳求它们通情达理一点。如果他不是睡过几个礼拜石板地铺稻草，快忘了厚毯子捂到下巴的温馨感觉，他可能还会醒得更早些。

他坐起来，先揉揉眼睛，然后揉揉正在诉苦的脚指头。有一会儿他很纳闷自己究竟身在何处，竟四下里张望，寻找熟悉的石墙和加铁栅的小窗，然后他心儿一阵狂跳，把一切都记起来了──逃出监狱，一路逃亡，遭到追捕。他记起了最最重要、最最好的一件事，那就是，他自由了！

自由！这一个念头两个字，就值五十条毯子。想着外面的快活世界，他从头到脚都暖和起来了：它正像厄运降临前那些老日子里一样，热切地等待他凯旋；它时刻准备着投他所好、为他效劳；它已经急不可耐地要给他帮助、同他做伴。他抖一抖身子，用手指梳理掉头发里的枯叶。梳洗完毕，他迈步走到那令人舒畅的朝阳下──虽然冷，却信心十足；虽然饿，却充满希望。昨天的紧张恐惧，全都被休息和睡眠，被真诚而且令人振奋的阳光，驱散了。

在这夏日的初晨，整个世界都属于他自己。他穿过缀满露珠的树林，树林里静悄悄空无一人。他来到树林外的绿色田野，田野只属于他一个，任凭他随心所欲。他走上马路，马路像四周每一处一样，寂寞冷清，如一只迷路的狗，仿佛正焦急地要找一个伴儿。可托德呢，他要找一个会说话的活物，清楚地告诉他该去哪个方向。如果你心情轻松，良心清白，兜里有钱，没有人在乡间到处搜查你，要把你拖走，送回监狱，你可以不在乎去哪里，只管顺着马路往前走，那倒是不错。可面对现实的托德当然是非常在乎的，现在对他来说，每分钟都很重要。但是马路却无可救药地不说话，他真想踹它几脚。

矜持的马路不久就有了一个害羞的小兄弟与它同行，它的形状是一条水渠。它挽着马路的手，在旁边缓缓地前行着，对马路百分之百地信赖，但对陌生人同样是一种舌头打结、沉默寡言的态度。“讨厌！”托德自言自语道，“可至少有一点很清楚：它们俩一定有个来处，也一定有个去处。这一点你不能不放在心上。托德，好样的！”于是，他耐心地沿着水渠大步往前走去。

水渠转个弯，过来了一匹孤独的马。他低垂着脑袋，脚步沉重缓慢地向前走着，好像心事很重。系在马轭上的缰绳被加长过，成了一根很长的绳子，绷得紧紧的。但马每跨出去一步，绳子就在水里蘸一下，绳子后面的部分滴着珍珠般的水珠。托德把马让过去，站在那里等着，看命运会给他送来什么。

平静的水面被船头搅起了一个令人愉快的漩涡，一艘宽头平底驳船徐徐行驶着，从旁边赶了上来。这艘船的船舷跟纤绳平齐，漆得艳丽花哨，唯一的占用者是一个大块头女人，她戴一顶亚麻布阔边遮阳帽，一条健壮的胳膊搁在舵柄上。

“一个晴朗的早晨，太太！”船赶上来跟托德平齐时，她招呼道。

“要我说，没错，太太！”托德彬彬有礼地答道，沿着纤路和她并排往前走，“要我说，一个人，如果没像我这样遇上麻烦，那对他来说，这确实是一个晴朗的早晨。我那个出嫁的女儿，送了急信来，叫我立刻去看她，所以我出来了。也不知道出了什么事，或者将要出什么事，就担心出现最坏的情况。太太，如果你也是当妈的，一定会理解。我把自己的营生丢下不管了──我干的是洗洗熨熨这一行，你一定看出来了，太太──还有几个小的丢在家里，让他们自个儿照顾自个儿，世上没有比他们更调皮捣蛋的淘气鬼了，太太。我把所有的钱都弄丢了，又迷了路，至于我出嫁的女儿出了什么事，嗨，我都不愿意去想，太太！”

“你出嫁的女儿住在哪里，太太？”船娘问。

“她家靠近大河，太太，”托德答道，“离一座名叫蛤蟆府的漂亮宅子不远，就在这一带什么地方吧。也许你听说过。”

“蛤蟆府？嗨，我正是去那个方向呢，”船娘答道，“再过去几英里，这条水渠就同大河汇合了，蛤蟆府就在那地方下游不远，走过去很容易。到船上来吧，我捎你一段。”

她把驳船行到岸边，托德低声下气地说了许多感恩的话，轻轻巧巧地跨上船去，满意至极地坐了下来。“托德的运气又来啦！”他心想，“我总是最棒的！”

“这么说，你是干洗衣行当的，太太？”船徐徐地前行着，船娘客客气气地说道，“要我说，你这一行也挺不错，我这样说不是太放肆吧？”

“全国最好的行当，”托德信口开河道，“所有的上等人都找我洗衣服，别人家就是倒贴钱他们也不去，他们非常信任我。你瞧，我对工作是很精通的，全都亲自去处理。洗、熨、上浆，整理绅士们晚会上穿的讲究衬衫，每一项工作都在我亲自监督下完成！”

“那些工作肯定不会都要你亲自动手干吧？”船娘恭敬地问。

“哦，有姑娘们干，”托德轻飘飘地说，“常年干活儿的姑娘有二十来个。可你知道姑娘们是些什么东西，太太！邋遢的小贱妇，我是这样叫她们的！”

“我也是，”船娘衷心地表示赞同，“可是要我说，你那帮姑娘一定被你整得规规矩矩吧，那帮子懒骨头烂货！你非常喜欢洗衣服吗？”

“我爱洗，”托德说，“简直就是太爱了。把两条胳膊往洗衣盆里一泡，我就感到再快活不过了。还有，衣服到我手里，洗起来很轻松！一点也不麻烦！一种真正的乐趣，请相信我，太太！”

“遇见你真是有点运气！”船娘若有所思地评论道，“我们俩都算交上了一点好运！”

“哟，你这是什么意思？”托德问，有点紧张。

“嗯，听我说，喏，”船娘答道，“我像你一样，也喜欢洗衣服。要说呢，像我这样到处跑，不管喜欢不喜欢，活儿自然全得自己干。要说我丈夫，他可是个偷懒不干活儿的家伙，而且把驳船丢给了我，弄得我没有一点工夫料理自个儿的事情。按理，现在他应该在这里，要么掌掌舵，要么管管马，幸好马够懂事，能管好自己。可他不来，带着狗出去了，看看能不能在哪里逮个兔子当晚饭。说是说他会在下一道船闸那里赶上我。嗳，那可没个准儿──他一带着狗出去，我就信不过他了，那狗比他还坏。可这样一来，我拿那些脏衣服怎么办呢？”

“哦，别管洗衣服的事啦，”托德说，他不喜欢这话题，“试试一心只想着兔子吧。我敢肯定，准是一只肥美的嫩兔子。你这里有洋葱吗？”

“我一心只想着洗衣服，别的事都没心思去想。”船娘说，“真纳闷，这样一幅快乐景象摆在面前，你还有心思说兔子。你找找看，船舱角落里有我一堆脏衣服。你就挑个一两件最急等着洗的──对你这样一位太太，我不想冒昧直说，但你只消瞄一眼就认出来了──丢到洗衣盆里，一边行船，一边洗。嗯，这对你来说是一种乐趣，就像你刚才说的；对我来说呢，是实实在在的帮忙。你找找看，洗衣盆就在附近，还有肥皂。水壶在炉子上，还有一只桶给你从水渠里打水。那样子，我就能看到你很愉快、很享受，不用像现在这样无聊地坐着，看看风景，哈欠连天。”

“嘿，你还是让我来掌舵吧！”托德说，吓坏了，“那样你就可以用自己的方法洗自己的衣服。我会把你的东西洗坏的，我的洗法你不喜欢。我本人更习惯洗先生们的衣服。那是我的特长。”

“让你掌舵？”船娘大笑着答复道，“给驳船掌好舵是要有些经验的。再说，这工作枯燥乏味，而我是想让你开开心。不，你还是做你喜欢做的事，去洗衣服吧。掌舵我在行，这活儿我盯着。好好款待你是我的快乐，别剥夺它！”

托德被逼到了墙角。他左顾右盼，想找个方向逃跑，却发现离岸边太远，一个飞跃够不着，只好闷闷不乐地听凭命运安排了。“到了这一步，”他绝望地想，“我看傻瓜也有本事洗衣服的！”

他从船舱里拿来洗衣盆和别的洗衣用品，随意挑了几件衣服，回忆着偶尔从洗衣房的窗户里瞥见过的情形，动手干起来。

长长的半小时过去了，这期间每过去一分钟，托德的火气就大一分。似乎无论他怎么弄，都无法讨那些衣物的欢心，把它们弄好。他哄它们，拍它们，用拳头砸它们，它们却以嬉皮笑脸来回报他，在盆中快乐地坚持着它们的原罪，毫不悔改。[1]他紧张地扭过头去看了船娘一两次，但她两只眼睛似乎只盯着前方，专心致志地掌舵。他背酸得厉害，并且惊恐地注意到，自己的两只爪子泡得全起了皱。这双爪子一向是托德引以为自豪的。他悄声嘀咕了几句既不该从洗衣妇也不该从癞蛤蟆嘴里说出来的话，第五十次把肥皂滑落了。

一阵爆笑声使他绷直了身子。环顾四周，只见船娘在仰天放声大笑，笑得眼泪滚下了腮帮子。

“我一直留神看着你，”她喘着气说，“看你那副骄傲自大的样子，自始至终我都觉得你一定是个骗子。装什么熟练的洗衣妇！我敢打赌，这辈子你连一块擦盘子的抹布都没洗过！”

托德一肚子的怨愤早已经憋着炖了好一会儿，这时咕噜噜开了锅，完全失去了控制。

“你这个粗野、下贱的肥猪船娘！”他吼道，“竟敢这样对老子说话！洗衣妇个鬼！我要让你知道知道，我是一只癞蛤蟆，一只大名鼎鼎、受人尊敬、高贵显赫的癞蛤蟆！眼下也许我有点失势，可也轮不上一个船娘来嘲笑我！”

那女人凑近他，用锐利的目光仔细端详着女帽下他那张脸。“哟，果然是只癞蛤蟆！”她嚷道，“咳，真没想到！一只叫人恶心、浑身起鸡皮疙瘩的癞蛤蟆！居然在我的漂亮干净的驳船上！我可容不下这样一个烂玩意儿。”

她把舵柄丢开片刻，一条长斑点的大胳膊箭一样抄过来，抓住托德一条前腿，另一只手夹住了他一条后腿。于是，世界突然上下翻转，驳船仿佛轻盈地从天空掠过，风在耳边啸响，托德发现自己腾空飞起，一边飞，一边快速地旋转。

当他最后到达水中，很响亮地溅起一片水花时，水证明了自己够凉，很合他的口味。不过，那凉意仍然不足以平息他的骄傲气焰，浇灭他的狂暴怒火。他浮上水面，喷溅出一片水花。擦去眼睛上的浮萍后，他第一眼看到的是，肥胖的船娘正从远去的驳船的船尾回望着他，笑个不停。他一边咳着呛着，一边发誓，要向她报复。

他扑打着水向岸边游去，但是棉布罩衫很碍事。当他终于碰到岸沿时，却发现它太陡。没人扶一把，爬上去好难呀，他只好歇一两分钟，缓一口气。然后，他把湿裙子捞在手上，以他最快的速度，拔腿去追驳船。他已经愤怒得发了狂，一心只想着报仇雪恨。

当他追到和船并排时，船娘还在笑个不停。“把你自己丢进轧布机里轧一轧，洗衣妇，”她喊道，“熨一熨你的脸，压出些褶子，出来的就是一只十分体面的癞蛤蟆了！”

托德没有停下脚步答理她。虽然他肚子里有一两句很想回敬她的话，但他想要的是实实在在的报复，而不是廉价、空洞的口头上的胜利。他看到了前面想要的那样东西。他不停地飞跑着，赶上那匹马，解开纤绳扔掉，轻轻一跃，跨上马背，使劲儿一踢马肚子，催马飞奔。他策马离开纤路，驰入空旷的乡间，拨转马头，上了一条布满车辙的林荫小路。他回头望了一眼，看见驳船在靠近对岸的水面上搁了浅，打着转。船娘在疯狂地比划着，大喊：“停下，停下，停下！”“我以前听过人家这样唱歌。”托德大笑着说，继续策马向前狂奔。

给驳船拉纤的马是没有脚力持续猛跑很长时间的。不久速度就降下来了，疾驰变成小跑，小跑又变成了踱步。但托德仍然十分满意，因为他知道，无论如何，自己还是在行进着，驳船却已经动弹不了。既然他干出了一件在他看来实在聪明的事，他的心情就好多了。他努力忘掉自己已经很久没有正儿八经吃上一顿饭，勒着马走上偏僻小路和马道，心满意足地在太阳底下安安静静慢跑着，终于把水渠远远地甩在了后面。

他和马已经跑出去好几英里，在热烘烘的阳光里，昏昏欲睡。这时，马停住脚步，低下头去啃吃青草，托德因此惊醒过来，正好来得及做个自救的动作，没摔下马背。他看了看四周，发现自己停在一块公地上，目力所及之处全都点缀着一小片一小片的金雀花和黑莓。离他不远处停着一辆褪色泛黄的吉卜赛大篷车，车子旁边有一个人坐在倒扣的水桶上，正忙着抽烟、眺望广阔世界。那人近旁燃着一堆用枯枝生的火，火堆上方吊着一口铁锅，锅里响着啵啵啵咕咕咕的冒泡声，冒着勾引人的模模糊糊的蒸汽。还有许多气味──暖暖、浓浓的混杂气味──缠缠绕绕，交融在一起，最终合成了一种十全十美、闻了舒服无比的香味，仿佛大自然的灵魂显了形，让她的孩子们见到了一位真正的女神，一个带来安慰和舒适的母亲。托德现在明白了，他以前从来没有真正感到过饥饿。那一天他早先的感觉只不过是一种轻微的不舒服。现在，真正的饥饿终于来了，肯定没错，而且得赶紧对付它，否则就会给某人或某物带来麻烦。他上上下下、仔仔细细把吉卜赛人打量了一番，心里面含含糊糊，不知道跟对方动拳头容易呢，还是耍嘴皮子容易。于是，托德坐在马上，鼻子不断地嗅着，眼睛看着吉卜赛人。吉卜赛人坐在桶上，嘴里抽着烟，眼睛看着托德。

吉卜赛人把烟斗从嘴里拿开，做出一副漫不经心的样子，说道：“想卖掉你那匹马？”

托德完全没料到这个，吃了一惊。他不知道，吉卜赛人都很喜欢做马匹交易，从不错过一次机会。他不明白，大篷车是一直在走动的，需要马来拉。他从没想到把马变成现钱，不过，吉卜赛人的建议似乎铺平了一条道，通向他急需的两样东西──现钱和一顿丰盛的早餐。

“什么？”他说，“让我卖掉这匹年轻漂亮的马？哦，不。这件事免谈。卖了马，每个礼拜谁来驮我为顾客洗的衣服？再说，我忒喜欢他了，他也跟我亲得要命。”

“试试喜欢上一头驴，”吉卜赛人提议道，“有人就用驴子。”

“你好像没看出来，”托德接着说道，“我这匹骏马给你根本就是大材小用。他是一匹纯种马，部分是的，当然，是你没看出来的那部分，另一部分。他是从海克尼[2]出来的，当年还得过奖。他走红的时候你还不认识他，不过，如果你多少有点识马，还是一眼就能看出来的。不，卖马的事想也别想。也罢，你真想要我这匹年轻漂亮的马的话，考虑出个什么价？”

吉卜赛人把马上上下下打量了一番，接着同样仔细地上上下下打量了一番托德，然后又重新把马打量了一回。“一先令一条腿，”说完他转过脸去，一边继续抽他的烟，一边盯着广阔世界看，要看得她[3]发窘。

“一先令一条腿？”托德嚷道，“请等一等，给我点时间算一算，看看总共是多少。”

他从马背上爬下来，丢下马让他自个儿去吃草，自己在吉卜赛人旁边坐下，扳着手指算起来。最后他说：“一先令一条腿？哟，总共正好是四先令，就这么多。哦，不，这匹年轻漂亮的马卖四先令我可不干。”

“好吧，”吉卜赛人说，“我把底牌亮给你。我给你加到五先令，这价码已经比那动物的价值多出三先令六便士。这是我的最后出价。”

托德坐在那里盘算了好久。他肚子很饿，身无分文，离家还有一段路──他不知道究竟多远──而且敌人可能仍然在找他。对这种处境中的人来说，五先令满可以看作不少的一笔钱。再转念一想，一匹马卖这几个钱似乎少了点。可是话又说回来，那匹马没花他一个子儿，所以无论卖到多少钱都是净赚。最后，他坚定地说：“听我说，吉卜赛人！我把我们的底牌摊开来吧，这是我的最后要价。你给我六先令六便士，要现钱。另外，作为附加条件，你供我一顿早饭，让我敞开了吃，当然，只吃一顿。就是你那只铁锅里一直在冒着馋人香气的东西。作为回报，我把我这匹精力充沛的年轻马转让给你，外带他身上所有的漂亮挽具和饰物，免费赠送。如果你觉得不太合算，就直说，我走我的路。我认识这附近的一个人，他想要我这匹马已经好几年了。”

吉卜赛人发了一通很吓人的牢骚，说什么再做几桩这样的交易他就要倾家荡产。可说完之后他就从裤兜最底下拽出一个脏兮兮的帆布钱袋，数出六先令六便士放到托德的爪子里。然后他钻进大篷车里消失了片刻，拿出来一个大铁盘子，一副刀叉匙勺。他把锅子一倾斜，一股子热腾腾、外表壮观、内容丰富的炖菜流进了铁盘子里。事实上，那是世界上最出色的炖菜，是把山鹑、野鸡、家鸡、野兔、家兔、雌孔雀、珍珠鸡和一两样别的东西一起放在锅里炖出来的。托德接过盘子，放在膝上，差一点哭出来。他一个劲儿地狼吞虎咽、狼吞虎咽、狼吞虎咽，不断地要求再添一点、再添一点，吉卜赛人却也并未说一句嫌恶他的话。托德觉得，他一辈子从来不曾吃过这么美的一顿早餐。

炖菜有的是，托德一直吃到觉得再也吃不下为止，然后他站起身来，跟吉卜赛人说了再见，也依依不舍地和马道了别。吉卜赛人对河边地形很熟悉，指点给他该走的路线，他就在最好的精神状态下，重新上路了。说实在的，他已经跟一小时前的托德判若两个动物。太阳闪耀着明亮的光芒，湿衣服已经差不多晒干，口袋里重新有了钱，距离家、朋友和安全越来越近了。最棒最重要的是，饱饱地吃了一顿，浑身热乎乎的，营养充足，他感到无忧无虑，强大而自信。

他欢欢喜喜地一路走去，心里想着自己如何冒险、如何逃脱、如何逢凶化吉、遇难呈祥，那股子骄傲自大的劲儿又在心里膨胀起来。“嚯，嚯，”他一边昂起下巴大步往前走，一边自言自语，“我是一只多么聪明的癞蛤蟆呀！全世界肯定没有一只动物聪明程度及得上我！敌人把我关进监牢，哨兵围了几层，看守日夜监视，我全凭着才智加勇气，从他们眼皮子底下走了出来。他们乘着火车头，带上警察和左轮手枪来追我。我打个响指，大笑一声，他们就消失得无影无踪。我不幸被一个身体肥胖、心地恶毒的女人扔进水渠。结果怎样？我游上岸来，逮住她的马，骑着他得胜而去。我用马换来满满一口袋钱币，还有一顿很棒的早餐！嚯，嚯！我是癞蛤蟆托德，英俊的公众人物，成功人士托德！”他自负得飘飘然如腾云驾雾，不禁边走边编了一首赞美自己的歌，扯直嗓门唱起来，虽然除了他自己无人听见。这也许是动物编出来的歌里面最最自高自大的了：

世上有过伟大的英雄，
如同历史书所载所叙；
但流芳百世的名字中
没一个能和托德相比！

牛津大学聪明的人们
知道一切该知道的事物。
但他们的知识没一个及得上
大才子托德先生的半数！

动物们坐在方舟里哭泣，
他们的脸上泪水纵横。
是谁指明：“前面有陆地”？
是鼓舞人心的托德先生！

军队在大路上齐步行进，
他们齐刷刷行礼致敬。
向谁？国王还是基钦纳[4]？
不，是向着托德先生。

女王和她的侍从女官们
坐在窗前缝衣。她嚷道：
“看，那英俊男子是谁？”
她们回答：“是托德先生。”

这种词还有好多好多，但是狂妄自大得太可怕了，不宜写下来。上面几段是里面比较温和的。

他边走边唱，边唱边走，一分钟比一分钟自我膨胀。但是很快，他的傲气就要一落千丈了。

走过几英里林荫小路后，到了公路边。他拐上公路，沿着长长的白色路面一眼望去，看见远处一个小黑点正向他这边移动，接着变成了一个大黑点，接着变成了一个小团团，接着变成了一样十分熟悉的东西。然后，两声表示警告的鸣笛传进了他愉快的耳朵：没别的，太熟悉了。

“这才像样！”托德激动地说，“真正的生活回来了，又来到了我思念好久的伟大世界里！我要招呼他们，叫那些车轮上的兄弟们停一停，编个故事哄哄他们，就用目前为止一直很管用的那个故事。他们自然会捎我一程，我就再给他们编些故事。运气好的话，最后也许能开着汽车进蛤蟆府！那才叫班杰开眼呢！”

他自信地走到路中央，招呼汽车停下。它从容地驶过来，靠近林荫小路路口时减缓了速度。这时他突然脸色煞白，一颗心化成了水，两只膝盖哆哆嗦嗦直往下坍，身子伛起来，五脏六腑一阵翻江倒海似的难受，一下子他就垮了。那不幸的动物这个样子并不是无缘无故，因为驶近的汽车正是那要命的一天他从红狮客栈院子里偷走的那一辆。他所有的麻烦都是从那一天开始的！车子里的人正是那一天他坐在咖啡室里边吃午饭边观看的那一伙！

他瘫软成一堆惨兮兮的破烂，倒在路上，在绝望中自言自语地嘀咕着：“全完了！一切都结束了！重新落到警察手里，戴上镣铐！再进监狱！又要吃面包加白水了！噢，我真是个大傻瓜！我干吗要趾高气扬在乡间到处晃荡，唱着狂妄自大的歌，大白天在公路上招呼人家哟。我干吗不躲到天黑下来，从僻静的小路，静悄悄地溜回家去！哦，倒霉蛋托德！哦，厄运当头的动物！”

可怕的汽车慢慢开过来，越驶越近，最后吱的一声，在差一点就要碰到他的地方停了下来。两位绅士下了车，绕着躺在路上的这一堆皱巴巴、惨兮兮、瑟瑟发抖的东西转悠。一位绅士说：“天哪！真叫人难过！这里有位可怜的老人家──看来是个洗衣妇──晕倒在路上了！也许她是中暑了，可怜的人，也可能她今天没吃过东西。我们把她抬上车，送到离这里最近的村子里，她在那里肯定有朋友。”

他们轻手轻脚把托德抬进汽车，用柔软的垫子支着他坐起来，继续赶路。

托德听见他们说话的口吻那么友好、充满同情，知道自己没有被识破，他的胆子又开始壮起来了。他小心翼翼地先睁开一只眼睛，又睁开了第二只。

“看！”一位绅士说，“她已经好些了。新鲜空气对她有好处。你现在感觉怎样，太太？”

“谢谢你，好心的先生，”托德用虚弱的声音说，“我觉得好多了！”

“那就好，”绅士说，“现在保持安静，最重要的是别说话。”

“我不说话，”托德说，“我只是在想，如果可以坐到前排，坐在司机旁边，满脸都能吹到新鲜空气，我会很快就好的。”

“头脑多清楚的女人！”绅士说，“当然可以。”于是，他们小心地扶着托德坐到前排司机旁边，然后继续赶路。

托德现在差不多恢复了常态。他坐直身子，看看左右，想击退心中的兴奋、渴望和老瘾头。它们起来了，不断围攻着他，完全控制住了他。

“这是命呀！”他对自己说，“干吗抗争？干吗挣扎？”他把脸转过去，对着身旁的司机。

“我求你件事，先生，”他说，“让我试试，开一会儿车子。我一直仔细看着你开，好像很容易又很有趣，我希望能对朋友们说，我开过一回汽车！”

这提议把司机逗笑了，他笑得那么开怀，那位绅士便问怎么回事。他听完说了一番让托德高兴的话：“好哇，太太！我喜欢你的勇气。让她试试吧，在旁边看着点。她不会闯祸的。”

托德急不可耐地挤过去，坐到司机让出来的驾驶座上，将方向盘握在手里，假装很谦虚地听着别人的指点，发动了汽车。不过，一开始他开得很慢，因为他决心谨慎一些。

后面的绅士们鼓掌喝彩，托德听见他们在说：“她开得多好啊！想不到一个洗衣妇开车这么棒，第一回见识！”

托德开快了一点，又快了一点，越来越快。

他听见绅士们大声警告：“小心点，洗衣妇！”这话惹恼了他，他开始头脑发昏。

司机想插手，但他用一只胳膊肘把司机摁在座位上不能动，将车速加到了顶。扑在脸上的气流、引擎的嗡鸣、身子下面车厢的轻轻弹跳，把他那容易发昏的大脑醉得晕晕乎乎。“洗衣妇个鬼！”他不顾一切地大叫起来，“嚯！嚯！我是癞蛤蟆托德，抢车的窃贼，越狱的囚犯，永远能逃脱的癞蛤蟆托德！安安静静地坐着吧，你们会知道什么才是真正的驾驶，因为你们是在名声赫赫、技艺高超、天不怕地不怕的托德手里！”

那伙人惊心动魄一声喊，站起来，全体扑到他身上。“抓住他！”他们喊道，“抓住癞蛤蟆托德，偷我们汽车的坏动物！把他绑起来，铐起来，拉到最近的警局去！打倒亡命之徒危险分子托德！”

唉！他们本该动动脑子，他们本该谨慎一些，他们本该记着先想办法停下车子，然后再上演这样一场闹剧：方向盘转过去半圈，癞蛤蟆托德送车子哗啦啦冲过了公路沿边的矮树篱。它猛地一跳，狠狠地一撞，掉进一个饮马塘，轮子就在里面搅起厚泥浆来。

托德发现自己往上一蹿，像燕子一样划一道优美的弧线，飞上了天。他喜欢这动作，正开始纳闷会不会继续飞，最后长出翅膀，变成一只癞蛤蟆鸟，却已经砰的一声仰面朝天着了地，落在一块草质柔软茂密的草甸子上。他坐起来，刚好还能看见池塘里的汽车，它几乎已经淹没在水中。几位绅士和司机，被长长的外套拖累着，正不由自主地在水中扑腾。

他飞快地爬起来，撒腿就跑。他使出最大的劲儿，钻过树篱，冲过田野，直跑得上气不接下气，累得放慢脚步慢悠悠地走。等到稍稍缓过气来，能定下心来想一想时，他咯咯地笑起来，又从咯咯傻笑发展到哈哈大笑，直笑得站不住，一屁股坐到树篱下面。“嚯，嚯！”他陶醉在自我欣赏之中，喊叫着，“还是托德！托德，像往常一样，最棒的！是谁骗他们让他搭车的？是谁借口要呼吸新鲜空气，设法坐到前排去的？是谁说服他们让他试试看能不能开车的？是谁让他们全都掉进饮马塘的？是谁快活地飞起来，毫发无伤地腾空逃走，将那帮心胸狭窄、记人前仇、胆小怕事的游客丢在正该他们待的泥浆里面不管的？嗨，当然是托德。聪明的托德，伟大的托德，善良的托德！”

接着，他突然就又唱起歌来，拉直了嗓门哇啦哇啦地唱：

汽车开起来噗噗噗，
沿大路向前飞奔。
是谁把它开进了池塘？
聪明能干的托德先生！

“我多么聪明啊！聪明啊，聪明啊，聪明啊……”

后面很远的地方传来微弱的喧闹声，引得他回过头去看：恐怖啊！悲惨啊！绝望啊！

只见从大约两块田以外，一个扎着皮绑腿的司机和两个大块头乡村警察，正使足了劲儿向他奔过来！

可怜的托德蹦起来，再一次开始仓皇逃窜，他的心提到了喉咙口。“哦，天！”他气喘吁吁地一边跑，一边说，“我真是头驴！一头自高自大、冒冒失失的驴！又得意忘形了！又大喊大叫大唱起来了！又坐着不动胡吹乱侃了！哦，天！哦，天！哦，天！”

他向后瞄了一眼，很沮丧地看到他们越追越近。他拼死地往前跑，又不断地往后看，看到他们不断地逼近。他使出了最大的劲儿拼命跑，但他是一只肥胖的动物，腿又短，所以他们一直在逼近。现在他听得出来，他们已经追到身后不远处了。他再也不管东南西北，发了狂似的盲目乱窜，一边还回头看那几个马上就要得胜的敌人，突然，脚下的地坍了下去，他的手在空中乱抓乱挠，紧接着，噗通！他发现自己淹没在水里：深深的水，湍急的水，以不可抗拒的力量挟带着他奔流向前的水。他明白过来了：自己慌不择路，盲目乱窜，一头栽进了大河！

他浮上水面，想抓住河岸下面贴着水边生长的芦苇和灯芯草，可是水流的力量太大，把他抓到手里的草夺走了。“哦，天！”可怜的托德气喘吁吁地说，“要是我再偷一辆汽车！要是我再唱一首自高自大的歌……”话没说完他就沉了下去，然后浮上来，上气不接下气，嘴巴里直往外喷水。他就看见自己正接近河岸上一个大黑洞，就在他头顶上。当水流挟带着他从旁经过时，他举起一只爪子，抓住洞的边沿，抓牢了。然后，他很吃力地把自己慢慢拽出水面，两只胳膊肘支在洞的边沿上。好几分钟，他就这样待着不动，呼哧呼哧直喘气，因为他实在是精疲力竭了。

他正叹息着，喘着粗气，盯着眼前黑乎乎的洞向里面张望，就看见一个亮晶晶的小东西在洞的深处闪烁着，向他移动过来。当它来到近前时，一张脸渐渐地在它周围显现出来，一张熟悉的脸！

一张棕色的小脸，长着胡须。

一张严肃的圆脸，玲珑的耳朵，丝绸一样的毛发。

是水鼠兰特！

[1]作者用基督教的原罪之说来比喻脏衣服洗不干净。原罪是人与生俱来、洗脱不掉的罪，而衣服是可以洗干净的。这种比喻中显然有调侃的意味。

[2]伦敦近郊一个以育马闻名于世的镇子。

[3]这个“她”指“广阔世界”。

[4]英国元帅，第一次世界大战时任陆军大臣。

第十一章　泪如夏日暴雨

水鼠兰特伸出一只整洁的棕色小爪子，紧紧抓住托德的颈背，使出好大的劲儿往上拽。在水里泡得沉甸甸的托德，很缓慢但是稳稳当当地升到了洞口边沿，翻上去，安然无恙地站在了门厅里。自然，他身上沾着一道道污泥和水草，直往下淌水，但他又像往日一样幸福快乐、兴致勃勃了，因为他又来到了朋友家里，逃亡已经结束，那一身与他的身份太不相符、太不般配的伪装，可以扔掉了。

“哦，鼠仔！”他嚷道，“自从上次和你分手以后，我经历了好多事情，你没法想象！那样的磨难，那样的苦难，全都被我那么高贵勇敢地扛住了！然后是化装逃跑、耍花招逃脱，都是我聪明地计划和实施出来！进监狱──逃出来，当然！被扔进水渠──游上岸！偷一匹马──卖了一大笔钱！把每一个人都骗了──让他们全都照我的意思去做！啊，我确确实实是一只聪明伶俐的癞蛤蟆，没错！你猜我的最后一项英勇业绩是什么？别着急，听我慢慢讲来……”

“托德，”水鼠兰特严肃而坚决地说，“你立刻给我上楼去，脱掉这件好像是洗衣妇穿过的破烂旧棉布衫，把自己浑身上下洗干净，穿上我的衣服。如果没问题的话，下楼来时要像个绅士。我一辈子从没见过谁像你现在这样湿漉漉、黏糊糊，衣衫褴褛，丢人现眼！打住，别自吹自擂了，别争辩，快去！待会儿我有话跟你说！”

一开始托德不愿意动，还想回敬他几句。坐牢的时候人家对他颐指气使，他已经受够了，现在还要对他再来这一套，而且是一只鼠！可是，隔着衣帽架，他不经意地从镜子里看到了自己的模样，还有那顶很别致地扣住他一只眼睛的褪色黑女帽。他就改变了主意，快快地、温温顺顺地上了楼，来到水鼠兰特的梳妆室里。他彻彻底底地洗了一遍，梳理了一番，换好衣服，在镜子前面站了很长时间，很得意很开心地端详着自己，心想：谁把我错当成洗衣妇，哪怕只是一会会儿，他也肯定是个十足的白痴。

托德回到楼下时，午饭已经在桌上摆好，他看见了很高兴，因为吃过吉卜赛人提供的那一顿特棒的早餐后，他有过一些磨炼人的经历，做过许多剧烈的运动。他们一边吃，托德一边给水鼠兰特讲他所有的冒险事迹，主要强调他自己多么聪明，危急时脑子好使，困境中诡计多端。他的那一番遭遇，反而被他说成了一次轻松愉快、色彩缤纷的经历。但他说得越多，吹得越厉害，水鼠兰特就越是神情严肃、沉默不语。

托德一个人说呀说，终于住了嘴。沉默片刻之后，水鼠兰特说话了：“喏，蛤蟆仔，你已经吃了那么多苦，我不想再给你添烦恼。可是说真的，你就没看出来，你把自己变成了一头多么蠢的驴吗？你自己招认了，你戴手铐，蹲大牢，忍饥挨饿，遭到追捕，吓得死去活来，受人侮辱和嘲笑，被人很丢面子地扔进河里──而且是被一个女人！这里面哪里来的乐趣？有什么好玩的地方？全都因为你偏偏要去偷一辆汽车。你心里明白，自从你第一眼看到汽车后，它们给你带来的只有麻烦。你既然愿意同它们搅和在一起──你总是五分钟就能爱上一个新花样──干吗又要去偷呢？如果你觉得腿瘸了刺激，那就做瘸子好了；要是你想换换口味，一心要倾家荡产，那就破产好了。干吗偏要去做囚犯？什么时候你才会理智些，能够考虑到朋友们，给他们增点光？比如，我在外面走动时，听到动物们说我就是那个与囚犯为伍的家伙，你觉得我心里面会很高兴吗？”

喏，在托德性格中，有一点是非常令人欣慰的：他是一只心地十分善良的动物，只要是真正的朋友，再怎么数落他也从不介意。哪怕是在他最痴迷一样东西的时候，他也总是能看到问题的另一面。所以呀，在水鼠兰特那么严肃地数落他时，他虽然很不服气，一直在自言自语：“可是确实很好玩！好玩得要命！”并且压低了嗓门，暗自发出一些怪声音：“嘁──咔──咔──咔，噗──呜──呜──呜”还弄出一些类似捏着鼻子喷鼻息和撬开苏打水瓶盖的声响，但是，当水鼠兰特差不多说完时，他深深地叹了口气，很拘谨很谦虚地说：“十分正确，鼠仔！你说得总是那么合情合理！是的，我十分清楚，我是一头自高自大的老驴子。但现在我要做一只好癞蛤蟆，再也不做驴子了。至于汽车，自从最后我一头扎进你这条河里，我对汽车已经完全不像以前那么热心了。其实，我吊在你的洞口边沿喘过气来的时候，突然有了一个想法──真正绝妙的想法──跟摩托艇有关的──得，得！别生那么大气，老家伙，莫跺脚，别再把东西打翻喽。这只是个想法，现在不提它行了吧。我们喝杯咖啡，再来支烟，安安静静聊一会儿，然后我就安安静静溜达回蛤蟆府去，换上我自己的衣服，让一切回到原来的轨道上去。我已经冒险够了。我要过一种平静、稳定、受人尊敬的生活，慢悠悠地经营经营我的产业，作些改进，偶尔弄弄花草，美化美化景观。朋友们来看我时，总是有饭菜招待的。我要备一辆小型轻便马车，乘着它到乡间各处转悠转悠，就像在过去的好日子里那样。我再不会心浮气躁，老想着搞事情了。”

“安安静静溜达回蛤蟆府去？”水鼠兰特嚷道，激动得要命，“你在说什么呀？听这意思，你还没听说吗？”

“听说什么？”托德问，脸变得煞白，“说下去，鼠仔！快说！别顾惜我！我没听说什么？”

“你不会告诉我，”水鼠兰特用小拳头擂着桌子，大喊大叫，“白鼬和黄鼠狼的事你一点都没听说吧？”

“什么，野树林那帮子？”托德嚷道，四肢打着哆嗦，“不，一个字都没听说！他们干了些什么？”

“你没听说他们怎样占了蛤蟆府？”水鼠兰特接着说。

托德把胳膊肘支在桌上，两只爪子托住下巴，两只眼睛里各涌上来一汪泪水，它们夺眶而出，摔在桌上，啪嗒！啪嗒！

“接着说，鼠仔，”他就喃喃地说，“全都告诉我。最坏的事已经过去。我已经找回了自己。我挺得住。”

“你遇上那件……那件……麻烦事以后，”水鼠兰特说得很慢，很感人，“我是说，你从社交界消失了一段时间，为了那个误会，关于一台……一台机器，你知道的……”

托德只点点头。

“嗯，自然，这一带大家议论纷纷，”水鼠兰特接着说，“不光是沿河一带，连野树林那边也是。动物们照例分成两派。河边的居民都支持你，说他们那样对待你很可耻，如今这国家真是找不着公理了。野树林那帮子动物却说得很难听，他们说你活该，是时候制止你的胡作非为了。他们趾高气扬，到处讲你这回完蛋了！你永远不会回来了，永远，永远！”

托德又点点头，一言不发。

“那帮小动物就是这德行，”水鼠兰特继续往下说，“可莫尔和班杰呢，他们却和你风雨同舟，一口咬定你很快就会回来，总有办法回来的。他们并不知道你究竟怎样回来，但说你总有办法回来！”

托德在椅子里重新坐直身子，脸上露出一丝得意的笑容。

“他们用历史事实来证明，”水鼠兰特接着说道，“他们说，像你这样一只没脸没皮、巧言善辩的动物，加上大钱包的力量，没有一条已知的刑法能把你打倒。他们就收拾收拾行李，搬进了蛤蟆府，睡在那里，让房子保持通风，把一切准备妥当，只等你回来。当然啦，他们猜不到后来发生的事，可对野树林那帮子动物还是有戒心的。现在我要说事情最令人悲痛的部分了。一个黑咕隆咚的夜晚──那真是一个漆黑漆黑的夜，还刮着大风，那雨哦，简直像泼下来的一样。一帮子武装到牙齿的黄鼠狼，悄悄沿着马车道摸到了前门。同时，一伙雪貂[1]通过菜园子开进去，占领了后院和处理家事的各个房间。另外，一群肆无忌惮的白鼬，打打闹闹占据了暖房和台球室，把守住了面对草坪的法式窗户。

“莫尔和班杰正在吸烟室里，坐在炉火旁讲故事，一点都没起疑心，因为那样一个夜晚是不适合动物出来入侵的。就在这个时候，那些凶残的暴徒砸开门，从四面八方向他们扑来。他俩尽力抵抗了一阵，可有什么用呢？他们没有武器，而且是遭到了偷袭。两只动物对几百只，能有什么结果？那两个忠实可靠的可怜生灵，被他们抓住，用棍子打，用许多没来由的话辱骂，被赶到冰冷的屋外淋雨。”

听到这里，没心没肺的托德忍不住扑哧一声笑，然后又正襟危坐，装出一副特别严肃的神情。

“从此，野树林那帮家伙就住进了蛤蟆府，”水鼠兰特接着往下说，“日子过得乱七八糟！大白天有半天时间躺在床上，吃早饭不管时间，把府里弄得一塌糊涂（我听说的）、不堪入目！吃你的，喝你的，用恶劣的笑话编排你，唱粗俗下流的歌，唱些──嗯，监狱、法官、警察什么的，都是些骂人的歌，讨厌得要命，一点也不幽默。他们对做生意的人说，见人就说，说他们来了就不走了，永远待下去了。”

“哦，他们敢！”托德说，站起身来，抄起一根棍子，“我倒是很高兴马上去看看他们怎么个待法！”

“没用的，托德！”水鼠兰特冲着他的背影喊道，“你还是回来坐下吧。你去只会招惹麻烦。”

可癞蛤蟆托德已经走了，叫也叫不住。他沿着大路快速前进，棍子扛在肩上，怒气冲冲，边走边气哼哼地喃喃自语。当他快走到正门口时，突然从木栅栏后面冒出来一只长腰黄色雪貂，手里端着一杆枪。

“来的是什么人？”雪貂厉声喝问。

“废话！”托德非常气愤地说。

“你敢这样对我说话，想怎么样？立刻给我滚出来，否则我……”

雪貂一个字也不回答，只把枪抵在肩头。托德还算精明，一下子趴倒在路上，砰！一颗子弹从他头顶上呼啸而过。

受了惊吓的托德爬起来就往回跑，沿着来路连蹦带跳，能跑多快跑多快。他一边跑一边听到雪貂的笑声，还有一些可怕的尖细的笑声在跟着起哄。

他垂头丧气地跑回来，把经过告诉了水鼠兰特。

“我是怎么对你说的？”水鼠兰特说，“不管用。他们有哨兵站岗，他们全都有武器。你必须等待。”

可托德不肯马上认输。他把船弄出来，划向上游蛤蟆府花园前沿的河边。一到能看到老宅的地方，他就趴在桨上，仔细观察岸上的情形。似乎一切都很平静，不见一个人影。他能看到蛤蟆府的整个正面，看见它辉映着夕阳的光芒。鸽子三三两两，栖息在笔直的屋顶轮廓线上；花朵满园，如同火焰；通往停船棚屋的小河湾里，横跨河湾的小木桥上，一片宁静，杳无人迹，显然在等待他归来。他心想，先去停船棚屋看看吧。他很小心地把船划到河湾口，正要从桥下通过，这时……哗啦！

从上面掉下来一块大石头，把船底砸了个洞。水涌进来，船沉了，托德发现自己在很深的水中挣扎。仰脸望去，只见两只白鼬身子探过桥栏杆，看着他，乐坏了。“下回砸烂的就是你的脑袋，蛤蟆仔！”他们向他喊叫着。气愤的托德游上了岸，两只白鼬却笑啊笑，笑得抱成一团，又笑啊笑，直笑得差一点晕过去两回──当然啦，确切地说，一人一回。

癞蛤蟆托德有气无力地靠两条腿走回去，又对水鼠兰特讲了一次令人扫兴的经历。

“咳，我是怎么对你说的？”水鼠兰特很不高兴地说，“这下好了吧！瞧瞧你干的好事！把我那么喜爱的船弄没了，这就是你的成就！就知道弄坏我借给你的一套好衣服！说真的，托德，你是一只顶顶折磨人的动物──真不知道你还能不能留得住一个朋友！”

癞蛤蟆托德立刻明白了自己的行为有多么错误和愚蠢。他承认自己做错了，头脑犯了浑。他为自己丢船、弄坏衣服向兰特说了一大堆道歉的话。他爽爽快快地甘愿举手投降，这样做总是能化解朋友们的怨气，让他们回心转意的。就这样，他说了一番话作为了结：“鼠仔！我明白了，我一意孤行，是一只任性的癞蛤蟆！相信我，从今以后，我会谦虚谨慎，乖乖听话。没有你们的忠告，不经过你们完全同意，绝不擅自行动！”

“如果真是这样，”和善的兰特已经消了气，他说，“那我给你的忠告就是，现在时间已经不早了，坐下来吃晚饭，过一分钟饭菜就上桌，耐心等待。因为我确信，我们什么也不能干，得先见到鼹鼠莫尔和獾子班杰，听听他们的最新消息，开个会，看看他们在这件棘手的事情上有什么意见。”

“哦，是啊，当然啦，鼹鼠莫尔和獾子班杰，”托德轻飘飘地说，“那两个亲爱的家伙，他们怎么样？瞧我把他们忘了个一干二净。”

“亏你还好意思问！”水鼠兰特责备道，“你开着豪华汽车满世界兜风，骑着纯种马神气活现地奔驰，吃着山珍海味的早饭。那两个可怜的忠诚的动物，却不论刮风下雨，都在外面露宿，白天受苦，晚上遭罪，替你守望房子，巡察地界，不断地监视着白鼬和黄鼠狼，费心思筹谋策划，想替你夺回产业。你不配有这样真诚忠实的朋友，托德，你真的不配。将来有一天，你会后悔当初没有好好珍惜他们，到那时候就晚了！”

“我是个忘恩负义的畜生，我知道，”托德呜咽道，流下了酸楚的泪，“让我出去找他们，在寒冷漆黑的夜里，去外面分担他们的艰辛，我要证明──等一下！我听到了餐具碰托盘的声音，不会错！晚餐终于上来了，万岁！快来吧，鼠仔！”

水鼠兰特记着可怜的托德吃了好长时间牢饭，所以饭菜的量准备得很多。他跟着托德来到餐桌旁，热情地鼓励他放开了吃，补偿一下前段时间吃的亏。

他们刚吃完饭，坐回到扶手椅里，就听见响起了重重的敲门声。

托德有些紧张，但水鼠兰特很神秘地冲他点了一下头，就径直走过去把门打开。班杰先生走了进来。

他的模样完全像是一个好多个晚上没进过家门的人，好久没享受过家里的各种小小的舒适和方便。他鞋子上沾满了泥，衣裳凌乱，蓬头垢面。话说回来，獾子班杰最体面的时候也从来不是一个非常整洁的人。他庄严地走到托德跟前，和他握握爪子，说道：“欢迎回家，托德！唉！我说些什么呀？家个鬼哟！这个家回得好惨。不幸的托德！”说完他背过身去，将椅子拉近些，在桌旁坐下，拿起一大片冷馅饼吃了起来。

这种欢迎风格很严肃、很不祥，让托德十分惊惶。水鼠兰特悄声对他说：“别在意，别往心里去，现在什么也不要对他说。他肚里没食的时候，情绪总是有几分低落的。半小时后，他就会完全变个样。”

于是，他们静静地等待着，不久，又响起了一阵比较轻的敲门声。水鼠兰特冲托德点了一下头，跑到门口，把鼹鼠莫尔迎了进来。莫尔也是衣裳破烂，邋里邋遢，皮毛上还沾着些干草和稻草。

“万岁！这不是老托德吗！”鼹鼠莫尔嚷道，脸上放出光来，“没想到你这就回来了！”他围着他跳起了舞。“做梦也没想到，这么快你就出现在我们面前！你一定是想办法逃出来的，你这只聪明机灵的癞蛤蟆！”

水鼠兰特慌了，忙去拉他的胳膊肘，但已经太晚了。托德已经膨胀起身子，吹起牛来。

“聪明？哦，不！”他说，“按照朋友们的看法，我其实并不聪明。我只是从英国最牢固的监狱里逃脱了，仅此而已！俘获了一列火车，乘着它逃亡，仅此而已！乔装打扮，在乡间到处跑，骗过了每一个人，仅此而已！哦，不！我是一头笨驴，是的！莫尔，我给你讲一两回我的小小冒险，然后你自己去判断吧！”

“嗯，好的，”鼹鼠莫尔说，向餐桌走过去，“我一边吃，你一边讲。从吃早饭到现在，我还一口东西没吃过呢！哦，天！哦，天！”他坐下来，大吃冷牛肉和酸黄瓜。

托德叉开腿站在炉前地毯上，把爪子猛插到裤兜里，掏出一把银币。“瞧这个！”他嚷道，“几分钟就搞到手了，不坏吧？你猜我是怎么搞到的，莫尔？马匹交易！我卖马换来的！”

“接着说，托德。”鼹鼠莫尔说，兴趣浓得要命。

“托德，拜托你安静些！”水鼠兰特说，“你别再怂恿他了，莫尔，你不是不了解他这人。既然托德终于回来了，还是尽快告诉我们情形如何，最好怎么办。”

“情形坏得不能再坏了，”鼹鼠莫尔气呼呼地答道，“至于说怎么办，嗨，我要知道就谢天谢地了！獾子班杰和我白天晚上在周围转悠，情形一直没什么两样。到处有哨兵站岗，枪口指着我们，石头向我们砸过来。瞭望台上始终有动物值班，一看见我们，天！笑成那个样子！最让我恼火的就是他们的笑！”

“情形确实很困难，”水鼠兰特深思着说道，“不过，我想，我心底里已经知道了，知道托德其实应该怎么干。听我说。他应该……”

“不，不该！”鼹鼠莫尔大叫，嘴里包得满满的，“不能做那种事！你不明白。他应该做的是，他应该……”

“哟，我可不干，反正不干！”托德嚷道，激动起来，“我不想被你们这些家伙支使来支使去！现在说的是我的宅子，怎么干才好我知道，我来告诉你们，我要……”

这时他们三个一齐扯直了嗓门说话，吵闹得震耳欲聋，却有一个细弱、冷冰冰的声音，大家都听见了：“马上全都给我安静下来！”霎时间，鸦雀无声。

是獾子班杰发话了，他已经吃完馅饼，在椅子里转过身来，严厉地看着他们。看到他们的注意力已经被抓牢，明显在等他开讲，他又回过身去对着桌子，伸手拿干酪。这只令人钦佩的动物，他的可以信赖的人品受到了超乎寻常的敬重。直到他用餐完毕，掸掉膝头上的碎屑，没有一个人再说出一个字。癞蛤蟆托德坐立不安，但水鼠兰特牢牢地摁住了他。

獾子班杰吃饱喝足了，从座位上起来，站在壁炉前沉思着。终于，他开口说话了。

“托德！”他严厉地说道，“你这个烦人的小坏动物！你不为自己害臊吗？如果你父亲，我的老朋友，今晚在这里，知道了你的所作所为，你觉得他会怎么说？”

托德原本高翘着腿坐在沙发上，一下子就侧翻过去脸贴着沙发，痛悔地抽泣起来，哭得浑身打颤。

“好啦，好啦！”獾子班杰语气温和了些，继续往下说，“没关系。别哭啦。过去的事就让它过去，我们来掀开新的一页吧。不过，鼹鼠莫尔说的全是实情。每个要紧地点都有白鼬站岗，他们形成了世上最好的哨兵阵。正面攻击是完全不会有效果的。我们寡不敌众。”

“那就全完了，”癞蛤蟆托德呜咽道，哭着哭着把脸埋在了沙发垫子里，“我要去报名当兵，永远不再见我亲爱的蛤蟆府！”

“得啦，振作起来，蛤蟆仔！”獾子班杰说，“要收复一个地方，除了强攻以外，还有别的办法呀。我话还没说完呢。现在我要告诉你们一个大秘密。”

托德慢慢地坐起来，擦干眼泪。秘密对他的吸引力是极其巨大的，因为他从来守不住秘密。每次信誓旦旦地保证不泄露秘密之后，他都会跑去告诉别的动物，从中体验到一种很罪孽的刺激和快感，他喜欢这种享受。

“有——条——地——下——通——道，”獾子班杰一字一顿地强调说，“从离这里很近的河岸，直通到蛤蟆府中央。”

“哦，胡扯！班杰，”托德相当轻率地说，“你是听附近酒馆里那帮人胡编的天方夜谭吧。蛤蟆府里里外外，每一英寸，我都了如指掌。根本没什么地道的，我向你保证！”

“我的年轻朋友，”獾子班杰极其严肃地说，“你父亲，那是一个值得尊敬的人，比我认识的一些人可敬得多。他是我的至交，曾经告诉过我许多他不敢让你知道的事。他发现了那条地道，当然，不是他挖的。他搬到那里住之前就有，几百年前挖出来的。他把它修好，打扫清理了一番，因为他觉得，也许有一天，万一遇到麻烦或危险，它会派上用场。他带我去看了。‘别让我儿子知道这事，’他说，‘他是个好孩子，但性格很轻佻，没定性，简直管不住自己的舌头。哪一天他真的处在困境中，用得上它时，你可以让他知道这条秘密地道，但事先别告诉他。”

另外两只动物紧盯着托德，看他作何反应。一开始，托德绷着面孔好像要生气了，但他脸上立刻就露出了喜色。他一向就是个心地善良的家伙。

“好吧，好吧，”他说，“也许，我是有点多嘴多舌。像我这样一个公众人物，老是有朋友围着，一起逗逗乐子，露露才华，讲些风趣的故事，不知怎么地我的舌头就要东拉西扯了。我口才好。曾经有人说我应该办个沙龙，无论那是个什么东东。不管它了。接着说，班杰。你这条地道能帮上我们什么忙呢？”

“最近我发现了一两个情况，”獾子班杰接着说道，“我让奥特装扮成扫烟囱的，扛着刷子去后门口叫门，讨活儿干。他探听到明天晚上要大办宴席。有人过生日──我估摸着是黄鼠狼头领，所有的黄鼠狼都会聚集在宴会厅里，大吃大喝，大笑大闹，什么都不会怀疑。不带枪不带剑不带棍棒，什么武器都不带！”

“可是还会像平时一样，有哨兵站岗的呀。”水鼠兰特评论道。

“正是这样，”獾子班杰说，“我想说的要点就在这里。黄鼠狼们会完全信赖他们的优秀哨兵。地道的用场就在这里。那条非常有用的通道直通到备膳室下面，就在宴会厅隔壁！”

“啊哈！备膳室里那块嘎吱嘎吱响的地板！”托德说，“现在我明白了！”

“我们悄悄地从地道里爬出来，溜进备膳室……”鼹鼠莫尔嚷嚷。

“带着手枪、刀剑和棍棒……”水鼠兰特大叫。

“冲进去，扑向他们。”獾子班杰说。

“狠揍他们，狠揍他们，狠揍他们！”癞蛤蟆托德欣喜若狂地喊叫着，在房间里跳过一张张椅子，绕圈跑。

“那好，”獾子班杰说，态度又像平时那样冷冰冰的，“计划已经定下来，你们没有什么可争吵的了。时间已经很晚，都立刻去上床睡觉吧。明天早晨，我们再安排一切必要的准备工作。”

托德当然跟其他人一起，乖乖地去睡觉了。他虽然觉得兴奋，睡不着，却也知道，犟着不肯睡是行不通的。他经历了漫长的一天，很多事情挤在一起发生。前些天又只有稻草当铺盖，稻草还不多，就那么铺在石板地上，而且牢房还透风。所以，现在，床单和毯子真是让人感到亲切和舒适呀。他把脑袋搁到枕头上没几秒钟，就幸福地打起了呼噜。自然，他做了好多梦，梦见他正需要道路时，道路就溜走了；梦见水渠在后面追他，把他抓住；梦见自己正开宴会，一条驳船驶进宴会厅，送来了要他这个礼拜洗好的衣服；梦见自己在一条秘密通道里，正慢慢向前走，它却扭动着转过身来，抖抖身子，坐直了……不知怎么回事，最后他一下子发现自己得胜还朝，平安无事地回到了蛤蟆府，所有的朋友都围着他，很认真地向他保证说，他确实是一只聪明的癞蛤蟆。

第二天早晨，他睡到很晚才起床。下楼后，他发现别的动物都已经吃过早饭好一会儿了。鼹鼠莫尔自个儿溜了出去，没告诉任何人他去哪里。獾子班杰坐在扶手椅里，正在看报纸，对那一天晚上就要发生的事，丝毫也不关心。另一方面呢，水鼠兰特却在屋子里跑来跑去地忙，怀里抱着各式各样的武器，倒在地板上把它们分成四小堆。他一边跑，一边压低嗓门兴奋地念叨着：“这把——剑——给——兰特，这把——剑——给——莫尔，这把——剑——给——托德，这把——剑——给——班杰！这支——手枪——给——兰特，这支——手枪——给——莫尔，这支——手枪——给——托德，这支——手枪——给——班杰！”等等等等，他这样有规律、有节奏地念叨着，那四个小堆就渐渐地越长越高了。

“活儿干得挺不错，兰特，”獾子班杰的目光从报纸边缘瞥过来，看着那忙个不停的小动物，他就说，“我不是在责怪你，可一旦避过白鼬和他们那些可恶的枪，我们就用不着刀剑和手枪了，这个我可以向你保证。我们四个，带上棍棒，一旦进入宴会厅，呃，五分钟就可以把那帮家伙全部清除。本来整件事我一个人就可以解决的，只是不想剥夺你们这些家伙的乐趣而已！”

“还是保险一点的好。”水鼠兰特一边沉思着说，一边用袖子擦一支手枪的枪管，并用眼睛瞄着它。

癞蛤蟆托德吃完了早饭，抄起一根粗棍子，使劲儿挥舞着，痛打想象中的坏动物。“抢我的宅子，我要领教他们！”他叫喊着，“我要领教他们，我要领教他们！”

“别说‘领教他们’，托德，”水鼠兰特说，惊愕得要命，“这样说英语不恰当。”

“你干吗老挑剔托德？”獾子班杰有些生气地责问道，“他的英语怎么啦？我自己也这样说，如果我听着觉得没什么不好，那你听着也该没什么不好！”

“对不起，”水鼠兰特温顺地说，“我只是觉得应该说‘教训他们’，而不是‘领教他们。’”

“可我们不想教训他们，”獾子班杰回敬道，“我们想领教他们，领教他们！而且，我们就要去领教了！”

“哦，那好吧，你们想怎样说就怎样说吧。”水鼠兰特说。他自己也有几分糊涂起来，就退缩到一个角落里。只听见他在那边一个劲儿地咕哝着：“领教他们，教训他们；教训他们，领教他们！”最后獾子班杰厉声喝叫，他才停止。

不久，鼹鼠莫尔就跌跌撞撞地进屋来了，他显然很得意。“真带劲儿！”他迫不及待地说，“我耍弄那些白鼬，把他们惹急了！”

“你没有闯祸吧，莫尔？”水鼠兰特着急地说。

“我也希望没有，”鼹鼠莫尔自信地说，“我是在厨房里想到这个主意的。我去厨房，是想确保托德的早餐在炉子上焐着，他起来时有热乎的吃。我发现，他昨天穿回家的那套洗衣妇的旧衣服就挂在炉子前面的毛巾架上。我就穿上了，又戴上那顶女帽，披上披肩，出发去蛤蟆府，要多勇敢有多勇敢。当然啰，有哨兵端着枪站在瞭望台上，问我‘来的是什么人？’还把他们那一套废话，全说了一遍。‘早上好，先生们！’我恭恭敬敬地说，‘今天有衣服要洗吗？’

“他们非常傲慢非常生硬地看着我，说道：‘滚开，洗衣妇！我们在值班，不洗衣服。’‘要不改天再洗？’我说。嚯，嚯，嚯！我搞笑不搞笑，托德？”

“这么轻浮，真是个可怜的动物！”托德很高傲地说。其实呢，对莫尔的作为，他妒忌得要命。他真希望干那事的是他本人。要是他先想到这主意，而且没有睡过头，那该多好呀。

“有几只白鼬涨红了脸，”鼹鼠莫尔接着说道，“那个小队长，他对我说，他非常暴躁地说：‘快滚蛋，我的个好大姐，滚蛋！别招惹我的兵值班时闲聊。’‘滚蛋？’我说，‘快要滚蛋的人不是我，用不了多久的！’”

“鼹仔啊，你怎么能那么干？”水鼠兰特非常惊慌地说。

獾子班杰放下了报纸。

“我看见他们竖起了耳朵，面面相觑，”鼹鼠莫尔接着说道，“小队长对他们说：‘别把她的话当真，她不知道自己在说什么。’

“‘是吗！我不知道？’我说，‘好啊，那我就给你们说说。我女儿是给班杰洗衣服的，你们自己想吧，我到底知道不知道自己在说什么。你们也很快就会知道我在说什么了！今天晚上，一百只杀气腾腾的獾子会端着来复枪，从养马场那边进攻蛤蟆府；六船水鼠，会挎着手枪和短剑，从大河上过来，在花园前面登岸；同时一队挑选出来的癞蛤蟆，号称“癞蛤蟆敢死队”，“不成功便成仁”，会呐喊着报仇，对果园发动突击，所过之处，鸡犬不留。遇上他们的话，你们就没多少衣服好洗喽，除非你们趁着还有机会，赶快开溜！’说完我就跑开了。一离开他们的视线，我就躲起来，然后沿着地沟爬回去，透过树篱偷看他们。那些白鼬全都紧张极了，慌乱极了，立刻四散奔逃，互相碰撞，摔倒在对方身上。他们个个向别人发号施令，个个不听号令。小队长不停地派一批批白鼬去前沿，接着又派别的家伙把他们叫回来。我听到他们互相之间在议论：‘黄鼠狼就是这德行，他们舒舒服服待在宴会厅里，大吃大喝，碰杯唱歌，寻欢作乐，却要我们站岗。这里又冷又黑，到头来，我们还不是让杀人不眨眼的獾子切成碎片！’”

“哦，你个蠢驴，莫尔！”托德嚷道，“你把一切都搞砸了！”

“莫尔，”獾子班杰用他那冷冰冰的平静态度说道，“我觉得，你一个小指头里的见识比某些动物整个胖身体里的还要多。你干得好极了，我对你寄予厚望。好莫尔！聪明的莫尔！”

癞蛤蟆托德简直嫉妒得发了狂，尤其是，他赌上性命也弄不明白，鼹鼠莫尔怎么就特别聪明了。不过，幸好他还没来得及冲着獾子班杰的讥讽言语发脾气午饭铃就已经响起来了。否则的话，他可要丢人现眼了。

这顿饭简单但是营养充足──熏肉和蚕豆，还有通心粉布丁。大家吃完后，獾子班杰在扶手椅里坐下来，说道：“嗯，我们今晚的活儿已经安排好了，可能要干到很晚才能全部完成。所以我要趁着还有时间，打四十个盹。”他拉过一块手绢盖在脸上，很快就打起呼噜来。

心急而勤劳的兰特又立刻开始做准备工作。他在他的四小堆装备之间跑来跑去，嘴里念叨着：“这根——皮带——给——兰特，这根——皮带——给——莫尔，这根——皮带——给——托德，这根——皮带——给——班杰！”等等等等，不断地添上新装备，好像没完没了似的。于是，鼹鼠莫尔挽着托德的胳膊，把他领到屋外，推进一张藤椅里，要他把冒险经历从头到尾讲一遍。托德那是求之不得，一百个愿意呀。鼹鼠莫尔是个好听众，这回又没有人推敲核实、提出不友好的批评，托德就随心所欲胡侃起来。说实在的，他的许多叙述归到“要是我及时想到，而不是十分钟以后想到，事情可能就会是这样”一类里会更加合适。冒险故事永远是最精彩最刺激的，为什么就不能把它当成我们的真实经历呢，就像现实生活中发生的那些有点不够味的事情一样？

[1]在中文里，雪貂（ferret）和白鼬（stoat）常被用来称呼同一种动物。事实上，ferret是欧洲臭鼬家养驯化的后代，棕黄毛色；stoat则是白色的。它们和黄鼬（黄鼠狼，weasel）同类不同种。

第十二章　尤利西斯归来[1]

天开始黑的时候，水鼠兰特带着兴奋而诡秘的神气召集大家回到客厅里。他让伙伴们各自站在一小堆装备跟前，为即将进行的征战着手武装他们。这件事他做得很认真、很周全，整个过程花了很长时间。首先，给每一只动物腰里系上皮带，然后在皮带上插一支剑；为了保持平衡，又在另一侧插上一把弯刀。然后佩上两支手枪，一根警棍，几副手铐，一些绷带和胶布，一瓶水和一盒三明治。獾子班杰和蔼可亲地笑着说道：“行啊，鼠仔！这样子你高兴，我又没损失。我就用这根棍子，把我该干的活儿都干了。”可水鼠兰特只是说：“行行好，班杰。你知道，我不想你事后责备我，说我忘带东西！”

一切准备就绪。獾子班杰一只爪子提着一盏没点亮的灯笼，另一只爪子握着一根棍子，说道：“行啦，跟着我！莫尔排第一，因为我对他很满意，兰特第二，托德最后。听着，蛤蟆仔！别像平常那样唠叨许多废话，否则就把你打发回去，绝不含糊！”

癞蛤蟆托德很担心被留下，只好一声也不吭，接受了指派给他的低等位置。动物们出发了。獾子班杰领着他们沿着大河走了一小段，然后，突然攀住岸沿，身子一荡，进了稍微高出水面的一个洞。鼹鼠莫尔和水鼠兰特学着獾子班杰的样子，不声不响，一个接一个，成功地荡了进去。轮到托德了，不出所料，他居然脚下一滑，噗通一下掉进水里，发出一声惊慌的尖叫。两个朋友把他拉上来，连忙把他上上下下擦了一遍，拧干他的衣服，安慰他几句，扶他站了起来。可獾子班杰真的生气了，他对托德说，如果下一回他再出丑，没二话，肯定把他丢下。

他们终于进了那条秘密地道，驱逐入侵者的征战正式开始了！

地道很冷、很黑、很湿、很矮、很窄，可怜的托德开始打哆嗦，一是因为害怕，不知道前面会碰到什么，二是因为他浑身都是湿的。灯笼在前面很远的地方。在黑暗中，他没办法，落下了一小段路。这时，他听见水鼠兰特向他发出警告：“快跟上，托德！”一阵恐怖感袭上心头，他害怕被丢在后面独自待在黑暗里，就猛地往前冲去。他一下子撞倒了兰特，兰特又撞倒了莫尔，莫尔又撞倒了班杰，顿时一片混乱。獾子班杰以为他们背后遭到了袭击，因为空间狭小，没法用棍子或弯刀，他就拔出了手枪。眼看就要冲着托德扣动板机时，他弄明白了真相，火气一下子真的上来了，他说：“这一回，必须把讨厌的托德丢下！”

可是托德呜呜地哭了起来，另外两只动物就出来担保，说保证让他好好表现，最后獾子班杰息怒了。队伍继续前进，不过这一回是水鼠兰特殿后，而且他牢牢地抓着托德的肩膀。

就这样，他们摸索着一步一步往前走，耳朵支着，爪子按着手枪。走啊走，终于，獾子班杰发话了：“现在，我们应该已经快到蛤蟆府下面了。”

这时，他们突然听见一片低沉的、乱哄哄的声音。那声音其实有可能还离得很远，却好像就在他们头顶上很近的地方似的。仿佛是有人在喊叫、欢呼、跺地板、捶桌子。癞蛤蟆托德再一次陷入神经质的恐惧之中，但獾子班杰只是平静地评论了一句：“是那些黄鼠狼，他们在闹！”

现在地道开始向上倾斜了，他们又向前摸索着走了一小段路，然后那噪音一下子又响了起来，这一回十分清晰，就在他们上面很近的地方。“万——岁——万岁——万——岁——万岁！”只听见哇啦哇啦在叫，小脚爪在跺地板，小拳头捶在桌子上时玻璃杯在叮叮当当响。“他们过得可真快活！”獾子班杰说，“快跟上！”他们就快步往前走去。然后，地道一下子就到了头，他们发现自己站在活板门下面，它通往上面的备膳室。

宴会厅里吵翻了天，几乎不存在被他们听到动静的危险。獾子班杰说：“现在，小伙子们，一起使劲儿！”四只动物用肩膀顶住活板门，把它掀了开来。他们一个拽一个，到了上面，发现自己站在备膳室里，跟宴会厅之间只隔着一道门，蒙在鼓里的敌人正在隔壁狂饮胡闹呢。

他们刚从地道里爬上来时，那吵闹声简直震耳欲聋。这会儿，欢呼声和捶桌子的声音终于渐渐减弱了，一个分辨得出来的声音在说话：“嗯，我不打算耽误你们很长时间，”（一阵极其热烈的鼓掌声）“但是在我重新坐下去之前，”（又是一阵欢呼）“我想说一句话，谈谈我们仁慈的主人托德先生。我们都认识托德！”（一阵哄堂大笑）“善良的托德，谦虚的托德，诚实的托德！”（一阵阵兴高采烈的尖叫声）

“别让我抓住他！”托德咬牙切齿地低声说。

“忍耐一分钟！”獾子班杰说，好不容易摁住了他，“大家准备好！”

“我来给你们唱一支小曲儿，”那声音接着说道，“这是我以托德为题编出来的。”（经久不息的掌声）

于是，黄鼠狼头领──那声音正是他──用又高又尖的声音开始唱：

托德他高高兴兴
喜洋洋走在大街上……

獾子班杰挺直身子，两只爪子握紧棍子，扫了一眼同伴，喊道：

“时候到了，跟我上！”

猛一下推开了门。

天！

吱吱吱、唧唧唧、哇呀呀，满屋子的尖叫声响成一片！

四位英雄怒气冲冲大踏步冲进宴会厅的恐怖一刻，那一阵恐慌呀，好家伙，吓坏了的黄鼠狼有的一头钻到桌子底下，有的发疯似的跳上了窗台！好家伙，雪貂们狂乱地奔向壁炉，无可救药地挤在一起，卡在了烟囱里！好家伙，桌子椅子被撞倒了，玻璃杯和瓷器被碰翻了，在地板上摔得粉碎！那大力士班杰，胡须根根直立起来，大棍子带着啸声从空中划过。莫尔黑着脸，凶巴巴挥舞着棍棒，恶狠狠发着战斗的呐喊：“鼹鼠来了！鼹鼠来了！”兰特腰带上鼓鼓囊囊插满了各个年代各种式样的兵器，不顾一切不要命地冲杀着。托德因为自尊心受了伤害，激动得发了狂，身体鼓胀得比平时大一倍，跳到空中，发出癞蛤蟆那种哇哇的怪叫，吓得他们毛骨悚然！“托德他高高兴兴！”他叫喊着，“我让你们高兴！”直奔黄鼠狼头领而去。他们总共只有四个，但在那些惊惶失措的黄鼠狼眼里，宴会厅里仿佛全是妖怪似的动物，灰的、黑的、棕色的、黄色的，哇哇地怪叫着，挥舞着巨大的棍棒。他们惊恐地尖叫着，向四面八方夺路而逃，跳出窗户，窜上烟囱，有地方去就行，只要能躲开那些可怕的棍子。

这件大事很快就结束了。四个朋友在整个宴会厅里大踏步来回巡视着，只要有一个脑袋露出来，就给它一棍子。五分钟后，厅里面就已经清除干净。那些吓坏了的黄鼠狼逃过草坪时发出的尖叫声，透过破碎的窗户，隐隐约约地传到他们耳朵里。地板上倒着几十个敌人，鼹鼠莫尔正忙着给他们戴手铐。獾子班杰辛苦了一场，正靠在他的大棍子上休息，擦去他那正直的额头上的汗水。

“莫尔，”他说，“你是最棒的伙伴！跑快点，去外面瞧一眼你打过交道的那些白鼬哨兵，看看他们在干什么。我看啊，今天晚上，他们不用我们再怎么劳神费心了！”

鼹鼠莫尔立刻跳出窗户，不见了人影。班杰吩咐另外两位扶起一张桌子，从地板上的碎片中捡出一些刀叉杯盘来，看看能不能找出些材料，凑齐一顿晚饭。“我想吃点东西，真的，”他用平时那种平平常常的口吻说道，“动作快些，托德，拿出点活泼的样子来！我们给你夺回了房子，你却连三明治都不拿一个出来。”托德觉得挺伤心：獾子班杰表扬了莫尔，却没有对他说些好听的，没有夸他是一个优秀的伙伴，打仗时表现出色。他自己对自己可是相当满意，特别是扑向黄鼠狼头领那一幕，一棍子就把他打飞到桌子的另一边。伤心归伤心，他还是四下里忙碌起来，水鼠兰特也一起帮忙。他们很快就找到了一玻璃盘番石榴果酱、一只冷鸡、一根几乎没动过的口条、一些屈莱弗甜食[2]，还有许多龙虾沙拉。在备膳室里，他们发现了一篮子法式面包卷，还有要多少有多少的干酪、黄油和芹菜。他们正要坐下，却看见鼹鼠莫尔从窗户里爬进来，抱着一堆来复枪，咯咯地笑着。

“我估摸着呀，”他报告说，“已经全结束了。那些白鼬本来就神经紧张、心惊肉跳的，有的一听见宴会厅里的尖叫、呐喊和吵闹声就扔下来复枪逃了。另外一些坚守了一会儿，可一看见黄鼠狼从房里逃出去奔向他们，就觉得自己被出卖了。白鼬就揪住黄鼠狼不放，黄鼠狼就挣扎着想脱身，他们扭打成一团，互相用拳头狠揍，在地上翻过来滚过去，最后那些家伙大多数滚下了河！不管是怎样跑的，反正现在他们全都没了踪影。我就把他们的来复枪弄来了。所以呀，万事大吉喽！”

“你表现很出色，立了大功！”獾子班杰说，嘴里包着鸡肉和屈莱弗甜食，“现在，你再替我做一件事就行了，莫尔，然后，你就坐下来，同我们一起吃晚饭。我本不想麻烦你的，只是我知道，事情交给你肯定能办好，能让人放心。要是我能对我认识的每一个人都这样说，那该多好哟。假如兰特不是个诗人，这件事我就叫他去办了。我要你去那边，把地板上那帮家伙带上楼，让他们打扫出几间卧室来，整理好，布置得舒舒服服。叫他们务必把床底下扫干净，换上干净床单和枕套，把被子掀开一只角，该掀成什么样你知道的。还要给每个房间备上干净毛巾、新开包的肥皂、一壶热水。然后，要是揍他们能让你高兴的话，就给他们每人一顿拳脚，让他们从后门滚蛋。我看呐，从此以后我们再也不会看见他们了。办完事你就过来，尝尝这种冷口条，上等的好东西哟。我对你很满意，莫尔！”

好脾气的莫尔捡起一根棍子，指挥犯人在地板上排成一行，命令他们“齐步走！”就带着一队人马上楼去了。过了一段时间，他走下楼来，笑呵呵地，说每个房间都打扫布置好了，像一根新别针一样干净。“还有，我没揍他们，”他补充道，“我想呀，总的说来，他们一个晚上挨那么多揍已经够了。我把这个想法对黄鼠狼说了，他们十分赞成，说今后再也不想麻烦我动手了。他们的悔罪态度很好，还说他们对自己的所作所为后悔至极，不过全是黄鼠狼头领和白鼬们的错。今后任何时候，只要我们言语一声，他们愿意赴汤蹈火，将功补过。所以我发给他们每人一个面包卷，放他们从后门出去，他们撒开腿就溜哇，能跑多快就跑多快！”

鼹鼠莫尔说完，把椅子拉近桌子坐下，拿起那根冷口条，埋头大吃起来。托德毕竟是个绅士，他把满心的嫉妒丢开，诚心诚意地说：“衷心感谢你，莫尔，谢谢你今晚费心费力，尤其谢谢你今天早晨的聪明机智！”獾子班杰听了很高兴，说道：“说这话的才是勇敢的托德！”他们欢天喜地、扬眉吐气地吃完晚饭就钻进干净的被窝里休息了。他们安安稳稳地就寝在托德的祖宅里，这是靠无比的勇气、完美的韬略和恰如其分的武力夺回来的。

第二天早晨，托德像往常一样睡过了头，下楼来吃早饭时已经晚得不像话了。他发现桌子上只剩下一些蛋壳，几片冷透了已经变韧的烤面包，一只空了四分之三的咖啡壶，别的几乎就没有了。这下子，他的心情好不起来啰，想想看，这毕竟是他自己的家呀。透过早餐室的法式窗户，他看见鼹鼠莫尔和水鼠兰特坐在草坪上的藤椅里，显然正在互相讲故事给对方听。他们把两双短腿朝天乱踢乱蹬，笑得好疯哦。獾子班杰坐在扶手椅里，正埋头看晨报。托德走进房间时，他只抬起眼睛看了他一眼，点了下头。不过托德知道班杰就是那么样一个人，只好坐下来，尽量凑合着吃一顿早饭。他只在心里面对自己说，迟早有一天，要跟这几个家伙算账。他快吃完的时候，獾子班杰抬起头来，简明扼要地说：“对不起，托德，恐怕今天上午有好多事摆在你面前呢。你瞧，我们实在应该马上举办一个宴会，庆祝这件大事。这要你来操持了，规矩就是如此。”

“噢，没问题！”癞蛤蟆托德心里很乐意，说，“一切遵命。可我不明白，干吗一定要在上午举办宴会。不过呢，你知道，亲爱的老班杰，我活着不是为了自己开心，只是为了探询朋友们的需要，然后设法予以满足！”

“别在这里装傻，”獾子班杰脾气很大地回敬道，“不要一边说话，一边吱溜吱溜地喝咖啡，这不礼貌。我的意思是，宴会当然在晚上举行，但邀请函得马上就写好发出去，得你来写。坐到那张桌子跟前去，那边有一叠空白邀请函，抬头是蓝底子烫金的“蛤蟆府”。给我们的所有朋友每人写一张，如果你抓紧时间，午饭之前就可以发出去。我会搭一把手，分担一些任务。酒席由我来预订。”

“什么！”托德沮丧地嚷道，“这么愉快的早晨，让我待在屋里写一大堆烂邀请函？我想到这园子里四处走走，把各种人和事恢复正常，神气神气，快活快活！我才不干呢！我要去……我要看着你们……不过，停一分钟！嗯，我当然会干，亲爱的班杰！我自己的快乐和方便，跟别人的相比算得了什么！你要我干，我就去干。去吧，班杰，去预订酒席吧，你喜欢什么样的就订什么样的。然后就到外面去，同那两个年轻朋友一起无忧无虑地欢笑，不用管我，不用留意我怎样操心劳神、辛苦工作。为了神圣的责任和友谊，我愿意牺牲这个美好的早晨！”

獾子班杰疑心很重地看着他，可是托德神情坦然自若，很难想象这种态度转变的背后，能有什么不光彩的动机。于是，他离开早餐室，向厨房方向走去。门刚在班杰身后关上，托德就急不可待地奔向写字台。刚才和班杰说话时，他突然想到了一个好主意。他愿意写邀请函了，他要记着在每一封邀请函里提到自己在战斗中的主导作用，提到他怎样把黄鼠狼头领撂倒。他要在里面暗示自己的冒险生涯，暗示那是一段不得不讲一讲的充满凯歌的经历。在邀请函的扉页上，他要列出一个晚会表演节目单之类的东西──诸如此类吧，他脑子里是这样筹划的：

演讲

演讲者：托德

（晚会期间托德还要发表其他演讲）

致词

发言人：托德

大纲：我们的监狱体制──老英格兰的航道──马匹处理及处理方法──财产、产权和义务──回归故土──典型英国乡绅。

唱歌

演唱者：托德（本人创作的歌曲）

其他作品

作曲：托德

晚会期间由作曲者演唱。

这个主意让他心里美滋滋的，他便很努力地动手干起活儿来。中午，所有邀请函都写好了。这段时间里他得到禀报，门口来了一只衣衫褴褛的小个子黄鼠狼，怯生生地询问能否为老爷们效劳。托德昂首阔步来到外面，发现原来是昨晚被俘的黄鼠狼之一，这会儿恭敬而热切地来拍马屁了。托德拍拍他的脑袋，把一扎邀请函塞进他的爪子，叫他路上赶紧些，尽快把它们分送出去。如果他晚上愿意再过来，也许会给他一个先令，不过也可能不给。可怜的黄鼠狼好像真的十分感恩戴德，急切匆忙地去执行任务了。

另位三只动物在河上玩了一个上午，热热闹闹、轻松愉快地回来吃午饭了。鼹鼠莫尔本来一直觉得良心不安，就疑神疑鬼地看着托德，估摸着他要么在生闷气，要么垂头丧气。才不是呢，托德可是打足了气，神气活现。鼹鼠莫尔心里犯起了嘀咕，水鼠兰特和獾子班杰则意味深长地交换了一个眼色。

午饭刚吃完，托德就把两只爪子深深地插进裤兜，随意地说了一句：“嗨，照顾好自己，你们这些家伙！一切自便！”就大摇大摆地向花园走去，他想在那里琢磨一下晚上演讲的事，这时水鼠兰特抓住了他的胳膊。

托德疑心他接下来要干什么，使足劲儿想挣脱。可是当獾子班杰牢牢地捉住他另一只胳膊时，他开始明白过来：游戏结束了。两只动物把他夹在中间，带着他进了与大堂相通的小吸烟室，关上门，把他摁进椅子里。他们俩堵在他面前，托德一声不吭地坐着，疑神疑鬼、情绪恶劣地望着他们。

“现在听好了，托德，”水鼠兰特说，“是这次宴会的事。对不起，我不得不这样对你说话。我们希望一劳永逸地让你明白，宴会上不会有演讲，不会有唱歌。你要搞清楚，这一回我们不是在同你讨论，只是通知你一声。”

托德看懂了：他掉进了圈套。他们了解他，他们看透了他，他们抢在了前面。他的美梦粉碎了。

“我就唱一支短歌，行不行？”他惨兮兮地央求道。

“不行，一支也不行，”水鼠兰特很坚决地说，虽说他注意到可怜的托德很失望地颤抖着嘴唇，也挺心疼的，“那没有好处，蛤蟆仔。你清楚得很，你那些歌全都是自高自大，自吹自擂。你的演讲全是自赞自夸，和……和……嗯，令人恶心的夸张，和……和……”

“和吹牛。”獾子班杰用他那种平淡的口吻插言道。

“这是为你自己好，蛤蟆仔，”水鼠兰特接着说，“你知道，你迟早要翻开新的一页。现在似乎正是重新开始的大好时机，是你人生的转折点。你要知道，说这些话时我心里面一点也不比你好受。”

托德沉默着，埋头想了好久。最后他抬起头来，脸上带着经历过强烈情感冲动的痕迹。“你们胜利了，我的朋友们，”他语不成声地说，“其实，我提出来的只是一个小小的要求，只求允许我再灿烂、盛开一个晚上，让我尽情表现一下，听听喧腾的欢呼声。不知为什么，我觉得那声音似乎总是能显现出我最好的品质。但我知道，你们是对的，我错了。从今天起，我要重新做人。我的朋友们，你们再也不会有机会为我脸红了。天哪，天哪，这世界真冷酷！”

他用手绢捂住脸，脚步蹒跚地离开了吸烟室。

“班杰，”水鼠兰特说道，“我觉得自己像一头没人性的野兽，不知道你感觉怎样？”

“啊，我明白，我明白，”獾子班杰忧郁地说，“但事情非这么办不可。这位仁兄得在这里生活下去，守住自己的家业，得到别人的尊敬。总不能让他成为大家的笑柄，让白鼬和黄鼠狼嘲讽讥笑吧？”

“那当然，”水鼠兰特说，“提到黄鼠狼，那只小黄鼠狼带着托德的邀请函正要出发，碰巧让我们遇上了，真是万幸。我想到你对我说过的话，起了疑心，就看了一两封，简直是太丢人了。被我一股脑儿全没收了。现在，好莫尔正坐在那间天蓝色的起居室里，填写简单朴素的请柬。”

举行宴会的时间终于临近了。托德一直避开众人，躲在自己的卧室里，现在仍然孤独地坐在那里，想着心事。他用爪子撑住额头，长久地深思着。渐渐地，他的面容开朗起来，慢慢地、长时间地展露着笑颜。然后他咯咯地笑了起来，笑得有点害羞、有点忸怩。最后他站起身，锁上门，拉上窗帘，把房间里所有的椅子拉过来，排成一个半圆形，自己站在前面，身子很明显地鼓胀着。然后他鞠一躬，咳嗽两声，对着他在想象中清清楚楚看到的欣喜若狂的观众，放开嗓门，尽情地唱了起来：

托德的最后一支短歌！

癞蛤蟆托德——回转——家门！
客厅里恐慌一片，
大堂里嗥叫连连；
牛棚里鬼哭狼嚎，
马厩里叫声贼尖，
当癞蛤蟆托德——回转——家门！

当癞蛤蟆托德——回转——家门！
有动物破窗而入，
有动物砸门而入；
黄鼠狼四处逃窜，
晕倒在地板上面，
当癞蛤蟆托德——回转——家门！

嘭！鼓儿声声！
喇叭手把喇叭吹起，
士兵们举手敬礼，
炮手们鸣放礼炮，
汽车鸣响了汽笛，
当英雄——回转——家门！

喊叫吧——万岁——万岁！
让人群中每一个人
都这样高声喊叫；
向一只动物表示敬意，
他正是你们的骄傲，
因为托德的大日子——正是——今朝！

他大声地唱着，唱得津津有味，绘声绘色；唱完一遍，又从头再唱了一遍。

然后他发出一声叹息，一声很长很长很长的叹息。

然后，他拿发刷在水罐里浸湿，把头发从中间分开，刷平伏，让它们整齐光滑地贴在两边的脸颊上。他打开门，平平静静地下楼去接见客人们，他知道，他们一定已经聚集在客厅里了。

他进去的时候，所有动物欢呼致意，围拢来祝贺他，称赞他勇敢、聪明，打仗好本事。但托德只是淡淡一笑，低声说一句：“哪里的话！”有时换个说法：“正相反呢！”水獭奥特这时站在壁炉前的地毯上，正向一圈怀着羡慕之情的朋友描述如果在场他会怎么干。看见托德，他大叫一声走上前来，搂住他的脖子，要拉他在客厅里凯旋式地绕场一周。托德却委婉地拒绝了他，一边脱开身子，一边温和地说：“做决策的是班杰，冲锋陷阵的主力是莫尔和兰特，我只是充当了一个普通的士兵，做得很少，也可以说没做什么。”他这种出人意料的态度，显然把动物们弄糊涂了，让他们傻了眼。托德感觉到，当他从一个个客人面前走过，谦虚地答谢他们时，他吸引了每一只动物的兴趣。

獾子班杰把一切安排得尽善尽美，宴会获得了巨大的成功。动物们有说有笑，逗闷子打趣，但是，理所当然坐在主位上的托德，自始至终眼睛看着鼻子尖，只对左右两侧的动物低声说几句令人愉快的闲话。他不时偷偷地瞄一眼獾子班杰和水鼠兰特。每次他望过去时，他们俩总是张大嘴巴，互相对视着。这给了托德极大的满足。晚会进行了一段时间，一些比较年轻活泼的动物耐不住了，交头接耳议论说，过去的好日子里宴会都很好玩，这一回不行了。有的就敲起桌子来，嚷嚷道：“托德！演讲！托德说上一段！唱歌！唱一支托德先生的歌！”托德只轻轻地摇摇头，举起一只爪子温和地表示反对。他殷勤地劝客人们多多享用美食，偶尔就时下大家关注的话题闲聊几句，还郑重其事地问候他们家庭中尚未成年、不能参加社交集会的成员。他以此向大家传达了一个信息：这次餐会是严格按照传统方式来进行的。

托德确确实实变了个样！

这次高潮事件过后，四只动物继续快快乐乐、心满意足地过他们的日子。这种生活虽说曾经被内战野蛮地打断过一阵子，但后来再也没有受到过叛乱或入侵的骚扰。托德和朋友们好好商量一番之后，选了一条漂亮的金项链，配上一只镶珍珠的小匣子，附上一封连獾子班杰也承认很谦虚知恩的感谢信，派人送给狱卒的女儿。接下来是火车司机，他为托德吃苦受累惹麻烦，所以得到了适当的酬谢和补偿。在獾子班杰的严厉逼迫下，就连船娘也被他们费了些周折寻找到，照价赔偿了她的马。不过，托德咬牙跺脚，对这件事极其不满，坚持认为自己是命运之神的工具，是被派来惩罚那些胳膊上长斑点、有眼无珠不识真绅士的胖女人的。其实，涉及的金额并非令人无法承受：当地估价员承认，那吉卜赛人给的价大体上差不离。

在悠长的夏日黄昏里，四个朋友有时会一起在野树林里散步。对他们来说，这林子现在已经是一块温温顺顺的地方。他们散步的情景真是令人愉快哟：居民们恭恭敬敬向他们问好，黄鼠狼妈妈们把小家伙带到洞口，指着他们，说道：“瞧，宝贝儿！那就是了不起的托德先生！走在他旁边的是勇敢的兰特，一位可怕的战士！再过去一点是有名的莫尔先生，你们常听爸爸说起的就是他！”宝宝们犯倔管不住的时候，妈妈们就说，要是他们再闹，再不听话，可怕的大灰獾就会把他们抓走。这真是对班杰的可耻诽谤：事实上，虽然他对社交界不感兴趣，却是相当喜欢孩子们。可是呀，拿这种话吓唬孩子，没有一回不是百分之百奏效的。

[1]尤利西斯是西方神话中的英雄，他在特洛伊战争后经历千辛万苦才得以返回家中。作者此处即是寓指托德经受磨难后最终得以重返家园。

[2]一种用蛋白、奶油、果酱、糕饼等做成的食物。

第一章　旋风

多萝西住在堪萨斯大草原中部，她同农夫亨利叔叔和他的妻子艾姆婶婶一起生活。他们的房子很小，因为建房子用的木料要用马车从好多英里外运来。这栋房子只有四面墙、地板和天花板围成的一间屋子；屋里有一只锈迹斑斑的煮饭炉、一个碗柜、一张桌子、三四把椅子，还有两张床。亨利叔叔和艾姆婶婶的大床摆在房间的一角，多萝西的小床摆在另一角。房子没有阁楼，也没有地下室，只在地板上挖了一个小洞，叫“旋风地窖”。万一刮起旋风，一家人可以躲进去。大风威力强劲，所过之处，无不墙倒屋塌。地板中央有一扇活板门，沿着梯子走下去，就到了又小又黑的地窖。

多萝西站在门口，朝四周望去，只见灰蒙蒙的大草原。这片广阔、平坦的原野四面延伸到天际，连一棵树、一座房子也没有。太阳炙烤着耕种过的土地，将它变成一大片灰色，布满小裂缝。就连草也不绿，因为长长的叶子梢儿被太阳晒焦，成了和四周一样的灰色。房子粉刷过一次，但是涂料被太阳晒得冒泡，又被雨水冲刷，现在这栋房子就像其他东西一样单调灰暗。

艾姆婶婶刚来这里住的时候，是一个年轻漂亮的妻子。日晒和风吹也改变了她。她眼睛里的神采消失了，只留下淡然的灰色；脸颊和嘴唇不再红润，也变成了灰色。她又瘦又憔悴，现在从来都不笑。多萝西是个孤儿，她刚到这里时，艾姆婶婶被这个孩子的笑声吓了一跳，只要多萝西欢快的笑声传进她的耳朵，她就捂紧胸口尖叫；她惊奇地看着这个小姑娘，不明白有什么好笑的。

亨利叔叔从来也不笑。他从早到晚辛勤劳动，不知道什么是快乐。他从长胡子到粗陋的靴子，浑身也灰蒙蒙的，表情严厉，很少说话。

是托托逗多萝西笑，不让她变得像周围其他东西一样灰蒙蒙。托托不是灰色的；它是一只黑色的小狗，缎子一样的长毛，黑色的小眼睛长在滑稽的小鼻子两边，欢快地闪闪发亮。托托整天玩耍，多萝西陪它玩，她非常喜爱托托。

但今天，他们没有玩。亨利叔叔坐在门前的台阶上，担忧地望向天空，天色比平时更灰暗。多萝西站在门前，怀里抱着托托，也望着天空。艾姆婶婶在洗盘子。

北方远远传来低沉的风吼，亨利叔叔和多萝西可以看见高草在风暴来临之前像波涛般翻滚。这时，南方的空中也传来尖利的呼啸声，他们朝那边转过头，看见从那个方向草的波涛也正一浪一浪地逼近。

亨利叔叔突然站起来。

“旋风要来了，艾姆。”他冲妻子喊道，“我去看看牲口。”说完，他就朝关牛马的牲口棚跑去。

艾姆婶婶放下手中的活儿，来到门边。只看了一眼，她就知道危险近在眼前。

“快，多萝西！”她尖叫道，“跑到地窖去！”

托托从多萝西的怀里跳出来，藏到床下，小姑娘去抓它。艾姆婶婶吓坏了，一把拉开地板上的活板门，沿着梯子爬进又小又黑的地窖。多萝西终于抓住了托托，要跟上婶婶。她已经走到屋子的中央，突然传来一阵猛烈的风啸声，房子剧烈地摇晃起来，多萝西脚下不稳，一屁股跌坐在地板上。

这时，一件奇怪的事发生了。

房子转动了两三下，缓缓升空。多萝西感觉自己像是坐在气球里往上升。

北风和南风在房子所在的地方会合，房子正好位于旋风中心。旋风中央的空气一般是静止的，但房子四周巨大的风压使它缓缓升高，直升到旋风的顶端，然后它就停在那里，随风飘移了好多英里。旋风带动房子，就像你拿起羽毛一样容易。

天色很暗，狂风在周围嘶吼，但多萝西发现她飞得挺轻松。房子起初旋转了几圈，有一次又倾斜得厉害，这之后她就觉得自己好像摇篮中的婴儿，被轻柔地摇晃着。

托托不喜欢这样。它大声吠叫着乱跑，一会儿跑到这里，一会儿跑到那里。而多萝西却静静地坐在地板上，等着看会发生什么。

有一次，托托离打开的活板门太近，掉了下去；小姑娘一开始以为自己永远失去了托托。可是不一会儿，她看见托托的一只耳朵竖在洞口，原来强大的气压托住了它，它掉不下去。她爬到洞口，抓住托托的耳朵，把它拉回屋里，然后关上活板门，这样就不会再发生意外了。

一小时又一小时过去了，多萝西渐渐战胜恐惧，但她觉得很孤独，四周狂风嘶吼，她几乎什么也听不见。一开始，她担心房子落地时自己会摔得粉碎，但几个小时过去了，什么可怕的事也没发生，她就不再担心，打算静静等待，看将来会怎样。最后，她爬过摇动的地板到自己的床边，躺了下来；托托跟着她，躺在她身边。

尽管房子在摇晃，风在呼啸，但多萝西很快闭上眼睛，睡熟了。

第二章　遇见芒奇金人

她被震醒了，这震动突然而剧烈，要不是多萝西躺在柔软的床上，就被震伤了。实际上，这震动使她屏住呼吸，想弄明白发生了什么事。托托冰凉的小鼻子贴着她的脸，惊恐地哀叫。多萝西坐起来，注意到房子不动了；天也不黑了，明亮的阳光照进窗口，小屋里亮堂堂。多萝西跳下床，跑去开门，托托紧跟在她身后。

小姑娘惊叫一声，她环顾四周，看到眼前奇妙的景象，眼睛睁得越发大了。

旋风轻轻地——对旋风来说很轻——把房子安放在一片异常美丽的国度中央。这里到处草儿青青，高大的树木上结满甜美的果子。坡上到处鲜花绚烂，树林间、灌木丛中鸟儿一身珍奇、鲜艳的羽毛，扑棱着翅膀在歌唱。不远处是一条闪亮的小溪，在翠绿的河岸间奔流。小溪那潺潺的低语，对一个长期在干旱的、灰蒙蒙的大草原上生活的小姑娘来说，真是动听极了。

多萝西站在那里，热切地望着奇异、美丽的景色，这时，她注意到有一小群怪模怪样的人朝她走来，她从没见过长这么怪的人。他们没有她平常见到的大人那样高，可也不是特别矮小。其实，他们跟多萝西差不多高，在她这个年纪，她算个子高的，但这群人看上去比多萝西年纪大很多。

这三男一女，都打扮古怪。他们戴着圆帽，尖尖的帽顶有一英尺高，帽檐缀着小铃铛，他们一走动，这些小铃铛就发出清脆的叮当声。男人戴蓝帽，女人戴白帽。那女人身穿白袍，衣褶从两肩垂落，上面点缀着小星星，在太阳底下像钻石一样闪闪发亮。男人们穿蓝衣，和帽子的色调一样，脚蹬锃亮的靴子，靴筒顶端有厚厚的卷边。多萝西心想，这三个男人和亨利叔叔岁数差不多，因为其中两个长着大胡子。不过那个矮个子女人肯定年纪更大。她满脸皱纹，头发差不多全白了，走路姿势非常僵硬。

多萝西站在门口，这几个人朝房子走来，不一会儿，他们停下了脚步，交头接耳一番，像是不敢继续往前走。最后，那矮个老太太走到多萝西面前，深鞠一躬，用甜美的声音说道：

“欢迎你，最高贵的魔法师，欢迎来到芒奇金国。我们非常感激你杀死了邪恶的东方女巫，使我们的人民获得自由。”

听到这番话，多萝西很吃惊。矮个老太太管她叫魔法师，还说她杀死了邪恶的东方女巫，这是什么意思？多萝西是个天真的小姑娘，没伤害过什么，她被旋风带到离家很多英里的地方；她可从来没有杀死过任何东西。

但矮个老太太显然等着她回答；于是，多萝西犹豫地说：

“你真好，可是你肯定搞错了。我什么也没杀死啊。”

“不管怎么说，是你的房子杀死了她，”矮个老太太笑道，“这是一回事。看！”她指着房子一角，又说道，“她的两只脚还伸在木块下。”

多萝西往那边看去，吓得轻轻叫了一声。是的，就在架起房子的大梁一角下面，伸出两只脚，脚上穿着尖头银鞋。

“噢，天哪！噢，天哪！”多萝西喊道，惊愕地紧握双手，“房子肯定掉到了她身上。我们该怎么办啊？”

“不怎么办啊。”矮个老太太平静地说。

“可她是谁？”多萝西问。

“她是邪恶的东方女巫，我刚才说了。”矮个老太太回答，“她奴役所有芒奇金人好多年了，让他们日日夜夜伺候她。现在他们都自由了，很感激你帮忙。”

“芒奇金人是谁？”多萝西问。

“他们是在这片东方土地上生活的人，而这片土地由邪恶的女巫统治着。”

“你是芒奇金人吗？”多萝西问。

“不是，但我是他们的朋友，我生活在北方土地上。芒奇金人看见东方女巫死了，就赶紧捎信给我，我马上就来了。我是北方女巫。”

“噢，天哪！”多萝西叫道，“你真的是女巫？”

“真的。”矮个老太太答道，“但我是好女巫，人们都喜欢我。邪恶女巫统治着这地方，她法力比我强大，不然我自个儿早就让这些人自由了。”

“可我还以为所有的女巫都是邪恶的。”小姑娘面对真正的女巫，有些害怕。

“噢，不，这真是个大误会。整个奥兹国只有四个女巫，其中两个，就是住在北方和南方的女巫，是好的。我知道真是这样的，因为我自己就是其中一个，错不了。住在东方和西方的那两个女巫确实很邪恶；但现在你杀死了她俩中的一个，那么整个奥兹国就只剩下一个邪恶女巫，就是住在西方的女巫。”

“可是，”多萝西想了一会儿，说，“艾姆婶婶告诉过我，女巫全都死了，好多好多年以前就死了。”

“艾姆婶婶是谁？”矮个老太太问。

“她是我婶婶，住在堪萨斯州，我就是从那里来的。”

北方女巫低头看着地面，好像在思考。过了一会儿，她抬起头，说：

“我不知道堪萨斯州在哪里，我从来没听谁提过这个国家。你告诉我，这是个文明国家吗？”

“是的。”多萝西回答。

“这就对了。我想，文明国家现在已经没有女巫、男巫，也没有女魔法师或男魔法师了。但是，你看，奥兹国从来没有过文明，因为我们与世界的其他地方隔绝了。所以，我们中间还有女巫和男巫。”

“谁是男巫？”多萝西问。

“奥兹本人就是大巫师。”女巫压低嗓子回答，“他的魔力比我们几个加在一块儿还要强。他住在翡翠城。”

多萝西正想再问一个问题，突然，一直站在旁边没出声的芒奇金人大叫起来，他们指着邪恶女巫躺着的屋角。

“怎么了？”矮个老太太问，她朝那边看了一眼，就笑了。死去的女巫的两只脚完全不见了，只剩下一双银鞋。

“她年纪太大了，”北方女巫解释道，“被太阳晒干了。这就是她的下场。这双银鞋归你了，你应该穿上。”她说着弯身捡起鞋子，抖抖上面的灰土，递给多萝西。

“东方女巫很为这双银鞋得意，”一个芒奇金人说，“它们带有一些魔力，但我们从来不知道究竟是什么魔力。”

多萝西把鞋拿进屋，放到桌上。之后，她又走出来，对芒奇金人说：

“我要赶紧回到我叔叔婶婶那里，他们肯定会担心我的。你们能帮我找到回去的路吗？”

芒奇金人和女巫先是看看彼此，然后又看看多萝西，最后摇摇头。

“往东去，离这里不远，”一个芒奇金人说，“是一片大沙漠，没有人能够活着走出去。”

“南方也一样，”另一个说，“我去过那里，亲眼见过。南边是夸德令人的国家。”

“我听说，”又一个说，“西方也是这样。那个国家生活着温基人，由邪恶的西方女巫统治。她会把过路人抓去做奴隶。”

“北方是我的家，”老太太说，“那四周和这奥兹国周围的是同一个大沙漠。亲爱的，恐怕你得和我们一起生活了。”

听到这话，多萝西抽抽搭搭地哭了，因为在这些陌生人中，她感到孤独。她的眼泪好像使好心的芒奇金人伤心起来，因为他们立刻掏出手绢，也哭了。这时，那个矮个老太太摘下帽子，把帽尖顶在鼻尖上，她声音庄重地数着“一，二，三”。帽子立时变成一块石板，上面用白色粉笔写着几个大字：

“让多萝西去翡翠城”。

矮个老太太从鼻子上取下石板，读出上面的话，她问：

“亲爱的，你叫多萝西吗？”

“是的。”小姑娘抬起头，擦擦眼泪。

“那你必须去翡翠城。也许奥兹会帮助你。”

“这座城在哪里？”多萝西问。

“就在这个国家的正中央，由奥兹统治，他就是我跟你说的大巫师。”

“他是好人吗？”多萝西担心地问。

“他是个好巫师。他是不是人，我就不知道了，因为我从来没见过他。”

“我怎么去那儿呢？”多萝西问。

“你得走路去。路途遥远，你要经过的土地有时舒适宜人，有时又黑暗可怕。不过，我会使出我知道的全部魔法，保护你不受伤害。”

“你不和我一起去吗？”小姑娘恳求道，她已经开始把矮个老太太当成她唯一的朋友了。

“不行，我不能去，”她回答，“但我会给你一个吻，没有人敢伤害一个被北方女巫吻过的人。”

她走近多萝西，在她额头上轻轻一吻。不久之后，多萝西发现北方女巫嘴唇触碰过的地方，留下了一个闪亮的圆形记号。

“通往翡翠城的路铺着黄砖，”女巫说，“所以你不会迷路。你见到奥兹，不要害怕，把你的故事讲给他听，请他帮助你。再见了，亲爱的。”

三个芒奇金人向她深鞠一躬，祝她旅途愉快。说完，他们穿过树林，离开了。女巫朝多萝西友好地点点头，随后左脚跟着地转了三圈，立即消失了。这让小托托吃惊极了，女巫一消失，它就在她身后大声吠叫，因为女巫在的时候，它吓得都不敢叫。

但多萝西知道她是女巫，料到她会那样消失，所以一点也不吃惊。

第三章　多萝西救稻草人

只剩下多萝西自己了，她开始觉得饿了。于是，她走到橱柜边，切了几片面包，抹上黄油。她分给托托一些，然后从架子上取下水桶，提到小溪那里，打了满满一桶澄澈、闪亮的溪水。托托跑到树下，冲着树上的鸟儿吠叫。多萝西过去逮托托，抬头看见枝头挂着鲜美的果子，于是她就摘下几颗，发现正好当早餐。

接着，她回到屋里，和托托一起痛快地喝饱清凉、澄澈的溪水，她准备要踏上去往翡翠城的旅途了。

多萝西只有一件换洗衣服，恰好干干净净地挂在小床旁的挂钩上。这是一条蓝白格子的棉布连衣裙，因为洗过很多次，蓝色褪色了，但还是很漂亮。小姑娘仔细梳洗一番，穿上干净的格子裙，系好粉色的太阳帽。她拿了一只小篮子，装满从橱柜里拿出的面包，再盖上一块白布。接着，她一低头，看到脚上的鞋破旧不堪。

“这双鞋肯定不能走远路，托托。”她说。托托仰着头，小黑眼睛望着多萝西的脸，它摇摇尾巴，表示明白她的意思。

这时，多萝西看到了桌上的银鞋，这双鞋从前是东方女巫的。

“不知道我穿合不合脚？”她对托托说，“穿这双鞋走远路正合适，穿不坏。”

她脱下自己的旧皮鞋，试穿上银鞋，这双鞋就像专为她定做的一样合脚。

最后，她挽起篮子。

“走啦，托托。”她说，“我们去翡翠城，问问大巫师奥兹怎么回堪萨斯去。”

多萝西关上门，上好锁，又小心地把钥匙放进裙子口袋。就这样，她起身上路，托托一副认真模样，快步小跑跟着她。

附近有好几条路，但多萝西没费多少工夫就找到了铺着黄砖的那条。不一会儿，她就步伐轻快地朝翡翠城赶去，银鞋踏着坚硬的黄砖路面，发出悦耳的叮叮声。阳光灿烂，鸟儿歌声美妙，多萝西几乎没有像大家可能认为的那样，因为突然被大风刮到远离家乡的陌生地方而感到沮丧。

她走在路上，惊奇地发现周围的景色十分美。路旁是整齐的篱笆，刷成清爽的蓝色，篱笆那边是成片的田地，种着许多庄稼和蔬菜。显然，芒奇金人都是种田的好把式，能取得很好的收成。多萝西不时路过一所房子，房子里的人都出来看她，深深地鞠躬送她离去；人人都知道是多萝西杀死了邪恶女巫，使他们重获自由。芒奇金人的房子外观古怪，每一所都是圆形的，都有一个大圆屋顶。所有房子都刷成蓝色，因为这个东方国家的人最喜欢蓝色。

傍晚，多萝西经过一天的长途跋涉，十分乏累，她开始考虑该去哪里过夜。这时，她走到一所房子门口，这所房子比别的房子都大。门前的绿草地上，有不少男男女女在跳舞。五个小提琴手卖力地拉琴，人们欢笑歌唱。旁边的大桌子上摆满了美味的水果、坚果、馅饼、蛋糕，还有许多别的美食。

人们和善地跟多萝西打招呼，邀请她共进晚餐并在他们这里过夜。这所房子的主人是这地方最富有的一个芒奇金人，他和朋友们在这里欢聚，庆祝脱离邪恶女巫的奴役，重获自由。

多萝西吃了一顿丰盛的晚餐。那个富有的芒奇金人叫波克，他亲自招待多萝西。饭后，多萝西坐在长椅上，看人们跳舞。

波克看见她穿着银鞋，就说：

“你一定是个大魔法师。”

“为什么？”小姑娘问。

“因为你穿着银鞋，还杀死了邪恶女巫。还有，你的连衣裙上有白色格子，只有女巫和魔法师才穿白色衣服。”

“我的裙子是蓝白两色的。”多萝西说着，拉平裙子上的褶皱。

“你这么穿非常好。”波克说，“蓝色是芒奇金人的颜色，白色是女巫的颜色。这样，我们就知道你是个友好的女巫。”

多萝西不知道应该怎么回答，因为所有的人好像都以为她是个女巫，可她十分清楚自己只是个普普通通的小姑娘，很偶然地被旋风带到这个陌生的地方。

多萝西看人们跳舞看累了，波克就领她进了房子，来到一个摆着漂亮小床的房间。床上铺着蓝布床单，多萝西美美地睡到天亮。托托蜷着身子睡在她旁边的蓝色毯子上。

多萝西边吃丰盛的早餐，边看着一个小不点儿的芒奇金宝宝和托托玩，小宝宝拽托托的尾巴，又叫又笑，这把多萝西逗乐了。托托勾起了所有人的好奇心，因为这之前他们谁也没见过狗。

“这里离翡翠城多远啊？”小姑娘问。

“不知道，”波克严肃地回答，“我从来没去过那里。要是没有什么事非要和奥兹打交道，还是离他远一点好。但我知道翡翠城还很远，要走好几天。这里富饶舒适，可你要走过崎岖危险的地方，才能到达旅途的终点。”

这番话让多萝西有些担心，不过，她知道只有大巫师奥兹才能帮她回到堪萨斯州，于是她做出勇敢的决定，就是不回头。

她告别了朋友，又沿着黄砖路出发了。走了几英里后，她觉得该停下歇歇脚，于是爬上路边的篱笆，坐下来。篱笆那边有一大片玉米地。多萝西看见不远处有个稻草人，高高地绑在一根竿子上，让鸟雀不能靠近成熟的玉米。

多萝西手托下巴，望着稻草人出神。他的脑袋是一只装满稻草的小麻袋，画着眼睛、鼻子、嘴巴，代表一张脸。一顶破旧的蓝色尖顶帽，从前是哪个芒奇金人的，现在戴在他头上。他身上穿着一套蓝色衣服，已经破旧褪色，里面也塞满稻草。脚上是一双蓝色筒旧靴子，与这国度里所有人一样。他背后绑着竿子，竖在玉米地里，比玉米秆还高。

多萝西仔细盯着稻草人那张画上去的、奇怪的脸，惊奇地发现他的一只眼睛竟然在朝自己慢慢眨动。一开始，她以为自己看错了，因为堪萨斯没有一个稻草人眨眼睛；可是现在这个稻草人冲她友好地点头呢。于是，多萝西爬下篱笆，走近稻草人，这时托托绕着竿子，边跑边叫。

“你好。”稻草人哑着嗓子说。

“你会说话？”小姑娘很惊讶。

“当然。”稻草人回答，“你好吗？”

“我很好，谢谢。”多萝西礼貌地回答，“你呢？”

“我感觉不好。”稻草人微笑着说，“因为整日整夜被挂在这里吓唬乌鸦，真没趣。”

“你不能下来吗？”多萝西问。

“不能。我后背绑在这根竿子上。如果你能把竿子拿走，我会很感激你的。”

多萝西伸出双臂，把稻草人从竿子上取下来，因为他身子里面塞的是稻草，所以很轻。

“谢谢你。”等稻草人被放到地上，他说，“我觉得自己是个新人了。”

多萝西听到这话，有些糊涂。听一个里面塞着稻草的人说话，看他鞠躬还跟自己并肩走路，这真稀奇。

“你是谁？”稻草人舒展身子，打了个哈欠，问道，“要去哪儿？”

“我叫多萝西。”小姑娘说，“我要去翡翠城，请伟大的奥兹送我回堪萨斯。”

“翡翠城在哪儿？”稻草人问，“奥兹是谁？”

“啊，你不知道吗？”多萝西吃惊地反问道。

“是的，我真不知道。我什么也不知道。你看，我是稻草填充起来的，所以我根本没有脑子。”他伤心地回答。

“噢，”多萝西说，“我很难过。”

“你觉得，”稻草人问，“如果我和你一起去翡翠城，奥兹会给我些脑子吗？”

“我说不准，”多萝西回答，“不过如果你愿意的话，可以和我一起去。就算奥兹一点脑子也不给你，你的情况也不会比现在更糟。”

“那倒没错。”稻草人说，“你知道，”他诚恳地接着说，“我不介意自己的腿、胳膊和身子是填充的，因为这样我不会受伤。要是有人踩我的脚趾或者用针扎我，也不要紧，因为我感觉不到。但我不想被人叫笨蛋，可是如果我的脑袋一直填满稻草，而不是像你一样装满脑子的话，我怎么能知道哪怕一点事情呢？”

“我理解你的感受。”小姑娘说，她真的为稻草人难过，“如果你跟我一起走，我会请求奥兹尽力帮助你。”

“谢谢。”稻草人感激地说。

他们回到路上。多萝西扶稻草人翻过篱笆，之后他们就沿着黄砖路继续往翡翠城去。

一开始，托托不喜欢稻草人加入。它绕着稻草人一个劲地嗅，仿佛怀疑稻草里面藏着一窝老鼠，还不时凶巴巴地朝稻草人大叫。

“别在意托托。”多萝西对她的新朋友说，“它从不咬人。”

“噢，我不害怕。”稻草人回答，“它伤害不了稻草。请让我为你提篮子，我不会在乎，因为我不会觉得累。我要告诉你一个秘密，”他一边走一边说，“在这世界上，我只怕一件东西。”

“是什么？”多萝西问，“是那个做出你的芒奇金农夫吗？”

“不是，”稻草人说，“我害怕划燃的火柴。”

第四章　穿过森林的路

走了几个小时，路开始变得崎岖，越来越难走，稻草人经常被高低不平的黄砖绊倒。有的地方，黄砖甚至破碎或者干脆不见了，地面坑坑洼洼，这时，托托就跳过去，多萝西就绕着走。可是稻草人没有脑子，只会笔直地往前走，于是他一脚踩进坑里，直挺挺地摔倒在坚硬的砖头上。不过，他从来不会受伤。多萝西看见后，就把他提起来，帮他重新站好。对刚才的倒霉事，他和多萝西一起开心地大笑。

这里的农场不像已被他们远远留在身后的那些地方，没有得到那么精心的照料。房子和果树也都少了，他们越往前走，沿路的景象越荒凉、冷清。

中午，他们在靠近一条小溪的路边坐下。多萝西打开篮子，拿出几片面包。她递给稻草人一片，但稻草人没要。

“我从来不饿，”他说，“这是一件幸运的事。我的嘴只是画上去的，要是割开一道口子，我也能吃饭。但那样的话，填充我的稻草就会钻出来，会破坏我脑袋的形状。”

多萝西立刻就看出确实是这样，于是她只是点点头，继续吃面包。

“跟我讲讲你自己的事，还有你来自的那个国家。”稻草人等多萝西吃完，说道。多萝西就把堪萨斯所有的事都跟稻草人说了，告诉他那里一切都是灰蒙蒙的，还告诉他旋风怎样把她带到了这个奇异的奥兹国。

稻草人认真地听完，然后说：

“我不明白你为什么想离开这个美丽的国家，而回到那个你叫作堪萨斯的干旱的、灰蒙蒙的地方。”

“因为你没有脑子。”小姑娘说，“不管我们的家乡有多么干燥、多么灰蒙蒙，我们这些有血有肉的人都宁愿住在那里，而不愿住在别的国家，就算它再美也不行。哪里也比不上家乡。”

稻草人叹了口气。

“我当然明白不了，”他说，“要是你们的脑袋里塞的是稻草，就像我一样，也许你们就会都住在美丽的地方，而堪萨斯就会根本没人住。你们有脑子，这是堪萨斯的幸运。”

“我们休息时，你给我们讲个故事好吗？”小姑娘请求道。

听到这话，稻草人用责备的眼神望着多萝西，回答道：

“我的生命太短暂，所以我什么事也不知道。我是前天才被农夫做好的。那之前世界上发生的事，我一点都不知道。幸运的是，农夫扎好我的脑袋以后，首先就给我画上耳朵，于是我听到了那会儿正在发生的事。他身边还有一个芒奇金人，我听到的第一件事是，那个农夫问：

“‘你觉得这两只耳朵怎么样？’

“‘它们不直。’另一个芒奇金人回答。

“‘没关系，’那个农夫说，‘反正它们还是耳朵。’这话倒是很对。

“‘现在，我要做眼睛了。’那个农夫说着，给我画了右眼。他一画好，我就发现自己怀着强烈的好奇心看着他，看着我周围的一切，因为这是我第一次看到世界。

“‘这只眼睛很漂亮。’那个芒奇金人看着农夫，评论道，‘蓝漆做眼睛的颜色正好。’

“‘我想把另一只眼睛画得更大一点。’农夫说。第二只眼睛画好后，我看得比之前更清楚了。随后，他又给我画了鼻子和嘴。但我没有说话，因为那时候我还不知道嘴是用来做什么的。我看着他们给我做身子、胳膊和腿，觉得很有趣。最后，他们固定好我的脑袋，那一刻，我非常自豪，以为自己也和别人一样。

“‘这家伙会很快吓走乌鸦的，’农夫说，‘他看着真像个人。’

“‘对啊，他就是人。’另一个说。我很赞同他的说法。那个农夫把我夹在胳膊下，走进玉米地，将我挂在一根高高的竿子上，你们就是在那儿看到我的。之后，他和他的朋友很快就离开了，留下我一个人。

“我不想这样被他们丢下，所以就想跟他们走。但我的脚着不了地，我只好待在竿子上。我过得孤独，因为没有什么事可想，毕竟我才被做好不久。许多乌鸦和小鸟飞进玉米地，但一看见我，它们就又飞走，以为我是个芒奇金人；这让我很开心，让我觉得自己是个重要人物。后来，一只老乌鸦一点点飞近我，他对着我仔细端详一番后，落在我肩膀上，说道：

“‘我怀疑那农夫想用这个蠢办法愚弄我。任何有脑子的乌鸦都看得出来，你不过是稻草填充的。’说着，他跳到我脚边，尽情地吃玉米。其他鸟看见我伤害不了那老乌鸦，也来吃玉米，这样不一会儿，我身边就围了一大群鸟。

“为此，我很伤心，因为这说明我根本不是一个称职的稻草人。但老乌鸦安慰我说：‘如果你脑袋里有脑子的话，就会像他们任何人一样棒，甚至比其中一些人还要棒。脑子是这个世界上唯一值得拥有的东西，不管你是乌鸦还是人。’

“乌鸦们走后，我琢磨这件事，决定尽力弄些脑子来。这是运气好，你们路过，把我从竿子上放下来，照你们说，我们一到翡翠城，伟大的奥兹肯定就会给我一些脑子。”

“我希望是这样，”多萝西真诚地说，“既然你好像急着要得到脑子。”

“噢，是的；我很着急。”稻草人回答，“知道自己是个傻瓜，这感觉真不好。”

“那好，”小姑娘说，“我们走吧。”她把篮子递给稻草人。

这段路边上一根篱笆也没有，路两旁是坑坑洼洼、没有开垦的荒地。傍晚，他们来到一大片森林边上，这里树木高大，一棵挨着一棵，茂密的树枝在黄砖路上方交叠，遮住了阳光，树下几乎一片黑暗。但是几个旅行者没有停步，继续走进了森林。

“如果这条路能进森林，那肯定也能出去，”稻草人说，“翡翠城在路的另一头，所以我们必须沿着这条路走，不管它通向哪里。”

“这个谁都知道。”多萝西说。

“当然；所以我才知道啊。”稻草人回答，“如果需要脑子才能弄明白，我无论如何也说不出来。”

约莫一个小时后，光线渐渐暗淡，他们在黑漆漆的森林里一路磕磕绊绊。多萝西什么也看不见，但托托能看见，因为有的狗在暗处也看得清清楚楚；而稻草人说他看得像白天一样清楚。于是，多萝西挽着稻草人的胳膊，安安稳稳地往前走。

“如果你看见什么房子，或者什么我们可以过夜的地方，”她说，“你一定要告诉我；因为摸黑赶路太不舒服了。”

没多久，稻草人站住脚。

“我看见我们右边有个小屋，”他说，“是用圆木和树枝建成的。我们过去吗？”

“当然过去。”小姑娘说，“我累坏了。”

于是，稻草人领着多萝西穿过森林，走到小木屋门口。多萝西走进小屋，发现屋角有一张干树叶铺成的床。她立刻躺下，不一会儿就沉沉入睡，托托就卧在她身边。稻草人永远也不知疲倦，他站在另一个角落，耐心地等待清晨到来。

第五章　解救铁皮樵夫

多萝西醒来时，太阳照进森林，托托早已出去追逐周围的小鸟和松鼠。她坐起身，四下张望。稻草人还耐心地站在那个角落，等着她。

“我们得去找水。”她对稻草人说。

“你为什么要水？”稻草人问。

“洗净脸上赶路的灰尘，喝点水，不让干面包卡在嗓子里。”

“血肉之躯肯定有不便之处，”稻草人若有所思，“你必须睡觉，还要吃饭喝水。可是，你有脑子，能真正思考，这些麻烦算不了什么。”

他们离开小木屋，在森林里走，直到看见一股清澈的泉水。多萝西喝了水，洗了脸，吃过早餐。她看到篮子里剩的面包不多了，幸好稻草人不用吃东西，因为食物连自己和托托吃一天都不太够。

她吃完早餐，正要回到黄砖路上，突然附近传来一声低沉的呻吟，她吓了一跳。

“什么声音？”她怯怯地问。

“我想不出来，”稻草人回答，“但我们可以去看看。”

就在这时，又是一声呻吟，似乎就从身后传来。他们转回身，在森林里又走了几步，这时，多萝西发现一束阳光照进林间，把什么东西照得闪闪发亮。她朝那儿跑过去，突然收住脚，发出轻声的惊叫。

一棵大树已经有一部分被砍断，树旁站着一个全身用铁皮做成的人，两手举着斧头。他的头、胳膊和腿都连在身上，但他站着一动不动，好像根本活动不了。

多萝西惊奇地看着铁皮人，稻草人也一样，而托托尖声叫唤，一口咬住他的腿，这硌痛了托托的牙。

“是你在呻吟吗？”多萝西问。

“是我，”铁皮人说，“是我。我已经呻吟一年多了，以前从没有人听见，也没有人来帮助我。”

“我能帮上什么忙？”多萝西柔声问道，她被铁皮人忧伤的声音感染了。

“拿来油壶，给我的关节上上油。”他答道，“我的关节锈得很厉害，一点也动弹不得；如果上足油，我马上就又好了。油壶放在我小屋里的一个架子上。”

多萝西马上跑回小木屋，找到油壶，然后跑回来，急切地问：“你的关节在哪儿？”

“先给我的脖子上油。”铁皮樵夫回答。于是，多萝西给他的脖子上了油，因为那儿锈得太厉害，所以稻草人扶住铁皮脑袋，轻轻地左右摇晃，直到脖子转动自如，铁皮人终于可以自己转头了。

“现在给我胳膊的关节上油吧。”他说。多萝西又给胳膊上油，稻草人小心翼翼地弯曲它们，直到胳膊上的锈除净，像新的一样。

铁皮樵夫满意地舒了一口气，把斧头放下，斜靠在树上。

“太舒服了。”他说，“自从锈住之后，我就一直举着斧头，我很高兴终于可以放下了。现在，如果你们给我腿上的关节上点油，我就又能正常了。”

于是，他们就给铁皮樵夫的腿上油，直到他的腿活动自如；他一再感谢他们解救了自己。铁皮樵夫看起来很有礼貌，很懂得感恩。

“要不是你们路过，我可能要在这里站一辈子，”他说，“所以你们真是救了我的命。你们怎么到这儿的？”

“我们要去翡翠城见伟大的奥兹，”多萝西回答，“在你的小木屋过了个夜。”

“你们为什么想见奥兹？”他问。

“我想请他送我回堪萨斯，稻草人想请他给自己的脑袋装些脑子。”她回答道。

铁皮樵夫似乎沉思了一会儿，然后说道：

“你觉得奥兹能给我一颗心吗？”

“哎，我觉得能，”多萝西回答，“这就像给稻草人脑子一样好办。”

“没错。”铁皮樵夫回答，“那要是你们允许我加入，我就也去翡翠城，请奥兹帮助我。”

“来吧。”稻草人热情地说。多萝西又补充说，自己很高兴有铁皮樵夫做伴。于是，铁皮樵夫扛起斧头，他们几个穿过森林，直走到铺着黄砖的路上。

铁皮樵夫已经让多萝西把油壶装进了篮子。“因为，”他说，“如果我淋了雨，又锈住了，我会非常需要油壶。”

铁皮樵夫新加入队伍，这对大家来说挺幸运的，因为他们才上路没多久，就走到一个地方，树木和树枝特别茂密，挡住道路，他们过不去了。还好，铁皮樵夫挥动斧头，卖力地劈砍，不一会儿就为大家清理出一条通道。

大家一边走，多萝西一边认真地想事，所以没注意到稻草人一脚踏进地上的坑，滚到了路旁。他只得喊多萝西扶他起来。

“你为什么不绕开坑呢？”铁皮樵夫问。

“我脑子不够使。”稻草人高兴地回答，“我的脑袋塞满了稻草，你知道的，我就是为此要去找奥兹，请他给我一些脑子。”

“噢，我明白了。”铁皮樵夫说，“可是脑子毕竟不是世界上最好的东西。”

“你有脑子吗？”稻草人问。

“没有，我脑袋空空，”樵夫回答，“但我曾经有脑子，也有一颗心；所以，我两样都尝试过，我宁愿有一颗心。”

“那是为什么？”稻草人问。

“我给你讲讲我的故事，你就知道了。”

于是，他们在森林里走着，铁皮樵夫讲起了下面的故事：

“我是一个樵夫的儿子，他在森林里砍树，然后把木头卖掉，以此为生。我长大后，也成了一名樵夫。父亲去世后，我照顾老母亲，直到她也去世。后来，我打定主意要结婚，而不是独自生活，这样就不会孤单了。

“有一位芒奇金姑娘，她非常美貌，我很快就一心一意地爱上了她。她答应，只要我攒够钱，能给她建一栋好一点的房子，她就嫁给我；所以，我开始比以前更卖力地干活儿。可是，姑娘和一个老妇人一起生活，那老妇人不想让姑娘嫁给任何人，因为她自己太懒了，希望姑娘留在身边，给她煮饭、做家务。所以，老妇人去找邪恶的东方女巫，许诺要是女巫阻止了这桩婚事，就给女巫两只羊和一头牛。于是，邪恶的女巫对我的斧头施了魔法。有一天，我正在奋力砍树，因为我急着要尽快建新房、讨媳妇，这时，斧头突然从手中滑落，砍掉了我的左腿。

“一开始，这似乎特别不幸，因为我知道一个独腿的人做不好伐木工。于是，我找到一位铁匠，让他用铁皮给我做了一条新腿。我一适应这条铁皮腿，它就活动自如了。可我的做法惹恼了邪恶的东方女巫，因为她许诺那老妇人，要让我娶不了漂亮的芒奇金姑娘。后来，我又开始砍树时，斧头滑落，砍掉了我的右腿。我又去找铁匠，他又给我装了一条铁皮腿。这之后，被施了魔咒的斧头又先后砍掉了我的两条胳膊；但这没什么可怕的，我把它们换成了铁皮的。后来，邪恶的女巫又让我的斧头滑落，这次把我的脑袋砍了下来。起初，我以为自己完了。但铁匠碰巧路过，他给我装上了新的铁皮脑袋。

“那时，我以为自己已经打败了邪恶女巫，干活儿比以前更卖劲了；但是我想不到自己的敌人多么残忍。她想出了一个新办法，来消灭我对芒奇金姑娘的爱。她让我的斧头再次滑落，这次斧头正划过我的身体，把我劈成两半。铁匠又来帮忙，他给我做了一个铁皮身体，用关节把我的铁皮胳膊、腿还有脑袋固定到身上，这样我就能像以前一样活动自如。可是，唉！我现在没有心了，所以我不再爱那个芒奇金姑娘，不在乎和不和她结婚。我想，她还和那老妇人住在一起，等着我去娶她。

“我的身体在阳光下闪闪发亮，我对此很骄傲，这下斧头滑落也不要紧了，因为它不能割伤我。只有一个危险，就是我的关节会生锈；但我的小木屋里一直放着一只油壶，我留心在需要的时候给自己上油。然而，有一天我忘记上油，而且遇上了暴风雨，没等我意识到危险，我的关节就锈住了，于是我只能站在林子里，直到你们过来帮忙。这经历非常可怕，但我在这里站了一年，有的是时间思考，我想自己最大的损失是失去了心。恋爱时，我是世上最快乐的人；但谁也不会爱一个没有心的人，所以我决定去找奥兹，请他给我一颗心。如果他给我一颗心，我就回去娶芒奇金姑娘。”

多萝西和稻草人都对铁皮樵夫的故事很有兴趣，现在他们知道了为什么他这么急着要得到一颗心。

稻草人说：“我仍然要脑子而不是心；因为一个傻子就算有一颗心，他也不知道能做什么。”

“我要心，”铁皮樵夫说，“因为脑子不能让人快乐，而快乐是世上最美好的东西。”

多萝西什么也没说，因为她搞不清两位朋友谁说得对。她决定只要自己能回到堪萨斯，回到艾姆婶婶身边，那樵夫没有脑子而稻草人没有心，或者他们都得到自己想要的，就不那么要紧了。

多萝西最担心的是，面包只剩下一点，她和托托再吃一顿，篮子就空了。樵夫和稻草人确实什么也不吃，但她不是用铁皮或者稻草做的，不吃东西可活不下去。

第六章　胆小狮

这段时间，多萝西和她的伙伴们一直走在密林中。这条路还是铺着黄砖，但被厚厚的枯枝败叶覆盖，所以一点也不好走。

这一带森林中，鸟儿很少，因为它们喜欢阳光充足的旷野。可时不时，藏身茂密树丛中的野兽会发出一声低沉的吼叫。小女孩听到这声音，吓得心怦怦急跳，她不知道这是什么东西发出的；然而，托托知道，它紧贴着多萝西腿边走，都不敢叫一声来回应。

“还有多久，”小女孩问铁皮樵夫，“我们才能走出森林？”

“不知道，”铁皮樵夫回答，“我从没去过翡翠城。不过，我爸爸去过一次，那时候我还小。他说路途遥远，要穿过一片危险的区域，虽然奥兹住的那座城附近风景很美。不过只要带上油壶，我就不怕，什么也伤害不到稻草人，而你的额头上有好女巫的吻痕，它能保护你不受伤害。”

“可是，托托！”小女孩焦急地说，“什么来保护它？”

“要是他遇上危险，我们就得亲自保护它。”铁皮樵夫答道。

话音未落，森林中传来一声可怕的嘶吼，接着，一头大狮子跳到路上。他一挥爪子，稻草人就被打倒，骨碌碌滚到路边，然后他用锋利的爪子攻击铁皮樵夫。樵夫被打翻在地，一动不动，可是令狮子大吃一惊的是，铁皮上一点爪印也没有。

小托托现在要面对敌人了，它吠叫着冲向狮子。那只大野兽张嘴就要咬小狗，多萝西害怕托托被咬死，就不顾危险，冲上前照着狮子的鼻子就是狠狠一巴掌，同时还喊叫道：

“你敢咬托托！你应该感到羞愧，像你这样的大家伙，居然咬一只可怜的小狗！”

“我没咬它。”狮子一边争辩，一边用爪子揉被多萝西打中的鼻子。

“没咬着，但是你想。”她反驳道，“你只不过是个大个头的胆小鬼。”

“我知道，”狮子说，羞愧地低下头，“我一直都知道。但我能怎么办？”

“我不知道，我肯定。想想吧，你竟然打一个可怜的稻草填充的人！”

“他是填充的？”狮子惊奇地问，他看着多萝西捡起稻草人，把他两脚立起来，拍打几下，稻草人恢复了原来的样子。

“他当然是填充的。”多萝西说，她气还没消。

“难怪他那么容易翻倒。”狮子说，“看他那样骨碌碌滚，我心里很吃惊。另一个也是填充的吗？”

“不，他是铁做的。”多萝西说着，扶起樵夫。

“所以他差点磨钝我的爪子，”狮子说，“我听到刮铁皮的声音，就脊背发凉。这是什么小动物，你这么护着它？”

“它是我的狗，托托。”多萝西说。

“它是铁做的，还是填充的？”狮子问。

“都不是。它是一只，呃，一只有血有肉的狗。”

“噢！它是个稀奇的家伙，我看看，个头可真小。没有谁会想咬这小不点儿，除了我这种胆小鬼。”狮子伤心地继续说。

“什么使你胆小？”多萝西好奇地望着这头大野兽，他跟小马一般大。

“这是个谜，”狮子回答，“我想我生来就这样。森林里所有的动物都很自然地觉得，我应该很勇敢，因为无论在哪里，狮子都被认为是万兽之王。我知道，如果我大声吼叫，所有的活物都会害怕，四散奔逃。每次我遇到一个人，都害怕极了；但我只要冲他吼，他就飞奔逃命去了。如果大象、老虎、熊想要和我打架，我就会自己逃跑。我就是个胆小鬼；但大家一听到我的吼声，就全要逃跑，而我当然会放它们走。”

“但这不对啊。万兽之王不应该是胆小鬼。”稻草人说。

“我知道，”狮子说着，用尾巴尖擦去一滴眼泪，“这件事让我非常伤心，生活很不快乐。但每次一遇到危险，我就开始心跳加速。”

“也许你有心脏病。”铁皮樵夫说。

“有可能。”狮子说。

“真是这样的话，”铁皮樵夫接着说，“你应该高兴，因为这证明你有一颗心。而我，我没有心；所以我得不了心脏病。”

“有可能，”狮子若有所思，“如果没有心，我就不会胆小。”

“你有脑子吗？”稻草人问。

“我想我有。我从来没想过要脑子。”狮子回答。

“我要去找伟大的奥兹，请他给我脑子，”稻草人说，“因为我的脑袋里填满了稻草。”

“我要请他给我一颗心。”樵夫说。

“我要请他把我和托托送回堪萨斯。”多萝西说。

“你们觉得奥兹能给我胆量吗？”胆小狮问。

“就跟他能给我脑子一样容易。”稻草人说。

“跟给我一颗心一样容易。”铁皮樵夫说。

“跟送我回堪萨斯一样。”多萝西说。

“那如果你们不介意，我想和你们一起去，”狮子说，“因为一丁点勇气也没有，我的生活无法忍受。”

“非常欢迎你，”多萝西说，“因为你可以帮忙赶走别的野兽。在我看来，它们如果那么轻易被你吓走，就肯定比你还胆小。”

“它们确实更胆小，”狮子说，“但那不能让我更勇敢。只要知道自己是个胆小鬼，我就不会开心。”

于是，这几个小伙伴又上路了，狮子威严地大步走在多萝西身旁。托托一开始不赞成这个新伙伴加入，因为他忘不了自己差点被狮子的大牙咬碎。过了一段时间，他感觉更自在了一些，而现在托托和胆小狮已经成了好朋友。

那天余下的时间里，没有其他危险来破坏他们平静的旅途。只是有一次，铁皮樵夫踩上一只沿路爬行的甲虫，要了这可怜的小家伙的命。这让铁皮樵夫很不开心，因为他总是注意不伤害任何生命；他一边走，一边流出几滴伤心悔恨的泪。泪水从他脸上缓缓流下，流到下巴的关节上，关节锈住了。过了一会儿，多萝西问铁皮樵夫一个问题，他张不开嘴，因为他的下巴牢牢地锈住了。铁皮樵夫害怕极了，朝多萝西打了很多次手势，请她解救自己，可是多萝西没有看懂。狮子也莫名其妙，不知道出了什么事。这时，稻草人从多萝西的篮子里拿出油壶，给铁皮樵夫的下巴上了油，于是不一会儿，樵夫就能和从前一样自如地说话了。

“这给我一个教训，”他说，“当心脚下。因为要是我再踩上一只甲虫，我肯定还会哭，泪水会把我的下巴锈住，我就不能讲话了。”

从此，他走路非常小心，眼睛盯着路面。有一次，他看见一只小蚂蚁艰辛地爬过，他就迈过去，不伤害小蚂蚁。铁皮樵夫很清楚自己没有心，所以非常注意绝不对任何东西冷酷残忍。

“你们这些有心的人，”他说，“有东西指引你们，你们永远不会做错事；但我没有心，所以我得特别小心。等奥兹给我一颗心，我当然就不用这么小心了。”

第七章　寻找伟大的奥兹的旅程

那天晚上，因为附近没有房子，他们只好在森林里一棵大树下露营。树冠像一个密实的盖子，为他们遮挡露水。铁皮樵夫用斧头砍了一大堆木头，多萝西搭起熊熊燃烧的火堆，她暖和起来，也觉得没有那么孤独了。她和托托吃完了最后几片面包，现在她不知道早餐怎么办。

“如果你愿意，”狮子说，“我就到森林里去，给你逮一头鹿。你可以烤着吃，因为你的口味很奇怪，喜欢熟食。那样，你能美美地吃一顿早餐。”

“别！千万别！”铁皮樵夫恳求道，“如果你杀死一头可怜的鹿，我肯定会哭的，那我的下巴就又要生锈。”

但狮子还是走进森林，为自己寻食。谁也不知道他吃了什么，因为他自己没提。稻草人找到一棵挂满坚果的树，他给多萝西装了满满一篮子坚果，这样她很久都不会挨饿了。多萝西觉得稻草人善良又周到，可看到这可怜的家伙笨手笨脚摘果子的样子，她还是放声大笑。他那稻草填充的手笨拙极了，坚果又那么小，所以掉在地上的果子和装进篮子的几乎一样多。但稻草人不在乎花多久才能装满篮子，因为这让他可以远离火堆，他害怕火星会蹦进身上的稻草，把他烧着。所以，他离火堆远远的，只是在多萝西睡着后给她盖上干树叶时，才靠近火堆。多萝西盖着这些树叶，舒服又温暖，她一觉睡到了早上。

天亮后，小姑娘在潺潺的溪水中洗好脸。很快，他们又朝翡翠城出发了。

这一天，他们将遇上很多事。他们才走了不到一小时，面前就出现一条壕沟，切断了道路，把他们能看见的森林一分为二。这是一条很宽的沟。他们爬到沟边，朝下张望，发现壕沟很深，沟底布满棱角尖锐的巨石。壕沟两侧非常陡，他们谁也爬不下去。一时间，他们以为旅途似乎要到此为止了。

“我们怎么办？”多萝西绝望地问。

“我一点主意也没有。”铁皮樵夫说。狮子摇着蓬松杂乱的鬃毛，若有所思。但稻草人说：

“我们不会飞，这点是肯定的。我们也不能爬下这条大沟。所以，如果我们不能跳过去的话，就只能停在这里了。”

“我想我能跳过去。”胆小狮在心里仔细估量壕沟的宽度之后，说道。

“那咱们就好办了，”稻草人答道，“你可以把我们都背在背上，一次一个带过去。”

“好，我试一试。”狮子说，“谁第一个？”

“我来，”稻草人表示，“因为要是你发现自己跳不过壕沟，那多萝西就会摔死，铁皮樵夫会碰到下面的巨石，撞得凹凸不平。但如果你背的是我，就不要紧，因为我就算摔下去，也不会受伤。”

“我自己很害怕掉下去，”胆小狮说，“但我想没有别的办法，只有试一试。所以，到我背上来，我们试一试。”

稻草人骑到狮子背上，这个大家伙走到壕沟边，蹲了下来。

“你为什么不助跑然后起跳呢？”稻草人问。

“因为我们狮子不是那样做的。”狮子说完，纵身一跃，轻盈地划过空中，稳稳地落在壕沟对面。大家看到狮子这么轻松地跳过去，都非常开心。稻草人从狮子背上下来后，狮子又跳回壕沟的这一边。

多萝西想第二个过去；于是，她怀抱着托托，爬上狮子的后背，用一只手紧紧抓住狮子的鬃毛。接下来，她感觉像在空中飞翔，还没来得及想什么，就安全地到达了壕沟对面。狮子第三次跳过壕沟，去接铁皮樵夫。然后，他们坐了一会儿，好让狮子有机会歇一歇。几次奋力跳跃之后，狮子呼吸急促，他像一只跑了很久的大狗，呼呼直喘。

他们发现壕沟这边的森林特别茂密，看起来昏暗阴沉。狮子休息好后，大家又踏上黄砖路，每个人都在心里默默地想，他们到底能不能走出这片林子，再次看到灿烂的阳光。更加让大家不安的是，不一会儿，他们就听到森林深处传来奇怪的声音，狮子悄声告诉他们，卡利达就住在这个地方。

“卡利达是什么？”小姑娘问。

“它们是巨兽，身子像熊，脑袋像老虎，”狮子回答，“爪子又长又锋利。它们可以把我撕成两半，就像我杀死托托一样容易。我怕极了卡利达。”

“我不奇怪你会怕它们，”多萝西说，“它们肯定是可怕的野兽。”

狮子正要答话，突然他们面前又出现一道大沟，切断道路。但这条沟又宽又深，狮子马上知道自己跳不过去。

于是，大家坐下来想办法。稻草人仔细思考一番，开口说：

“这里有一棵大树，长在沟边。如果铁皮樵夫能砍倒它，它就会倒向大沟那边，那我们就能很容易地从树上走过大沟。”

“这真是个好主意，”狮子说，“我差点要怀疑你脑袋里有脑子，而不是塞满稻草。”

樵夫马上动手砍树，他的斧头非常锋利，很快，树就要被砍断了。这时，狮子两只前爪抵住大树，用尽全力使劲一推，大树缓缓倾斜，接着重重地倒在沟上，树冠落在大沟对面。

大家刚走上这座奇特的桥，就听见一声尖利的吼叫。他们抬头一看，惊恐地发现两只巨大的野兽正冲他们跑来，野兽的身子像熊，脑袋像老虎。

“他们就是卡利达！”胆小狮说着，开始颤抖。

“快！”稻草人大喊，“咱们快过去。”

于是，多萝西打头，怀里抱着托托，铁皮樵夫跟在她身后，再后面是稻草人。虽然狮子确实很害怕，但他还是转身面对卡利达，发出一声洪亮可怕的吼叫。这一吼吓得多萝西尖声喊叫，稻草人仰面跌倒，就连凶恶的野兽也猛地站住，吃惊地看着狮子。

但它们看出自己比狮子个头大，还想起它们有两个，而狮子是一个，就又冲上来。狮子从大树上跑到沟对面，转身看它们接下来要怎样。凶恶的野兽一刻没停，也跑上大树。狮子对多萝西说：

“我们完了。它们肯定会用锋利的爪子把我们撕碎。站在我身后，靠紧我，我来和它们拼死一战。”

“等等！”稻草人喊道。他刚才在考虑最好的办法是什么，现在他让樵夫砍掉他们这边的树冠。铁皮樵夫立刻亮出斧头，眼看两头卡利达马上要过沟，大树轰隆一声掉进深沟，两只咆哮着的丑陋野兽也跟着摔了下去，在沟底尖锐的巨石上粉身碎骨。

“好了，”胆小狮长长地松了一口气，“我看咱们又能再多活一会儿，我很开心，因为不能活肯定让人很难受。这些野兽吓死我了，我的心现在还怦怦跳。”

“啊，”铁皮樵夫伤心地说，“我真想有颗心可以跳动。”

这番冒险的经历之后，几个旅行者要走出森林的心情比之前更加急切了，于是他们步子飞快，多萝西走累了，只好骑到狮子背上。他们很开心的是，越往前走，树木越稀疏。午后，他们突然来到一条水流湍急的大河边。河对岸，看得见黄砖路穿过一片美丽的原野，翠绿的草坪上绚烂的花儿星星点点，路边的树木挂满鲜美的果子。他们望见面前的美丽景色，满心欢喜。

“我们怎么过河？”多萝西问。

“那很容易。”稻草人回答，“铁皮樵夫得造一条木筏，这样我们就能漂到对岸去。”

于是，铁皮樵夫拿起斧头，动手砍倒小树，制作木筏。他正忙活着，稻草人在河岸上找到一棵结满甜美果子的树。多萝西很开心，因为她已经吃了一天的坚果，现在她美美地吃了一顿成熟的水果。

可是，制作木筏很花时间，即使铁皮樵夫这么勤劳而不知疲倦，夜幕降临的时候，木筏还是没有完工。于是，大家在树下找了一块舒适的地方，一直安睡到天亮。夜里，多萝西梦到翡翠城，还有好巫师奥兹，他马上就要送她回家。

第八章　要命的罂粟花田

第二天早晨，我们这一小队旅行者醒来，精力充沛，满怀希望。多萝西像个公主一样吃早餐，食物是从河边树上摘来的桃子和李子。他们身后是阴暗的森林，虽然他们经历了许多挫折，但已经安然通过；他们面前则是一片阳光照耀的美丽原野，像在召唤他们继续去往翡翠城。

现在，宽阔的大河把他们和这美丽的土地隔开。但木筏就要做好了，铁皮樵夫又砍了几根圆木，用木钉把它们固定在一起，这样，他们可以上路了。多萝西坐在木筏正中，抱着托托；胆小狮一上来，木筏就倾斜得厉害，因为他个头大，身子重；稻草人和铁皮樵夫站在木筏的另一头，好稳住木筏，他俩手握长杆，撑着木筏过河。

起初，他们行进得很顺利，但到河中央时，湍急的水流把木筏往下游冲去，离黄砖路越来越远。河水也越来越深，长杆够不着河底。

“这不妙，”铁皮樵夫说，“如果我们靠不了岸，就会被带到邪恶的西方女巫的国度，她会给我们施咒，让我们成为她的奴隶。”

“那我就得不到脑子了。”稻草人说。

“那我就得不到胆量了。”胆小狮说。

“那我就得不到心了。”铁皮樵夫说。

“那我就永远也不能回堪萨斯了。”多萝西说。

“如果我们能够，就一定要去翡翠城。”稻草人接着说，他使劲一撑长杆，不料长杆牢牢地卡进了河底的淤泥。他还没来得及拔出长杆或者松手，木筏已被大水冲走。可怜的稻草人紧紧抱住长杆，留在了河中央。

“再见！”稻草人冲着他们的背影大喊。大家只好非常伤心地离开了他。铁皮樵夫真的要哭了，幸好他记起自己会生锈，于是在多萝西的围裙上擦干眼泪。

这件事对稻草人来说，确实够糟糕的。

“我现在比当初见到多萝西的时候更不幸，”他想，“那时候，我被绑在玉米地里的一根竿子上，不管怎么说，还能装装样子，吓唬乌鸦。可是被困在河中央木杆上的稻草人，肯定什么用也没有。恐怕我永远不会得到脑子了！”

木筏向河下游漂去，可怜的稻草人被远远落在后面。这时，狮子说：

“我们必须采取点行动来自救。我想我可以拖着木筏游到岸边，你们只要抓住我的尾巴尖就行。”

于是，狮子纵身跳下水，铁皮樵夫紧紧抓住他的尾巴。接着，狮子使出全部的劲朝岸边游去。他个头很大，但游起来仍然很费力；一点一点地，狮子把大家拖出了激流。多萝西拿起铁皮樵夫的长杆，帮着把木筏推上岸。

最后，大家终于到岸，踏上美丽的绿草坪。每个人都筋疲力尽，也知道他们被水流冲向下游，远离了去往翡翠城的黄砖路。

“我们现在怎么办？”铁皮樵夫问。这时，狮子正躺在草地上，让太阳把自己晒干。

“我们得想个办法，回到黄砖路。”多萝西说。

“最好的办法就是沿着河岸走，直到我们回到那条路。”狮子说。

于是，他们休息好之后，多萝西拎起篮子，大家沿着草色青青的河岸，去往他们被河水冲走之前走的那条路。这是一片美丽的乡野，处处是赏心悦目的鲜花、果树和阳光。要不是为稻草人伤心的话，他们本来会非常开心的。

他们以最快的速度赶路，多萝西只停下来一回，去摘一朵美丽的花儿。过了一会儿，铁皮樵夫喊道：

“看呐！”

大家闻声向河面望去，只见稻草人在河中央紧紧抱着长杆，看起来孤独而忧伤。

“我们怎样才能救他？”多萝西问。

狮子和樵夫都摇摇头，想不出办法。他们坐在岸边，发愁地盯着稻草人，这时飞来一只鹳，她发现了他们，于是在水边停下来歇息。

“你们是什么人，要往哪里去？”鹳问道。

“我叫多萝西，”小姑娘回答，“这两位是我的朋友，铁皮樵夫和胆小狮；我们要去翡翠城。”

“不是这条路。”鹳说，她扭动长长的脖子，机警地看着三个奇怪的家伙。

“我明白，”多萝西回答，“可是我们失去了稻草人，不知道怎样救他回来。”

“他在哪儿？”鹳问。

“在那边河里。”小姑娘回答。

“要是他个头不这么大、身子不这么重，我就帮你们把他救回来。”鹳说。

“他一点都不重，”多萝西急忙说，“因为他是用稻草填充的；如果你能把他带回到我们身边，我们会永远感激不尽。”

“好吧，我试试，”鹳说，“可要是我觉得他太重带不动，我就得把他又抛回河里。”

于是，大鸟飞上天空，掠过河面，直飞到抱着长杆的稻草人身旁。她用大爪子抓起稻草人的胳膊，把他带到空中，送回多萝西、狮子、铁皮樵夫和托托坐着的河岸上。

稻草人见自己又与朋友们团聚了，他高兴得拥抱了所有人，连狮子和托托也拥抱了；大家往前走，稻草人每走一步都唱着“托—得—日—得—噢！”，他快活极了。

“我还以为我要永远待在河里了，”他说，“想不到好心的鹳救了我。要是我有了脑子，我一定去找她，做点什么事报答她。”

“不客气。”鹳在一旁飞，与他们一起往前走，“无论谁遇到困难，我总乐意帮忙。可我得走了，孩子们还在窝里等我回去呢。祝你们找到翡翠城，得到奥兹的帮助。”

“谢谢。”多萝西说。随后，好心的鹳飞上天空，一会儿就飞远不见了。

大家往前赶路，羽毛艳丽的鸟儿们的歌声在耳畔唱响，美丽的鲜花在面前盛开，这些花非常繁茂，像在地上铺了一层花毯。除了硕大的黄花、白花、蓝花、紫花，还有一大丛一大丛鲜红夺目的罂粟花，简直让多萝西看花眼。

“这些花儿美吧？”小姑娘深吸一口花朵浓郁的香气，问道。

“美。”稻草人回答道，“等我有了脑子，我应该会更喜欢这些花。”

“要是我有一颗心，我会喜欢的。”铁皮樵夫说。

“我一直很喜欢花，”狮子说，“它们的样子多么无助、脆弱。可森林里的花都没有这么鲜艳。”

他们越往前走，鲜红的大罂粟花越多，别的花越少；不久，他们发现自己走进了一大片罂粟花田。现在，众所周知，这些花多了香味会特别强烈，人闻到就昏睡，如果没有被从花香里抬出来，就会永远睡下去。可多萝西不知道这回事，而且她也摆脱不了遍地都是的鲜红罂粟花；所以不一会儿，她就眼皮发沉，觉得必须坐下来休息睡一觉。

但铁皮樵夫不让多萝西停下来。

“我们得快点走，在天黑前赶回到黄砖路上。”他说。稻草人同意樵夫的想法。因此，他们继续赶路，直到多萝西再也站不起来，眼睛不由自主地闭上了。她忘了自己在哪里，倒在罂粟花丛中，熟睡过去。

“我们该怎么办？”铁皮樵夫问。

“要是把她留在这里，她一定会没命的，”狮子说，“我们都要被花要了命去。我自己也快睁不开眼了，而狗已经睡着了。”

没错，托托已经睡倒在小主人身边。只有稻草人和铁皮樵夫没被花香熏倒，因为他俩不是血肉之躯。

“快跑，”稻草人对狮子说，“你能跑多快就跑多快，赶紧跑出这片要命的花田。我们会把小姑娘抬出去，可是你个头太大，我们抬不动。”

狮子听到这话，挣扎起身，奋力往前跳跃。不一会儿，他就跑远了。

“我们用手搭成一把椅子抬她。”稻草人说。他们抱起托托，放在多萝西的膝头，然后用手当座位，胳膊当扶手，搭成一把椅子，抬着熟睡的小姑娘穿过花田。

他们走啊走啊，要命的罂粟花连成一片大花毯，包围着他们，似乎永远走不到头。他们沿着河弯走，最后终于遇到了睡倒在罂粟花中的狮子。原来花香太浓，这个大家伙也终于受不住，在离花田尽头不远的地方倒下了，前头就是一片芳草青青的美丽田野。

“我们帮不了他，”铁皮樵夫伤心地说，“他太重，我们抬不动。我们不得不让他留在这里，永远睡下去，也许他会梦见自己终于拥有了胆量。”

“我很难过，”稻草人说，“狮子虽然胆小，却是一个好伙伴。我们还是走吧。”

他们把睡着的小姑娘抬到河边一处美丽的地方，这里远离罂粟花田，再也吸不到有毒的花香。他们把多萝西轻轻放在柔软的草地上，等着清新的微风唤醒她。

第九章　田鼠女王

“我们现在离黄砖路不会很远了，”稻草人站在小姑娘身边说，“因为我们走的路差不多有河水冲走我们那么远。”

铁皮樵夫正要答话，突然听到一声低沉的吼叫，他转头（头靠脖子关节旋转得很优美）看见一头奇怪的野兽跳过草丛，朝他们奔来。这其实是一只巨大的黄色野猫。樵夫想它一定是在追赶什么，因为它的耳朵紧贴着脑袋，嘴巴大张，露出两排难看的牙齿，血红的眼睛像燃烧的火球。野猫越来越近，铁皮樵夫看到跑在它前面的是一只灰色的小田鼠。尽管樵夫没有心，但他还是知道野猫想要杀死这样一个漂亮、无辜的小东西是不对的。

于是樵夫举起斧头，趁野猫跑过，迅速地一挥，这野兽的头就被齐刷刷地从身子上砍下来，骨碌碌滚到他脚边，碎成两半。

田鼠终于摆脱了敌人，突然收住脚，慢慢走到樵夫身边，用尖细微小的声音说：

“噢，谢谢！万分感谢你救了我一命。”

“请千万别这么说。”樵夫答道，“我没有心，所以就留意帮助那些可能需要朋友的人，哪怕那只是一只老鼠。”

“只是一只老鼠！”小家伙气愤地叫道，“我可是女王，所有田鼠的女王！”

“噢，是的。”樵夫说着，鞠了一个躬。

“所以你救了我一命，这是崇高之举，也是勇敢之举。”女王补充道。

这时，樵夫他们看见一些田鼠飞快地迈动小腿跑来，一看到他们的女王，就喊叫起来：

“噢，陛下，我们以为您被害了！您是怎么从那只大野猫那里逃脱的？”他们冲着小小的女王深深鞠躬，脑袋低得都要碰到地面了。

“是这位有趣的铁皮人，”女王说，“杀死野猫，救了我一命。所以，从今以后，你们都要为他效力，遵从他的意思。”

“遵命！”所有的田鼠齐声尖叫。接着，他们突然四散奔逃。原来托托睡醒了，看见身边围着一群田鼠，高兴地叫了一声，跳进这群田鼠中间。托托在堪萨斯的时候，就一直喜欢追田鼠，它看不出这会伤害谁。

铁皮樵夫把狗抱起来，紧紧搂住，然后对田鼠说：“回来吧！回来吧！托托不会伤害你们的。”

听到这话，田鼠女王从一丛青草下面探出脑袋，怯怯地问：

“你确定他不会咬我们？”

“我不会放开它的，”樵夫说，“你们别害怕。”

田鼠们小心地一只接一只爬回来。托托不再吠叫，但它想挣脱樵夫的胳膊，要不是非常清楚樵夫是铁皮做的，就要咬他一口了。最后，一只最大的田鼠开口了。

“你救了我们的女王一命，”他说，“我们能做点什么来报答你吗？”

“我想不出有什么。”樵夫说。稻草人努力地想，也想不出来，因为他的脑袋里塞满稻草。于是，他脱口而出：

“噢，是的。你们可以救我们的朋友胆小狮，他睡在罂粟花田里。”

“一头狮子！”小女王叫道，“天啊，他会把我们吃光的。”

“噢，不会的，”稻草人声明，“这头狮子是个胆小鬼。”

“真的？”大田鼠问。

“是他自己这么说的，”稻草人回答，“而且他绝不会伤害我们的朋友。如果你们帮我们救他，我保证他会对你们大家很友好。”

“那好，”女王说，“我们相信你。但我们该怎么做？”

“这里有很多称你为女王、愿意听你命令的田鼠吗？”

“噢，是的，有几千只呢。”女王回答。

“那请你叫所有田鼠都尽快过来，每只都带一根长绳。”

女王转身吩咐服侍她的田鼠们，让他们立即去召集所有的臣民。他们一听到女王的命令，就飞快地四散跑开。

“现在，”稻草人对铁皮樵夫说，“你必须到河边的树林去，做一辆搬运狮子的推车。”

樵夫一听就立刻到树林去，忙活起来；不一会儿，他就用大树枝做好一辆推车。他砍去大树枝上所有的树叶和枝杈，用木钉把大树枝钉在一起，又把一根大树干截成四段做车轮。他干得又快又漂亮，等田鼠们开始陆陆续续地到达时，推车已经做好了。

田鼠从四面八方过来，有好几千只：大田鼠、小田鼠，还有不大不小的田鼠；他们每只的嘴里都衔着一条长绳。就在这时，多萝西从长长的睡梦中醒来，睁开眼。她发现自己躺在草地上，身边站着几千只胆怯地望着她的田鼠，大吃一惊。稻草人给她讲了事情的所有经过，然后转身对着那只威严的小田鼠，说：

“请允许我给你介绍女王陛下。”

多萝西严肃地点点头，女王行了一个屈膝礼，随后她待小姑娘十分友善。

稻草人和樵夫这时开始用田鼠们带来的绳子，把他们套上推车。每条绳子都是一头绕住田鼠的脖子，另一头系在推车上。当然，推车比每一只拉它的田鼠都大一千倍，但所有的田鼠一齐使劲，就能轻易拉动推车。连稻草人和铁皮樵夫都能坐在推车上，由他们的这群奇异的小马拉着，迅速地去往狮子睡着的地方。

大家费了好大劲，才把狮子抬上车，因为他太重了。随后，女王急忙命令她的臣民开始拉车，因为她害怕田鼠们在罂粟花田里待久了，也会睡着。

一开始，这些小家伙虽然数目很多，但还是不大拉得动载着狮子的沉重推车。幸好樵夫和稻草人从后面推，才减轻了他们的负担。很快，他们拉着狮子出了罂粟花田，狮子才终于又能呼吸到清凉的新鲜空气，而不是花的毒气了。

多萝西迎上来，热情地感谢小田鼠们救了她的同伴一命。她这时已经非常喜欢大狮子，很高兴他获救了。

随后，田鼠们被从推车上解下来，他们蹦蹦跳跳地穿过草丛，各自回家了。田鼠女王一直待到最后。

“要是你们还需要我们帮助，”她说，“就到田野里喊一声，我们听见就会来帮忙。再见！”

“再见！”大家齐声回应。女王跑走了。这时，多萝西紧紧抱住托托，怕它去追赶女王，把她吓着。

大家送走田鼠女王，坐到狮子身边，等着他醒来；稻草人从附近一棵树上摘下水果，给多萝西做晚餐。

第十章　守门人

过了好一会儿，胆小狮才醒来，因为他在罂粟花田躺得太久，吸入了罂粟花致命的香气；当他终于睁开眼，从推车上滚下来的时候，他发现自己还活着，高兴极了。

“我拼命地跑，”他坐下来，打着哈欠说，“但是花香对我来说太浓烈。你们是怎么把我弄出来的？”

于是，他们跟他说起田鼠，说起他们怎样慷慨地救了他一命。胆小狮听完，大笑着说：

“我总是以为自己个头大、样子吓人；可是像花儿这样的小东西竟差点要了我的命，而像田鼠这样的小家伙竟又救活了我。这一切多么奇怪啊！可是，伙伴们，现在我们该怎么办？”

“我们必须继续赶路，直到再找到黄砖路，”多萝西说，“然后，我们才能接着往翡翠城去。”

于是，狮子重又神清气爽，精神抖擞，大家都起身上路，走过柔软、清新的草地，满心喜悦。没走多久，他们就到了黄砖路上，随后又转向伟大的奥兹居住的翡翠城的方向前进。

现在，道路通顺而平坦，四周是乡野美景，因此这队旅行者很高兴将森林远远留在身后，也将在它那阴森森的暗影里遇到的许多艰难险阻远远留在身后。他们又能看见路旁围着篱笆，但这些篱笆漆成了绿色；他们走过一所里面显然住着农民的小屋，它也是绿色的。下午的时候，他们路过了好几所这样的房子，有时人们站在门口，仿佛带着疑问般地望着他们；但没有谁走过来或者对他们说话，因为他们非常害怕大狮子。这地方的人都穿着漂亮的翡翠绿色衣服，戴着芒奇金人那样的尖帽。

“这一定是奥兹国，”多萝西说，“我们肯定离翡翠城不远了。”

“是的。”稻草人回答，“这里所有东西都是绿色的，而在芒奇金国，人们最喜欢蓝色。可是这里的人似乎不像芒奇金人一样友好，我们恐怕找不到地方过夜。”

“我想吃点水果以外的东西，”小姑娘说，“托托肯定也快饿得不行了。我们在下一所房子停一下，和人们说说话吧。”

于是，当他们走到一所大农舍时，多萝西勇敢地上前敲门。一个女人把门打开一道缝，刚够伸出脑袋。她问：

“孩子，你想要什么？那头大狮子为什么和你在一起？”

“如果你允许的话，我们想在你家过夜。”多萝西回答，“狮子是我的朋友和伙伴，他绝对不会伤害你。”

“他温顺吗？”女人一边问，一边把门缝开大了一些。

“噢，是的，”小姑娘说，“他胆子还特别小。你怕他，可他更怕你呢。”

“好吧，”女人仔细想了想，又瞥了一眼狮子，才说，“要是这样的话，你们可以进来，我给你们提供晚餐和睡觉的地方。”

于是，他们都进了房子。这家除了那女人，还有两个孩子和一个男人。男人伤着了腿，正躺在屋角的沙发上。这家人看见这群奇怪的人，好像非常吃惊。那女人忙着摆饭桌的时候，那男人问道：

“你们都要往哪儿去？”

“往翡翠城去，”多萝西说，“去见伟大的奥兹。”

“噢，真的！”男人惊叫道，“你们确定奥兹会见你们吗？”

“为什么不见？”多萝西反问。

“为什么？因为据说他从来不见任何人。我去过翡翠城很多次，那是一个美丽奇妙的地方；但我从来没有获准拜见伟大的奥兹，我也没听说有哪个在世的人见过他。”

“他从来不出门吗？”稻草人问。

“从不。他日复一日地坐在宫殿中的大觐见室里，就连那些服侍他的人也没有见过他的面。”

“他长什么样？”小姑娘问。

“这很难说。”男人若有所思地说，“你知道，奥兹是一位伟大的巫师，他想变成什么样子就能变成什么样子。所以，有些人说他像一只鸟，有些人说他像一头大象，有些人说他像一只猫。对另一些人，他以美丽的仙女，或者小精灵，或者他喜欢的任何其他样子出现。但是奥兹本人是谁，哪个才是他真正的样子，在世的人谁也不知道。”

“这非常奇怪，”多萝西说，“但我们还是得试一试，想办法见到他，不然我们这趟旅程将一无所获。”

“你们为什么想见可怕的奥兹？”男人问。

“我想请他给我一些脑子。”稻草人急切地说。

“噢，这个奥兹轻而易举就能做到，”男人说，“他拥有的脑子，比他需要的多。”

“我想请他给我一颗心。”铁皮樵夫说。

“这对他来说，一点都不费事，”男人接着说，“因为奥兹收藏了很多心，各种大小和形状的他都有。”

“我想请他给我胆子。”胆小狮说。

“奥兹的觐见室里有一大罐胆子，”男人说，“他用一只金盘子盖住罐口，好不让胆子流出来。他会很高兴给你一些的。”

“我想请他送我回堪萨斯。”多萝西说。

“堪萨斯在哪儿？”男人惊奇地问。

“我不知道，”多萝西伤心地说，“但我家在那里，我确定它在某一个地方。”

“很可能是这样。嗯，奥兹什么都能办到，所以我觉得他能帮你找到堪萨斯。但首先你得见着他，而这很难办到；因为这位大巫师不喜欢见任何人，他通常有自己的行事方式。那你想要什么？”他转而对托托说。托托只是摇摇尾巴；因为说来奇怪，它不会讲话。

这时，女人对他们喊：晚饭好了。于是大家都围到桌边。多萝西喝了一些美味的粥，吃了一碟炒鸡蛋、一盘白面包。她吃得很开心。狮子也喝了一些粥，但他不喜欢喝，他说粥是用燕麦做的，而燕麦是给马吃的，不是给狮子吃的。稻草人和铁皮樵夫什么也没吃。而托托每样都吃了一点，能再次吃到这样美味的晚餐，他很开心。

晚饭后，女人给多萝西安排了一张床睡觉，托托卧在多萝西身边，狮子守在房间门口，免得她受到打扰。而稻草人和铁皮樵夫站在屋子一角，虽然他们当然不能睡觉，但整晚都保持安静。

第二天清早，太阳一出来，他们就上路了，没走多久，就看见前方不远处的天空中闪着一片美丽的绿光。

“那肯定是翡翠城。”多萝西说。

他们越往前走，绿光越明亮，看起来他们终于要到达旅行目的地了。但直到下午他们才走到环绕着翡翠城的巨大墙壁前。这城墙又高又厚，颜色翠绿。

在他们前方、黄砖路的尽头，是一扇大门，上面镶满翡翠。这些翡翠在阳光下闪闪发亮，就连稻草人那画上去的眼睛都被它们的光彩晃花了。

门边有一只铃，多萝西按下按钮，就听到门内响起清脆的叮当声。接着，大门缓缓打开，大家都走进去，进入一个房间，高高的天花板是拱形的，四面的墙壁上无数翡翠灼灼闪亮。

在他们面前站着一个小人，个头和芒奇金人相当。他从头到脚穿着绿色的衣服，连皮肤都带着一丝绿色的色泽。他身边有一只绿色的大箱子。

这人见到多萝西和她的伙伴，问道：

“你们来翡翠城有什么事吗？”

“我们来这里拜见伟大的奥兹。”多萝西说。

小绿人对这回答很吃惊，他坐下仔细想了一番。

“已经很多年没人找我要拜见奥兹了。”他困惑地摇着头说，“他强大而可怕，如果你们是为无聊、愚蠢的事去打扰大巫师的智慧思考，他没准会生气，并在眨眼之间摧毁你们。”

“但我们的事并不愚蠢，也不无聊，”稻草人回答，“我们的事很重要。而且我们听说奥兹是位好心的巫师。”

“是的，”小绿人说，“他智慧而有序地统治着翡翠城。但对那些不诚实的人，或者出于好奇而接近他的人，他极其可怕，没有什么人敢要求见他的面。我是守门人，既然你们要求拜见伟大的奥兹，那我就得带你们去他的宫殿。但你们得先戴上眼镜。”

“为什么？”多萝西问。

“因为如果你们不戴眼镜，翡翠城的光辉会使你们失明。就连住在这城里的人，都要日夜戴着眼镜。按照翡翠城最初建造时奥兹的吩咐，人们的眼镜都锁上了，只有我有一把打开它们的钥匙。”

他说完打开大箱子，多萝西看见里面装满各种大小和形状的眼镜。这些眼镜镜片都是绿色的。守门人找出一副刚好适合多萝西的眼镜，给她戴上。眼镜上的两根金色带子，绕到她的脑后，由守门人用颈上链子末端的小钥匙锁住。眼镜一戴上，多萝西想摘也摘不下来，但她当然不想被翡翠城耀眼的光芒刺瞎眼睛，所以她什么也没说。

随后，守门的小绿人为稻草人、铁皮樵夫和狮子甚至托托都戴上眼镜，告诉他们他准备好带他们去宫殿了。他从墙上的钉子上取下一把金色大钥匙，打开另一扇门。于是，大家都跟着他走过大门，走进了翡翠城的街道。

第十一章　奥兹的奇妙翡翠城

即使眼睛得到绿眼镜的保护，多萝西和她的朋友们起初还是被这座奇妙之城的绚烂光彩晃花了眼。道路的两旁排列着绿色大理石建造的美丽房屋，处处点缀着闪亮的翡翠。他们走上一条同样用大理石铺成的人行道，石块间的缝隙满满当当地填着一排排的翡翠，在明亮的阳光下光彩灼灼。窗子上装着绿色玻璃；就连城市之上的天空也泛着淡淡的绿色，洒下的阳光也是绿色的。

许多人，有男有女，还有小孩，在这里来来去去。这些人都穿着绿衣服，皮肤也是浅绿色的。他们拿惊奇的目光望着多萝西和她怪模怪样的同伴，孩子们一看到狮子，都纷纷跑开，躲到母亲身后；没有一个人和他们讲话。路边有许多商店，多萝西看见里面的所有东西都是绿色的：绿色糖果、绿色爆米花，还有绿鞋、绿帽、各种绿衣服。有一家店卖绿色柠檬汁。孩子们来买柠檬汁时，多萝西发现他们付的钱也是绿色的。

这里好像没有马，没有任何动物。人们推着绿色的小车运东西。每个人看起来都幸福、满足而富裕。

守门人领他们走过一条条街，一直来到一座大房子前。这座房子在城市正中央，是大巫师奥兹的宫殿。有一名身穿绿制服、长着绿色长胡子的士兵站在门前。

“这几位外乡人，”守门人对士兵说，“请求拜见伟大的奥兹。”

“进来。”士兵回答，“我去向他禀报。”

于是，他们穿过宫殿大门，被领进一个大房间，里面铺着绿地毯，摆着镶嵌翡翠的漂亮家具。在进门之前，士兵让他们都在一只绿垫子上擦净脚底。大家落座后，士兵礼貌地说：

“请别拘束。我去觐见室门口，禀告奥兹你们来了。”

大家等了很久，士兵才终于回来。多萝西问：

“你见到奥兹了吗？”

“噢，没有。”士兵回答，“我从来没有见过他。但他坐在屏风后面，我隔着屏风和他说话，向他禀告了你们的口信。他说，如果你们这么想见他，他就恩准你们拜见；但是你们每个人要单独见他，而且每天只许一个人去。这样的话，你们就得在这宫殿住些日子了。我领你们去房间，旅行之后，你们可以在那里舒舒服服地歇息。”

“谢谢，”小姑娘回答道，“真要谢谢奥兹。”

这时，士兵吹响一只绿色的哨子，一位身穿漂亮绿丝裙的年轻姑娘立刻走进来。她长着一头美丽的绿头发和一双美丽的绿眼睛，朝多萝西深鞠一躬，说道：

“跟我来，我带你去房间。”

于是，多萝西告别朋友们，怀里抱着托托，跟随绿姑娘走过七条走廊、三段楼梯，一直来到宫殿前部的一个房间。这是世界上最可爱的小房间，房里摆着柔软舒适的床，上面是绿色丝绸床单和绿色天鹅绒被罩。房间中央有一座小小的喷泉，朝空中喷洒着绿色香水，再落回到雕刻精美的绿色大理石盆中。窗口盛开着美丽的绿色鲜花，书架上摆着一排绿色小书。多萝西有空打开这些书时，发现里面都是引她发笑的奇怪的绿色图画，有趣极了。

衣柜里挂着许多丝绸和天鹅绒料子的绿衣裙；每一件都正合多萝西的身。

“请千万别客气，”绿姑娘说，“有什么需要，你就按这个铃。奥兹明早会派人叫你。”

说完，她留下多萝西独自一人，又回到其他人那里去。她也把这些人领到各自的房间，大家都发现自己住进了宫殿里非常舒适的地方。当然，这样的礼待对稻草人是多余的；因为当房间里只剩下他一个后，他只是傻乎乎地站在门内的一个地方，一直等着天亮。就算躺下，他也得不到休息，而且他还闭不上眼睛；于是，稻草人整夜都盯着一只在屋角织网的小蜘蛛，就好像这不是世界上最好的房间一样。铁皮樵夫出于习惯在床上躺下，他记得自己还是血肉之躯时的日子；但是他睡不着，于是整夜上上下下地活动关节，以保证这些关节状态良好。狮子宁愿睡在森林中一张干树叶堆成的床上，也不喜欢被关在房间里；但他非常明智，不被这想法困扰，于是他跳上床，像猫一样蜷起身子，不到一分钟就呼呼地睡着了。

第二天早晨，吃过早餐，绿姑娘来领多萝西，她给多萝西穿上一件绿色锦缎做的最美的衣裙。多萝西围上一条绿丝绸围裙，给托托脖子上系了一条绿丝带。随后，他们出发去大巫师奥兹的觐见室。

他们首先来到一间大厅，里面有许多宫廷的淑女绅士，都穿着华美的服装。这些人无所事事，只是和彼此聊天，但他们每天早晨都来觐见室外等候，虽然他们从来没有获得准许拜见奥兹。多萝西走进大厅，大家都好奇地望着她，其中一个人轻声问：

“你真的要去面见可怕的奥兹吗？”

“当然，”多萝西回答，“如果他肯见我的话。”

“噢，他会见你的，”把多萝西的口信禀告巫师的那名士兵说，“虽然他不愿意人们求见他。实际上，他一开始很生气，说我应该把你送回你来的地方。接着，他问我你什么模样，我提起你的银鞋时，他非常感兴趣。最后，我说起你额头上的印记，他就决定准许你面见他。”

就在这时，铃响了，绿姑娘对多萝西说：

“这是信号。你必须一个人走进觐见室。”

绿姑娘打开一扇小门，多萝西勇敢地走进去。她发现自己到了一个美妙的地方。这是一个圆形的大房间，有高高的拱顶，墙面、天花板和地板上都密密麻麻地镶嵌着大颗的翡翠。穹顶中央挂着一盏大灯，像太阳一样明亮，灯光照耀下，翡翠散发着绚烂的光辉。

不过，多萝西最感兴趣的是房间中央那张绿色大理石做的大宝座。它形状像一把椅子，和所有其他东西一样，闪烁着宝石的光彩。椅子正中有一个巨大的脑袋，下面竟没有身子，也没有胳膊或者腿支撑它。这脑袋上没长头发，却长着眼睛、鼻子和嘴，它比最大的巨人的脑袋还要大。

多萝西惊恐地盯着大脑袋，这时，那双眼睛缓缓转动，敏锐而坚定地看着她。接着，那嘴巴也动了，多萝西听到一个声音说：

“我是奥兹，伟大而可怕的奥兹。你是谁，为什么找我？”

这声音没有多萝西预想的大脑袋会发出的声音那么可怕；于是她鼓起勇气，回答道：

“我是多萝西，渺小而温顺的多萝西。我是来请您帮忙的。”

那双眼睛若有所思地端详了她整整一分钟。接着，那声音说道：

“你的银鞋是从哪儿得到的？”

“我从邪恶的东方女巫那儿得到的，那会儿我的房子落在她身上，压死了她。”多萝西回答。

“你额头上的印记是怎么留下的？”那声音又问道。

“那是善良的北方女巫与我告别、送我到您这里来时吻的。”小姑娘说。

那双眼睛又一次敏锐地看着多萝西，它们看出她说的是实话。奥兹又接着问：

“你希望我做什么？”

“送我回堪萨斯吧，我的艾姆婶婶和亨利叔叔住在那里。”多萝西恳切地说，“我不喜欢您的国家，尽管它非常美丽。我离开这么久，艾姆婶婶肯定担心坏了。”

那双眼睛眨了三下，然后向上看看天花板，向下看看地面，又古怪地转动了一圈，好像看遍了觐见室的所有地方。最后，它们又望向多萝西。

“我为什么要为你做这件事？”奥兹问。

“因为您强大，我弱小；因为您是一位大巫师，而我只是一个需要帮助的小姑娘。”多萝西回答。

“可是你强大到杀死了邪恶的东方女巫。”奥兹说。

“那是凑巧的，”多萝西简单地说，“我没有办法。”

“好吧，”大脑袋说，“我来回答你。你没有权利期待我送你回堪萨斯，除非为我做事作为报答。在这个国家，每个人都要为自己得到的一切付出代价。如果你希望我用魔法送你回家，你就得先为我做事。你帮我，我就帮你。”

“我必须做什么？”小姑娘问。

“杀死邪恶的西方女巫。”奥兹回答。

“可我办不到！”多萝西大吃一惊，叫道。

“你杀死了东方女巫，穿着魔力强大的银鞋。现在世界上只剩一个邪恶女巫，等你可以告诉我她也死了的时候，我就送你回堪萨斯——这之前可不行。”

小姑娘开始哭起来，她失望极了；那双眼睛又眨了一下，焦急地看着她，仿佛大巫师奥兹觉得，只要多萝西愿意，她就能帮上他。

“我从来没有自愿地杀死过任何东西，”她抽泣道，“就算我想，我又怎么能杀死邪恶的西方女巫？如果您，伟大而可怕的奥兹，自己都不能杀死她，那怎么能指望我做到呢？”

“我不知道，”大脑袋说，“可这就是我的回答。等邪恶的西方女巫死去，你才能再见到你的叔叔和婶婶。记住，那女巫很邪恶——恶贯满盈——应该被杀死。现在，你走吧，完成任务之前不要再求见我。”

多萝西伤心地离开觐见室，回到狮子、稻草人和铁皮樵夫那里，他们等着听奥兹对她讲了什么。

“我没有希望了，”多萝西说，“因为要等我杀死邪恶的西方女巫，奥兹才会送我回家；而那是我永远都办不到的。”

她的朋友们都很难过，但又帮不上什么忙。于是，多萝西回到自己的房间，躺在床上哭泣，哭着哭着睡着了。

第二天早晨，绿胡子士兵来到稻草人的房间，说：

“跟我来，奥兹派我带你去见他。”

于是，稻草人跟着士兵走，获准进入了大觐见室。他看见翡翠宝座上坐着一位非常可爱的女士。她穿着绿绸薄纱裙，飘动的绿发上戴着一顶宝石皇冠，两肩上长着一对翅膀，色彩绚烂，轻盈得仿佛最轻微的气息都能拂动它们。

稻草人用他填充着稻草的身体，尽可能优雅地向面前这位美丽的女士鞠躬。女士温柔地望着稻草人，说：

“我是奥兹，伟大而可怕的奥兹。你是谁，为什么找我？”

这时，稻草人非常惊讶，他原以为会看到多萝西说的那个大脑袋；但他还是勇敢地回答：

“我只是一个稻草人，用稻草填充的。所以我没有脑子，我来恳求您给我脑袋里放些脑子，代替稻草，那样我就能和您国土上的其他人一样了。”

“我为什么要为你做这件事？”女士问。

“因为您是智慧而强大的奥兹，别人都帮不了我。”稻草人回答道。

“我从不不求回报地帮助人。”奥兹说，“但我许诺，如果你为我杀死邪恶的西方女巫，我就赐给你许多脑子，这些好使的脑子会让你成为全奥兹国最聪明的人。”

“我以为你曾让多萝西去杀死女巫。”稻草人吃惊地说。

“是的。我不在乎谁杀死女巫。但要等到她死了，我才会给你实现愿望。现在，你走吧，等你有资格获得你这么想要的脑子的时候，再来找我。”

稻草人伤心地回到朋友们那里，告诉了他们奥兹的话；多萝西吃惊地得知，大巫师奥兹不是她看到的大脑袋，而是一位可爱的女士。

“但是要求没变，”稻草人说，“她像铁皮樵夫一样需要一颗心。”

第二天早晨，绿胡子士兵来到铁皮樵夫的房间，说：

“奥兹派我带你去见他。跟我来。”

于是，铁皮樵夫跟着士兵走，来到大觐见室。他不知道自己见到的奥兹会是一位可爱的女士还是一个大脑袋，但他希望是那位可爱的女士。“因为，”铁皮樵夫心里想，“如果是大脑袋的话，我肯定得不到一颗心，因为脑袋自己没有心，不会同情我。但如果是那位可爱的女士，我就恳求她给我一颗心，因为所有的女人都自称心地善良。”

但是铁皮樵夫走进大觐见室时，他看到的既不是大脑袋，也不是女士。奥兹变身成一头十分可怕的野兽，个头跟大象差不多，绿色宝座似乎支撑不了它的重量。这野兽长着像犀牛一样的头，但脸上有五只眼睛，身上长出五条长胳膊，还有五条细长的腿，满身覆盖着厚羊毛一样的毛发。再也想象不出有什么野兽比它样子更可怕。幸亏铁皮樵夫那时还没有心，不然的话，它会因为恐惧而怦怦直跳。因为铁皮樵夫只是铁做的，所以他一点也不害怕，只是非常失望。

“我是奥兹，伟大而可怕的奥兹。”野兽大吼道，“你是谁，为什么找我？”

“我是一个樵夫，用铁皮做的。所以，我没有心，不能爱。我恳求您给我一颗心，那样我就能和其他人一样了。”

“我为什么要为你做这件事？”野兽问。

“因为我请求您，而且只有您能准许我的请求。”铁皮樵夫回答。

奥兹听了，发出一声低沉的吼叫，粗声说：

“你如果真想要一颗心，就得努力赢得它。”

“怎么赢得？”樵夫问。

“帮助多萝西杀死邪恶的西方女巫。”野兽回答，“等那女巫死了，你再来找我，那时我会给你一颗全奥兹国最大、最善良、最有爱的心。”

于是，铁皮樵夫只好伤心地回到朋友们那里，把自己看到的可怕野兽以及后来的事全告诉了他们。大家都对这位大巫师能变成各种样子惊奇不已。狮子说：

“如果我见到他是一头野兽，我就发出最响亮的吼声，吓住他，他就会答应我所有的请求。如果他是那位可爱的女士，我就装作要扑到她身上，逼她按照我的命令去做。如果他是那颗大脑袋，他就随我处置了；我会满屋滚动他，直到他答应给我们实现愿望。所以，高兴起来吧，我的朋友们，因为一切都会好起来。”

第二天早晨，绿胡子士兵领狮子去大觐见室，他吩咐狮子进去面见奥兹。

狮子立刻走进门，他环顾四周，惊讶地发现宝座前有一个大火球，火势凶猛，红光熊熊，让他难以注目。他首先想到的是，奥兹不小心着火烧起来了；但是当他想要靠近一些时，炽热的火焰烤焦了他的胡须，狮子颤抖着爬回靠近门边的一个地方。

这时，火球中传出一个低沉、平静的声音，它这样说道：

“我是奥兹，伟大而可怕的奥兹。你是谁，为什么找我？”狮子回答：

“我是胆小狮，什么都害怕。我来恳请您给我胆量，那样我就会真正成为名符其实的万兽之王。”

“我为什么该给你胆量？”奥兹问。

“因为在所有巫师中，您是最了不起的，只有您有能力完成我的请求。”狮子回答说。

火球熊熊燃烧了一会儿，那声音说道：

“把邪恶的西方女巫死去的证据带给我，那时我会给你胆量。只要那女巫还活着，你就得一直是个胆小鬼。”

狮子听到这话很愤怒，却无言以对，他站在那里，默默地凝视着火球。火焰越发炽烈，他只好转头冲出觐见室。狮子很高兴看到朋友们在等他，他把与巫师的可怕会面告诉了大家。

“我们现在该怎么办？”多萝西伤心地问。

“我们只能做一件事，”狮子回答说，“就是去温基国，找到邪恶的女巫，把她杀死。”

“要是我们办不到呢？”小姑娘说。

“那我就永远不会有胆量。”狮子表示。

“那我就永远不会有脑子。”稻草人补充说。

“那我就永远不会有一颗心。”铁皮樵夫说。

“而我就永远见不到艾姆婶婶和亨利叔叔了。”多萝西说着哭起来。

“小心！”绿姑娘叫道，“泪珠会落到你的绿丝裙上，留下斑点。”

听到这话，多萝西擦干眼泪，说：

“我想我们必须试一试；但我确定自己不想杀死任何人，哪怕是为了再见到艾姆婶婶。”

“我和你一起去。但是我太胆小，不敢杀死女巫。”狮子说。

“我也去。”稻草人表示，“但我这么笨，帮不上你什么忙。”

“哪怕是一个女巫，我也不忍心伤害，”铁皮樵夫说，“但如果你去，我也要跟你走。”

就这样，大家商定第二天早晨出发上路。于是，铁皮樵夫在一块绿色磨刀石上磨快了斧头，并给自己的所有关节上足了油。稻草人给自己填充了新鲜稻草，多萝西用油漆给他重新描画眼睛，这样他可以看得更清楚。绿姑娘对大家很好，她给多萝西的篮子装满好吃的，又用绿丝带把一只小铃铛系在托托脖子上。

大家早早上床，一直熟睡到天亮。是宫殿后院里一只绿公鸡的报晓啼鸣，还有一只生了绿蛋的母鸡的咯咯叫声唤醒了他们。

第十二章　寻找坏女巫

绿胡子士兵领着大家穿过翡翠城的街道，一直来到守门人住的房间。守门人为大家解下眼镜，放回他的大箱子，随后他礼貌地为我们的朋友打开大门。

“哪条路通往邪恶的西方女巫那里？”多萝西问。

“没有路，”守门人回答说，“从来没有人想要去那儿。”

“那我们怎么才能找到她？”小姑娘问。

“很简单，”守门人答道，“她一旦知道你们到了温基国，就会找上你们，让你们全给她做奴隶。”

“也许不会，”稻草人说，“因为我们想要杀死她。”

“噢，那是不一样。”守门人说，“以前从没有人杀死她，所以我很自然地以为她会把你们也变成奴隶，就像对别人一样。不过你们要小心，她邪恶凶暴，也许不会让你们杀死她。一直朝西方，就是太阳落山的方向走，你们一定能找到她。”

他们感谢了守门人，与他道别，然后朝西方出发，走上长满柔软青草、处处点缀着雏菊和金凤花的田野。多萝西还穿着在宫殿里穿上的漂亮丝绸衣裙，可是现在，她惊奇地发现，裙子不再是绿色的，竟变成了纯白色。再看托托脖子上的丝带，也褪去绿色，像多萝西的裙子一样白了。

很快，翡翠城就被远远留在身后。他们越往前走，地面越崎岖多山，因为这片西方的国度里没有农田和房屋，土地也没有开垦过。

下午的时候，太阳火辣辣地照着他们的脸，因为这地方没有树木遮阴。于是，天没黑，多萝西、托托和狮子就累了，他们躺倒在草地上睡着了，铁皮樵夫和稻草人为他们放哨。

邪恶的西方女巫只有一只眼睛，但它却像望远镜一样厉害，能看到每一个地方。此时，坏女巫坐在自己的城堡门口四处张望，碰巧看见多萝西睡着了，她的朋友们围在她身边。这几个旅行者离城堡还有很长一段路，但坏女巫看见他们来到自己的国家，就非常生气，于是她吹响了挂在脖子上的银哨。

哨声一响，立刻有一群大狼从四面八方向女巫跑来。它们长着长腿、凶恶的眼睛和锋利的牙齿。

“到那些人那里去，”女巫说，“把他们撕碎。”

“您不要他们给您做奴隶了？”狼群头领问。

“不要了，”女巫说，“一个是铁皮做的，一个是稻草做的，再加上一个小丫头，还有一头狮子。没有哪个适合干活，所以你们去把他们撕碎吧。”

“好。”那匹狼说完，全速飞奔而去，其他的狼也跟着他跑开了。

幸好，稻草人和铁皮樵夫十分清醒，听到狼群来了。

“我来应战，”樵夫说，“大家都到我身后，等它们来了，让我来对付它们。”

他抓起磨得十分锋利的斧头，等狼群头领扑上来时，他挥动胳膊，砍掉了狼头，那狼立刻就死了。樵夫刚能举起斧头，又一匹狼扑上来，它也倒在铁皮樵夫锋利的斧头下。每次一匹，樵夫一共砍死了四十匹狼。最后它们都堆积在樵夫面前。

之后，樵夫放下斧头，坐到稻草人身边。稻草人说：

“干得漂亮，朋友。”

他俩一直等到第二天早晨多萝西醒来。小姑娘看到一大堆毛烘烘的死狼，吓坏了。铁皮樵夫就把昨晚的事情都告诉了她。多萝西听完，感谢樵夫救了他们。等她吃完早餐，大家又开始赶路了。

还是这天早晨，女巫来到城堡门口，用她那只看得很远的眼睛朝外张望。她看见她的狼全死了，而那几个外乡人还在自己的国家旅行。这让她火气更大了，她第二次吹响银哨。

听到哨音，一大群野乌鸦立即朝女巫飞来，遮蔽了天空。坏女巫对鸦王说：

“马上飞到那些外乡人那里，啄出他们的眼睛，把他们撕成碎片。”

于是，这一大群野乌鸦向多萝西和她的伙伴们飞去。小姑娘看到乌鸦飞来，非常害怕。这时，稻草人说：

“我来对付它们，你们躺在我身边，就不会受伤。”

于是，大家都躺在地上，只有稻草人站立着，伸直胳膊。乌鸦一看到他，都害怕了，不敢再靠近，因为它们之前总是受到稻草人惊吓。然而，鸦王说：

“他只是个稻草人。我要把他的眼珠啄出来。”

鸦王说完，冲稻草人飞来，却被稻草人一把抓住头扭断脖子，死了。又一只乌鸦飞来，也被稻草人扭断了脖子。一只接着一只，稻草人一共扭断了四十只乌鸦的脖子。最后它们都死在稻草人脚边。这之后，稻草人才叫伙伴们起身。大家又继续赶路。

坏女巫又往外看去，只见她的乌鸦全倒成一片，她勃然大怒，第三次吹响银哨。

哨声一响，空中立刻传来一大片嗡嗡声，一群黑蜂朝女巫飞来。

“到那些外乡人那里去，蜇死他们！”女巫命令道。黑蜂们听了转身疾飞，一直来到在赶路的多萝西和她的朋友们周围。幸好樵夫已经看到黑蜂飞来了，而稻草人也决定了要怎么行动。

“把我的稻草掏出来，撒在小姑娘、狗和狮子身上，”稻草人对樵夫说，“那样黑蜂就蜇不着他们了。”樵夫照他的话做了。多萝西紧挨着狮子躺下，怀里抱着托托，稻草把他们完全盖住了。

黑蜂飞来了，它们发现除了樵夫，谁也蜇不着，就都飞向樵夫，结果全在铁皮上折断了毒刺，却丝毫没有伤到樵夫。黑蜂折断毒刺后就活不了，所以它们全都死了，密密麻麻地落在樵夫周围，像是一小堆一小堆的煤屑。

这时，多萝西和狮子站起来，小姑娘帮着铁皮樵夫把稻草塞回稻草人身体里，让他恢复原样。随后，大家又动身上路。

坏女巫看到她的黑蜂都死了，一小堆一小堆像煤屑一样，气得又是跺脚，又是扯头发，又是咬牙切齿。于是，她叫来十二个温基人奴隶，给他们锋利的长矛，让他们去杀死那几个外乡人。

温基人不是一个勇敢的民族，但他们不得不听从女巫的命令。于是，他们动身出发，一直走到多萝西附近。这时，狮子大吼一声，扑向他们。可怜的温基人吓得撒腿往回飞跑。

他们回到城堡后，坏女巫用皮带狠狠地抽打他们，又派他们回去干活。这之后，女巫坐下来为下一步做打算。她不明白为什么消灭这些外乡人的计划都失败了；但她是一个法力强大的女巫，而且心地邪恶，不一会儿就想好了该怎么办。

女巫的橱柜里有一顶金冠，上面镶嵌着一圈钻石和红宝石。这顶金冠有一种魔力。无论谁拥有它，都可以召唤三次飞猴，无论发出什么命令，飞猴都会听从。但没有人能控制这些奇怪的动物超过三次。坏女巫已经用了两次金冠的魔力。第一次，她使温基人做了她的奴隶，让自己统治了温基国。飞猴在这件事上帮助了她。第二次，她与伟大的奥兹本人交战，把他赶出了西方的国土。飞猴在这件事上也帮助了她。女巫只能再用一次金冠，正因为这个原因，她直到自己的所有其他魔力都用完了，才愿用这个办法。现在，她的恶狼、野乌鸦、蜇人的黑蜂都死了，她的奴隶也被胆小狮吓跑了，女巫意识到只剩下一个办法能消灭多萝西和她的朋友们。

于是，坏女巫从橱柜里取出金冠，戴在头上。

接着，她左脚独立，慢慢念道：

“艾—普，派—普，卡—克！”

然后，她又右脚独立，念道：

“西—罗，霍—罗，哈—罗！”

这之后，她两脚站立，大喊道：

“兹—兹，祖—兹，兹克！”

魔力开始发动。天色暗下来，空中传来低沉的隆隆声。接着，传来许多翅膀扑扇的声音，还有响亮的嘶叫声和笑声。随后，太阳钻出昏暗的天空，照亮了被一群猴子围绕着的坏女巫，这些猴子每只的肩上都长着一对巨大、有力的翅膀。

有一只飞猴比其他飞猴大许多，像是他们的头领。他飞近女巫，说：

“您已经是第三次，也是最后一次召唤我们了。您有什么吩咐？”

“到那几个我国土上的外乡人那里去，把他们全部消灭，只留下狮子，”女巫说，“再把那头野兽带到我这里，我要像驾驭马一样将他驯服，让他干活。”

“遵命。”飞猴头领说。随后，就听到一大片嘶叫声和吵闹声，飞猴们飞向正在赶路的多萝西和她的朋友们。

一些飞猴抓住铁皮樵夫，拽着他飞上天空，一直飞到一片布满尖利岩石的原野上空。他们把可怜的樵夫从这里扔下去。樵夫从高空坠落，狠狠地摔在岩石上，摔得浑身坑坑洼洼，躺在那里，动不了身，也哼不出声。

还有一些飞猴抓住了稻草人，用他们的长手指拽出他身子和脑袋里的所有稻草，把他的帽子、靴子和衣服捆成一小团，扔上一棵大树的树顶。

其余的飞猴用几根结实的绳子缠住狮子，绕着他的身子、脑袋和腿绑了一道又一道，直到狮子怎么也咬不着、抓不到、挣扎不得时才住手。之后，他们抬着狮子飞向女巫的城堡，把狮子放进一个围着高高的铁栅栏的小院子，免得他逃跑。

可是，飞猴们一点也没伤害多萝西。小姑娘怀抱托托站在那里，看着伙伴们一个个惨遭厄运，心想马上就轮到自己了。飞猴头领飞向多萝西，他伸出毛烘烘的长臂，丑陋的脸上露出可怕的笑容。正在这时，他看到多萝西额上有好女巫的吻痕，猛然停住了，并示意其他飞猴不要碰多萝西。

“我们不敢伤害这个小姑娘，”头领对飞猴们说，“因为她受到善力的保护，它比恶力更强大。我们能做的就是，送她到坏女巫的城堡，把她留在那里。”

于是，他们小心翼翼地轻轻托起多萝西，带着她急速飞往城堡，然后把她放在前门台阶上。飞猴头领对女巫说：

“我们已经尽力遵循您的吩咐。铁皮樵夫和稻草人都毁掉了，狮子绑在了您的院子里。我们不敢伤害这个小姑娘，还有她怀里抱着的小狗。您对我们猴群的魔力已经用完，再也不会见到我们了。”

他说完这话，所有飞猴吵着嚷着笑着，飞上天空，一会儿便远去不见了。

坏女巫看到多萝西额头上的印记，又吃惊又担忧，她心里清楚不论是飞猴还是她自己，都不敢动这小姑娘一根指头。她又低头看多萝西的脚，看到那双银鞋，她吓得发抖，因为这银鞋的巨大魔力她知道。女巫起初想逃跑；这时她凑巧望见了多萝西的眼睛：这眼睛背后的心灵是多么单纯！小姑娘不会知道银鞋能给她多么神奇的魔力。想到这里，女巫径自笑了：“我还是可以奴役她，因为她并不知道怎样使用她的魔力。”于是，她凶巴巴地对多萝西说：

“跟我来；你一定要把我说的每句话放在心上，不然我就结果了你，让你的下场与铁皮樵夫和稻草人一样。”

多萝西跟着女巫穿过城堡里许多漂亮的房间，一直来到厨房，女巫让她在这里刷锅洗碗、扫地添柴。

多萝西乖乖地去干活，决心不遗余力，因为她很高兴邪恶女巫决定留她一命。

女巫看到多萝西卖力地干活后，就想到院子里去，像骑马一样驾驭胆小狮；女巫相信，以后无论到哪里去，都让狮子拉车，自己肯定非常开心。可是，她刚一开门，胆小狮就一声大吼，朝她猛扑过来，女巫吓得奔出院子，重又关上院门。

“我驾驭不了你，”女巫隔着院门栏杆冲狮子说，“也能饿着你。等到你听我的话，我才给你饭吃。”

从那以后，她什么也不给被囚禁的狮子吃，却每天中午都到门口，朝里面问：

“你愿意像马一样拉车吗？”

狮子总是回答：

“不。要是你走进院子，我就咬你。”

狮子之所以不用照着女巫的要求做，是因为每天夜里，等到女巫睡着了，多萝西就从橱柜里拿食物给狮子吃。狮子吃完，卧在稻草垫子上，多萝西躺在狮子身旁，头枕着他柔软蓬乱的鬃毛，他俩谈论自己身处的困境，盘算着要逃出去。可是，他们想不出怎样才能逃出城堡，因为这里时时刻刻都有黄色的温基人守卫，他们是坏女巫的奴隶，不敢不按她的意思办事。

小姑娘白天得卖力干活，女巫经常威胁说要用手里一直拿着的旧雨伞揍她。但其实女巫并不敢打多萝西，因为她额头上有印记。小姑娘却不知道这一点，她为自己和托托满心担忧。有一次，女巫用雨伞打了托托一下，这只勇敢的小狗做出反击，冲上去咬了女巫的腿。女巫竟没有流血，原来她太邪恶了，身上的血好多年前就已经枯干了。

多萝西渐渐明白，想要回到堪萨斯，回到艾姆婶婶身边，比以前更难了，因此她的日子变得很难过。有时候，她一连几个小时地痛哭，这时托托蹲在她脚边，望着她的脸，悲伤地呜呜叫，倾诉它为小主人感到多么难过。实际上，托托不在乎它是在堪萨斯还是在奥兹国，只要有多萝西陪伴就行；可它明白小姑娘不开心，因此它也开心不了。

现在，坏女巫非常渴望拥有多萝西脚上穿的银鞋。她的黑蜂、乌鸦和狼成了一堆堆正在风干的死尸，她也用尽了金冠的魔力；可要是能把银鞋搞到手，她就能得到巨大的魔力，比之前失去的所有魔力加起来还大。女巫紧紧盯着多萝西，看她会不会脱下银鞋，想找机会偷走鞋子。可是小姑娘太为漂亮的银鞋感到自豪了，除了夜里和洗澡时，她无时无刻不穿着银鞋。女巫特别害怕黑暗，不敢在夜里走进多萝西的房间偷鞋，至于水，她就更害怕了，因此多萝西洗澡的时候，她从不靠近。实际上，这个老女巫从不碰水，也从不让一星半点的水碰到自己。

但是，坏女巫很狡猾，她终于想到一条诡计，可以搞到自己渴望的东西。她在厨房的地板中央放了一根铁棍，然后施展魔法，让人眼睛看不到它。于是，多萝西走过地板时，由于看不到铁棍，被绊倒在地。她摔得并不重，但一只银鞋却掉落了；女巫不等她伸手够着鞋子，便一把抢去，套在了自己瘦骨嶙峋的脚上。

这坏心眼的女人诡计得逞，高兴极了。只要她有了一只银鞋，就拥有一半银鞋的魔力，多萝西就算知道怎么施展魔法，也对付不了她。

小姑娘见自己丢了一只漂亮的鞋子，生气地冲女巫说：

“把鞋还给我！”

“不给，”女巫反驳道，“它现在是我的鞋了，不是你的鞋。”

“你这个坏蛋！”多萝西大声说，“你没权拿走我的鞋。”

“我要留下这只鞋，随你怎么说，”女巫嘲弄地说，“总有一天，我会把另外一只也搞到手。”

这话激怒了多萝西，她提起身旁的一桶水，泼向女巫，把她从头到脚浇了个透。

立刻，女巫发出一声恐惧的大叫，多萝西惊讶地朝她望去，只见女巫开始收缩、变小。

“看你干的好事！”女巫尖叫着，“我马上就要融化了。”

“真是对不起。”多萝西看到女巫竟然像红糖一样在她眼前融化，她真的害怕了。

“你不知道水会要我的命吗？”女巫绝望地哭号。

“当然不知道，”多萝西回答，“我怎么能知道？”

“哎，一会儿我就会全化掉，城堡是你的了。我做了一辈子坏事，从没想到你这么一个小丫头能融化我，结束我的恶行。看呐——我走了！”

话音刚落，女巫倒在地上，化成一摊难看的棕色浆液，在厨房的干净地板上漫流。多萝西看到女巫真的融化不见了，就又提起一桶水，浇在那摊浆液上，再把它全部扫出门。随后，多萝西捡起那老巫婆身上仅剩的银鞋，用布擦干净，重新穿到自己脚上。多萝西终于自由了，她跑出厨房，来到院子里，告诉狮子：邪恶的西方女巫已经死了，他们不再是异乡的囚犯了。

第十三章　营救

听说坏女巫已经被一桶水融化了，胆小狮非常高兴。多萝西立刻打开牢门，放他出来。他俩一同走进城堡，多萝西做的第一件事就是召集所有温基人，告诉大家他们不再是奴隶了。

黄色的温基人欢呼雀跃，因为许多年来他们被迫为坏女巫辛苦做工，而她对待他们总是非常残忍。从那以后，他们一直把这一天当作节日，宴饮跳舞来庆祝。

“要是我们的朋友稻草人和铁皮樵夫和我们在一起，”狮子说，“我该多高兴。”

“你不觉得我们可以救他们吗？”小姑娘焦急地问。

“我们可以试试。”狮子回答。

因此，他们叫来黄色的温基人，问温基人愿意不愿意帮忙援救他们的朋友。温基人说他们乐意为多萝西竭尽全力，是她解放了他们。于是，多萝西挑选了一些看上去最有见识的温基人，大家一起上路了。他们走了一天多，终于来到那片布满岩石的原野，铁皮樵夫躺在那里，浑身坑坑洼洼。斧头落在他近旁，可斧刃生了锈，斧柄摔断了。

温基人轻柔地抱起樵夫，把他抬回黄色城堡，一路上，多萝西看到老朋友的可怜样子，洒下了眼泪，狮子脸色阴沉悲伤。等他们到达城堡，多萝西对温基人说：

“你们之中有铁匠吗？”

“噢，有。我们有几位很优秀的铁匠。”温基人回答。

“请把他们领到我这里来。”多萝西说。后来，铁匠们提着装满各种工具的篮子来了，多萝西问道：

“你们能敲平铁皮樵夫身上的凹坑，把他扳回原状，并补好摔破的地方吗？”

铁匠们仔细查看樵夫之后，回答说他们相信自己能把樵夫修复如初。于是，他们在城堡的一个黄色大房间里开始工作，一连干了三天四夜，把铁皮樵夫的腿脚、身子和脑袋敲敲打打、拧来拧去、修修补补、打磨擦净，终于修理完毕，樵夫恢复了原状，关节也像从前一样灵活自如。当然，樵夫身上还是多了几个补丁，但铁匠们补得很棒，而且樵夫不是虚荣的人，丝毫不在意这些补丁。

最后，樵夫走进多萝西的房间，感谢她救活了自己，他高兴得直流眼泪。多萝西用围裙仔细地为他擦去泪水，免得他的关节生锈。这时，多萝西自己却因为再次见到老朋友高兴得泪如雨下，而这些眼泪用不着擦去。再看狮子，他不住地用尾巴尖擦眼睛，尾巴尖都湿透了，他不得不走到外面院子里，在太阳下晒干尾巴。

“要是稻草人还和我们在一起，”铁皮樵夫听多萝西讲完发生的一切，说道，“我该多高兴。”

“我们必须想办法找到他。”小姑娘说。

说完，她叫温基人来帮忙。他们走了一天多，终于来到大树下，稻草人的衣服就是被飞猴扔上了这棵树的树顶。

这是一棵非常高的树，树干光溜溜，谁也爬不上去；这时，樵夫马上开口说：

“我来砍倒它，那样我们就能拿到稻草人的衣服。”

原来在铁匠们修补樵夫的时候，有一个温基人是个金匠，他用纯金打造了一根斧柄，装在樵夫的斧头上，换下了那根摔坏的斧柄。其他人则把斧刃打磨得一点锈渍都没有，像擦亮的银器一样闪闪发光。

铁皮樵夫说砍就砍，不一会儿大树就轰然倒下，稻草人的衣服从树枝上落下，掉在地上。

多萝西捡起那些衣服，让温基人带回城堡，塞满干净的上好稻草。看呐！稻草人又完好如初了，他一遍又一遍地感谢大家救了他。

就这样，多萝西和朋友们又团聚了，他们在黄色城堡度过了几天快乐日子，舒服生活所需要的一切，城堡里都有。可是有一天，小姑娘想起了艾姆婶婶，她说：

“我们得回奥兹城去，请奥兹履行诺言。”

“对，”樵夫说，“我终于要有一颗心了。”

“那我要有脑子了。”稻草人高兴地补充。

“那我要有胆量了。”狮子若有所思地说。

“那我要回到堪萨斯了。”多萝西拍着手叫道，“噢，我们明天就出发去翡翠城吧！”

他们决定就这么办。第二天，他们把温基人叫到一处，与温基人道别。温基人舍不得让这些伙伴离开，他们喜欢上了铁皮樵夫，请求他留下来，统治他们和黄色的西方国土。在得知伙伴们一定要走之后，温基人送给托托和狮子各一个金项圈，送给多萝西一只镶嵌钻石的漂亮手镯，送给稻草人一根金头手杖，免得他跌倒，还送给铁皮樵夫一只镶金嵌宝的银油壶。

每位旅行者都向温基人美言一番，表示感谢，又都与温基人握手告别，胳膊都摇疼了。

多萝西到女巫的橱柜里找食物，好装进篮子带在路上吃。在那里，她看见了金冠。她试着把它戴在自己头上，发现大小正合适。她对金冠的魔力一点都不知道，只是见它很漂亮，就决定戴着金冠，把太阳帽放进篮子。

大家都为旅行做好了准备，随后就朝翡翠城进发了；温基人向他们欢呼三声，说了许多祝福的话。

第十四章　飞猴

你应该还记得，在坏女巫的城堡和翡翠城之间没有路，连一条小道也没有。四位旅行者寻找坏女巫时，是女巫发现了他们，派飞猴把他们送到自己面前。这次没有人送，他们要穿过金凤花和黄色雏菊的广阔原野，回翡翠城去，就难得多了。当然，他们知道应该往东，往日出的方向直走；于是，他们朝着这个正确的方向动身了。可到了中午，太阳升到头顶，他们就不知道哪边是东哪边是西了，因此他们在茫茫原野中迷了路。然而，他们还是继续赶路，夜里，月亮升起来，洒下皎皎光明。于是，除了稻草人和铁皮樵夫，大家躺倒在芳香的黄色花丛中，熟睡到天亮。

第二天早晨，太阳躲在云后，可大家仍旧起身上路，好像十分确定该往哪个方向走。

“如果走得够快，”多萝西说，“我们肯定会在某个时候到达某个地方。”

可日复一日，他们眼前还是只有开满金凤花的黄色原野。稻草人开始发小牢骚。

“我们肯定迷了路，”他说，“要是不能及时找到去奥兹城的路，我就永远都不会得到脑子了。”

“那我就得不到心了，”铁皮樵夫大声说，“我觉得自己等不及到奥兹国，你们得承认，这段路确实很漫长。”

“你们看，”胆小狮抽泣道，“这根本没有终点，我没有胆量一直这么走下去。”

听大家这么一说，多萝西也灰心了。她坐在草地上望着伙伴们，而他们也坐在那里望着她；托托觉得这辈子头一次，它没有力气再去追逐飞过头顶的蝴蝶。它伸出舌头，直喘气，也望着多萝西，好像在问下一步大家该怎么办。

“如果叫来田鼠，”多萝西提议，“他们也许能告诉我们怎么去翡翠城。”

“他们当然能，”稻草人叫起来，“我们之前怎么没想到这个主意？”

多萝西吹响小哨子，自从田鼠女王送给她这只哨子，她就一直戴在脖子上。不一会儿，大家听到一阵细微的脚步声，一大群灰色的小田鼠朝多萝西跑来。女王自己也一同来了，她用尖细的声音问：

“我能帮上朋友们的忙吗？”

“我们迷路了，”多萝西说道，“你能告诉我们怎么去翡翠城吗？”

“当然了，”女王回答，“但翡翠城很远，因为你们一直都在往反方向走。”这时，她看见了多萝西的金冠，“你为什么不用金冠的魔力召集飞猴来帮助你们？用不了一个小时，他们就能送你们到奥兹城。”

“我不知道金冠有魔力。”多萝西很吃惊，“咒语是什么？”

“咒语写在金冠里面，”田鼠女王回答，“但是，如果你要召集飞猴，我们就得跑开了，因为他们爱搞恶作剧，以捉弄我们为乐。”

“他们不会伤害我吗？”小姑娘担心地问。

“噢，不会的。他们必须服从金冠的主人。再见！”说完，她急匆匆跑走，不见了踪影，别的田鼠也跟着她跑了。

多萝西查看金冠的里面，发现内衬上有字。她想这些一定就是咒语，于是她仔细读完说明，把金冠戴在头上。

“艾—普，派—普，卡—克！”她左脚独立，念道。

“你说什么？”稻草人不明白多萝西在做什么。

“西—罗，霍—罗，哈—罗！”多萝西又右脚独立，继续念道。

“哈罗！”铁皮樵夫平静地答道。

“兹—兹，祖—兹，兹克！”多萝西两脚站立，念道。咒语念完之后，大家听到巨大的翅膀扑扇声，还有笑闹的声音，就见那群猴子飞来了。猴王向多萝西深鞠一躬，问道：

“您有什么吩咐？”

“我们想去翡翠城，”小姑娘说，“可我们迷路了。”

“我们送你们去。”猴王答道。话音刚落，两只飞猴就抱起多萝西，带着她飞走了。别的飞猴带起稻草人、樵夫和狮子，一只小飞猴不顾托托竭力想咬他，抱着托托跟在后面。

一开始，稻草人和铁皮樵夫很害怕，因为他们还记得飞猴以前对待他们有多凶狠；可现在他们看到飞猴没有恶意，就高高兴兴地在高空飞行，欣赏地上美丽的花园和树林。

多萝西坐在两只飞猴中间轻松地飞行。这两只飞猴个头最大，其中一只就是猴王，他们用手臂搭成椅子，小心翼翼地不让多萝西受伤。

“你们为什么要服从金冠的魔力？”小姑娘问。

“说来话长，”猴王笑道，“不过我们的旅途也很漫长，要是你想听，我就讲讲其中的缘由，来打发时间。”

“我很愿意听。”多萝西答道。

“从前，”猴王打开了话匣子，“我们自由自在地生活在大森林里，从一棵树上飞到另一棵树上，吃坚果和水果，高兴做什么就做什么，不用听任何人的吩咐。也许我们有些飞猴有时太爱搞恶作剧了，他们从大树上飞下来拉扯没有翅膀的动物的尾巴，追逐鸟儿，还朝路过森林的人扔坚果。可那时，我们真是无忧无虑、开心有乐子，每时每刻都快活得很。这是很多年以前的事了，那时奥兹还没有从云上降下来统治这片土地。

“那时北方住着一位美丽的公主，她也是一位法力强大的魔法师。她把自己所有的魔法都用来帮助他人，从没听说她伤害过哪个好人。公主名叫加叶莱特，她住在用大块的红宝石砖建造的美丽宫殿中。人人都爱她，但她最苦恼的是找不到一个人来付出她的爱，因为所有男子都太蠢太丑，配不上如此美丽智慧的加叶莱特。最后，她终于找到一位合意的少年，他英俊、健美、智慧，远比同龄男子出色。加叶莱特打定主意，等少年长大成人，就嫁给他。于是，她把少年带去红宝石宫殿，倾尽魔力把他培养成所有女人都会爱慕的强健、善良又秀美的男子。少年名叫奎拉拉，后来据说他长成了世上最优秀、最智慧的男子，俊美非凡，加叶莱特深深爱着他，迫不及待地为婚礼做好了一切准备。

“我爷爷那时是猴王，他们住在加叶莱特宫殿附近的森林里。老人家特别喜欢开玩笑，为了一个玩笑宁可不吃一顿美餐。有一天，那是婚礼前夕，爷爷带着猴群飞出森林，正巧看到奎拉拉在河边散步。见奎拉拉身穿粉色绸缎和紫色天鹅绒裁成的华美衣服，爷爷想要捉弄他一番。爷爷一声令下，猴群飞下来，抓住奎拉拉，抱着他一直飞到河中央的上空，把他扔到了河里。

“‘游上来，好小伙子，’爷爷叫道，‘看看衣服有没有泡花！’奎拉拉聪明得很，当然会游泳，他一点都没被好运气宠坏。他冒出水面，大笑着游上岸。加叶莱特赶来，却看见奎拉拉的丝绸和天鹅绒衣服全被河水泡坏了。

“公主很恼火，她当然知道这是谁干的。于是，她让人叫来所有飞猴，先是说要绑上飞猴们的翅膀，就像他们对待奎拉拉那样，也把他们扔到河里。爷爷知道飞猴们被绑住翅膀扔到河里，一定会淹死，他苦苦恳求公主，再加上奎拉拉也为他们求情，最后公主饶过了他们，但她提出一个条件：从那以后飞猴要服从金冠主人的三次吩咐。金冠是作为送给奎拉拉的结婚礼物打造的，据说花去了举国财富的一半。自然，爷爷和其他飞猴立刻同意了那个条件，这就是为什么我们要给金冠的主人做三次奴隶，不管这主人是谁。”

“他们后来怎样了？”多萝西问，她对这个故事很有兴趣。

“奎拉拉成了这顶金冠的第一位主人，”猴王答道，“他是第一个吩咐我们的人。因为他的新娘受不了看见我们，所以他们结婚后，他就到森林里把我们都叫到他跟前，吩咐我们永远待在公主再也看不见一只飞猴的地方。我们很乐意这么做，因为我们都怕她。

“金冠落入邪恶的西方女巫手里之前，我们要做的就只有这些。那坏女巫让我们奴役温基人，后来又把奥兹本人赶出了西方的国度。如今金冠属于你了，你有权让我们听你三次吩咐。”

猴王的故事讲完了，多萝西从天空中往下看，只见翡翠城闪闪发光的绿色城墙出现在前方。小姑娘感到惊讶，猴子们竟然飞得这么快，但她很高兴旅行终于结束了。这些怪家伙小心翼翼地把旅行者们放在城门口，猴王向多萝西深鞠一躬，就带着猴群迅速地飞走了。

“这是一次美妙的空中旅行。”小姑娘说。

“是呀，还是摆脱麻烦的快捷方法。”狮子答道，“幸好你拿走了那顶奇妙的金冠！”

第十五章　发现可怕的奥兹的真面目

四位旅行者走到翡翠城的大门前，按响门铃。铃响了几声以后，他们从前见过的那位守门人打开了大门。

“怎么！你们又回来了？”他吃了一惊，问道。

“你看不见我们吗？”稻草人反问。

“可我以为你们去找邪恶的西方女巫了。”

“我们确实去找她了。”稻草人说。

“她又放了你们？”守门人惊讶地问。

“她没办法不放我们，因为她已经融化了。”稻草人解释道。

“融化了！噢，这可真是好消息。”守门人说，“是谁把她融化了？”

“是多萝西。”狮子郑重其事地说。

“太好了！”守门人高声说道，并朝多萝西深鞠一躬。

随后，守门人把他们领进自己的小屋，像上一次一样，他从大箱子里取出绿眼镜，帮大家戴上并锁好这之后，他们穿过大门，走进翡翠城。人们从守门人那儿听说多萝西把邪恶的西方女巫融化了，就都围住这几位旅行者。一大群人跟着他们往奥兹的宫殿去。

绿胡子士兵依然守在门前，但这次他立刻让大家进去了。美丽的绿姑娘再次接待他们，马上领他们到各人之前住过的房间休息，等伟大的奥兹准备好接见他们。

士兵直接禀告奥兹：多萝西和其他几位旅行者消灭坏女巫后，又回来了。可是奥兹没有回复。他们原以为大巫师奥兹会立刻召见他们，但是他没有。第二天，他们没有得到他的消息，第三天没有，第四天还是没有。他们等得无聊而疲倦，最后越来越恼火——奥兹让他们去经历困难和奴役后，竟然这样怠慢他们。于是，稻草人请绿姑娘再给奥兹捎个信，说如果奥兹不马上让他们进去拜见他，他们就召唤飞猴来帮忙，看看奥兹说话算不算数。奥兹得到这个消息，十分害怕，传话说隔天早晨九点四分在觐见室接见他们。奥兹在西方的土地上见识过飞猴，他不想再见到它们。

四位旅行者度过了一个无眠的夜晚，各人想着奥兹许诺送给自己的礼物。多萝西只睡着了一会儿，她梦见自己在堪萨斯，艾姆婶婶正对她说，真高兴自己的小姑娘又回家了。

第二天早晨九点，绿胡子士兵准时来到他们房间，四分钟后，他们都走进大巫师奥兹的觐见室。

很自然，每个人都以为要见到的奥兹是原来的样子，而当他们环顾四周，发现觐见室内空无一人时，都大吃一惊。他们紧靠房门，彼此紧紧挨在一起，因为空屋的寂静比他们之前看到的奥兹变换出的任何样子都吓人。

不一会儿，他们听到一个声音，好像是从靠近大圆顶中心的某个地方传来的。那个声音严肃地说道：

“我是奥兹，伟大而可怕的奥兹。你们为什么找我？”

大家又看看房间的每一个角落，还是没有看到任何人。多萝西就问：

“您在哪里？”

“我无处不在，”那声音说，“但凡人的眼看不到我。现在，我要坐上宝座，你们可以和我讲话。”这时，那声音好像真的正从宝座传来；于是，大家走到宝座前，站成一排。多萝西说：

“我们是来请您履行诺言的，奥兹。”

“什么诺言？”奥兹问。

“您许诺过，坏女巫死后，就送我回堪萨斯。”小姑娘说。

“您许诺过给我脑子。”稻草人说。

“您许诺过给我一颗心。”铁皮樵夫说。

“您许诺过给我胆量。”胆小狮说。

“坏女巫真的死了吗？”那声音问。多萝西觉得它有点发颤。

“是的，”她回答说，“我用一桶水把她融化了。”

“天啊，”那声音说，“太突然了！你们明天再来见我吧，因为我需要时间想一想。”

“你已经用了很多时间。”铁皮樵夫生气地说。

“我们不会再等一天了。”稻草人说。

“你得对我们说话算话！”多萝西喊叫着。

狮子觉得不妨吓唬一下巫师，于是发出一声洪亮的咆哮。这声音非常凶猛可怕，托托吓得惊慌地从狮子身边跳开。它一不小心踢翻了屋角的一面屏风。屏风哗啦一声倒在地上，大家都朝那边看，顿时惊呆了。因为他们看到屏风后面原来躲着一个小老头，他脑袋光秃，满脸皱纹，看起来跟大家一样惊讶。这时，铁皮樵夫举起斧头，朝小老头冲过去，他大声问：

“你是谁？”

“我是奥兹，伟大而可怕的奥兹。”小老头声音颤抖地说，“别打我——千万别打我！——你们要我做什么，我都照做。”

我们的朋友们吃惊又失望地看着他。

“我以为奥兹是一个大脑袋。”多萝西说。

“我以为奥兹是一位可爱的女士。”稻草人说。

“我以为奥兹是一头可怕的野兽。”铁皮樵夫说。

“我以为奥兹是一只火球。”狮子大声说。

“不，你们都错了。”小老头温和地说，“这些全是我装成的。”

“装成的！”多萝西喊道，“你不是一位伟大的巫师？”

“小声点，亲爱的，”他说，“别这么大声说话，让别人听见，我就完了。我装成大巫师。”

“你不是吗？”多萝西问。

“根本不是，亲爱的；我只是个普通人。”

“你连普通人都不如，”稻草人伤心地说，“你是个骗子。”

“一点也没错！”小老头搓着手说，好像听到这话很高兴，“我是个骗子。”

“可这很可怕，”铁皮樵夫说，“我究竟该怎么得到心呢？”

“我该怎么得到胆量呢？”狮子问。

“我该怎么得到脑子呢？”稻草人哭着说，用衣袖擦去眼中流出的泪水。

“我亲爱的朋友们，”奥兹说，“请你们不要提这些小事。想想我吧，我被揭穿了，要惹上大麻烦。”

“再没有人知道你是个骗子吗？”多萝西问。

“除了你们四个——和我自己，再没有人知道。”奥兹回答，“我愚弄了大家这么久，还以为永远不会被揭穿。让你们进入觐见室，是我犯的一个大错。平常，我连自己的臣民都不见，他们因此相信我非常可怕。”

“可是我不明白，”多萝西很困惑，“我看到的你是一个大脑袋，这是怎么回事？”

“这是我的一个把戏，”奥兹回答说，“请过来，我把这一切都告诉你们。”

小老头领路，大家跟着他来到觐见室后面的一个小房间。他指向房间的一角，那儿放着一颗大脑袋。这脑袋是用许多厚纸糊成的，脸画得十分精细。

“我用绳子把它挂在天花板上，”奥兹说，“然后，我站在屏风后拉一根线，控制眼睛的转动和嘴巴的张合。”

“可那声音是怎么回事？”多萝西问。

“我会口技，”小老头说，“我能让自己的声音从任何地方传出，所以你觉得声音是脑袋发出的。看，我还用这些东西骗你们。”

他接着向稻草人展示了他假扮可爱女士时穿的衣裙、戴的面具。铁皮樵夫看见凶恶的野兽只是一堆缝在一起、靠板条支撑的兽皮。而那火球也是假巫师吊在天花板上的，它其实是一团棉花，一浇上油就熊熊燃烧。

“真的，”稻草人说，“你应该为自己这样骗人感到羞愧。”

“是的，我确实感到羞愧，”小老头的语气充满悔恨，“可我只能这么办。大家请坐，这里有很多椅子。我给你们讲讲我的故事。”

于是，大家坐下，听他讲下面这个故事。

“我出生在奥马哈市——”

“噢，那儿离堪萨斯不远！”多萝西叫道。

“是的，但离这儿很远。”小老头伤心地摇摇头，“长大后，我做了口技艺人，还在一位口技大师那里受过良好训练。我能模仿任何鸟兽。”说到这儿，他学小猫喵喵叫了几声。托托竖起耳朵，四面张望，看小猫在哪里。“过了一段时间，”奥兹接着说，“我厌倦了口技，又当了一名气球驾驶员。”

“什么是气球驾驶员？”多萝西问。

“他在表演马戏的日子，乘气球上天，以此吸引人群，让人们掏钱看马戏。”他解释道。

“噢，”多萝西说，“我明白了。”

“有一天，我乘气球升空，绳子绞在了一起，我落不了地。就这样，气球一直升上高高的云端，被一股气流卷带着，飞了很远很远。我在空中飞了一天一夜，第二天早晨我醒来，发现气球飘在一座美丽的陌生国度上空。

“气球缓缓下落，我一点也没有受伤。但我发现自己在一群陌生人中，他们见我从云上来，以为我是一位大巫师。我当然默认了他们的想法，因为他们害怕我，并且许诺我让他们做什么，他们都照做。

“只是为了让我自己开心，让这些好人忙碌，我下令建造这座城市和我的宫殿；他们甘心乐意，并且做得很好。我想，这国度这么绿这么美，就叫它翡翠城吧。为了让它更名符其实，我给所有人戴上绿眼镜，这样他们看到的一切都是绿色的。”

“难道这里的一切不都是绿色的吗？”

“并不比其他城的更绿，”奥兹说，“不过你戴上绿眼镜后，看到的一切当然都是绿色的。翡翠城是多年前建造的。我被气球带来时还是一个小伙子，现在我已经很老了。我的人民戴绿眼镜太久了，于是大部分人以为这真是一座翡翠城，也自然是一个美丽的地方，盛产珠宝和贵金属，还有人让人们幸福所需的各样美好事物。我对人民很好，他们爱戴我。但自从这宫殿建成后，我就把自己关在里面，不见他们任何人。

“我最害怕的是那些女巫，因为我没有一点魔力，却很快发现她们确实能做奇妙的事。这国度里有四位女巫，分别统治住在东西南北四方的人民。幸运的是，北方和南方的女巫是好女巫，我知道她们不会伤害我；但东方和西方的女巫邪恶至极，如果她们认为我不比她们法力强，她们肯定会杀死我。就这样，有很多年我都怕极了她们；所以你想想，我听说你的房子掉在邪恶的东方女巫身上时多么高兴。你们到我这里来时，我什么都愿意答应，只要你们能除掉另一个坏女巫；可是，现在你已经把她融化了，而我却要羞愧地说，我履行不了自己的诺言。”

“我觉得你是个大坏蛋。”多萝西说。

“噢，不，亲爱的，我真的是一个好人，但我必须承认，我是一个糟糕的巫师。”

“您难道给不了我脑子吗？”稻草人问。

“你不需要脑子。你每天都在学习。婴儿有脑子，但知道的并不多。只有经验能带来知识，你在这世上生活得越久，得到的经验肯定就越多。”

“也许是那样的，”稻草人说，“但除非您给我脑子，否则我就开心不起来。”

假巫师仔细打量着稻草人。

“好吧，”他叹了口气说，“我说过，我不算是一个魔法师。但明天上午你来吧，我会往你脑袋里装些脑子的。可是，我不能告诉你怎么用这些脑子，你得自己领会。”

“噢，谢谢——谢谢您！”稻草人叫道，“不用担心，我会找到用脑子的方法！”

“那我的胆量呢？”狮子焦急地问。

“我相信你很有胆量，”奥兹回答，“你所需要的只是相信自己。没有什么生物遇到危险不害怕。真正的胆量是在感到害怕时能直面危险，而这样的胆量你有许多。”

“也许我有，但我还是一样害怕。”狮子说，“除非您给我那种让人忘记恐惧的胆量，不然，我真的会很不开心。”

“好的，我明天给你那种胆量。”奥兹回答道。

“那我的心呢？”铁皮樵夫问。

“哎呀，至于那个，”奥兹说，“我觉得你不该想要一颗心。心让许多人不幸福。你没有心是很幸运的，要是你明白这点就好了。”

“这事见仁见智。”铁皮樵夫说，“如果您给我一颗心，我愿意毫无怨言地承受它带来的一切苦恼。”

“好，”奥兹温和地说，“明天你来我这里，我给你一颗心。我扮了许多年巫师，不妨再扮一阵子。”

“那么，”多萝西说，“我怎么能回到堪萨斯？”

“这我们得想一想。”小老头回答说，“请给我两三天时间考虑这件事，我会想个办法把你送出沙漠。这期间，你们就是我的客人，你们住在这座宫殿里，我的人会服侍你们，哪怕是你们最微小的愿望，都会得到满足。我只求你们也帮我一个忙——不是什么大事。请你们保守秘密，不告诉任何人我是个骗子。”

大家答应不透露一点所见所闻，随后兴高采烈地回到自己的房间。就连多萝西也希望这个被她称为“伟大而可怕的骗子”的人能设法送她回堪萨斯。如果他真做到了，多萝西愿意原谅他之前的一切所作所为。

第十六章　大骗子的魔术

第二天早晨，稻草人对朋友们说：

“祝贺我吧。我终于要去奥兹那里得到脑子了。我回来时，就和其他人一样了。”

“我一直喜欢你本来的样子。”多萝西直白地说。

“谢谢你喜欢一个稻草人。”他回答道，“等你听到我的新脑子冒出的奇思妙想时，你肯定会对我刮目相看。”说完，他愉快地告别大家，来到觐见室门口，轻轻地敲敲门。

“请进。”奥兹应声说。

稻草人走进觐见室，看见小老头坐在窗边，陷入沉思。

“我是来要脑子的。”稻草人有点不安地说。

“噢，好的。请坐在那把椅子上，”奥兹说，“请你原谅，我不得不拆下你的脑袋，这样我才能把脑子放到合适的地方。”

“没关系，”稻草人说，“非常欢迎您拆下我的脑袋，只要您再把它缝上时，它能变得更好就行。”

于是，奥兹拆下稻草人的脑袋，掏空里面的稻草，然后到里屋取出一升掺了许多大头针和缝衣针的谷糠，摇晃一番让它们彻底混合，再把混合物倒进稻草人头顶，用稻草塞满空隙，让脑袋成型。奥兹把稻草人的脑袋重新缝在他的身子上，对他说：

“从今以后，你就是个了不起的人了，因为我给了你许多新糠脑子。”

稻草人实现了自己最大的愿望，又高兴又骄傲，他热情地感谢了奥兹，回到朋友们那里。

多萝西好奇地看着他。他的脑袋因为装了脑子，顶上鼓鼓囊囊的。

“你感觉怎么样？”多萝西问。

“我觉得自己确实聪明了，”稻草人真诚地说，“等我习惯了自己的脑子，我就会无所不知。”

“为什么这些大头针和缝衣针从你脑袋里突出来？”铁皮樵夫问。

“这证明他思想敏锐。”狮子说。

“噢，我必须到奥兹那里去得到我的心。”樵夫说完，走到觐见室门口，敲了敲门。

“请进。”奥兹答道。樵夫走进觐见室，说：

“我是来要心的。”

“好的，”小老头回答，“但我得在你胸口开一个洞，这样我才能把心放到合适的地方。我希望这不会弄疼你。”

“噢，不会的，”樵夫说，“我一点也感觉不到。”

于是，奥兹拿来一副铁匠的大剪刀，在铁皮樵夫的左胸口开了一个方形的小洞，又从五斗橱里拿出一颗漂亮的心。这颗心整个是用丝绸做的，里面填满锯末。

“漂亮吗？”他问。

“真漂亮！”樵夫十分满意地说，“这颗心善良吗？”

“噢，非常善良！”奥兹回答。他把那颗心放进樵夫的胸膛，然后把方形的小洞补好，焊牢切口。

“好了，”奥兹说，“现在你有一颗会让任何人都感到骄傲的心。很抱歉，我不得不在你的胸口打个补丁，我实在是没有办法。”

“没关系，”樵夫高兴地大声说，“非常感谢您，我会永远记得您的帮助。”

“不客气。”奥兹回答。

铁皮樵夫回到朋友那里。大家都因为他的好运而祝贺他。

这次，狮子走到觐见室门口，敲了敲门。

“请进。”奥兹应声说。

“我是来要胆量的。”狮子一边走进房间，一边宣布。

“好，”奥兹答道，“我拿给你。”

他走到橱柜边，伸手从高架上取下一只绿色方瓶，把里面的液体倒进一只雕工精美的绿金色碟子，端到胆小狮面前。狮子用鼻子嗅嗅，似乎不喜欢那味道。奥兹说：

“喝吧。”

“这是什么？”狮子问。

“噢，”奥兹说，“如果你把它喝下肚，它就变成胆量。你当然知道，胆量在身体里；所以，只有你喝下去以后，这东西才能叫作胆量。我劝你赶紧喝了它吧。”

狮子听完不再犹豫，喝干了碟子里的液体。

“现在你感觉怎么样？”奥兹问。

“浑身是胆。”狮子回答。他高高兴兴地回到朋友们那里，告诉他们自己多么幸运。

大家都离开后，奥兹想到他成功地给了稻草人、铁皮樵夫和狮子他们以为自己没有的东西，就笑了。“我怎么能不骗他们呢？”奥兹自言自语道，“他们几个让我办的事，人人都知道是办不到的。让稻草人、铁皮樵夫和狮子开心不难，因为他们把我想象得无所不能。可是要送多萝西回堪萨斯，光靠想象力可不够，我真不知道怎么才能办到。”

第十七章　气球升空

三天了，多萝西没有听到奥兹给她的任何消息。尽管朋友们都非常高兴又满足，但这些日子多萝西很伤心。稻草人告诉大家，他脑袋里充满奇思妙想，但没说这些想法是什么，因为他知道除了自己，没人能明白。铁皮樵夫感觉走路时，心在胸腔里怦怦跳动；他对多萝西说，他发现这颗心比他还是血肉之躯时的那颗心还要善良温柔。狮子声称，他在这个世界上什么也不怕，乐意直面一支军队或十几头凶猛的卡利达。

因此，除了多萝西，小伙伴们个个心满意足。而她越发渴望回到堪萨斯。

第四天，奥兹终于召见多萝西，小姑娘高兴极了。她走进觐见室，奥兹愉快地说：

“请坐，亲爱的。我想我找到了送你离开这个国度的办法。”

“回到堪萨斯吗？”多萝西急切地问。

“噢，不一定能到堪萨斯，”奥兹说，“因为我根本不知道它在哪个方向。但我们要做的第一件事是跨越沙漠，之后你就很容易找到回家的路了。”

“我怎么能跨越沙漠呢？”多萝西问。

“好，我来说说我的想法。”小老头说，“你看，我是乘气球来到这个国度的。你被旋风卷带着，也是从空中来。所以，我相信最好从空中跨越沙漠。要制造一场旋风，我完全办不到；但我仔细考虑了这件事，我自信能造一只气球。”

“那怎么造呢？”多萝西问。

“气球，”奥兹说，“用绸缎缝制，刷上胶，让里面的氢气漏不出来。我的宫殿里有许多绸缎，造一只气球没问题。不过，这个国度里没有氢气来充气球，好让它飘起来。”

“如果气球飘不起来，”多萝西说，“它对我们就没有用了。”

“对。”奥兹说，“但还有一种办法可以让它飘起来，就是给它充热气。热气比不上氢气，因为如果热气冷却下来，气球会落在沙漠里，我们就要迷路。”

“我们！”小姑娘叫道，“您要和我一起走吗？”

“是呀，当然。”奥兹回答说，“我厌倦了当这样的骗子。如果我走出宫殿，我的人民很快就会发现我不是一位巫师，他们会因为我欺骗了他们而恼怒。因此，我不得不整天关在这些房间里，这无聊得很。我宁愿跟你去堪萨斯，回到马戏团里。”

“我很高兴有您做伴。”多萝西说。

“谢谢。”奥兹说，“现在，如果你愿意帮我缝绸缎，我们就开始造气球。”

于是，多萝西拿起针线，奥兹把缎带裁成合适的形状，小姑娘飞快地把它们缝合整齐。先是淡绿色缎带，然后是深绿色缎带，接着是翡翠绿色缎带；奥兹想要气球由不同色调的绿缎带拼成。他们花了三天缝完所有的缎带，缝好了一只长二十多英尺的绿色大绸布袋。

接着，奥兹在里面刷上一层薄胶，使它不透气。之后，他宣布气球造好了。

“可我们还需要一只篮子来载我们。”奥兹说。于是，他派绿胡子士兵取来一只绿色的大洗衣篮，用许多根绳子系在气球底下。

这一切准备好后，奥兹向他的人民传话说，他要去拜访一位住在云端的大巫师兄弟。这个消息很快传遍了翡翠城，人们都来观看这场盛况。

奥兹下令将气球抬到宫殿前面，人们好奇地看着气球。铁皮樵夫已经劈好一大堆木柴，他生起火，奥兹把气球的底部举在火堆上，这样从火堆上腾起的热气就会被收集到绸布袋里。气球渐渐膨胀升空，直到篮子触到地面。

这时，奥兹走进篮子，大声对他的人民宣布：

“我要外出访问。在我离开的这段时间，稻草人将统治你们。我命令你们服从他，如同服从我一样。”

这时，气球拽紧了将它系在地面的绳子，因为内部充满热气，气球比外部的空气轻了许多，所以它把绳子扯得紧紧的往空中飞升。

“快来，多萝西！”巫师大喊道，“快点，否则气球就要飞走了。”

“我怎么也找不到托托了。”多萝西回答。她不想落下她的小狗。原来托托钻进了人群，去冲一只小喵吠叫。多萝西终于找到它，抱起它朝气球飞跑。

眼看多萝西离气球只差几步了，奥兹正伸着手要帮她跨进篮子。突然，咔嚓一声，绳子断了！气球一下子升上天空，多萝西被留在了地上。

“回来！”她尖叫着，“我也要走！”

“我回不去，亲爱的，”奥兹从篮子上冲下边喊，“再见！”

“再见！”人们都喊道。所有人都抬头望着乘篮子升空的奥兹，篮子越升越高，飞上天空。

这是人们最后一次见到神奇的巫师奥兹。也许他已经安全到达奥马哈市，并且现在还在那里。不过，人们深切地怀念他，对彼此说：

“奥兹一直是我们的朋友。他在的时候为我们建造了这座美丽的翡翠城，如今他走了，又留下智慧的稻草人统治我们。”

可是，人们还是为失去这位神奇的巫师伤心了很多日子，心情难以平静。

第十八章　到南方去

多萝西回堪萨斯的希望破灭了，她伤心痛哭。但她细想一番后，又为自己没有乘气球飞去而高兴。同时，她为失去奥兹感到惋惜，她的伙伴们也感到惋惜。

铁皮樵夫对她说：

“奥兹给了我一颗可爱的心，如果我不为失去他难过，那我真是忘恩负义。他走了，我多想哭一会儿。你愿意好心地帮我擦去眼泪，免得我生锈吗？”

“当然愿意。”多萝西说完，立刻拿来一条毛巾。铁皮樵夫哭了好几分钟。多萝西仔细盯着他流出的眼泪，用毛巾擦干。樵夫哭完，真诚地感谢多萝西，并用镶嵌着宝石的油壶给自己从头到脚上了一遍油，免得生锈。

稻草人现在是翡翠城的统治者。尽管他不是一位巫师，但人们还是为他感到骄傲。“因为，”他们说，“世界上再没有哪座城市是由稻草人统治的。”据他们所知，他们这说法完全正确。

气球带着奥兹飞走后的那个早晨，四位旅行者聚在觐见室商量。稻草人坐在大宝座上，其他人恭敬地站在他面前。

“我们并不算太不走运，”新统治者说，“因为这座宫殿和翡翠城属于我们，我们可以随心所愿。我记得我不久前还被农夫绑在玉米地里的一根竿子上，现在却成了这座美丽城市的统治者，我对我的命运很满意。”

“我也是，”铁皮樵夫说，“对自己的新心很满意；说真的，它是我在世界上唯一想要的东西。”

“至于我，我现在就算不比世界上其他野兽更勇敢，也至少和他们一样勇敢。知道这一点，我就心满意足。”狮子谦虚地说。

“要是多萝西乐意住在翡翠城，”稻草人说，“我们就都能开心地在一起了。”

“可是我不想住在这儿，”多萝西叫道，“我想回堪萨斯，同艾姆婶婶和亨利叔叔一起住。”

“噢，这可怎么办？”樵夫问。

稻草人决心想个办法，他绞尽脑汁，大头针和缝衣针都开始钻出他的脑袋。最后，他说：

“为什么不召唤飞猴，让他们带你飞越沙漠？”

“我从来没想过这个！”多萝西开心地说，“就这么办。我马上去拿金冠。”

多萝西把金冠拿进觐见室，念起咒语。不一会儿，那群飞猴从敞开的窗户飞进房间，落在她身旁。

“这是您第二次召唤我们。”猴王朝小姑娘鞠了一躬说，“您有什么愿望？”

“我想请你们带我飞回堪萨斯。”多萝西回答。

猴王听了这话，摇摇头。

“那可办不到，”他说，“我们只属于这个国度，不能离开。堪萨斯还从来没有过飞猴，我想以后也不会有，因为他们不属于那里。我们愿意在我们能力范围之内为您效力，但我们不能飞越沙漠。再见。”

猴王又鞠了一躬，然后展开翅膀，从窗口飞走了，他的猴群也跟着飞走了。

多萝西失望得快要哭出来了。

“我白白浪费了一次金冠的魔力，”她说，“因为飞猴帮不了我。”

“这真是太糟糕了！”心软的樵夫说。

稻草人又在想办法，他的脑袋鼓胀得很厉害，多萝西害怕它会爆炸。

“我们叫绿胡子士兵进来，”稻草人说道，“问问他有什么建议。”

随后，士兵被召见，他胆怯地走进觐见室，因为奥兹在这里时，从来不许他跨进房门。

“这个小姑娘，”稻草人对士兵说道，“想越过沙漠。她该怎么办？”

“我不知道，”士兵回答，“因为除了奥兹本人，还没有谁曾越过沙漠。”

“没有人能帮助我吗？”多萝西诚恳地问。

“格林达也许能。”士兵建议道。

“格林达是谁？”稻草人问。

“她是南方女巫，在所有女巫中魔力最大，统治着夸德令人。还有，她的城堡在沙漠边上，所以也许她知道怎么越过沙漠。”

“格林达是位好女巫，对吗？”小姑娘问。

“夸德令人认为她很好，”士兵说，“而且她对每个人都很友善。我听说格林达是个美丽的女人，她知道怎样保持青春，尽管她已经活了许多年。”

“那我怎样才能到她的城堡去？”多萝西问。

“那条路直通南方，”士兵回答，“但据说对旅行者充满危险。树林里有野兽，还有一群不喜欢陌生人经过他们国度的怪人。因此，没有一个夸德令人来过翡翠城。”

士兵告退后，稻草人说：

“尽管充满危险，但多萝西似乎最好还是到南方去，请格林达帮助她。因为，毫无疑问，要是多萝西待在这儿，她就永远回不了堪萨斯。”

“你肯定又考虑过这个办法吧。”铁皮樵夫说。

“是的。”稻草人回答。

“我要和多萝西一起走，”狮子说，“因为我厌倦了你的城市，渴望到树林和乡野中去。你知道，我的确是一头野兽。再说，多萝西需要人来保护她。”

“没错。”樵夫表示同意，“我的斧头可能派得上用场，所以我也要和她一起去南方。”

“我们什么时候出发？”稻草人问。

“你也走？”大家吃惊地反问。

“当然。要不是多萝西，我绝不会有脑子。她把我从玉米地里的竿子上解下来，带我来到翡翠城。所以，我的好运都出于她，在她永远回堪萨斯之前，我绝不会离开她。”

“谢谢你们。”多萝西感激地说，“你们对我真好。可我想尽快出发。”

“我们明天一早就走。”稻草人回答道，“现在大家做好准备，因为这将是一次漫长的旅行。”

第十九章　遭到卫士树袭击

第二天早晨，多萝西吻别漂亮的绿姑娘，大家都与绿胡子士兵握了手，士兵一直把他们送到翡翠城大门口。守门人又见到了大家，听说他们要离开这座美丽的城市，陷入新的麻烦，他十分惊讶。但守门人马上解下他们的眼镜，放回绿箱子，又对他们说了许多祝福的话。

“您现在是我们的统治者，”守门人对稻草人说，“所以您必须尽快回来。”

“只要我能，肯定会的，”稻草人回答，“但我得先帮多萝西回家。”

多萝西最后一次告别和蔼的守门人，她说：

“我在你们这座美丽的城市受到了友善的招待，每个人都对我很好。你不知道我有多么感谢你们。”

“别这样说，亲爱的，”守门人说，“我们很想留住你，但既然你想回堪萨斯，我希望你能找到办法。”说完，他打开外墙上的大门，大家走出大门，踏上旅途。

我们的朋友们转身面朝南方的土地，灿烂的阳光照耀他们。大家兴高采烈，有说有笑。多萝西又满怀着回家的希望。稻草人和铁皮樵夫为自己能帮上多萝西而开心。再看狮子，他快活地嗅着新鲜空气，因为回到乡野而开心地来回摆动尾巴。托托围着大家跑，追逐飞蛾和蝴蝶，不住地欢叫。

“城市生活根本不适合我，”大家步子轻快地赶路时，狮子评论道，“住进翡翠城以后，我瘦了许多，现在我真等不及去让其他野兽看看我已经变得多么勇敢。”

这时，大家转身看了翡翠城最后一眼。只见绿色城墙后面一片高楼和尖塔，它们之上高高耸立着奥兹宫殿的尖顶和圆顶。

“奥兹毕竟不是一位那么糟糕的巫师。”铁皮樵夫说，他感觉到心在胸膛里跳动。

“他知道怎么给我脑子，还是很好用的脑子。”稻草人说。

“如果奥兹喝一口他给我的那种胆量，”狮子补充道，“他就会成为一个勇敢的人。”

多萝西什么也没说。奥兹没有履行对她的诺言，但他尽了力，于是她原谅了奥兹。就像奥兹自己说的一样，他虽然是位糟糕的巫师，但是个好人。

第一天，几位旅行者穿过了在翡翠城四周延伸的绿色原野和艳丽花丛。夜晚，他们睡在草地上，只披盖着漫天的繁星，睡得实在香甜。

早晨，他们继续赶路，一直来到一片茂密的森林边。这树林好像朝左朝右都看不到尽头，没有办法绕过去，再说，大家害怕迷路，也不敢换个方向走。所以，他们要找一个最容易进入森林的地方。

稻草人走在最前面，他终于发现了一棵枝干舒展的大树，树下的空间足够这群人通过。于是，稻草人朝大树走去，他刚到最外层的树枝下面，就见树枝突然弯下来缠住他，紧接着，他被从地上举起来，头冲前被猛地扔回了这群旅行者中间。

稻草人没有受伤，但他惊呆了。多萝西扶他起来时，他好像晕头转向的。

“树之间还有一个地方。”狮子说。

“让我先试一试，”稻草人说，“因为我被扔来扔去也不会受伤。”他说着向另一棵树走去，但树枝立刻缠住他，又把他扔了回来。

“真奇怪。”多萝西叫道，“我们怎么办？”

“这些树好像打定主意要和我们作对，不让我们过去。”狮子说。

“我相信我可以来试一试。”樵夫说着，扛起斧头，直朝刚才粗暴对待稻草人的第一棵树走去。当一根大树枝弯下来抓他时，樵夫挥动斧头猛砍，把树枝砍成了两段。顿时，大树开始摇晃所有的树枝，像是被砍疼了。铁皮樵夫安全地从树下通过了。

“跟上！”他冲其他人喊，“快点！”

大家都跑过去，安然无恙地从树下通过。可是托托被一根小树枝缠住摇晃，它嚎叫起来。不过，稻草人立刻砍断树枝，解救了小狗。

森林里其他的树没有拦阻他们，所以他们认定只有最外层的树才能弯下树枝，也许它们是森林的卫士，所以被赋予这种神奇的能力，好把陌生人拦在森林外。

四位旅行者轻松地从树木间穿过，一直走到森林边上。这时，他们惊奇地发现前面有一堵高墙，好像是白瓷砌成的。这墙像碟子表面一样光滑，比他们几个都高。

“我们现在怎么办？”多萝西问。

“我来做一架梯子，”铁皮樵夫说道，“因为我们肯定得爬过墙去。”

第二十章　精致的瓷国

在樵夫用他从森林里找到的木料做梯子时，多萝西躺下睡着了，她因为长途跋涉而感到疲倦。狮子也蜷起身子睡着了，托托趴在他身边。

稻草人专注地看着樵夫干活儿，说：

“我想不明白这儿为什么有堵墙，也不知道它用什么砌成。”

“歇歇你的脑子吧，别想墙的事了。”樵夫答道，“等我们翻过去，就知道那边是什么了。”

过了一会儿，梯子做好了。它看上去很粗陋，但铁皮樵夫确信它十分结实，能够满足他们的需要。稻草人叫醒多萝西、狮子和托托，告诉他们梯子做好了。稻草人第一个爬上梯子，可他太笨手笨脚，多萝西不得不紧紧跟在他后边，怕他摔下来。当稻草人脑袋探过墙头时，他惊叫道：

“噢，天啊！”

“继续爬。”多萝西大声催促。

于是，稻草人爬上去，坐在墙头上。多萝西也像稻草人一样，把脑袋探过墙头，叫道：

“噢，天啊！”

这时，托托也爬了上去，立马开始吠叫，多萝西让它安静下来。

狮子跟在托托后头，铁皮樵夫在最后；当他俩爬上梯子，往墙那边一望，都惊叫道：“噢，天啊！”最后，大家在墙头上坐成一排，向下望去，看到了奇异的景象。

他们面前是一片广阔的原野，地面像大盘底一样光滑、闪亮、洁白。原野上散布着许多房子，里里外外都是瓷的，色彩绚烂无比。这些房子很小巧，最大的只到多萝西的腰那么高。还有一些漂亮的小牲口棚，四周围着瓷栅栏；成群的牛、羊、马、猪和鸡也都是瓷的。

不过，最奇妙的还是住在这个奇异国度里的人。挤奶女工和牧羊女穿着色彩鲜艳的上衣和缀满金点的裙子；公主们穿着金色、银色和紫色的华美连衣裙；牧羊人穿着粉黄蓝三色条纹的齐膝短裤，鞋子上缀着金色鞋扣；王子们头戴珠宝冠冕，穿着貂皮礼袍和绸缎紧身上衣；滑稽的小丑身穿有褶皱饰边的长袍，脸颊上涂着红点，带着尖顶高帽。最奇异的是，这些人全是瓷的，就连他们的衣服也是瓷的，他们非常小，其中最高的只到多萝西的膝盖。

起初，瓷人们谁也没有注意到这几位旅行者，只有一只紫色的大脑袋小瓷狗来到墙边，细声朝他们吠叫，然后又跑走了。

“我们怎么下去呢？”多萝西问。

他们发现梯子太重，拉不上去。于是，稻草人从墙上倒下去，其他人再跳到他身上，这样就不会被坚硬的地面弄伤脚。当然，大家都很小心，不踩到稻草人的头，免得被针扎伤脚。所有人都安全落地之后，大家拾起被踩扁的稻草人，把他拍回原来的形状。

“我们必须穿过这个奇怪的地方，到另一边去，”多萝西说，“因为除了正南方，走其他的路都不明智。”

大家开始穿过瓷国。他们最先遇到的是一位瓷做的挤奶女工，她在给一头瓷牛挤奶。他们走近时，奶牛突然尥蹶子，踢翻了板凳、牛奶桶甚至挤奶女工，这些都摔倒在白瓷地面上，发出哗啦一声巨响。

多萝西惊讶地发现，奶牛断了一条腿，牛奶桶摔成了几块小瓷片，而可怜的挤奶女工左胳膊肘碰裂了一道缝。

“瞧！”挤奶女工生气地喊道，“看看你们干了些什么！我的牛断了一条腿，我得带它去修补匠那儿，把腿重新粘上。你们来这儿吓唬我的牛，算怎么回事？”

“对不起，”多萝西回答，“请原谅我们。”

可是，漂亮的挤奶女工气坏了，没搭理多萝西。她气呼呼地拾起牛腿，牵上牛就走。那头可怜的牛用三条腿一瘸一拐地跟着她。女工一边走，一边几次回头愤恨地看着这群笨手笨脚的外乡人，并把裂了缝的胳膊肘紧贴着身子。

多萝西为他们闯了祸而难过。

“我们在这儿要格外小心，”善良的樵夫说，“不然我们会伤害这些漂亮的小人，让他们永远也复原不了。”

多萝西又往前走了没多久，遇上一位衣着十分漂亮的年轻公主。公主见到这些外乡人，突然站住了，转身要跑。

多萝西想再看看这位公主，就跟她跑。可瓷公主喊道：

“别追我！别追我！”

多萝西听见她细小、惶恐的声音，就停住脚步问道：

“为什么？”

“因为，”公主也停下来，和多萝西保持一段安全距离，“我跑起来可能会摔倒，伤到自己。”

“可是你不能被修补吗？”小姑娘问。

“噢，可以。可是你知道吗，一个人被修补过后，就没有这么漂亮了。”公主回答说。

“我想是的。”多萝西说。

“我们这儿有一位笑话先生。”瓷公主接着说，“他是个小丑，总是用头倒立，经常把自己摔破，所以身上修补过上百处，样子一点也不好看。瞧，他来了。你自己看吧。”

还真是，一位快活的小个子小丑正向他们走来。多萝西看见他尽管穿着红黄绿三色的漂亮衣服，但身上布满朝各个方向开裂的细纹，这清楚地表明他被修补过很多处。

小丑手抄口袋，鼓起双颊，顽皮地朝他们点点头，说道：

“我美丽的姑娘，
你为什么凝望
可怜的笑话老先生？
你这副样子真呆愣，
又是多么羞涩，
像吞了一张扑克！”

“安静，先生！”公主说，“你没看到这几位外乡人吗？你该尊重他们。”

“那么，我希望这个表示尊重。”小丑说着，马上用头倒立。

“别介意笑话先生，”公主对多萝西说，“他头上的裂缝太严重了，让他变得很傻。”

“噢，我一点也不介意。”多萝西说，“可是你非常漂亮，”她接着说，“我真的非常喜欢你。我能把你带回堪萨斯，摆在艾姆婶婶的壁炉架上吗？我可以把你装在篮子里带走。”

“那样我会很不开心。”瓷公主说，“你看，我们在自己的国度里活得很幸福，可以随意说话、走动。但是，我们中的任何人一旦被带走，关节就会立刻僵硬，只能直直站着当一件漂亮的摆设了。当然，人们对我们的全部期望，就是在壁炉架上、橱柜里还有客厅桌上当漂亮摆设。但我们在自己的国度里活得愉快得多。”

“我绝对不会让你不开心！”多萝西大声说，“所以我们就此再见吧。”

“再见。”公主说。

大家小心翼翼地从瓷国穿过。路上，小动物和所有人都赶紧跑开，怕这些外乡人损坏他们。大概走了一个小时，旅行者们来到瓷国的另一边，这里又有一堵瓷墙。

不过，这堵墙没有第一堵那么高，于是大家踩着狮子的后背，登上墙头。之后，狮子蹲下来一跃身，也上去了；可他起跳时，尾巴扫翻了一座瓷教堂，它摔成了碎片。

“太糟糕了。”多萝西说，“不过，我倒真的觉得我们挺幸运，除了跌断一条牛腿、打翻一座教堂，并没有给这些小人造成更大的伤害。他们都这么脆弱！”

“是啊。”稻草人说，“而我很庆幸自己是稻草做的，不容易损坏。这世界上还有比做稻草人更糟糕的事。”

第二十一章　狮子成为万兽之王

大家从瓷墙上下来之后，来到一片荒凉的原野。这里到处是沼泽和泥塘，地上长满又高又密的野草，遮住了许多泥坑，一不小心就会踩进去。不过，大家都小心翼翼地往前走，直到安全地踏上坚实的地面。但眼前这片原野似乎更加荒凉。大家在矮树丛中穿行了很长时间，疲惫不堪地走进了又一片森林。这里的树比他们之前见过的任何树都要高大古老。

“这片森林可爱极了，”狮子高兴地朝四周张望，“我从没见过比这儿更美的地方。”

“这里看起来阴森森的。”稻草人说。

“一点也不，”狮子答道，“我真想在这里住上一辈子。你看，脚下的干树叶多么软和，老树上的苔藓长得多密多绿啊。肯定没有野兽能想到一处比这里更舒服的窝。”

“也许这森林里有野兽。”多萝西说。

“我想是的，”狮子回答，“但是我一头也没看见。”

他们穿过森林，直到夜色太深、看不见路时才停下休息。多萝西、托托和狮子躺下休息，铁皮樵夫和稻草人像往常一样为他们放哨。

第二天一早，他们又上路了。大家没走多远，就听见一阵低沉的隆隆声，像是许多野兽一齐吼叫。托托呜呜叫了几声，但其余的人谁也不害怕，他们沿着被踩得路迹清晰的小径，来到林中一块空地。这里聚集着几百头各种野兽，有老虎、大象、熊、狼和狐狸，还有自然史上所有其他的野兽。一时间，多萝西感到害怕。不过，狮子向大家解释，这是动物们在开会，他从咆哮声和吼叫声可以听出来，他们遇上了大麻烦。

狮子正说话，几头野兽发现了他，聚集的大兽群像中了魔法一样，猛然间安静下来。这时，最大的一只老虎走到狮子面前，鞠了个躬，说：

“欢迎您，万兽之王！您来得正及时，请帮我们打败敌人，让森林里的所有动物重获安宁吧。”

“你们遇到什么麻烦了？”狮子平静地问。

“我们都受到了威胁。”老虎回答，“森林里最近来了一个凶猛的家伙。这个庞然大物长得像一只巨型蜘蛛，身子有大象那么大，八条腿跟树干一样长。这怪物在森林里爬行，用一条腿捉住一头动物送进嘴里，就好像蜘蛛捕食苍蝇。只要这个凶猛的家伙活着，我们就全都不安全，所以我们召开大会，商讨怎么保护自己。就在这时，您来了。”

狮子想了一想，问：

“这片森林里还有别的狮子吗？”

“没有。从前有过几头，可后来全被怪物吃了。再说，那几头狮子都没有您这样高大勇敢。”

“如果我为你们除掉敌人，你们愿意俯身尊我为森林之王吗？”狮子问。

“我们乐意。”老虎回答道。别的动物全都高声吼叫：“我们愿意！”

“你们说的大蜘蛛在哪儿？”狮子问。

“在那边的橡树丛里。”老虎说，用前爪给狮子指路。

“请照顾好我的这几位朋友，”狮子说，“我马上就去打那怪物。”

说完，狮子告别伙伴们，迈着骄傲的步子去与敌人决斗。

狮子找到大蜘蛛时，蜘蛛正在睡觉，它长得丑极了，狮子看见它就厌恶地皱起鼻子。它的腿确实像老虎说的一样长，浑身布满黑色粗毛。它有一张大嘴，里面长着一排一英尺长的尖牙。但它的头和圆滚滚的身子却由蜂腰一样细的脖子连起来。这让狮子想出了攻击怪物的最好办法。他趁怪物睡着比较容易袭击，纵身一跃，正扑上它后背，接着挥起长着利爪的厚实前掌，猛地把蜘蛛的头从身子上打了下来。随后，狮子跳下来，盯着大蜘蛛，一直等到它的长腿不再抽搐，确定它死了才离开。

狮子回到空地那里，森林里的动物正等着他。他骄傲地说：

“你们不用再害怕你们的敌人了。”

于是，野兽们俯身尊狮子为王。狮子答应他们，等多萝西安全地回堪萨斯，他就马上回来统治他们。

第二十二章　夸德令国

四位旅行者安全地走过了森林里的余下路程。他们刚走出阴暗的森林，又遇上一座陡峭的山，从山顶到山脚都覆盖着大石块。

“这座山很难爬，”稻草人说，“但我们必须翻过去。”

于是，稻草人领路，大家跟着他。他们刚要爬上最下面的一块石头，突然一个粗鲁的声音喊道：

“别过来！”

“你是谁？”稻草人问。接着，一个脑袋从石头后面探出来，那个声音又说：

“这座山是我们的，任何人都不许过去。”

“但我们必须过去，”稻草人说，“我们要去夸德令国。”

“你们不能过去！”那声音回答。话音刚落，从石头后面走出一个人，旅行者们从没见过这么奇特的长相。

这人矮墩墩的，布满皱纹的粗脖子上长着一颗头顶扁平的大脑袋。更怪的是，他没有胳膊。稻草人看到这情景，并不害怕，他觉得这个无助的家伙并不能拦阻大家翻山赶路。于是，稻草人一边勇敢地往前走，一边说：

“很抱歉，我们不能按你说的办，不管你愿意不愿意，我们都必须翻过山去。”

突然，那人闪电般飞快地伸展脖子，嗖地射出脑袋，拿扁平的头顶击中了稻草人的腰。稻草人被撞翻了，骨碌碌滚下山。转眼间，那脑袋又迅速缩回去，那人刺耳地笑着说：

“没你想得那么简单！”

一阵狂笑从其他石头后面传出。多萝西看见山坡上有几百个长着锤子头的没有胳膊的人，每块石头后面都有一个。

狮子听见他们嘲笑稻草人滚下山坡，非常生气。他怒吼一声，冲上山坡，吼声像雷一样隆隆回响。

这时，一个脑袋又嗖地射出，狮子像被炮弹击中一样，滚下山坡。

多萝西跑下去扶起稻草人。狮子浑身肿痛，走过来对多萝西说：

“和这些会发射脑袋的人打也没用；谁也抵挡不住他们。”

“那我们怎么办？”多萝西问。

“召唤飞猴，”铁皮樵夫说，“你还有一次使唤他们的权力。”

“太好了。”多萝西说着，戴上金冠，念起了咒语。飞猴像往常一样迅速，不一会儿整个猴群就站在了多萝西面前。

“您有什么吩咐？”猴王深鞠一躬，问道。

“请带我们飞过这座山，去夸德令国。”小姑娘回答。

“遵命。”猴王说。飞猴们立刻托起四位旅行者和托托，带着他们飞去。他们飞过山上时，长着锤子头的人气得大叫，把脑袋高高地射向空中，但他们够不到飞猴。飞猴们托着多萝西和她的伙伴们安全地飞越石山，把他们送到了美丽的夸德令国。

“这是您最后一次能召唤我们，”猴王对多萝西说，“再见，祝您好运。”

“再见，非常感谢你们。”小姑娘回答。随后，飞猴们飞上天空，转眼不见踪影。

夸德令国看起来富裕幸福。平坦的小路隔开一片连一片的成熟稻田，潺潺的溪流穿田而过，溪上架着坚固的桥。篱笆、房子和桥都漆成鲜红色，像在温基国漆成黄色，在芒奇金国漆成蓝色一样。夸德令人又矮又胖，长得圆滚滚的，他们性格温和，都穿着红衣服，红色在绿草和变黄的稻谷映衬下格外鲜艳。

飞猴们把他们放在一间农舍旁。四位旅行者走过去敲门。一位农妇打开了门，多萝西问她要一些吃的。于是，农妇请大家吃了一顿丰盛的晚餐，有三种蛋糕、四种饼干，还给了托托一碗牛奶。

“这里离格林达的城堡有多远？”小姑娘问。

“不是很远，”农妇回答，“沿着这条路往南走，很快就到了。”

大家谢过这位好心的农妇，又起身上路。他们穿过稻田，走过精巧的小桥，一直来到一座美丽的城堡前。城门由三位年轻姑娘守卫，她们都身穿漂亮的镶着金穗带的红色制服。见多萝西走过来，其中一个说：

“你为什么来南方国度？”

“来拜见统治这里的好女巫，”多萝西答道，“你能带我去见她吗？”

“请你们报上名来，我去请示格林达，看她是不是愿意见你们。”于是，大家把名字告诉女卫兵，那姑娘就走进城堡去了。不一会儿，她回来对多萝西他们说，格林达请他们立即进城堡。

第二十三章　好女巫让多萝西心愿成真

大家在见到格林达之前，被带进城堡里的一个房间。多萝西洗了脸，梳好头；狮子抖落鬃毛里的尘土；稻草人把身体拍打成最好的形状；樵夫擦亮铁皮，给关节上足油。

等大家的样子都很拿得出手后，他们就跟着女卫兵走进一个大房间，只见女巫格林达坐在一张红宝石宝座上。

在大家看来，格林达美丽又年轻。她长着飘逸的大红色披肩卷发，穿着洁白的裙子，一双蓝眼睛温和地望着小姑娘。

“有什么事我能帮上忙吗，孩子？”她问。

多萝西把自己的全部经历告诉了女巫——怎样被旋风带到奥兹国，怎样遇到她的伙伴们，还有他们的奇妙历险。

“现在我最大的愿望，”多萝西说，“就是回堪萨斯。艾姆婶婶一定以为我遭遇了不幸，她会为我办丧事；除非今年庄稼收成比去年好，不然亨利叔叔肯定负担不起。”

格林达倾身向前，亲吻这位可爱的小姑娘扬起的甜美脸颊。

“你真好心，”她说，“我相信我能给你指一条去堪萨斯的路。”她接着说，“不过，要我这么做，你得把金冠给我。”

“我愿意！”多萝西叫道，“其实，它现在对我没用了。你拿到金冠后，可以使唤飞猴三次。”

“我想我恰好需要他们为我办三件事。”格林达微笑着说。

多萝西随后把金冠给了格林达。女巫问稻草人：

“多萝西离开我们之后，你打算做什么？”

“我要回到翡翠城，”稻草人回答，“因为奥兹让我统治那座城，那里的人们喜爱我。只有一件事让我发愁，就是怎样越过长着锤子头的人住的那座山。”

“我将用金冠召唤飞猴送你到翡翠城门口，”格林达说，“让人们失去这样好的一位统治者，是不应当的。”

“我真的那么好？”稻草人问。

“你与众不同。”格林达答道。

她又转向铁皮樵夫，问：

“多萝西离开这个国度之后，你打算做什么？”

樵夫靠着斧头，想了一会儿，说：

“温基人对我很好，坏女巫死后，他们想请我统治他们。我很喜欢温基人，如果能回西方国度，我最想做的就是永远统治他们。”

“我对飞猴的第二个命令，”格林达说，“将是让他们把你安全地送到温基国。你的脑袋不像稻草人的那么大，可你擦得亮闪闪的时候，确实比他聪明。我相信你能明智地治理好温基国。”

接着，女巫看着鬃毛乱蓬蓬的大狮子，问：

“多萝西回到她的家乡之后，你打算做什么？”

“在锤子头人住的山的那一边，”狮子回答，“有一片古老的大森林，那里的万兽尊我为王。只要我能回到那片森林，我就在那里快乐地度过一生。”

“我对飞猴的第三个命令，”格林达说，“将是送你到森林去。等用完金冠的魔力之后，我会把它还给猴王，那样猴王和他的猴群从此以后就永远自由了。”

听到这话，稻草人、铁皮樵夫和狮子诚恳地向好女巫道谢，感谢她的美意。这时，多萝西大声说：

“您的确美丽又善良！不过，您还没告诉我怎么回堪萨斯。”

“你的银鞋会带你飞越沙漠。”格林达回答，“要是你早了解这双鞋的魔力，那来这个国度的第一天，你就能回到艾姆婶婶身边去。”

“可是，那样我就不会有美妙的脑子了！”稻草人叫道，“我可能一生都将待在农夫的玉米地里。”

“我就不会有这颗可爱的心了，”铁皮樵夫说，“我可能会一直站在森林里，永远锈住。”

“而我将永远是一个胆小鬼，”狮子说，“所有森林里没有一只动物会对我说句好话。”

“你们说得都很对，”多萝西说，“我很高兴能帮助这些好朋友。现在你们每一位都得到了自己最渴望的东西，还很高兴地要去统治一座王国。那么，我想我该回堪萨斯了。”

“银鞋，”好女巫说，“有神奇的魔力。最不寻常的一点是，你只要走三步，它就能把你带到世界上任何地方，每一步都只要一眨眼工夫。你要做的就是把两只鞋跟撞三下，然后叫银鞋把你带到任何你想去的地方。”

“真是这样的话，”小姑娘高兴地说，“我要银鞋马上带我回堪萨斯。”

她张开双臂抱住狮子的脖子亲吻他，温柔地拍拍他的大脑袋。接着，她又亲吻铁皮樵夫，樵夫哭了，泪水对他的关节十分危险。最后，她抱住稻草人填满稻草的柔软身体，但没有亲吻他油漆画出的脸。多萝西伤心地告别亲爱的伙伴们，自己也忍不住哭了。

善良的格林达走下红宝石宝座，与小姑娘吻别。多萝西感谢格林达对她和她的朋友这么好。

于是，多萝西郑重地抱起托托，与大家最后道别了一声，然后把两只鞋跟撞了三下，说：

“带我去艾姆婶婶家！”

多萝西立即被带到空中，她飞速旋转着，只能看到、感觉到风在耳边呼啸。

银鞋只带着她走了三步，就突然停下了。多萝西在草地上滚了好几圈，才反应过来自己在哪里。

最后，她坐起来，环顾四周。

“天啊！”多萝西叫道。

原来，她正坐在堪萨斯广阔的草原上，面前是一座新房，是亨利叔叔在旧屋被旋风吹走后建造的。这时候，亨利叔叔正在牲口棚里给奶牛挤奶。托托已经从多萝西怀里跳下来，欢乐地狂吠着跑向牲口棚。

多萝西站起身，发现自己脚上只穿着袜子。原来，她在空中飞行的时候，银鞋掉了下去，永远地丢失在沙漠里了。

译者序

《怪医杜立德》是著名儿童作家休·洛夫廷（Hugh　Lofting，1886—1947）的天才之作，是真正的儿童典范读物。

休·洛夫廷出生在英国伯克郡的梅登黑德，1912年和一位美国女子结婚，婚后定居美国纽约。“一战”期间他曾服兵役。在战场上，他看到人受伤会得到救治，马则被枪杀。洛夫廷认为马也应有医生为它们救治。于是，他想塑造一个住在英国乡村、能听懂动物语言、能给动物治病的善良医生的形象。1919年，洛夫廷负伤回家，在妻子的鼓励下开始文学创作。1920年，他的《怪医杜立德》问世，广受读者欢迎。1922年，洛夫廷又出版了《杜立德医生航海记》，并获得了1923年纽伯瑞儿童文学奖。

《怪医杜立德》讲的是医学博士杜立德在家乡的离奇生活和在海外的历险经历。杜博士本来是一位给人看病的医生，但是，由于他非常喜爱动物，满屋子都是各种动物，因此吓跑了所有的病人。恰逢此时，鹦鹉波利尼西亚教会了他鸟兽语。于是，他专门给动物们看起了病。动物们口耳相传，纷纷来找他看病。甚至连非洲猴子国发生传染病，也不远万里来请他出诊。这样，心地善良的杜立德医生便开始了惊心动魄、扣人心弦的非洲之旅。

《怪医杜立德》神奇自然，引人入胜：猫头鹰的听觉，狗的嗅觉，鹰的视觉，海豚的灵性，鼠的预感……《怪医杜立德》跨越成人间的疆界，将善良的心地拓展到每个角落，使善良成为一种美德。如果我们在生活中也像杜博士那样尊重他人，付出挚爱，那么，整个世界就会充满爱的气息和幸福的味道。

第一章　泥塘镇

好多好多年以前，也就是我们的爷爷小的时候，有一位医生，名叫杜立德——约翰·杜立德，医学博士。“医学博士”意味着他是一位名副其实的医生，而且无所不知。

他住在一个小镇上，小镇名叫“沼泽地的泥塘镇”。所有碰见他的人，无论老少，没有不认识他的。每当他戴着高高的礼帽走在街上时，人们总会说：“医生来了！他是一个能人。”而街上的狗和孩子也都跑来跟在他的后面，甚至连那些住在教堂塔楼上的乌鸦也常常嘎嘎叫上几声，点点头。

他住的房子在小镇边上，相当小，但是他的花园很大，有一片宽阔的草坪，有石凳，还有依依垂柳。他的妹妹莎拉·杜立德，为他料理家务，但是医生会亲自打理花园。

他非常喜爱动物，养了好多种宠物。除了花园深处池塘里的金鱼之外，他还在餐具室里养了兔子，在钢琴里养了一窝小白鼠，在放日用纺织品的壁橱里养了一只松鼠，在地窖里养了一只刺猬。他还有一头带小牛犊的母牛、一匹已经二十五岁的老瘸马，还有鸡、鸽子、两只羊羔，以及许多其他的动物。不过，他最喜爱的宠物是鸭子嘎嘎、小狗吉普、小猪珈珈、鹦鹉波利尼西亚和猫头鹰秃秃。

他的妹妹过去经常抱怨所有这些动物，说它们把家里搞得乱七八糟。有一天，一个患风湿病的老太太来看病，一下子坐在了那只正在沙发上睡觉的刺猬身上，从此她再也没有来找杜医生看过病，而是每个星期六驱车十英里，到奥克森索普镇去找另一位医生看病。

过后，他的妹妹莎拉·杜立德前来对他说：“约翰，你在家里养这些动物，怎么能指望病人来找你看病呢？你以为好医生都是在客厅里养满刺猬和老鼠吧！这已经是动物们吓跑的第四位病人了。乡绅詹金斯和牧师都纷纷说，无论病得多么厉害，他们也绝不会靠近你的房子了。我们一天比一天穷了。你要是再这样下去，再好的人也不会让你看病的。”

“可是，我喜欢动物，胜过那些‘再好的人’。”医生说。

“你真可笑。”他的妹妹说着，走出了房间。

于是，随着时间的推移，医生得到的动物越来越多了，而来找他看病的人却越来越少了。到了最后，他连一个病人也没有留住，除了一个卖猫食的，因为这个人对任何动物都不在乎。可是，卖猫食的并不是很富有，而且每年只病一次，就是圣诞节时他会付给医生六便士，买一瓶药。

每年六便士可不够生活，即使在很久以前的那些日子也不够；要不是医生在存钱箱里存了一些钱，谁也不知道会发生什么情况。

而且，他还接着弄回家更多的宠物，当然，养这些宠物开销很大。他存的钱越来越少了。

后来，他变卖了钢琴，让那些小白鼠住在写字台的一只抽屉里。可是，卖钢琴的钱也渐渐地少了。于是，他又卖了自己礼拜日穿的那身褐色礼服，变得越来越穷了。

如今，每当他戴着高高的礼帽出现在街头时，人们常常会说：“医学博士约翰·杜立德来了！他曾是英格兰西部地区最有名的医生——瞧他现在——他连一分钱都没有了，长袜子上到处都是窟窿！”

可是，那些狗、猫和孩子仍会跑上去，跟着他穿过小镇，活像他有钱时那样。

第二章　动物语言

一天，杜立德医生正坐在厨房里和那个卖猫食的聊天，卖猫食的是来找他看胃痛的。

“你为什么不放弃给人当医生，改做动物医生呢？”卖猫食的问道。

鹦鹉波利尼西亚卧在窗户上，一边望着外面的雨，一边独自唱着一首水手歌。这时，它停住歌声，倾听起来。

“你明白，医生，”卖猫食的接着说道，“你对动物了如指掌，比这儿所有的兽医都懂得多得多。你写的那本猫的书，哇，可真棒！我自己既不会读也不会写，不然，我说不定也会写几本书呢。不过，我的妻子西奥多西亚，她可是有学问的，真的。她给我念了你的书。哎呀，真棒啊，只能这样说了——真棒。仿佛你自己过去就是一只猫似的。你明白它们的想法。听我说，你给动物看病会挣好多钱。你知道吗？你明白，我会让所有有病猫病狗的老太太都上你这儿来。要是这些猫狗病得不够快，我可以在卖给它们的肉里加点儿东西，让它们生病，明白吗？”

“噢，不，”医生马上说道，“你别那样做。那样做不对。”

“噢，我不是说真生病，”卖猫食的回答说，“我是说，就加一点儿东西，让它们无精打采。不过，正如你所说的那样，那可能对动物们很不公平。可是，不管怎样，它们都会生病，因为那些老太太总是给它们吃得太多。另外，还有周围那些家里有瘸马瘦羔的农夫，他们也会来找你的。当动物医生吧。”

等卖猫食的走后，鹦鹉飞下窗户，落到医生的桌子上说：“那个人有见识。你应该那样做。当动物医生吧。如果那些蠢人没有头脑，看不出你是世界上最好的医生，你就别再管他们了。去照看动物们吧，他们马上就会发现你是世界上最好的医生。当动物医生吧。”

“噢，动物医生有好多了。”说着，杜立德医生把花盆移到外面的窗台上淋些雨。

“是的，是有好多，”波利尼西亚说，“可是，他们根本不怎么样。听我说，医生，我来告诉你一件事儿。你过去知道动物会说话吗？”

“我知道鹦鹉会说话。”医生说。

“噢，我们鹦鹉能说两种语言：人语和鸟语。”波利尼西亚自豪地说，“如果我说：‘波利想吃饼干，’你就会明白我的意思。不过，你听听这个：卡─卡，噢─矣，菲─菲？”

“天哪！”医生嚷道，“那是什么意思？”

“意思是说：‘粥热了吗？’”

“哎呀！不会吧！”医生说，“你以前可从来没有对我这样说过啊。”

“有什么用啊？”说着，波利尼西亚拂去了左翅上的一些饼干屑，“就是我说了，你也不明白我的意思。”

“再对我说一些吧。”医生非常激动。他快步冲到碗柜抽屉跟前，拿来了肉店的账本和一支铅笔。“别说太快了，我要记下来。这很有趣，有趣极了，太新鲜了。先教我鸟语的基础知识，慢点儿。”

就这样，医生渐渐地知道了动物们都有自己的语言，而且能相互交谈。整个下午，天一直下着雨，波利尼西亚卧在餐桌上教他鸟词，让他记在本子上。

喝下午茶时，小狗吉普走了进来，鹦鹉对医生说：“瞧，它在对你说话。”

“在我看来，它好像是在挠耳朵吧。”医生说。

“可是，动物们并不总是用嘴巴说话，”鹦鹉扬了扬眉，高声说道，“它们用耳朵，用爪子，用尾巴，用所有的一切说话。有时，它们不想发出声音。你看见它在向上抽动一边的鼻子了吗？”

“那是什么意思？”医生问道。

“那是说：‘难道你没有瞧见雨已经停了吗？’”波利尼西亚回答说，“它是在向你询问。狗差不多总是用鼻子问问题。”

在鹦鹉的帮助下，医生不久便学会了动物语言，完全可以独自跟它们交谈，还能听懂它们说的所有的话。于是，他就彻底放弃了给人当医生。

卖猫食的一告诉大家约翰·杜立德要当动物医生，老太太们就往他这儿送起了她们那些蛋糕吃得太多的哈巴狗、狮子狗；农夫们也从好几英里以外赶来，让他看自家的病牛、病羊。

一天，一匹犁地的马被送到了他这儿。这个可怜的东西非常高兴自己终于碰到了一个会说马语的医生。

“你知道，医生，”马说，“山上的那个兽医一无所知。他到现在已经给我的跗节内肿治疗了六个星期。我需要的是一副眼镜。我的一只眼睛快要瞎了。为什么马不应该像人那样戴眼镜呢？毫无道理嘛！可是，山上的那个笨蛋甚至从来没有看过我的眼睛。他一直给我吃大药片。我曾试图告诉他，可是他对马语一窍不通。我需要的是一副眼镜。”

“当然，当然，”医生说，“我马上给你配一副。”

“我想要一副你这样的眼镜，”马说，“只不过要绿的。我犁那五十英亩地时，绿眼镜能帮我遮阳呢。”

“当然，”医生说，“你应该戴一副绿眼镜。”

“先生，你知道，问题是，”医生打开前门要送那匹犁马出去时，马又说道，“问题是，人人都以为自己能给动物看病，只是因为动物们不发牢骚。事实上，跟当一个好的人医相比，当一个真正的好兽医，需要人要聪明得多。我那个农夫的儿子以为他对马了如指掌。我希望你能看到他，他的脸胖得看上去就像没有眼睛似的，脑袋像薯虫那样大。上星期，他一心想往我身上抹芥子膏。”

“最终抹哪儿了？”医生问道。

“噢，哪儿也没有抹到，”马说，“他只是想那样干。我一下子就把他踢进了鸭塘。”

“好，好！”医生说。

“我通常都很安静，”马说，“对人很有耐心，不会大惊小怪。可是，那个兽医给我吃错了药，这就够我受的了。这个红脸笨蛋还来戏弄我，我再也忍不下去了。”

“你把那个男孩伤得厉害吗？”医生问道。

“噢，不厉害，”马说，“我踢得恰到好处。现在那个兽医正在照看他。我的眼镜什么时候配好啊？”

“下星期就会为你配好，”医生说，“你下星期二再来吧——再见！”

于是，约翰·杜立德搞了一副漂亮的大绿眼镜。那匹犁马的一只眼睛再也不会瞎了，可以像过去那样看见东西了。

不久，泥塘镇周边的村子里，经常可以看到一些干农活的动物戴着眼镜。从此，瞎马就销声匿迹了。

因此，那些被带到他这儿来的其他动物也一样。它们一发现医生会说它们的语言，就告诉他哪儿疼，感觉怎样。当然，这样他就能轻而易举地治好它们的病了。

现在所有就诊的动物回去后，都告诉自己的兄弟朋友，在那个带有大花园的小房子里有一位医生，他是一位真正的医生。从此，无论什么动物什么时候生病，不仅仅马、牛和狗，甚至连田野里的小动物，比如像巢鼠、麝香鼠、獾和蝙蝠，都会立马来到他位于镇边的家里，这样一来，他的大花园差不多总是挤满了想进去找他看病的动物。

因为要来的动物有好多，所以他只好为不同种类的动物专门设了各种门。他在前门上写着“马”，在侧门上写着“牛”，在厨房门上写着“羊”。每种动物都有一个单独的门——他甚至还为那些老鼠挖了一条小小的通道通向地窖，它们在那儿排成一行一行的，耐心等待医生过来给它们看病。

这样，没过几年，方圆好多英里的每一种生物都渐渐地知道了医学博士约翰·杜立德。冬天那些飞到其他国家去的鸟儿们把沼泽地的泥塘镇的这位神医的故事告诉了外国动物，说他能听懂它们说话，帮助它们治病。这样，他在全世界的动物中就渐渐地有了名气，比他给人当医生时在英格兰西部地区还有名气。所以，他开心极了，非常喜欢自己的生活。

一天下午，医生正忙着写东西，波利尼西亚卧在窗户上，它平时基本上总是这样，望着花园里被风吹来吹去的落叶。不一会儿，它大笑了起来。

“怎么了，波利尼西亚？”医生从书稿上抬起头来问道。

“我只是在思考。”说着，鹦鹉又看起了那些落叶。

“在思考什么？”

“我在思考有关人的事儿，”波利尼西亚说，“人让我讨厌。他们以为自己很了不起。这个世界一直运行了几千年，不是吗？人领会的唯一的动物语言就是狗摇尾巴时意味着它说‘我很高兴！’真有趣，不是吗？你是第一个会像我们一样说话的人。噢，有时人真让我生气，瞧他们谈论‘那些不会说话的动物’时趾高气扬的样子。不会说话！哼！哎，我曾认识一只金刚鹦鹉，它不用张嘴，就能用七种不同方式说‘早安’。它会说各种语言，包括希腊语。一位花白胡子的老教授买下了它。可是，它待不下去。它说那个老人说的希腊语不地道，它无法忍受听他用错误的发音教学生。我常常在想，也不知道它现在怎么样了。那只鸟知道的地理知识比人知道的还要多。——人，天哪！我想，人要是学会了飞——像任何一只普通的篱雀那样，那我们受到的纠缠就会没完没了！”

“你是一只聪明的老鸟，”医生说，“你到底有多大了？我知道鹦鹉和大象有时会活到很老很老。”

“我对自己的年龄从来都拿不准，”波利尼西亚说，“要么是一百八十三岁，要么是一百八十二岁。不过，我知道刚从非洲来到这儿时，查理国王还藏在橡树上，因为我看见他了。看上去他吓得要死。”

第三章　更多的金钱困难

不久，医生又开始挣钱了；他的妹妹莎拉·杜立德买了一条新裙子，很开心。有些来就诊的动物病得很重，只好在医生家里住一星期。渐渐好些后，它们常常坐在草坪的椅子上。

甚至康复后，它们也总是不愿离开，因为它们十分喜欢医生和他的家。当它们问是不是能跟医生待在一起时，他从来都不忍心拒绝它们。就这样，他的宠物越来越多了。

一天傍晚，他正坐在花园墙上抽烟斗，一个意大利手风琴艺人牵着一只猴子走了过来。医生马上就看出来，猴子的项圈太紧了，而且猴子脏兮兮的，闷闷不乐。于是，他从意大利人手里一把夺过猴子，给了那个人一先令，让他走人。手风琴艺人非常生气，说他不想卖猴子。可是，医生告诉他说，他要是不走开，就砸烂他的鼻子。尽管约翰·杜立德个子不高，但是身强力壮。于是，意大利人就骂骂咧咧地走了，那只猴子便留在了杜立德医生身边，有了一个安定的家。家里的其他动物都叫它“奇奇”——这在猴语里是一个常用词，是“活力”的意思。

还有一次，马戏团来泥塘镇演出，一条鳄鱼牙疼得厉害，半夜逃跑，钻进了医生的花园。医生和它用鳄语交谈，并把它带进了屋里，治好了它的牙疼。可是，当鳄鱼看到那是一个多么舒适的家，各种动物都在各自的窝里时，它也想跟医生住在一起。它请求说，它要是保证不吃鱼，能不能让它住在花园深处的鱼塘里。马戏团的人要带它回去，它一下子变得是那样疯狂野蛮，把他们都吓跑了。可是，对这家里的每个成员，它总是像小猫一样温顺。

但是现在，因为家里有了鳄鱼，老太太们不敢把她们的哈巴狗送到这儿来看病了，那些农夫相信鳄鱼会吃掉他们送来治疗的羊羔和小病牛。于是，医生对鳄鱼说，他必须回马戏团。可是，鳄鱼哭了，流下了大颗大颗的眼泪，苦苦哀求医生允许它留下来，医生不忍心把它赶走。

于是，他的妹妹走上前对医生说：“约翰，你必须赶走那只动物。现在农夫们和老太太们都害怕把他们的动物送到这儿看病，我们的日子眼看就要重新好起来了。现在我们会被完全毁掉的。这是压死骆驼的最后一根稻草。你要是不赶走那条美洲鳄，我就再也不给你管家了。”

“它不是美洲鳄，”医生说，“而是非洲鳄。”

“我不在乎你叫它什么。”他的妹妹说，“看到它趴在床底下真让人讨厌。我不允许它留在家里。”

“可是，它已经向我保证过了，”医生回答说，“它不会咬任何东西。它不喜欢马戏团，而我又没有钱把它送回非洲老家去。它不管闲事，总的看来非常规矩。你不要大惊小怪。”

“我告诉你，我绝不容忍它待在这儿。”莎拉说，“它还吃油毡。你要是此刻不把它赶走，我就——我就嫁人去！”

“好啊，”医生说，“那就嫁人去吧。这是无可奈何的事儿。”说完，他摘下帽子，走出去，进了花园。

于是，莎拉·杜立德打点东西后就走了。留下医生独自和他的动物家族待在一起。

没过多久，他变得比以前任何时候都穷了。有那么多张嘴等着吃，房子也需要照看，缝缝补补没有人手，也没有钱来支付肉店的账单了，情况看起来非常艰难。可是，医生一点儿也不担心。

“钱是个讨厌的东西，”他常常说，“要是从来都没有发明钱，我们就一定会过得更幸福。只要我们开心，钱算什么？”

可是，不久，那些动物就开始担心起来了。一天傍晚，医生坐在厨房火边睡着了。它们聚在一起低声商量起来。擅长算术的猫头鹰秃秃算出来，即使它们每天只吃一顿饭，剩下的钱也只够维持一星期了。

这时，鹦鹉说：“我想我们都应该亲自做家务，至少我们可以做那么多。毕竟，老人是因为我们才这样孤独、这样贫穷的。”

于是，大家商定，猴子奇奇负责做饭和缝补，狗负责扫地，鸭子负责除尘、铺床，猫头鹰秃秃负责记账，小猪负责园艺。它们让鹦鹉波利尼西亚管家和洗衣服，因为它年纪最大。

当然，一开始它们都觉得新工作很难做——除了奇奇，因为它有手，可以像人一样做事。但是，不久，它们就习以为常了，而且每当看到小狗吉普在尾巴上绑一块破布当扫帚扫地，它们总觉得非常有趣。没过多久，它们就把家务做得井井有条了。医生说，家里以前从来没有这样整洁过。

就这样，情况好了一阵子，可是，没有钱，它们发现日子很难熬。

于是，那些动物在园门外摆了一个蔬菜鲜花货摊，向过往的路人出售萝卜和玫瑰。

不过，它们挣的钱好像还是不够付账单，而且医生仍然不着急。鹦鹉对医生说，鱼贩子不愿再送给他们鱼吃了。他说：“不要紧。只要母鸡下蛋、奶牛产奶，我们就会有煎蛋卷和奶酪。再说，花园里还剩有不少蔬菜。冬天还远着哩。别大惊小怪。莎拉就有这毛病，她总是大惊小怪。我不知道莎拉现在怎么样了，她非常出色——某些方面——唉，算了！”

可是，那年雪下得比平常早。老瘸马从镇外的森林里驮回了好多木柴，大家得以在厨房里生一大堆火，但是花园里的蔬菜大部分都吃光了，剩下的也都被雪覆盖着，动物们有不少都是饥肠辘辘的。

第四章　非洲传来消息

那是一个非常寒冷的冬天。十二月的一天夜里，它们围坐在厨房温暖的炉火边，医生正在给它们大声朗读他用动物语言写的书，这时猫头鹰秃秃突然说道：“嘘！外面是什么声音？”

大家全都侧耳倾听，不一会儿就听到了奔跑的声音。接着，门突然打开，只见猴子奇奇上气不接下气，跑了进来。

“医生！”它叫道，“我刚刚收到我的一个表兄从非洲传来的消息，说那儿的猴群中流行一种可怕的疾病。它们全都被感染了，成百上千的猴子正在奄奄一息。它们听说了你，恳求你到非洲去阻止这场疾病。”

“是谁带来的消息？”医生摘掉眼镜，放下书，问道。

“是一只燕子，”奇奇说，“它就在外面的集雨桶上。”

“把它带到火边来，”医生说，“它肯定被冻坏了。燕子们六个星期前就飞到南方去了！”

燕子被带了进来，冻得缩成了一团，正在瑟瑟发抖。起先，它有点儿害怕，很快就暖和了，于是就卧到壁炉台沿上，开始讲了起来。

它讲完后，医生说：“我非常乐意去非洲，尤其是在这样寒冷的天气下。可是，我担心我们没有足够的钱去买票。奇奇，去把存钱箱拿来。”

猴子爬上柜子，从顶架上把存钱箱拿了下来。

里面空空荡荡，一个子儿都没有了！

“我敢肯定还有两便士。”医生说。

“以前有。”猫头鹰说，“但是獾的小娃娃出牙时，你用那两便士给它买了一只拨浪鼓。”

“是吗？”医生说，“噢，哎呀！真是的，钱是一个多么讨厌的东西！噢，别担心。也许我可以去海边借条船，这样我们就可以去非洲了。我以前认识一位水手，他带小孩来我这儿看过麻疹。也许他会把船借给我们，因为他小孩的病好了。”

于是，第二天一早，医生就去了海边。回来时，他告诉动物们，没问题，那位水手愿意把船借给他们。

鳄鱼、猴子和鹦鹉听了，都非常高兴，不禁唱起了歌，因为它们要回非洲了，那是它们真正的家乡。

医生说：“我只能带上你们仨，加上小狗吉普、鸭子嘎嘎、小猪珈珈和猫头鹰秃秃。剩下的，像睡鼠、麝香鼠和蝙蝠，它们必须回到出生的田间，直到我们再回到家来。不过，因为它们中的大多数都冬眠，所以对此都不介意。再说，去非洲对它们也不是什么好事儿。”

以前有过多次远洋航行经验的鹦鹉叮嘱医生上船务必携带的所有东西。

“务必带上充足的硬饼干，”它说，“也就是人们所谓的‘压缩饼干’。还必须带上罐装牛肉和一只锚。”

“我料想船上会有船锚。”医生说。

“啊，要确定，”波利尼西亚说，“因为这很重要。要是没有锚，船就停不下来。还需要一只铃铛。”

“要那干什么？”医生问道。

“靠它来计时。”鹦鹉说，“每半小时摇一次铃，这样你就知道几点钟了。还要带好多好多的绳子，海上航行绳子总是能派上用场的。”

然后，它们就开始琢磨到哪儿弄钱去买所有这些必需的东西。

“噢，讨厌！又是钱！”医生叫道，“天哪！我很高兴去非洲。到了那儿，我们就什么也不需要了！我去问问杂货店老板，看他是否愿意等到我们回来时再还他钱。不，得让水手去问他。”

水手去见了杂货店老板。不一会儿，他就带着他们想要的所有东西回来了。

接着，动物们就打点行装。它们关掉水，这样那些管子就不会结冰了，然后合上百叶窗，关上房门，把钥匙交给了住在马厩的老马。看到阁楼里有不少干草足够老马越冬后，它们便带着所有的行李前往海边，登上了那条船。

卖猫食的在那儿为他们送行。他还带了一块板油布丁，作为礼物送给医生，因为他听说在国外吃不到板油布丁。

他们一上船，小猪珈珈就问床在什么地方，因为现在是下午四点钟，它想打个盹儿。波利尼西亚把它带到了下面的船舱，但见那些床全都靠墙一个叠一个，像书架似的。

“哎呀，那不是床！”珈珈叫道，“那是架子！”

“船上的床就是这样。”鹦鹉说，“那不是架子。爬进去睡吧。这就是你所说的‘睡铺’。”

“我还不想上床。”珈珈说，“我太兴奋了。我想再上去，看他们起航。”

“好，这是你第一次航行。”波利尼西亚说，“不久，你就会习惯这种生活了。”

说完，它沿着船梯又回到了上面，独自哼唱起了这首歌：

我见过了黑海和红海；
我绕过了白岛；
我发现了黄河，
夜间还发现了橙河。
现在，绿色之乡又落在了后面，
我驶向蔚蓝色的海洋。
简，我厌倦了所有这些色彩，
我要回到你身边。

正要起航，医生说他得回去问问水手去非洲该怎么走。

可是，燕子说它去过那个地方好多次了，它愿意给他们指引航线。

听了这话，医生吩咐奇奇起锚。航行开始了。

第五章　伟大的航行

整整六个星期，他们一直在波涛起伏的大海上航行。燕子在船前飞行，给他们领路。到了夜里，它就提着一只小灯笼，以免他们在黑暗中找不到它。过往船只上的人们都说那道光肯定是一颗流星。

他们渐行渐远，来到了南方，天气变得越来越暖和。波利尼西亚、奇奇和鳄鱼都非常喜欢烈日。它们欢笑着跑来跑去，不时地到船边眺望一下，看是不是能看到非洲。

小猪、小狗和猫头鹰秃秃却对这种天气无可奈何，只能卧在船头一只大桶的阴影下，伸出舌头，喝柠檬水。

鸭子嘎嘎常常跳进海水里，游到船后面纳凉。每当感觉头顶太热时，它就潜到船下，从另一边钻出来。每到星期二和星期五，它还用这种方式逮青鱼。每当这时，船上的每个人和动物都吃鱼，好节省一些牛肉。

接近赤道时，他们看到一些飞鱼朝他们游了过来。飞鱼问鹦鹉，这是不是杜立德医生的船。鹦鹉告诉它们说正是。它们说真高兴，因为非洲的那些猴子正心急火燎，以为医生永远不会来了呢。波利尼西亚问它们还要走多少英里。飞鱼们说，现在离非洲海岸只有五十五英里了。

还有一次，一大群鼠海豚穿波越浪，纷纷游了过来。它们也问波利尼西亚，这是不是那位名医的船。一听说是，它们就问鹦鹉，医生旅程中需不需要什么东西。

波利尼西亚说：“需要。我们的洋葱吃完了。”

“离这儿不远有一座岛，”鼠海豚们说，“那儿的野葱长得又高又壮。你们继续前进，我们去弄些洋葱，然后再追赶你们。”

说完，鼠海豚们飞速地穿浪而去。不大一会儿，鹦鹉又看见它们正穿波越浪从后面追了上来，身后拖着几个海草做的、装满洋葱的大网。

第二天傍晚，太阳快下山时，医生说：“奇奇，把望远镜拿来。我们的航程就要结束了。很快，我们就能看到非洲海岸了。”

大约半小时后，果然，他们好像看到了前方有个类似陆地的东西。可是，天色越来越暗了，他们拿不准。

随后，一场暴风雨接踵而来，电闪雷鸣，狂风呼啸，大雨倾盆，海浪滔天，飞溅在了船上。

紧接着，的一声巨响！船停住了，朝一侧翻去。

“发生了什么事儿？”医生从船舱里跑上来问道。

“我拿不准，”鹦鹉说，“不过，我想，我们的船出事了。让鸭子下去看看吧。”

于是，嘎嘎潜到海浪下面，然后上来说，他们撞上了一块岩石，船底有一个大洞，海水正往里面涌，他们在迅速下沉。

“我们肯定是撞上了非洲大陆。”医生说，“哎呀，好家伙！噢，我们必须全都游到陆地上去。”

可是，奇奇和珈珈都不会游泳。

“拿绳子来！”波利尼西亚说，“我说过，绳子迟早用得上。鸭子哪儿去了？嘎嘎，过来。你拽着绳子这一头，飞上岸去，把它拴到一棵棕榈树上；我们在船上抓紧绳子的另一头。然后，那些不会游泳的可以顺着绳子爬到陆地上去。这就是人们所谓的‘救生索’。”

最终，他们全都安全上岸，有的是游过来的，有的是飞过来的；那些顺绳子爬过来的还把医生的行李箱和手提包带了过来。

可是，船再也不能用了，因为船底有一个大洞。不久，凶猛的海浪便把船在岩石上摔得粉碎，船骨也顺水漂走了。

他们在悬崖高处找了一个干爽的洞穴，躲了进去，直到暴风雨过去。

第二天早上，太阳出来了。他们来到沙滩上，让太阳把身子晒干。

“亲爱的老非洲，”波利尼西亚感叹道，“回来真好！请想一下吧——明天就是我离开它一百六十九年了！它一点儿都没有变！同样的棕榈树，同样的红土地，同样的黑蚂蚁！还是家乡好啊！”

动物们注意到，鹦鹉热泪盈眶。再次看到了故乡，它真是太高兴了。

这时，医生想起了自己的高帽，暴风雨中它被刮到了海里。嘎嘎下水去找。不一会儿，它就远远地看到了帽子，只见帽子像玩具船一样正漂在水上。

它飞过去，准备拾起来，这时它发现里面竟然卧着一只惊恐万状的小白鼠。

“你在这儿干什么？”鸭子问，“不是吩咐你留在泥塘镇的吗？”

“我不想被撇下。”小白鼠说，“我想看看非洲是什么样子。我那儿有亲戚。我就藏在行李中，跟压缩饼干一起被带上了船。船沉时，我害怕极了，因为我游不远。我尽力地游啊游，但是很快就筋疲力尽了，我以为自己要沉下去了。这时，老头儿的帽子恰好漂了过来，我就爬了进去，我不想被淹死啊。”

鸭子把帽子连同里面的小白鼠一起带上了岸，交给了医生。大家都围过来看。

“这就是人们所说的‘偷渡者’。”鹦鹉说。

很快，他们在行李箱里找了一处地方，这样小白鼠就可以舒舒服服地旅行了。猴子奇奇突然说道：“嘘！我听到丛林里有脚步声！”

他们全都不再说话，侧耳倾听。不大一会儿，一个黑人从树林里走了出来，问他们在那儿干什么。

“我叫约翰·杜立德，是医学博士，”医生说，“是被请来非洲给患病的猴子们治病的。”

“你们全都必须交由国王发落。”黑人说。

“什么国王？”医生问，他不想浪费任何时间。

“乔里金基的国王，”黑人回答说，“所有这些土地都属于他，所有的外地人都必须交给他处理。跟我走一趟吧。”

他们收拾行李，跟着那个人向丛林里走去。

第六章　波利尼西亚与国王

在密林中走了一小段路后，他们来到了一片开阔地，看到了国王的宫殿。宫殿是用泥砌成的。

这儿是国王、厄门特鲁德王后和他们的儿子邦波王子居住的地方。王子外出到河里钓鲑鱼去了。国王和王后正坐在宫殿门前的一把伞下面。厄门特鲁德王后已经睡着了。

医生走向宫殿。国王问他有什么事儿。医生把他来非洲的原因告诉了国王。

“不允许你从我的国土上经过。”国王说，“许多年前，有一个白人上岸来。我当时对他非常友好。可是，他却掘土挖金，为谋取象牙，杀死了所有大象，然后偷偷坐船跑了，甚至连声谢谢都没说。从那以后，我绝不再让一个白人从乔里金基的国土上通过。”

说完，国王转身对站在旁边的几个黑人说道：“把这个巫医和他所有的动物统统带走，锁到最结实的牢房里去。”

六个黑人将医生和他所有的宠物带了下去，把他们关进了一个石牢里。石牢仅有一扇小窗，开在高高的墙上，窗上插着一道道栅栏，牢门厚实而坚固。

大家都非常难过。小猪珈珈开始哭了起来。奇奇说，如果它再不住嘴，就要打它的屁股，它这才安静下来。

“我们全都在这儿吗？”医生渐渐地适应了牢里昏暗的光线后问道。

“在，我想都在。”鸭子说着，数了起来。

“波利尼西亚在哪儿？”鳄鱼问，“它不在这儿。”

“你肯定吗？”医生说，“再看看。波利尼西亚！波利尼西亚！你在哪儿？”

“我猜它逃走了。”鳄鱼嘟囔着说，“它就是这样！朋友们一有难，它就溜到林子里去了。”

“我才不是那样。”说着，鹦鹉从医生外套下摆的口袋里钻了出来，“大家知道，我体形小，可以从窗栅栏中间钻出去。我生怕他们把我关进笼子，趁国王忙着说话，我躲到了医生的口袋里，也进来了！这就是人们所说的‘计策’。”它用嘴巴梳理着羽毛说。

“我的天哪！”医生叫道，“幸亏我没有坐到你身上。”

“听着，”波利尼西亚说，“今天晚上，天一黑，我就从这个窗栅栏悄悄钻出去，飞到王宫。然后，你们明白，我会很快找到一个办法，让国王把我们全都放出去。”

“噢，你能做什么呀？”珈珈说着，翘起鼻子又哭了起来，“你只不过是一只鸟！”

“完全正确。”鹦鹉说，“可是，别忘了，尽管我仅仅是一只鸟，却能像人一样说话，而且我了解这些人。”

那天夜里，当月亮照在棕榈树上，国王的手下都睡着时，鹦鹉悄悄地钻过牢房的栅栏，飞到了王宫。一星期前，王宫餐具室的窗户被一只网球打破了。波利尼西亚就是从这个玻璃上的破洞中间飞进去的。

它听到邦波王子在宫殿后面的卧室里打呼噜，就踮起脚尖上了楼，它来到国王的卧室门前，轻轻推开门，偷偷向里张望。

那天晚上，王后到表妹家跳舞去了，国王在床上睡得正香。

波利尼西亚轻轻地溜了进去，钻到了床底下。

它咳嗽了一声，就像杜立德医生平时咳嗽的那样。波利尼西亚能模仿任何人。

国王睁开眼睛，睡意蒙眬地问道：“厄门特鲁德，是你吗？”他以为是王后跳舞回来了。

鹦鹉又咳嗽了一声——像男人一样声音洪亮。国王一下子坐了起来，睡意顿消，问道：“是谁？”

“我是杜立德医生。”鹦鹉说——跟医生平时说话的腔调一模一样。

“你在我的卧室干什么？”国王叫道，“你胆敢逃出牢房！你在哪儿？我看不见你。”

鹦鹉只是大笑——爽朗长久地欢笑，就像医生的笑声。

“别笑了。马上出来，让我看见你！”国王说。

“愚蠢的国王！”波利尼西亚回答说，“你忘了你是在跟世界上最了不起的人——医学博士约翰·杜立德说话吗？你当然看不见我了。我已经让自己隐身。我无所不能。你现在听着：我今天晚上是来警告你的。如果你不让我和我的动物们从你的王国经过，我就让你和你的所有臣民都像猴子一样生病。我只要抬抬小手指，就能让人康复，或者教人生病。你马上派你的士兵去把牢门打开，否则等不到明天太阳爬上乔里金基的山顶，你就会得流行性腮腺炎。”

这时，国王浑身哆嗦，他开始胆战心惊起来。

“医生，”他哭道，“我一定按你吩咐的去办。请不要抬小手指！”说着，他翻身下床，跑去叫士兵们打开牢门。

他一走，波利尼西亚就悄悄下楼，从餐具室的窗户离开王宫。

可是，王后用钥匙开后门进来时，正巧看见鹦鹉飞出那扇破窗。国王回来睡觉时，她就把自己看到的情景告诉了他。

国王这才明白自己上当了，他大为恼火，马上转身奔回牢房。

可是，为时已晚。牢门大开，地牢里空空荡荡。医生和他的所有动物都已经走了。

第七章　猴桥

厄门特鲁德王后从来没有见过丈夫像今天晚上这样可怕。他咬牙切齿，怒不可遏，见谁就说谁傻瓜。他气得向宫廷猫扔牙刷。他穿着长睡衣跑来跑去，把所有卫兵都派去丛林里抓医生，接着还把所有仆人也都派了去，厨师、园丁、理发师以及邦波王子的师傅，甚至连王后也被打发去帮士兵们搜人，即使她穿了一双紧脚鞋，跳舞已经跳得很累了。

在此期间，医生和他的动物们在密林中急速穿行，尽快朝猴国方向奔跑。

珈珈腿短，不一会儿就跑累了，医生只好抱着它跑。因为还要拎行李箱，提手提包，他们行动起来相当困难。

乔里金基的国王认为，卫兵轻而易举就能找到他们，因为医生是在一块陌生的土地上，不认识路。可是，他错了，因为猴子奇奇对丛林里的路无所不知，甚至比国王的手下还熟悉。它领着医生和宠物们跑进密林最深处一个从来没有人到过的地方，让他们藏进一个高大岩石间的大树洞里。

“咱们最好在这儿等着，”奇奇说，“一直等那些士兵都回去睡觉，咱们再继续往猴国那边赶吧。”

就这样，他们在树洞里待了整整一个晚上。

他们不时地听到国王的卫兵在附近搜寻和交谈的声音。不过，他们非常安全，因为除了奇奇之外，谁都不知道这个藏身地，甚至连其他猴子也不知道。

阳光穿过头顶茂密的叶子照射了下来。这时，他们终于听到了厄门特鲁德王后疲惫不堪地说道，再找也没用了，不妨回去睡觉吧。

士兵们一撤，奇奇就把医生和动物们从躲藏的地方领了出来，朝猴国进发了。

漫漫征程，他们经常会很累，尤其是珈珈。不过，它一哭，大家就给它椰子，让它喝里面它非常喜欢的椰奶。

他们总是吃喝不愁，因为奇奇和波利尼西亚了解丛林里生长的所有不同种类的水果和蔬菜，比如，椰枣、无花果、落花生、姜和山药，而且还知道在哪儿可以找到它们。他们经常用野橙汁制作柠檬水，再加入从树洞的蜂巢里搞来的蜂蜜，味道甜甜的。无论大家想要什么，奇奇和波利尼西亚似乎总有办法帮他们搞到，或者搞到类似的东西。一天，它们甚至还给医生搞了一些烟草。当时，医生随身带来的烟叶已经抽完了，他想抽烟。

晚上，他们睡在用棕榈叶搭成的帐篷里，躺在干草铺成的又厚又软的床上。没过多久，大家便习惯了这种长途跋涉，也不感到那么累了，而且还喜欢上了这种旅途生活。

不过，让大家始终高兴的是，每当夜幕降临时，他们总能驻足休息。这时，医生常常用树枝生上一小堆火。吃过晚饭，他们常常在火边围成一圈，听波利尼西亚唱大海的歌儿，或者听奇奇讲丛林的故事。

奇奇讲的好多故事都非常有趣。尽管在杜医生开始记载猴子的历史之前，它们根本没有自己的历史书，但是它们通过给自己的孩子们讲故事的形式，把发生的一切都记得清清楚楚。奇奇讲的好多事儿都是祖母告诉它的，是很久很久以前发生在诺亚和大洪水之前的故事，那时人们穿熊皮，住岩洞，吃生羊肉，还不懂得烹饪，从来没有见过火。奇奇还跟大家讲到了像火车那样长的巨大猛犸象和蜥蜴，说它们当时在山上到处溜达，啃吃树顶。大家常常听得兴致勃勃，总是在它讲完故事了，才发现火早已熄灭，只好赶忙又去拾一些树枝，再点上一堆火。

话说国王的卫队回去后，报告国王说他们没有找到医生。国王又把他们派了出来，并下令他们必须守在丛林里，直至抓住医生。在此期间，医生和他的动物们一直在向猴国进发，他们以为自己平安无事了，不知道其实国王的手下仍然在后面追寻。如果奇奇知道这个情况，它十有八九就会把大家再次藏起来。可是，它并不知道。

一天，奇奇爬上一块高高的岩石，越过树梢向远处眺望。下来后，它说，他们现在离猴国已经很近了，很快就会到达那儿。

就在那天傍晚，他们果然见到了奇奇的表兄和好多其他的猴子。这些是没有生病的猴子，它们正坐在沼泽地边的树上，一边瞭望，一边等待他们。这些猴子看到这位名医真的来了，便发出了很大的声音，又是欢呼，又是挥舞树叶，它们从树枝间荡出来，向他致意。

它们争着为医生提包扛箱，帮他拿所有的东西，一只大猴子甚至还背起了珈珈，因为珈珈又累了。其中两只猴子急忙冲到前面，去告诉那些生病的猴子：那个了不起的医生终于来了。

然而，那些一直尾随其后的国王的手下听到那些猴子的欢呼声，知道了医生的方位，连忙赶来抓他。

背着珈珈的大猴子走得慢，落在后面。它看到国王的卫队长悄悄穿过树林摸了过来，赶紧追上医生，叫他快跑。

大家拼命跑了起来，比以往任何时候都卖力，尾随其后的国王的手下也开始跑了起来，卫队长跑得最猛。

突然，医生绊在医药包上，摔倒在了泥里。卫队长想，这下他保准能抓住医生。

可是，卫队长虽然头发很短，耳朵却非常长。在他冲过来想要抓住医生时，他的一只耳朵牢牢地挂在了树上，其他卫兵只好停下来帮他。

医生趁这个机会连忙爬起来，他们又接着向前跑，跑着跑着，奇奇喊道：“太好了！我们快到了！”

可是，在进入猴国之前，他们先来到了一个陡峭的悬崖边，悬崖下面是湍急的河水。这儿是乔里金基国的边界。猴国在另一边——河对岸。

小狗吉普向这异常陡峭的悬崖下面一看，说道：“天哪！咱们可怎么穿过去呀？”

“哎呀！”珈珈叫道，“国王的卫队近在咫尺了——瞧，他们来了！恐怕咱们又要被抓回去坐牢了。”说着，它就哭了起来。

这时，那只背着珈珈的大猴子一把将它放到地上，冲其他猴子大喊：“小子们——吊桥！快！——搭吊桥！我们只有一分钟的时间了。卫队长已经脱开身来，像鹿一样追上来了。快点儿！吊桥！吊桥！”

医生开始纳闷它们用什么东西搭桥，便四下打量，看看它们是不是在什么地方藏有木板。

可是，当他掉头再看悬崖上时，只见跨河之上已经为他搭好了一座吊桥，是活生生的猴子搭成的！他刚才一转身的工夫，猴子们快如闪电，相互抓住对方的手脚，用身体搭成了这座桥。

那只大猴子对医生喊道：“过！过！——你们大家——快过！”

珈珈有点儿害怕，不敢从那么高、高得让人眩晕的地方，踩着这么窄的桥过河。不过，它还是安然无恙地过去了，剩下的也都过去了。

约翰·杜立德最后一个过桥。他刚走到对岸，国王的卫队就冲到了悬崖边。

国王的卫兵们挥舞拳头，气得大喊大叫。他们知道自己来得太晚了。医生和他的所有动物已经安全抵达了猴国，“桥”也被拽到了对岸。

这时，奇奇转身对医生说：“好多大探险家以及有着花白胡子的博物学家们都曾一连几个星期躲在丛林里，等看猴子们玩那个把戏。我们从来没有让一个白人看过。你是第一个看见这著名‘猴桥’的白人。”

听了这话，医生感到非常开心。

第八章　狮子王

约翰·杜立德手忙脚乱，忙得不可开交。他发现成千上万只猴子都病了——有大猩猩、猩猩、黑猩猩、狗脸狒狒、金丝猴、灰毛猴、红毛猴等各种各样的猴子。而且好多已经病死了。

他做的第一件事儿，就是把生病的猴子和健康的猴子隔离开来，然后教奇奇和它的表兄盖了一座小草房，让那些仍然健康的猴子前来打预防针。

三天三夜，猴子们源源不断地从丛林、山谷和小山里赶到小草房。医生夜以继日地坐在那儿，不停地打针。

接着，他又建了一座房子——一座大房子，里面铺了好多床；他将那些生病的猴子安顿了进去。

然而，有这么多猴子得病，却没有足够多的健康猴子来护理。于是，他就给其他动物——比如，狮子、豹子和羚羊——捎信儿，让它们过来帮忙护理。

可是，狮子王是一个非常骄傲的家伙。它来到医生放满床的大病房，怒气冲冲、一脸不屑的样子。

“先生，你竟敢要求我？”它怒视着医生，“你竟敢要求我——我这个兽中之王来伺候这么多的脏猴子？哎呀，我甚至都不愿意把它们当饭后的零食吃哩！”

狮子看上去十分可怕，但是医生努力装出不怕它的样子。

“我并不是要求你去吃它们。”他平静地说，“再说，它们也不脏。今天早上全都洗了澡。倒是你的皮毛看上去需要梳理——迫切需要梳理。现在听着，我告诉你：狮子可能也有生病的那一天。如果你现在不帮其他动物，等狮子们倒霉时，你可能就会发现自己孤立无援了。这种事儿，骄傲者经常会碰到。”

“狮子从来不会有麻烦，它们只会制造麻烦。”说完，狮子王翘起鼻子，昂首阔步地走出去，进了丛林，它感觉自己相当聪明伶俐。

豹子也骄傲了起来，说它们不愿帮忙。当然还有羚羊，虽然它们胆子极小，不敢像狮子那样对医生无礼，但却用蹄子刨地，傻笑着说自己以前从来没有当过护士。

可怜的医生急得发疯，不知道从哪儿才能找到足够多的帮手，来照顾这几千只卧病在床的猴子。

狮子王回到自己的洞穴，竟看到妻子狮后头发凌乱地跑了出来。

“有一头小狮子不想吃东西。”它说，“我不知道该如何是好。它从昨晚起就没有吃什么东西了。”

说着，它就哭了起来，惶恐不安，浑身发抖，因为它不仅是一头母狮子，更是一位好母亲。

狮子王走进洞里，去看自己的孩子，只见两头非常漂亮的小狮子正躺在地上。其中一头好像病得不轻。

狮子王扬扬自得地把自己刚才对医生说的话说给妻子听。母狮气得差点儿把它赶出洞去。“你从来就不长脑子！”它尖叫道，“从这儿一直到印度洋，大家都在谈论这个神人，说他能治百病，说他人有多好，他可是全世界唯一能说动物语言的人啊！现在，眼下——咱们的孩子病了，你却要冒犯他！你这个大傻瓜！只有傻瓜才会对一个好医生粗鲁无礼。你──”说着，它就上前撕扯起了丈夫的头发。

“马上拐回去，”它大叫道，“向那个白人赔礼道歉。让其余所有没脑子的狮子跟你一起去，还有那些愚蠢的豹子和羚羊。全照医生吩咐的去做。用点儿劲儿！说不定，他会发善心，过来看看咱们的小狮子。现在就去！——快去，我告诉你！你不配做父亲！”

说完，它转身进了隔壁洞穴。那儿住着另一头母狮子。狮后就把这件事一五一十地告诉了它。

狮子王回到医生那儿，说：“我刚好路过这儿，进来看看。找到帮手了吗？”

“没有，”医生说，“没有找到。我急得要命。”

“时下帮忙的很难找，”狮子说，“动物们好像都不情愿再干活了。你不能怪它们——不管怎样……喏，看到你有困难，我不介意做一些力所能及的事儿，只是给你帮个忙，只要不必给那些猴子冲洗就行。我已经叫别的捕猎动物也过来帮忙了。豹子随时都可能到……噢，顺便说一句，我们家的小狮子病了。我觉得它没有什么大毛病。可是，我的妻子非常担心。如果你今晚路过那儿，能不能给它瞧瞧？”

这下可把医生高兴坏了，因为所有的狮子、豹子、羚羊、长颈鹿和斑马——森林中、山里和草原上的所有动物——都过来帮他干活了。由于来得太多了，他只好把其中一些打发走了，只留下了那些最聪明的。

没过多久，猴子们就渐渐地开始康复了。第一周结束时，原来放满病床的大房子已经空了一半。到第二周结束时，连最后一只猴子也都痊愈了。

医生总算把工作做完了。这时，他已经疲惫不堪，在床上一睡就是三天，连身子都没有翻一下。

第九章　猴子开会

奇奇守在医生的门外，不让任何动物去打扰他，直到他醒来为止。醒来后，约翰·杜立德告诉猴子们说，他现在必须返回泥塘镇。

听到这话，猴子们大为吃惊，因为它们还以为医生会永远跟它们在一起呢。当天夜里，猴子全都聚在丛林里，商议这件事儿。

黑猩猩首领站起来，说道：“为什么这个好人要离开呢？难道他跟我们在一起不开心吗？”

可是，谁也回答不了它。

接着，大猩猩站起来，说道：“我认为咱们应该一起去找他，请他留下来。也许咱们给他建一座新房子，铺一张更大的床，答应有足够多的猴子佣人为他干活，让他生活舒坦——说不定他到时候就不想走了呢。”

这时，奇奇站了起来。别的猴子全都小声说道：“嘘！瞧！大旅行家奇奇要讲话了。”

奇奇对它们说：“我的朋友们，恐怕你们挽留医生也没用。他在泥塘镇欠别人钱，他说他必须回去还钱。”

猴子们好奇地问道：“什么是‘钱’？”

奇奇告诉它们说，在白人的国家里，没有钱，就什么也得不到；没有钱，什么也干不成——没有钱，简直无法生活。

一些猴子问道：“可是，不付钱，就不能吃喝吗？”

奇奇却摇了摇头，随后告诉它们说，它跟着那个手风琴艺人那会儿，它甚至还被迫向孩子们讨过钱呢。

黑猩猩首领转身对最老的猩猩说道：“表兄，这些人肯定是怪物！谁会愿意住在那样的一个国家啊？哎呀，真没用！”

这时，奇奇说：“我们准备来你们这儿时，既没有船过海，也没有钱买旅途上吃的食物。有个人就借给了我们一些饼干。我们答应过他，等一回去就把钱付给他。我们还从一个水手那儿借了一条船，但是那条船在我们到达非洲海岸时撞在礁石上撞碎了。医生说他必须回去，给那个水手搞一条船——因为那个人很穷，那条船就是他的全部家当。”

一时间，猴子们全都不吭声了，一动不动地坐在地上，苦思冥想。

最后，最大的狒狒站起来，说道：“我认为，咱们应该送给他一件漂亮的礼物让他带上，才能让他离开咱们的国家，这样也许可以让他知道，我们对他所做的一切充满了感激之情。”

一只娇小的红猴子坐在树上，朝下面喊道：“我也这么认为！”

随即，大家纷纷大声嚷嚷着：“对，对。咱们送给他一件白人从来没有过的最漂亮的礼物！”

接着，它们又开始纳闷，相互询问，要送给他礼物，送什么最好。有一只猴子说：“五十袋椰子！”另一只猴子说：“一百把香蕉！在他那个付钱才吃得上东西的国家，他至少不用买水果了！”

奇奇告诉它们说，这些东西都太沉了，带不了那么远，而且吃不到一半就会腐烂。

“如果你们真想让他高兴，”它说，“送给他一只动物。你们放心，他会善待这只动物。送给他一只动物园里没有的珍稀动物。”

猴子们问它：“什么是动物园？”

奇奇对它们解释说，在白人的国家里，动物园就是把动物放进笼子、让人参观的地方。

猴子们听了，无不震惊，纷纷说道：“这些人像没有思想的小孩子——既愚蠢又可笑。唏！它说的是牢房。”

于是，它们又问奇奇，应该送给医生什么珍稀动物，才是那些白人以前从未见过的。

金丝猴长老问：“他们那儿有鬣蜥吗？”

奇奇说：“有，伦敦动物园有一只。”

另一个又问：“他们有霍加皮吗？”

奇奇说：“有。比利时有。五年前，那位手风琴艺人带我去过那儿，在一个叫安特卫普的大城市里有一只霍加皮。”

又一只猴子问道：“他们有‘推我拉你’吗？”

这回，奇奇说：“没有。没有一个白人见过推我拉你。咱们就送给他这个吧。”

第十章　最稀罕的动物

推我拉你现在已经灭绝了。那就是说，再也没有了。可是，很久以前，杜立德医生还健在时，非洲丛林的最深处还有一些；即使在那个时候，它们也非常非常稀少。它们没有尾巴，却在两端各长着一个头，每个头上都长有尖角。它们非常怕人，很难逮住。黑人捉动物大多都是趁动物不注意时从后面悄悄靠近。可是，对付推我拉你，就不能采取这种方法——因为，不管从哪个方向靠近它，它总是面对着你。此外，睡觉时只有半边身体入睡，另一边的脑袋一直醒着，观察着。这就是它们从来没有被捕获、从来没有在动物园里被参观的原因。尽管好多很伟大的猎手和很精明的动物园主用了数年时间，到丛林里风雨无阻地搜寻推我拉你，但是一只也不曾逮住过。就连在好多年前那个时候，它都是世界上唯一的双头动物。

猴子们动身前往森林，去捕捉这种动物。它们跋涉了好多英里后，其中一只猴子在河边发现了一些奇特的脚印。它们知道，在这附近必定有一只推我拉你。

它们沿着河岸没走多远，便看到有一个地方草长得又高又密；它们猜它就在那儿。

于是，猴子们全体手拉手，在高草四周围成了一个大圆圈。那只推我拉你听到它们过来，想冲破猴子的包围圈，但是怎么也冲不出去。看到自己逃也没用，它就索性坐了下来，等着看它们想干什么。

猴子们问它愿不愿意随杜立德医生去白人国，让人参观。

它使劲摇着两个脑袋，说：“当然不愿意！”

猴子们对它解释说，它不会被关在动物园里，仅仅是让人观看。它们还告诉它说，医生是一个非常善良的人，不过就是没有钱。人们愿意掏钱观看一只双头动物，这样医生就会富起来，就可以偿还他为来非洲向人家借的那条船的船钱了。

可是，它回答说：“不。你们知道我有多么不愿见人——我不喜欢让人盯着看。”说着，它几乎要哭起来了。

接下来的三天，猴子们试图说服它。

第三天结束时，它说，它要先跟它们去看看医生是一个什么样的人。

于是，猴子们就把推我拉你带了回来。它们来到医生的小草房跟前，敲了敲门。

鸭子正在里面装行李箱，说道：“进来！”

奇奇豪情满怀地带着那只动物走了进去，让医生瞧。

“它到底是什么？”约翰·杜立德盯着这个奇特的动物问道。

“天哪！”鸭子叫道，“它是怎么下定决心的呢？”

“我看，它好像就没有下决心。”小狗吉普说。

“医生，这就是推我拉你，”奇奇说，“非洲丛林里最稀罕的动物，世界上唯一的双头兽！带它回去，你可就发财了。人们掏多少钱都愿意来看它。”

“可是，我一点儿都不需要钱。”医生说。

“不，你需要。”鸭子嘎嘎说，“难道你不记得咱们在泥塘镇是怎样省吃俭用，才付清肉店账钱的吗？还有，你不是说过要赔给水手一条新船吗？怎么赔？——除非咱们有钱去买。”

“我准备给他造一条船。”医生说。

“噢，请理智点儿！”嘎嘎嚷道，“你要造船，去哪儿弄造船需要的所有木材和钉子呢？再说，咱们靠什么生活？回去后咱们会比以前更穷。奇奇说的对极了，带上这只模样奇特的动物！”

“好吧，也许你说的有道理。”医生咕哝道，“它一定会成为一只可爱的新宠物。不过，这个──你叫它什么来着──真想去国外吗？”

“是的，我愿意。”推我拉你说。它从医生的脸上一眼就看出他是一个值得信赖的人。“你对这儿的动物那么好——猴子们告诉我说，我是唯一可以用来报答你的动物。不过，你必须答应我，如果我不喜欢白人国的生活，你就要把我送回来。”

“啊，当然——当然，当然可以。”医生说，“请问，你和鹿科动物肯定有亲戚关系，对吧？”

“对，”推我拉你说，“我的母亲那边属于阿比西尼亚瞪羚和亚洲岩羚羊。我父亲的曾祖父是最后一只独角兽。”

“太有意思了！”医生低声说着，他从嘎嘎装好的箱子里掏出一本书，翻看起来，“让我们看看布封伯爵怎么说──”

“我注意到，”鸭子说，“你只用一张嘴说话。你的另一个脑袋也会说话吗？”

“噢，当然会。”推我拉你说，“不过，一般，我用另一张嘴来吃东西。这样的话，我就能边吃边谈，不会无礼。我们推我拉你总是很有礼貌。”

收拾完行李，一切准备就绪要出发时，猴子们为医生举办了一场盛大的宴会，丛林里所有的动物都来了。它们带来了菠萝、杧果、蜂蜜，还有各种好吃好喝的东西。

大家全都吃完后，医生站起来，说道：“我的朋友们，我不善于像一些人那样晚宴后长篇大论。我刚才吃了好多水果和蜂蜜。可是，我想告诉你们，离开你们这个美丽的国家，我很伤心。我在白人国还有事儿要处理，必须得走。我走后，你们记住吃饭前千万别让苍蝇落在你们的食物上，下雨时不要睡在地上。我——呃——呃——我希望你们从此全都生活幸福。”

说完，医生坐了下来。猴子们全体鼓掌，经久不息。它们相互转告：“我们可要永远记住，他曾和我们坐在一起吃过饭，在这儿，在这棵树下。因为他的确是一个最伟大的人！”

这时，大猩猩把一块巨石滚到了桌面上，它毛茸茸的胳膊有七匹马那么大的力气。它说：“这块巨石将会永远标明这个地方。”

即使到了今天，这块巨石也仍然耸立在丛林的中心地带。每当猴妈妈们带着家人穿过这片森林时，仍然会从树枝间指着下面那块巨石，小声对孩子们说道：“嘘！它在那儿——瞧，那就是大病之年那个善良的白人跟我们坐在一起吃饭的地方！”

宴会结束后，医生和他的宠物们起程前往海岸边。

猴子们一路随行，纷纷为他扛行李箱、拎提包，一直把他送到了国界边。

第十一章　黑王子

到了河边，他们驻足告别。这花了很长时间，因为数千只猴子都想跟约翰·杜立德握手。

最后，医生和他的宠物们独自上路了。波利尼西亚说：“咱们经过乔里金基国时，一定要蹑手蹑脚、轻言低语。一旦国王听到我们的声音，他一定会派卫兵再来抓我们。我相信，他还在为上次被我戏弄的事儿大动肝火。”

“我在想，”医生说，“我们到哪儿弄一条船坐回家……噢唔，说不定我们会在海滩上找到一条碰巧没有人使用的船。不过，‘千万要到台阶再抬脚’。”

一天，他们正通过森林一处非常茂密的地方，奇奇跑到前面去找椰子。奇奇离开这段时间，医生和剩下的动物们因为不太熟悉丛林里的小路，在密林深处迷了路。他们转来转去，怎么也找不到前往海岸的路。

奇奇哪儿都看不到大家的影子，心里七上八下。它爬上高树，从树梢上四下张望，想看到医生的高帽。它一边挥手，一边叫喊，把动物们的名字统统喊了一遍。可是没用。他们好像全都消失了。

他们的确迷了路，迷得还不轻，严重偏离了小路。丛林十分茂密，到处都是灌木丛、匍匐枝和藤蔓，有时他们根本无法行走。医生只好拿出随身小折刀，开路前进。他们跌跌撞撞地误入过一些沼泽地，被稠密的旋花缠绕植物完全缠住过身体，荆棘划得他们到处是伤，有两次差点儿把医药包丢在下层林丛里。他们的麻烦好像没完没了，而且哪儿都找不着路。

他们就这样晕头转向走了好多天，衣服破了，脸上沾满了泥，最后误入了国王的后花园。国王的卫兵们马上跑过来，抓住了他们。

波利尼西亚趁人不注意，飞到花园的一棵树上，藏了起来。医生以及其余的动物都被押到了国王面前。

“哈，哈！”国王叫道，“你们又被抓住了！这次你们可跑不了了。把他们统统押进牢房，门上加两道锁。这个白人后半辈子都要给我擦厨房的地板！”

医生和他的宠物们再次被带进牢房关了起来。随后，医生被告知说，明天早上他就必须开始擦厨房的地板。

大家都闷闷不乐。

“真烦。”医生说，“我真的必须赶回泥塘镇。如果不快点儿赶回家，那个可怜的水手会以为我偷走了他的船……不知道那些铰链拴没拴牢。”

门很结实，锁得也很牢。几乎没有逃出去的机会。珈珈又开始哭了起来。

在这期间，波利尼西亚还卧在后宫花园的那棵树上。它一声不吭，眨着眼睛。

这种情况出现在波利尼西亚身上，往往标志着形势非常不妙。每当它默默无语，光眨眼睛时，便说明有人一直在找麻烦，它正在想法摆平。谁要找波利尼西亚或它的朋友麻烦，以后十有八九总会后悔。

波利尼西亚突然看见奇奇在树丛中飞来荡去，在寻找医生。奇奇也发现了它，随即来到它藏身的树上，询问医生的下落。

“医生和所有那些动物都被国王的卫兵抓去，关进了牢房。”波利尼西亚低声说道，“我们在丛林里迷了路，误入了王宫花园。”

“可是，不是有你给他们带路吗？”奇奇问道。它开始责备鹦鹉，因为鹦鹉在奇奇去找椰子时让大家迷了路。

“都怨那头蠢猪，”波利尼西亚说，“它总是跑下小路寻找姜根吃。我动不动就得忙着去追赶它，把它带回原路，搞得我在沼泽那儿向左转，没有向右拐。嘘！瞧！邦波王子来花园里了！绝不能让他瞧见咱们。无论如何都不要动！”

果然是国王的儿子邦波王子。只见他打开园门，走了进来，腋下挟一本童话书，嘴里哼着一首忧伤的曲子，沿着沙砾小路溜达着来到了鹦鹉和猴子藏身的那棵树下。那儿有一个石凳。他就在石凳上躺下来，默念起了童话故事。

奇奇和波利尼西亚观察着他，一动也不敢动。

不一会儿，国王的儿子放下了书，疲惫地叹了口气。

“我要是个白王子，该多好啊！”他说，眼里露出了梦幻般悠远的神情。

鹦鹉像小女孩那样用又细又尖的嗓音大声说道：“邦波，有人说不定能把你变成白王子。”

国王的儿子惊得一下从凳子上跳了下来，四处张望。

“我听到的这是什么？”他叫道，“想必是从那边树荫里传来的仙女银铃般甜美的声音吧！好奇怪！”

“尊敬的王子，”波利尼西亚仍然一动不动，所以邦波看不到它，“你说得没错。是我——特丽普丝婷卡仙后跟你说话。我隐藏在一朵玫瑰花蕾里。”

“噢，告诉我，仙后，”邦波高兴得紧握双手叫道，“谁能把我变白呀？”

“你父亲的牢房里，”鹦鹉说，“躺着一位大名鼎鼎的奇人，名叫约翰·杜立德。他通晓不少医术和魔法，曾做出好多壮举呢。然而，你的父王却把他折磨得日渐憔悴、奄奄一息。等太阳落山时，你暗中找他去吧，勇敢的邦波。看吧，你将会变成最白的王子，永远赢得仙女的芳心。我只能说这么多了，现在我必须返回仙境了。再见！”

“再见！”王子叫道，“万分感谢，好心的特丽普丝婷卡！”

然后，他又在石凳上坐下来，面带微笑，等待太阳落下。

第十二章　医术和魔法

波利尼西亚确信没有人看到它时，就悄无声息地从树背后溜了出来，向牢房飞过去。

它看见珈珈把鼻子伸到窗户栅栏外，正用力闻王宫厨房飘来的饭香。它催小猪把医生叫过来，因为它想跟他说话。珈珈跑去叫醒了正在打盹的医生。

“听我说，”医生一露面，鹦鹉就低声说道，“邦波王子今晚要来见你。你得想个办法把他变白。不过，首先要让他向你保证，到时候他愿意打开牢门，给你找一条船过海。”

“这倒是很好。”医生说，“可是，把黑人变白不是那么容易。你说得就像他是一件衣服要重新染一遍似的。没有那么简单。‘是豹子能改变身上的斑点，还是埃塞俄比亚人会改变他们的肤色？’你懂吗？”

“那个我一窍不通。”波利尼西亚不耐烦地说，“可是，你务必把这个人变白。想办法，使劲儿想。你那包里还剩有好多药呢。如果你能改变他的肤色，他就什么事儿都愿为你做。这可是你逃出牢房的唯一机会。”

“好吧，我想也许有可能，”医生说，“让我来看看——”随后，他走到医药包前，喃喃说道，“在动物色素上加点儿氯化物——也许可以用氧化锌软膏，既然是暂时的，就厚厚地涂上一层。”

果然，当天夜里，邦波王子偷偷来到牢房找医生，他对医生说：“白人啊，我是一个不幸的王子。几年前，我去寻找书里说的睡美人。我周游世界很久，终于找到了她，像书上说的那样，我十分温柔地亲吻那位小姐，以唤醒她。她果真醒了过来。可是，她一看见我的脸，就大声叫道：‘噢，他真黑啊！’说完，她就跑了，不愿意嫁给我，又到别的地方睡去了。我带着满腔痛苦回到了父亲的王国。现在，我听说你是一个了不起的魔法师，带有好多有奇效的药剂。所以，我来向你寻求帮助。如果你把我变白，使我可以回到睡美人的身边，我愿意把半壁江山和你要求的任何东西送给你。”

“邦波王子，”医生一边若有所思地望着医药包里的那些瓶子，一边说道，“假如我把你的头发染成漂亮的金色，你开不开心？”

“不，”邦波说，“别的什么都不能让我满意。我必须成为一位白王子。”

“要知道，改变王子的肤色很难，”医生说，“是魔法师所能做的最难的一件事儿。你只想把脸变白，是吗？”

“是，仅此而已。”邦波王子说，“因为我要像其他白王子那样穿上闪亮的盔甲，戴上钢质的护手，骑在马背上。”

“要整个脸都变白？”医生问。

“对，整个脸，”邦波王子说，“我还想把眼睛变成蓝色，但是我又觉得那一定会很难。”

“是，是很难。”医生赶紧说道，“好吧，我会尽我所能。不过，你得很有耐心——你知道，有些药，谁也拿不太准。说不定得试两三次。你的皮肤很结实，对吧？噢，那就好。现在到灯这边来。噢，不过，在我做事之前，你必须先到海边准备好一条船，里面放上食物，以便渡我过海。你不能对任何人透露半个字。等我满足你的要求后，你必须放我和所有的动物出狱。你发誓，以乔里金基王冠的名义发誓！”

王子发完誓后，就到海边备好了一条船。

他回来后，说已经准备停当了。医生这才让嘎嘎拿来一个盆。他在盆里混合了好多药，让邦波王子把脸浸进去。

王子弯下腰，把脸伸进盆里，正好浸住耳朵。

他浸了好长时间，长得连医生似乎都忐忑不安起来，这条腿站站，那条腿站站，看看刚才用来混合的所有药瓶，又反复念念上面的标签。牢房里弥漫着一种强烈的味道，就像烧牛皮纸的气味。

最后，王子从盆里抬起头来，大口大口地喘着气。动物们都惊叫起来。

只见王子的脸变得雪白雪白的，原本土黄色的眼睛变成了具有男子汉气概的灰色！

约翰·杜立德借给他一面小镜子，让他照照看。他高兴地唱了起来，并开始在牢房里手舞足蹈。可是，医生要他别发出那么大的响声，他匆匆合上医药包，叫王子打开牢门。

邦波王子请求医生把小镜子留给他，因为这是乔里金基王国唯一的镜子，他想天天照镜子。可是，医生说他需要用它来照着刮胡子。

王子从口袋里掏出一串铜钥匙，打开了两道大锁。医生和他的所有动物尽其所能，飞快地向海边跑去。邦波王子靠墙站在空荡荡的牢房里，望着他们的背影，露出了开心的微笑。他那张大脸在月光下像磨光的象牙一样闪闪发光。

医生和动物们来到海边，看见波利尼西亚和奇奇正在船边的礁石上等候他们。

“我感觉对不起邦波王子。”医生说。

“我担心用的那种药维持不了多久。等他明天早上醒来时，十有八九还会像原来一样黑。正因为这样，我才不乐意把镜子留给他。不过，也许他会一直白下去——以前我从来没有用过那种混合剂。说实话，看到效果那么好，我自己也非常吃惊。可是，我不得不试一把，对吧？也许下半辈子我可以不给国王擦厨房了。那个厨房真脏！——我从牢房的窗户就能看到。唉，唉！可怜的邦波！”

“噢，他当然知道我们只是跟他开玩笑。”鹦鹉说。

“他们无权关押我们。”嘎嘎来回摇着尾巴生气地说，“我们从来没有伤害过他们。如果他真的又变黑了，那是他自作自受！我希望他的脸变成深黑色。”

“可是，他跟这件事没有任何关系。”医生说，“是国王，他的父亲，派人把我们关起来的——这不是邦波的错……我在想，该不该回去道歉——噢，算了——回泥塘镇后给他寄些糖果吧。谁知道呢？别忘了，也许他会一直白下去。”

“即使他变白，睡美人也绝不会要他。”嘎嘎说，“我认为，他原来的样子更好看。可是，不管变成什么颜色，他都不漂亮。”

“尽管如此，但他心好，”医生说，“当然，有些浪漫，但是心好。毕竟，‘做人漂亮才是真漂亮’。”

“我一点儿都不相信这个可怜的傻瓜见过什么睡美人，”小狗吉普说，“他十有八九是亲吻了苹果树下某个打盹的胖农妇。被吓一跳，也不能怪她！我不知道这回他会去亲吻谁。瞧他干的傻事儿！”

推我拉你、小白鼠、珈珈、嘎嘎、吉普和猫头鹰秃秃，都随医生上了船。可是，奇奇、波利尼西亚和鳄鱼留了下来，因为非洲才是它们真正的家，是它们出生的地方。

医生站在船上，隔海眺望，他这才想起，随行者当中，谁也不能给他们指引返回泥塘镇的路。

月光下，辽阔的海面看上去空旷而孤寂。他开始担心，等看不见陆地时，他们会不会迷失方向。

正在他一筹莫展时，透过夜幕，他们听到高空传来了一阵奇怪的沙沙声。动物们全都停止道别，侧耳倾听。

那声音越来越响，越来越大了，仿佛离他们越来越近了，听起来既像是秋风吹过白杨树叶的声音，又像是一场很大很大的雨打在屋顶的响声。

吉普鼻子朝天，尾巴绷直，说道：“是鸟！几百万只，飞得很快——就是！”

他们都抬头望去。只见成千上万只小鸟，像一大群小蚂蚁似的源源不断地掠过月亮表面。不一会儿，整个天空仿佛都飞满了小鸟，而且仍在源源不断地飞来，越来越多。小鸟太多了，一时间遮住了整个月亮，月光没有了，海上越来越暗，越来越黑了，就像暴雨云遮住太阳时那样。

很快，所有这些小鸟密密麻麻地向下飞来，贴着水面和陆地。夜空明朗，月亮又像先前那样明亮了。不过，它们始终没有喊叫，没有哭泣，也没有歌唱，只是此时比以往任何时候，翅膀扇动的声音都要大。它们纷纷落在沙滩上、船缆上，以及树以外的任何地方，医生这才看清，它们蓝翅白胸，一双毛茸茸的短腿。它们都找到地方落脚后，四周突然变得声息皆无。一切都是那么宁静，那么静寂。

在静谧的月光下，约翰·杜立德说道：“没想到咱们在非洲待了这么长时间。到家时，差不多都快到夏天了。这些是返回北方的燕子。燕子们，感谢你们等我们啊。你们考虑得真周到。现在，我们不必担心会在海上迷路了……拔锚起帆！”

海面上，船走远了，那些留下来的动物——奇奇、波利尼西亚和鳄鱼——都难过极了。一生中，它们还从来没有遇见过一个人，像沼泽地的泥塘镇的约翰·杜立德医生这样让它们喜欢。它们一遍一遍又一遍地大声说着再见，直到看不见船的踪影了，它们还站在岸边的礁石上挥泪招手。

第十三章　红帆蓝翅

回家途中，医生的船必须经过巴巴里海岸。这个海岸是大沙漠的海岸线，是一个荒凉孤寂的地方——到处都是沙子和石头。巴巴里海盗就生活在这儿。

这些海盗是一群大坏蛋，他们常常在海岸上等待水手们的船失事。看见有船经过，他们也经常驾驶快帆船追赶。在海上追上这样的船后，他们就会抢走船上所有的东西，带走船上的人，把船沉没，然后一路高歌返回巴巴里，而且还为自己做的坏事扬扬得意。他们常常让被抓的人给家里写信，向朋友们要钱。如果对方不送钱来，海盗们就会把人扔进大海。

一天，阳光明媚，医生和嘎嘎在船上走来走去锻炼身体，和煦的清风吹拂着船向前行进，大家都很高兴。这时，嘎嘎看到另一面船帆出现在海平面上，远远地跟在他们后面。那是一面红帆。

“我不喜欢那面船帆的外观。”嘎嘎说，“我有一种感觉，那只船不友善。恐怕我们又要有麻烦了。”

吉普当时正躺在不远处的阳光下睡觉，这时候忽然开始咆哮起来，还说着梦话。

“我闻到了烤牛肉的味道，”它咕哝道，“半生不熟的牛肉，上面还浇了棕色肉汁。”

“天哪！”医生叫道，“狗怎么了？睡梦中，它还在闻东西，说话？”

“我想是的，”嘎嘎说，“狗全都可以在睡梦中闻东西。”

“可是，它闻到了什么？”医生问道，“咱们船上没有烤牛肉呀。”

“是的。”嘎嘎说，“烤牛肉肯定是在那一只船上。”

“可是，隔着十英里远，”医生说，“它绝不可能闻那么远！”

“噢，能，它能。”嘎嘎说，“你问问它。”

这时，吉普还在熟睡，又开始咆哮起来，嘴唇生气地向上卷起，露出了洁白干净的牙齿。

“我闻到了坏人，”它咆哮说，“我闻到有史以来最坏的人。我闻到了麻烦。我闻到了打斗，六个坏蛋打一个勇士。我想帮他。汪──唔──汪！”于是，它大声吠叫着，把自己都吵醒了，一脸受惊吓的样子。

“看到了吧！”嘎嘎叫道，“那条船现在越来越近了。可以数出来有三面大帆——全都是红的。不管是什么人，他们是在追我们……我不知道他们是谁。”

“他们是坏水手，”吉普说，“他们的船非常快。他们肯定是巴巴里的海盗。”

“咱们必须给船再挂上些帆，”医生说，“这样能跑得更快，摆脱他们。吉普，下底舱，把你见到的帆统统拖上来。”

小狗急忙跑到底舱，把所能找到的帆全都拖了上来。

可是，即使把这些帆都挂上桅杆张起风，他们的船也还是不如海盗们的快。海盗船在后面不断往前，越来越近了。

“王子给我们的这条船真差劲儿，”小猪珈珈说，“想必是他所能找到的最慢的船。乘坐这条老驳船摆脱他们，还不如坐进盛汤的盖碗去赢得赛船比赛的希望大。瞧！他们现在有多近！那帮人脸上的胡子都能看清楚——他们一共六个人。我们打算怎么办？”

医生要嘎嘎飞到空中，告诉那些燕子，海盗在划快船追他们，问问燕子该怎么办。

闻听此事，燕子们全飞下来，落到了医生的船上。它们告诉医生尽快把长绳拆开，拆成好多根细绳，然后把所有这些细绳的一端系在船头。燕子们用爪子牢牢抓住那些细绳，拽着船向前飞行。

一两只燕子的话，力量不大，但是如果好大一群燕子聚在一起，那就不一样了。船头拴着千根细绳，每根上面又都有两千只燕子拽着，它们个个都是飞行高手。

医生立刻发现自己的船跑得那么快，快得让他不得不用双手抓紧帽子。他感觉像是船自己在波涛翻滚的大海上飞波穿浪。

身在急速飞驰的船上，动物们都又笑又跳，回头再看海盗船，只见它不是越来越大，而是越来越小了。红帆被远远地抛在了后面。

第十四章　老鼠的警告

海上拖船是一件辛苦活儿。两三个小时后，燕子们都翅膀酸痛，上气不接下气。它们给医生传话说，它们必须得马上休息一下，要把船拉到不远处的一座小岛边，把它藏在一个深海湾里，等喘足气后，再继续前进。

不一会儿，医生便看到了燕子提到的那座小岛。岛中央高高耸立着一座非常美丽的青山。

船安全驶进了海湾，从外面的远海看不到这条船。医生说他下船去岛上找些水——因为船上饮用水没有了。随后，他吩咐动物们全都出来，到草地上嬉戏玩耍，活动活动腿脚。

现在，当他们下船时，医生注意到一大窝老鼠从底舱窜出来，也在离开船。吉普便追了上去，追咬老鼠一向是他最喜欢的游戏。可是，医生叫住了它。

一只大黑鼠似乎想对医生说什么，它顺着船护栏，一边小心翼翼地爬过来，一边用眼角余光提防着小狗，它紧张不安地咳嗽了两三声，捋捋胡须，擦了擦嘴，说道：“啊哼——呃——医生，所有的船上都有老鼠，这你当然知道，是吧？”

医生说：“我知道。”

“那你听说过老鼠总是离开即将沉没的船吗？”

“是的，”医生说，“我听人说过。”

“人们说起这件事儿，”老鼠说，“总是嗤之以鼻，好像这是一件不光彩的事儿。可是，你不会怪我们，是吗？毕竟，要是能逃，谁愿意待在要沉的船上呢？”

“这很自然，”医生说，“很自然。我完全理解你……还有——你还有别的事儿想说吗？”

“有。”老鼠说，“我来是想告诉你，我们要离开这只船。不过，走之前，我们想提醒你，你坐的这条船问题成堆。它不安全，船帮不够结实，船板也朽了。不到明天晚上，它就会沉到海底去了。”

“可是，你怎么知道？”医生问。

“我们一向知道。”老鼠回答说，“我们尾巴尖上有那种刺麻感，就跟你脚麻时的感觉一样。今天早上六点钟，我正在吃早饭，尾巴尖突然开始刺麻。起先，我还以为是风湿病又犯了。于是，我去问姑妈她的感觉如何——你还记得它吗？就是那只长长的花斑鼠，相当瘦，去年春天曾去泥塘镇找你看过黄疸病——它说它的尾巴尖刺麻得很！于是，我们知道，不出两天，这只船肯定会沉没。我们全都打定主意，船一靠近陆地，我们就离开。医生，这条船有问题，不要再坐了，否则你肯定会被淹死……再见！我们现在要去岛上找一处好地方住。”

“再见！”医生说，“非常感谢你来告诉我。你考虑得很周到──非常周到！代我向你的姑妈问好。我完全记得她……吉普，别碰那只老鼠！过来！躺下！”

医生和他的动物们纷纷提着桶端着锅下了船，到岛上去找水。与此同时，燕子们抓紧时间休息。

“我不知道这岛叫什么名字。”医生一边爬山坡，一边说道，“看上去这是一个宜人的地方。鸟可真多啊！”

“噢，这是金丝雀群岛，”嘎嘎说，“你没有听见金丝雀在唱歌吗？”

医生驻足倾听。

“哎呀，真的是——一点儿没错！”他说，“我真笨哪！我想知道它们能不能告诉我们在哪儿能找到水。”

很快，那些金丝雀飞了过来。它们早就从候鸟那儿听说了杜立德医生的所有故事。它们把他领到一处清澈、凉爽又美丽的泉水边，那儿是金丝雀们经常洗澡的地方。它们还带他去看了长有鸟食的秀美草地，以及岛上其他所有的风景。

推我拉你很高兴他们来到这儿，因为它喜欢青草，远远胜过那些它一直在船上吃的干苹果。珈珈发现整个山谷都是野甘蔗，高兴得吱吱直叫。

不一会儿，他们便吃饱喝足，仰躺在草地上，金丝雀为他们唱着歌儿，这时两只燕子匆匆飞过来，慌里慌张，惶恐不安。

“医生！”它们叫道，“海盗们追进了海湾，他们全都上了你的船。他们正在底舱盗抢东西。他们离开了自己的船，船上没有人。你们赶紧到海边去，上他们的船逃走——这条船速度很快。不过，你必须抓紧时间。”

“好主意，”医生说，“太棒了！”

他马上把动物们召集起来，告别金丝雀，向海边跑去。

他们跑到海边，果然看见了挂着三面红帆的海盗船停在水里，而且正如燕子们所说，船上没有一个人，所有海盗都在医生的船舱里盗抢东西。

医生吩咐他的动物们放轻脚步。大家全都上了海盗船。

第十五章　巴巴里龙

要不是因为小猪在岛上啃湿甘蔗，头着凉感冒，事情本来会一帆风顺。当时的情形是这样的：

他们悄无声息地拔起锚后，正小心翼翼地把船划出海湾，珈珈突然打了个喷嚏，声音响亮。听到动静，另一条船上的海盗冲上了甲板，看是什么声音。

一见是医生要逃跑，他们就驾船横堵在了海湾入口处，不让医生逃到远海去。

隔着水面，坏蛋的首领，那个自称“巴巴里龙本·阿里”的人冲医生又是挥拳又是叫嚣：“哈！哈！你跑不掉了，我的好朋友！你想驾我的船逃走，呃？可是，你当水手不够好，比不过巴巴里龙本·阿里。我想要你那只鸭子，还有那只小猪。我们今天晚饭有猪排和烤鸭吃喽。务必让你的朋友送来满满一箱金子，我才会放你回家。”

可怜的珈珈开始哭了起来；嘎嘎也准备飞走逃命。可是，猫头鹰秃秃低声对医生说：“稳住他，别让他停嘴，医生，要对他和颜悦色。我们的旧船一定会很快沉没。老鼠说过，不到明天晚上，它就会沉到海底去——老鼠绝不会错的。要和颜悦色，直到船在他下面下沉。稳住他，别让他停嘴。”

“什么，直到明天晚上！”医生说，“好吧，我尽力而为……让我想想——我说什么呢？”

“噢，叫他们过来。”小狗吉普说，“我们可以打得过这帮可恶的混蛋。他们只有六个人。叫他们上来。等我们回到家，我很乐意讲给隔壁的那只牧羊犬，我曾咬过一个真正的海盗。让他们过来，我们能打过他们。”

“可是，他们有枪有剑。”医生说，“不，绝对不行。我必须跟他说话……喂，本·阿里──”

可是，还没等医生再说什么，那些海盗已经驾船靠得更近了。他们幸灾乐祸地哈哈大笑着，你一句我一句相互打趣道：“谁先去捉那只小猪啊？”

可怜的珈珈吓得要死；推我拉你开始在桅杆上磨头上的角，准备战斗；吉普不停地跳着、叫着，用狗语骂着本·阿里。

但是很快，海盗那边好像出了什么事儿，没有了欢笑，也不再打趣了，他们神情迷茫，一定有什么事儿搅得他们心神不安了。

本·阿里正盯着脚下看，突然大声吼道：“遭雷劈的！——伙计们，这船在漏水！”

于是，其他海盗仔细打量船侧外面，他们看到船确实一点点儿往下沉了。一个海盗对本·阿里说道：“这旧船真要沉的话，我们就应该看到有老鼠弃船的。”

吉普从对面船上喊道：“你们这群大傻蛋，船上绝不会再有老鼠离开了！它们两小时前就离开了！告诉你们，哈哈，‘我的好朋友！’”

不过，那帮人肯定听不懂它说的话。不久，那条船的船头就渐渐地开始下沉，而且越沉越快，直到船看上去几乎像头朝下竖着一般；海盗们只好紧紧抓住扶手、桅杆、缆绳以及可以防止滑落的任何东西。随后，海浪呼啸着冲了上来，灌进了所有的门窗。最后，船陡峭倾斜，沉入了海底，并发出了可怕的汩汩声，留下这六个坏蛋在海湾的深水里来回扑腾着。

他们中的一些人开始朝小岛岸边游去；另一些则向医生所在的船拼命游过来，想要上船。吉普不断地照他们的鼻子咬过去，所以他们吓得不敢爬上船沿。

突然，他们全都惊恐万状地大叫起来：“鲨鱼群！鲨鱼群来了！他们要吃掉我们！让我们上船吧！救命，救命啊！鲨鱼群！鲨鱼群！”

这时，医生才看到，整个海湾布满了飞快游过来的大鲨鱼的脊背。

一条大鲨鱼游到医生的船边，从水中伸出鼻子，对医生说：“你是著名的动物医生约翰·杜立德吗？”

“是，”杜立德医生说，“我就是约翰·杜立德。”

“是这样，”鲨鱼说，“我们知道这些海盗是一帮坏蛋，尤其是本·阿里。他们骚扰你，我们乐意为你效劳，吃掉他们，这样你就不会再有麻烦了。”

“谢谢你，”医生说，“这真是周到极了。可是，我想，没必要吃掉他们。我不发话，就不要让他们游上岸——只让他们在水里来回游，好吗？把本·阿里弄到这儿来，我有话对他说。”

鲨鱼游过去，把本·阿里驱赶到了医生这边。

“听着，本·阿里，”约翰·杜立德趴到船沿上，俯身对他说，“你一向作恶多端，我知道你杀了不少人。这些好鲨鱼刚才主动要求替我吃掉你们。海上要是没有你们，那将是一件幸事。可是，如果你答应按我说的去做，我就让你们平安离开。”

“我必须怎么做？”他低头斜视着水下正嗅着他一条腿的一条大鲨鱼问道。

“你绝不再杀人，”医生说，“你绝不再偷盗；你绝不再沉船；总之，你绝不再当海盗。”

“那我干什么？”本·阿里问道，“我怎么生活呀？”

“你和你那帮手下必须全部上这个岛当农夫，种鸟食，”医生回答说，“你们必须为金丝雀们种鸟食。”

巴巴里龙气得脸色发白。“种鸟食！”他厌恶地咕哝说，“难道不能当水手吗？”

“不能，”医生说，“你不能。你当水手的时间够长了，把多少好船好人都沉到了海底。后半辈子，你必须做一个安分守己的农夫。那条鲨鱼还在等着呢，别再浪费它的时间了，你做决定吧。”

“遭雷劈的！”本·阿里嘀咕道，“种鸟食！”随即，他又低头看了看水里，只见那条大鲨鱼正在嗅着他的另一条腿。

“很好，”他伤心地说，“我们愿意当农夫。”

“记住，”医生说，“如果你不遵守诺言，又开始杀人越货，我就会听到，因为那些金丝雀会来告诉我。毫无疑问，我会想法惩治你。尽管我没有你驾船在行，但是只要小鸟、野兽和鱼类还是我的朋友，我就不必害怕一个海盗头，哪怕他自称‘巴巴里龙’。现在去吧，做一个好农夫，平静地生活吧。”

说完，医生转身朝那条大鲨鱼挥了挥手，说道：“好了。让他们安全地游上岸吧。”

第十六章　神耳秃秃

再次谢过鲨鱼们的帮助，医生和他的宠物们坐上那条有三面红帆的快船，又一次踏上了回家的航程。

等来到开阔海域时，动物们全都跑下底舱去看他们这只新船里面是什么样子。此时，医生身靠扶手站在船尾，嘴里叼着烟斗，注视着金丝雀群岛渐渐地消失在傍晚的蓝色薄暮之中。

他站在那儿，正寻思那些猴子不知怎么样了，寻思家里的花园，等他回泥塘镇时，会变成什么样子，嘎嘎跌跌撞撞地爬了上来，满脸微笑，滔滔不绝。

“医生！”它叫道，“海盗们这条船真漂亮——漂亮极了。底舱里的床是用淡黄色丝绸做的，上面放了好几百个大枕头和垫子，地上铺着又厚又软的地毯，餐具是银质的，还有各种好吃好喝的，那可不是一般的东西。食物贮藏间，噢，就像一个食品店，应有尽有。你一辈子也没有见过像这样的——试想一下——那帮人，他们贮藏有五种不同的沙丁鱼！下去看看……噢，我们在下面还发现了一个小房间，门是锁着的。大家都非常想进去看看里面是什么。吉普说肯定是海盗们藏财宝的地方。可是，我们打不开门。你下去看看，能不能让我们进去。”

医生下到底舱一看，这的确是一只漂亮的船。他发现动物们围在一个小门前，争先恐后，议论纷纷，都在尽力猜测里面是什么。无论医生怎么转动门把手，门就是打不开。接着，他们开始寻找钥匙。门前蹭脚垫下面，所有地毯下面，所有碗碟柜、抽屉以及上锁的小柜里面，餐室内的大柜子里，什么地方都找遍了。

在寻找的过程中，他们发现了好多新奇的东西，肯定是海盗们从其他船上偷盗来的：几件克什米尔披肩，上面绣着金花，像蜘蛛网一样薄；几罐牙买加产的上好烟草；几只装满俄罗斯茶叶的象牙雕盒子；一把旧小提琴，断了一根弦，背面贴有一幅画；一套用珊瑚和琥珀雕成的大棋子；一副一拉手柄里面会有一把剑的拐杖；六只杯沿上镶有绿宝石和银子的葡萄酒杯；还有一只珍珠母做的大糖碗。可是，搜遍了整条船，他们也没有找到能开那把锁的钥匙。

他们又回到了那扇门前。吉普从锁眼向里瞧。可是，里面有什么东西背墙立着，它什么也看不见。

他们围站在那儿，不知道该怎么办。这时，猫头鹰秃秃突然说道：“嘘！——听！——我确信那里面有人！”

他们都安静下来，过了一会儿，医生说道：“你肯定弄错了，秃秃。我什么也听不见。”

“我敢保证有人。”猫头鹰说，“嘘！——又有了——难道你听不见吗？”

“是的，我听不见，”医生说，“那是什么声音？”

“我听见有人把手伸进口袋的声音。”猫头鹰说。

“可是，那几乎不会有任何声音，”医生说，“从这外面，你不可能听见。”

“对不起，可是我听见了。”秃秃说，“我告诉你，门那边有个人把手伸进了口袋。几乎一切东西都会发出声音，只要你的耳朵足够灵敏，就能听到。蝙蝠能听到鼹鼠在地下洞穴里走动的声音，它们认为自己是千里耳。可是，黑暗中，我们猫头鹰只用一只耳朵，就能根据小猫眨眼睛的方式，告诉你它是什么颜色。”

“好，好！”医生说，“你真让我吃惊。这非常有趣……再听一听，告诉我，他正在干什么。”

“我还拿不准，”秃秃说，“究竟是一个男的，还是一个女的。把我举起来，让我贴到锁眼上听听，我能很快告诉你答案。”

于是，医生举起猫头鹰，让它贴到了门锁上。

不一会儿，秃秃说：“现在他正用左手抹脸，是小手和小脸。可能是一个女的——不。现在他把前额上的头发拢到了后面——是一个男的，没错。”

“女人们有时也那样做。”医生说。

“对。”猫头鹰说，“不过，她们头发长，那样做时，会发出完全不同的声音……嘘！让那个坐立不安的小猪保持安静。现在都屏住呼吸，让我好好听听。我现在做的这件事难得很，而且这个讨厌的门又这么厚！嘘！大家都别动，闭上眼睛，屏住呼吸。”

秃秃埋下头，又用劲儿听了好久。

最后，它抬起头来，望着医生的脸，说道：“里面那个男的不开心。他哭泣。他小心翼翼，没有哭出声来，也没有抽鼻子，以免被我们发现他在哭。可是，我听见——一清二楚——一颗眼泪落在他袖子上的声音。”

“你怎么知道那不是天花板上的一颗水珠落在他身上呢？”珈珈问。

“啐！真无知！”猫头鹰嗤之以鼻，“天花板上落下一颗水珠会发出十倍大的声音！”

“好了，”医生说，“如果那个可怜的家伙不开心，我们就得进去看看他出了什么事儿。给我找一把斧子，我要把这个门劈掉。”

第十七章　海洋闲话篓

斧子马上就找来了。医生很快在门上劈了一个洞，刚好可以钻过去。

一开始，他根本什么也看不见，里面一团漆黑。他划了一根火柴。

房间相当小，没有窗户，天花板很低。至于家具，就一张小凳子。房间四周靠墙竖着一些大桶，桶底固定在地上，这样船颠簸时，桶就不会翻倒。大桶上方的木钉上面挂满了各种大大小小的白镴酒壶。房间里有一股浓烈的葡萄酒的气味。地板中央坐着一个小男孩，大约八岁，哭得正痛。

“我断言，这是海盗们的酒屋！”吉普低声说道。

“对。正是朗姆酒！”珈珈说，“这气味让我头晕。”

看到一个男人站在自己面前，还有些动物透过破门洞在盯着他看，小男孩仿佛吓得要命。可是，借着火柴的光亮，一看到医生的脸，他就不哭了，站了起来。

“你不是那帮海盗的人，对吗？”他问。

医生仰头朗声笑了好一会儿。小男孩也露出了微笑，走过来拉住医生的手。

“你笑起来像朋友，”他说，“不像海盗。你能告诉我，我舅舅在哪儿吗？”

“恐怕不能。”医生说，“你最后一次见他是什么时候？”

“是前天。”小男孩说，“我和舅舅乘小船出海打鱼，海盗上来抓住了我们。他们沉了我们的渔船，把我们俩带到了这条船上。他们对我的舅舅说，他们想让他像他们那样当海盗，因为无论在什么天气状况下，他都能很熟练地驾船。可是，舅舅说他不想当海盗，因为杀人偷盗绝不是好渔民干的事儿。海盗头本·阿里听了非常生气，他咬牙切齿说，如果舅舅不按他们说的做，就把他扔进海里。他们把我带到了底舱，我听到上面打了起来。第二天，他们再次让我上来时，我舅舅就不见了。我问海盗我舅舅在哪儿，可是他们不告诉我。我非常担心，怕他们已经把他扔进海里给淹死了。”

说着，小男孩又开始哭了起来。

“现在没事了，等一会儿，”医生说，“别哭。咱们先到餐室喝杯茶，商量一下这件事儿。说不定你的舅舅一直平安无事呢。你不知道他是不是被淹死了，对吗？这就好。也许我们能帮你找到他。我们先去喝杯茶，加上草莓果酱，然后我们商量一下看怎么办。”

动物们全都一直万分好奇地站在那儿听。医生领着小男孩进了餐室。他们正喝茶，嘎嘎来到医生的椅子后面，小声说道：“问一下鼠海豚，看男孩的舅舅是不是淹死了——它们一定知道。”

“好吧。”医生又拿起了一片果酱面包说。

“你的舌头发出的那些滑稽的咔嗒声是什么？”小男孩问道。

“噢，我刚才用鸭语说了两个词。”医生回答说，“刚才那位是嘎嘎，是我的一个宠物。”

“我根本不知道鸭子还有语言。”小男孩说，“所有这些动物也都是你的宠物吗？那个怪模怪样、俩脑袋的东西是什么？”

“嘘！”医生低声说道，“那是推我拉你。别让它看到我们在谈论它，它会非常难为情……告诉我，你是怎么被关进那个小屋的？”

“海盗去另外一条船上抢东西，就把我关到了那儿，当时我听到有人劈门，不知道会是谁。我很高兴是你。你认为，你能帮我找到舅舅吗？”

“噢，我们会竭尽全力。”医生说，“你的舅舅长什么样子？”

“他留着一头红发，”小男孩回答说，“红红的头发。他的胳膊上刺有一个铁锚图案。他身强力壮，是一个好舅舅，还是南大西洋上最棒的水手。他的渔船名叫‘俏萨利’，是一只装有索具的独桅纵帆船。”

“什么是‘索具独桅纵帆船’？”珈珈转身，小声问吉普。

“嘘！是那个人驾驶的船的种类。”吉普说，“保持安静，行吗？”

“噢，”小猪说，“这样啊？我还以为那是一种喝的东西呢。”

医生留小男孩在餐室里跟动物们玩耍。他来到甲板上，找寻一些路过这里的鼠海豚。

很快，一大群鼠海豚摇摆着，跳跃着，从水中游了过来，它们正要前往巴西。

见医生靠在扶手上，它们便游了过来，看他过得怎么样。

医生问它们，有没有见过一个满头红发、胳膊上文有一个铁锚的男人。

“你是说‘俏萨利’的主人吧？”鼠海豚们问道。

“是，”医生说，“就是这个人。他已经淹死了吗？”

“他的渔船沉没了，”鼠海豚们说，“我们看到它躺在海底。可是，里面没有人，我们去看过了。”

“他的小外甥跟我在一起，在我们的船上，”医生说，“他非常担心，那些海盗把他的舅舅扔进了海里。你们行行好，帮我查清楚，看这个人是不是的确已经被淹死了？”

“噢，他没有被淹死，”鼠海豚们说，“如果他被淹死了，我们肯定就会从深海十足目动物那儿听说了。海里的一切新闻，我们都无所不知。甲壳类动物叫我们‘海洋闲话篓’。——没有淹死，告诉小男孩，很抱歉我们不知道他舅舅的下落。不过，我们十分肯定，他没有淹死在海里。”

医生跑下底舱，把这个消息告诉了小男孩。小男孩高兴得直拍手。推我拉你背起小男孩，绕着餐室的桌子转起了圈儿。其他动物都跟在后面，用匙子敲打碟面，把这当成了一场庆祝游行。

第十八章　气味

“你的舅舅现在一定能找到，”医生说，“这是迟早的事儿——因为我们知道他没有被扔进海里。”

嘎嘎又过来，对医生低声说道：“请老鹰找找这个人。在活着的生物当中，只有老鹰视力最好，它们能在数英里高的空中数得清地上爬的蚂蚁。请老鹰们找找。”

医生派了一只燕子前去叫一些老鹰过来。

大约一小时后，小燕子带回来六只不同种类的老鹰：一只黑鹰，一只白头鹰，一只鱼鹰，一只金鹰，一只兀鹰，还有一只白尾海鹰。每只都有小男孩的两倍那么高。它们全都并排站在船扶手上面，就像一排弓背弯腰的士兵，冷峻、肃静、沉着，炯炯有神的大黑眼睛飞快地扫来扫去。

珈珈被它们吓得躲到了一只桶后面。它说，它感觉那些可怕的眼睛好像能一下子看进它的内心，看出午饭它偷吃了什么。

医生告诉老鹰们说：“有一个男的失踪了，是一个红头发的渔民，胳膊上有铁锚图案的印记。你们行行好，看能不能帮我们找到他？这个小男孩是这个人的外甥。”

老鹰们话不多。它们都声音粗哑，只回答说：“你可以放心，我们会为约翰·杜立德——竭尽全力。”

说完，它们就飞走了。随后，珈珈从木桶后面钻了出来，望着它们离去。它们向上飞呀飞，越飞越高，越飞越高。后来，医生只能看到，它们分开，朝东西南北不同方向飞走了，看上去就像几颗细小的黑色沙粒慢慢地爬过辽阔的蓝天。

“我的天哪！”珈珈压低嗓音说，“真高啊！我纳闷，它们离太阳那么近，却没有烧焦自己的羽毛！”

它们走了好大一会儿，回来时，差不多已是夜里。

老鹰们告诉医生说：“我们已经搜索了这大半个世界的所有海洋、所有国家、所有岛屿、所有城市和所有乡村，但是我们没能找到。在直布罗陀的主街上，我们看见面包店门口的手推车里有三根红发。可那不是人的头发，而是一件皮大衣上掉下来的毛。无论陆地还是海洋，都没有小男孩舅舅的任何踪影。如果我们都看不见他，他肯定不会被看到了……为了约翰·杜立德——我们已经尽了全力。”

说完，六只大鸟拍打着大翅膀，飞回了山中和岩石间它们各自的家。

“唉，”它们走后，嘎嘎说，“我们现在怎么办？必须找到这男孩的舅舅——没有其他办法。这孩子太小了，还不能独闯天下。男孩子们不像小鸭子，他们必须由人抚养长大……奇奇要是在这儿就好了，它肯定能很快找到那个人。好心的老奇奇！我不知道它现在过得怎么样！”

“要是波利尼西亚跟我们在一起就好了，”小白鼠说，“它很快就能想出办法来。你们还记得它第二次是怎样帮我们出狱的吧？哎呀，它可真聪明啊！”

“我不太看好那些老鹰，”吉普说，“它们就是自以为是。它们的视力也许很好。可是，你请它们去替你找个人，它们没有找到——居然还有脸回来说别人也找不到。它们太自以为是了，就像泥塘镇那只牧羊犬一样。我也不看好那些饶舌的鼠海豚，它们只能告诉我们，那个人不在海里。我们不想知道他不在哪儿——我们想知道的是他在哪儿。”

“噢，别说那么多了，”珈珈说，“说起来容易，满世界找一个人可不那么容易。说不定这个渔民因为担心小男孩，头发已经愁白了，所以老鹰们才没有发现他。你什么都不懂，就知道说。也没见你协助干点儿什么。老鹰们找不到小男孩的舅舅，你也一样找不到，不可能找得到。”

“我不可能找得到？”小狗说，“你就知道这些，你这块愚蠢的热熏肉！我不是还没试过吗？你等着瞧！”

说完，吉普就去找医生说：“请问一下小男孩，看他的口袋里有没有他舅舅的东西，好吗？”

于是医生就去询问小男孩。小男孩拿出来一枚金戒指。因为戒指太大了，他的手指戴不了，他就用一根细绳拴着挂在脖子上。他说，这是眼看海盗追上来时，舅舅给他的。

吉普闻了闻戒指，说：“这毫无用处。问一下他还有没有他舅舅的其他东西。”

这时，小男孩从口袋里掏出了一块漂亮的大红手帕说：“这也是舅舅的。”

小男孩一掏出手帕，吉普就大叫起来：“鼻烟，没错！黑拉皮烟。难道你们没有闻到？他舅舅吸过鼻烟——问问他，医生。”

医生就又问小男孩。小男孩说：“对。我的舅舅吸过好多鼻烟。”“好！”吉普说，“这个人差不多找到了，就像从小猫那儿偷牛奶一样容易。告诉小男孩，不出一个星期，我就能帮他找到舅舅。咱们到上面看看风向吧。”

“可是，天已经黑了，”医生说，“黑灯瞎火的，你找不到他！”

“寻找一个吸黑拉皮烟的人，我不需要任何光线。”吉普一边爬舷梯，一边说道，“如果这个人身上现在的气味一般，比如像绳子或是热水的味道，那就不一样了。可是，鼻烟！啧，啧！”

“热水有气味吗？”医生问道。

“当然有了。”吉普说，“热水闻起来跟冷水完全不一样。如果是温水或冰，那气味的确很难闻到。有一次，我曾在黑夜里尾随一个人走了十英里，就是靠那个人刮胡子用的热水的气味——因为那个可怜的家伙没有香皂……那么，让我们看看风朝哪个方向吹吧。风对远距离闻味至关重要。风力不必太强——当然，风向必须正好。平稳、湿润、宜人的微风最好……哈！风是从北方吹过来的。”

然后，吉普来到船头，迎风闻起了气味，开始喃喃自语：“焦油，西班牙大葱，煤油，湿雨衣，压碎的月桂树叶，燃烧的橡胶，正在洗的花边窗帘——不，我搞错了，是挂在外面晾晒的花边窗帘。还有狐狸，好几百只小狐狸。还有——”

“你真的能在这一种风里闻出所有那些不同的东西吗？”医生问道。

“哎呀，当然能！”吉普说，“那只是几种容易闻到的气味，比较强烈的气味。任何一只杂种狗，即使感冒，也能闻到那些气味。等一下，我要告诉你这风里几种比较难闻出来的气味——几种特别讲究的味道。”

说着，小狗紧紧闭上眼睛，仰起鼻子，半张嘴巴，用劲儿闻了起来。

好一阵子，它都没有说话，像一块石头纹丝不动。它几乎好像不喘气。终于，它开口说话了，听上去简直就像它在梦中伤心地唱着歌儿。

“砖，”它低声说道，声音很低，“老黄砖，在一堵花园的围墙上，因年久而碎裂；从山间小溪里吹来小母牛甜美的气息；正午阳光照射在鸽舍——也许是谷仓——的铅皮顶上；黑色羔皮手套躺在胡桃木做的衣柜抽屉里；一条土路边的悬铃木下面有一个饮水马槽；小蘑菇正从沤烂的树叶里拱出来；还有——还有——还有——”

“有欧洲防风草吗？”珈珈问道。

“没有。”吉普说，“你总是想着吃的。根本没有防风草。而且也没有鼻烟——有好多烟斗和香烟，还有几支雪茄。可是，没有鼻烟。我们必须等风向转南。”

“是，这风向不好。”珈珈说，“我想你是在骗人，吉普。有谁听说过，仅凭嗅觉，就能在茫茫大海中找到一个人啊！我早就说过，你不可能找得到。”

“听着，”吉普说，真的生气了，“你是想让你的鼻子马上被咬上一口吧！你别以为医生不让我们给你应有的惩罚，你就可以这样随心所欲不要脸面！”

“别吵了！”医生说，“住口！生命太短暂了。吉普，告诉我，你觉得，那些气味是从哪儿来的？”

“大多是从德文郡和威尔士来的，”吉普说，“风是从那个方向吹来的。”

“好，好！”医生说，“你知道，这的确非同凡响——非同凡响。我一定要把这记下来，写进我的新书。我不知道你是不是也能把我训练得嗅觉这么好……不过，算了，也许我对我现在的状况更满意。常言说：‘知足常乐。’我们下去吃晚饭吧。我饿极了。”

“我也饿了。”珈珈说。

第十九章　礁石

第二天一早，他们便从丝绸床上爬了起来。他们发现，阳光灿烂，风正从南边吹来。

吉普嗅了半小时南风，然后朝医生走过来，摇了摇头。

“我还是没有闻到鼻烟，”它说，“我们必须等风向转东。”

但是，下午三点钟，东风刮来时，小狗还是闻不到鼻烟的气味。

小男孩失望极了，又开始哭了起来，说好像没有人能帮他找到舅舅了。不过，吉普对医生说的是：“告诉他，等风向转西，只要他的舅舅还吸黑色拉皮鼻烟，即使是远在中国，我也能把他的舅舅给找到。”

他们只好又等了三天，西风才来。星期五一早，天刚刚亮，海面上笼罩着一层薄薄的雨雾，海风轻柔，温暖而湿润。

吉普一醒来，便跑上了甲板，仰起鼻子。随即，它兴奋起来，激动得不得了，飞快地跑下底舱去叫医生。

“医生！”它叫道，“我闻到了！医生！医生！快醒醒！听着！我闻到了！风从西边吹来，只有鼻烟的气味。快上来，开船——快！”

于是，医生慌里慌张，匆匆下床，直奔船舵去开船。

“现在我要上前，”吉普说，“你看着我的鼻子行事，我的鼻子冲哪个方向，你就把船转向哪个方向。气味这么强烈，这个人远不了。风惬意而湿润。现在注意看我！”

所以，整个一上午，吉普站在船头，一边嗅着风，一边指引医生转舵。动物们和小男孩都围着小狗，惊奇地瞪大眼睛，望着它。

大约午饭时分，吉普让嘎嘎告诉医生，说它越来越担心，想对医生说句话。于是，嘎嘎跑去把医生从船的另一头叫了过来。吉普对医生说：“这个男孩的舅舅快饿死了。我们必须尽可能把船开快点儿。”

“你怎么知道他快饿死了呢？”医生问。

“因为风中没有其他的味道，只有鼻烟的气味。”吉普说，“如果这个人在做饭或在吃什么食物，我就肯定也能闻到。他甚至连喝的淡水都没有了。他只有鼻烟可吸，一大捏一大捏地吸。我们越来越接近他，因为鼻烟味越来越浓烈了。不过，你尽可能把船开快点儿，我确信这个人快饿死了。”

“好的。”说着，医生派嘎嘎去请燕子们来拉船，就像上次海盗追赶他们时那样。

于是，顽强的小燕子飞了下来，再一次拽起绳子上路了。

船风驰电掣，破浪前进。海里的鱼只好纷纷跳闪逃命，以免被撞上。

动物们都群情激动，不再看着吉普，而是转身注视起前面的海水，辨认着那个快饿死的人可能待的任何陆地或岛屿。

可是，一个又一个小时过去了，船依然在平坦的海面上继续飞速前进，哪儿也看不到陆地。

此刻，动物们都不再说话，默默地围坐在那儿，焦急难受。小男孩再一次伤心起来。吉普的脸上也有了一丝焦虑。

下午晚些时候，太阳即将落下时，一直卧在桅杆顶上的猫头鹰秃秃突然声嘶力竭大叫起来，把他们都吓了一跳。“吉普！吉普！我看到我们前面有一块很大很大的礁石——瞧——就在海天相连的地方。看到了吧，阳光照在上面，像金子一样！气味就是从那儿来的吧？”

吉普高声回答说：“是的。就是。那个人就在那儿。终于找到了，终于找到了！”

越来越近了，他们可以看到那块礁石非常大，有一大块田地那么大。上面没有长树，也没有长草，什么也没有。这个大礁石像龟背一样平滑光秃。

医生开着船，绕着礁石转了一圈。可是，上面不见一个人。动物们都使劲儿眯着眼睛尽可能地瞅，约翰·杜立德还从舱里拿来了望远镜。

可是，他们连一个活的东西都没有看到——甚至一只海鸥、一只海星、一根海草都没有看到。

他们全都站在那儿，一动不动，使劲儿用耳朵听着声音。可是，他们听到的只有细浪轻轻拍打船帮的声音。

然后，他们都开始喊叫起来：“喂，有人吗？喂！”最后，他们把嗓子都喊哑了。可是，只有礁石的回声。

小男孩突然放声大哭道：“我怕我再也见不到舅舅了！回家可怎么向他们交代呀！”

吉普朝医生喊道：“他肯定在那儿——他肯定——他肯定在！再向前，那气味就没有了。他一定在上面，我告诉你！把船靠近礁石，让我跳上去。”

医生尽可能把船靠近礁石，他放下锚，和吉普一起从船上跳到了礁石上面。

吉普马上鼻子贴着地面，开始四处嗅着。它上上下下，前前后后，弯来绕去，低头转个不停。它走到哪儿，医生就跟到哪儿，寸步不离，直跑得上气不接下气。

终于，吉普大叫一声，卧了下去。医生跑过去，发现小狗正盯着礁石中央一个大深洞看。

“那个男孩的舅舅就在下面。”吉普平静地说道，“难怪那些傻老鹰看不见他！找人还是得让我们狗找。”

医生下到洞里。这好像是一个洞穴或隧道，向地下延伸了很长一段距离。医生划了一根火柴，开始沿着这条黑暗的通道往前走，吉普跟在后面。

火柴不一会儿就灭了，医生只好一根接一根地划燃。

最后，走到了通道尽头，医生发现自己来到了一个四面是石壁的小房间。

只见房间中央躺着一个头发很红的男子，头枕着胳膊，正在酣睡！

吉普走上前，闻了闻那个人身边放着的什么东西。医生弯腰拾了起来。原来是一只很大很大的鼻烟盒，里面装满了黑色拉皮鼻烟！

第二十章　渔民镇

这时，医生轻轻地唤醒那个人。

而就在此刻，火柴又灭了。那个人以为本·阿里又回来了，黑暗中不由分说朝医生抡起了拳头。

但是，当医生告诉他自己是谁，又对他说他的外甥在自己的船上，平安无事，那个人高兴得不得了，并为他刚才动手打医生赔礼道歉。不过，他并没有太伤着医生，因为太黑了，他打得并不准。他给了医生一撮鼻烟。

这个人告诉他们说，因为他不答应当海盗，巴巴里龙就将他扔到这块礁石上不管不问，他常常睡在下面这个洞里，因为礁石上没有供他取暖的房子。

他接着说道：“我已经四天没吃没喝了，一直靠鼻烟活着。”

“就是这样！”吉普说，“我对你说什么来着？”

他们又划燃几根火柴，穿过通道，来到了日光下。医生赶忙把那个人领到船上去喝些汤。

看到医生和吉普带着一个红发男子回到船上，动物们和小男孩又是欢呼又是尖叫，还在船上跳起了舞。上面的燕子也铆足了劲儿吹起了口哨——好几百万只燕子——以此表示它们也很高兴，小男孩的勇敢的舅舅找到了。他们发出的声音如此洪亮，远处海上的水手们还以为一场可怕的暴风雨就要来了呢。“听，大风在东边怒吼！”他们说。

吉普暗自扬扬得意，不过，他尽量不露出骄傲的神情。

嘎嘎走过来，对它说：“吉普，我真不知道，你原来这么聪明！”吉普只是摇了摇头，回答说：“噢，那没什么了不起的。但是，你知道，找人还得需要狗，这种游戏，鸟类根本玩不了。”

这时，医生问红发渔民家住哪儿。渔民如实相告。医生让燕子们在前面领航。

他们来到那个人所说的陆地前，看见石头山脚下有一个不大的渔镇，随后，那个人指出了他居住的房子。

他们正在放锚时，小男孩的妈妈（也就是那个人的姐姐）连哭带笑地从海岸上跑了下来，迎接他们。二十多天来，她一直守在山上，眺望着大海，盼望他们归来。

她一遍又一遍地亲吻着医生，吻得他咯咯直笑，脸红得像个女学生似的。接着，她想去亲吻吉普，但是，吉普拔腿跑开，躲进了船里。

“这样没头没脑地吻个不停，”它说，“我可受不了。如果她一定要亲吻的话，就让她亲吻珈珈去吧。”

渔民和他的姐姐都不想让医生匆匆离开。他们请求他在那儿待上几天。约翰·杜立德和他的动物们只好留下来，在他们家里待了星期六和星期天整整两天，还有星期一的半天。

渔村里所有的小男孩都跑到了海滩上，指着停泊在那儿的那只大船，窃窃私语：“瞧！那原来是海盗船，是本·阿里的，他曾是横行七大洋的最可怕的海盗！那个戴高帽的老先生，就是住在特里威廉太太家的那个人，是他把这船从巴巴里龙手里夺过来的，还让巴巴里龙做了农夫。谁会想到是他，他那么温和，再平凡不过了！瞧那些大红帆！好家伙！这不就是那条样子邪恶、速度又快的船吗？天哪！”

在渔民小镇这两天半的时间里，人们不断请医生去喝茶，吃午饭，吃晚饭，参加聚会；女士们给他送来了一盒又一盒的鲜花和糖果；村乐队每天夜里都会在他的窗下演奏乐曲。

最后，医生说道：“好人们，我现在必须回家了。你们真是太好了，我会永远记住的。可是，我必须回家，因为我还有事儿要做。”

于是，就在医生要准备离开时，镇长沿街走来，一同随行的还有好多身穿盛装的人。镇长在医生住的房前停住脚步，全村人都围拢过来，要看个究竟。

六名小听差对着闪亮的喇叭一吹，人们不再说话了，医生走出房门，来到台阶上。镇长讲起了话。

“约翰·杜立德医生，”他说，“我非常荣幸代表我们可敬的镇民，将这件小小的纪念品献给把巴巴里龙清除出海洋的人，以表谢意。”

说完，镇长从口袋里掏出一个小薄纸包，打开来，把一只非常漂亮、背面镶有真钻石的手表递给了医生。

接着，镇长又从口袋里掏出来一个大一点儿的纸包，说道：“那只狗在哪儿？”

大家赶忙去找吉普。最后，嘎嘎在村子另一头的马场里找到了它。当时村里所有的狗都正围绕它默默地站着，既羡慕又尊敬。

吉普被带到了医生身边，镇长打开那个大纸包，里面是一个纯金做的脖套！镇长弯下腰亲手把项圈戴在了狗的脖子上。这时，村民中响起了好一阵惊叹的低语声。

项圈上写着这样几个大字：“吉普——世界上最聪明的狗。”

之后，整个人群都来到了海边，为他们送行。等到红发渔民、他的姐姐和那个小男孩一次又一次地感谢过医生和他的狗后，这艘挂着红帆的大快船再一次转向泥塘镇方向，驶进了大海，这时村里的乐队在岸上奏起了音乐。

第二十一章　回到家乡

三月的风来了又去，四月的阵雨也已经下过，五月的花蕾早已绽放鲜花，六月的阳光照在喜人的田野上，此时约翰·杜立德终于回到了自己的国家。

可是，他还没有回到泥塘镇的家里。他先用吉卜赛大篷车载着推我拉你全国周游，见着乡村集市就停，一边表演杂技，一边演《庞奇和朱迪》傀儡戏，他们常常挂出一块大招牌，上面写着：“快来看来自非洲丛林的绝妙双头兽。门票六便士。”

推我拉你总是待在大篷车里，其他动物则躺在车下面。医生坐在车前的椅子上，一边收门票，一边向进场的人们报以微笑。嘎嘎总是不忘数落它，说医生总是趁它不留神，免费放孩子们进去。

动物园主和杂技团的人纷纷找到医生，请求他把这只奇异动物卖给他们，说他们会付给他一大笔钱。不过，医生总是摇摇头说：“不行。要把推我拉你关在笼子里，绝对不行。它一向有活动的自由，像你我一样。”

周游期间，他们见了好多奇景怪事。可是，因为刚从国外开过眼界闯荡回来，这些似乎也都变得稀松平常了。一开始参演马戏团那会儿，还非常有趣，可是，几个星期后，他们都厌倦透了，医生和它们全都渴望回家。

但是，好多人都聚集到小篷车跟前来，掏六便士进去看推我拉你，医生马上就不用再做演出经理人了。

在一个天气晴朗、蜀葵花盛开的日子，医生腰缠万贯地回到了泥塘镇。他又住进了带有大花园的那个小房子里。

马厩里那匹老瘸马见到他，非常高兴；那些总在他的屋檐下垒窝孵小鸟的燕子也非常高兴。回到了熟悉的家，嘎嘎很高兴，尽管有大量清扫工作要做，因为到处都是蜘蛛网。

吉普先跑到隔壁，向那只骄傲的牧羊犬炫耀一番它的金项圈。回来后，它便在花园里像疯了一样跑来跑去，又是寻找很久以前自己埋的骨头，又是把老鼠赶出工具房。与此同时，珈珈正忙着在挖花园墙角已经长出三英尺高的山葵。

医生前去看望借给自己船的那位水手，他给他买了两条新船，还给他的小孩子买了一个橡皮娃娃。他也还清了去非洲旅行时欠杂货店主的食品钱。他又买了一架钢琴，把小白鼠放了回去——因为小白鼠们说衣柜抽屉有冷风。

甚至医生装满衣柜上面那只老储钱箱后，还剩有好多钱。他不得不又弄来三个同样大的储钱箱，把剩下的钱放了进去。

“钱，”他说，“可真麻烦。可是，不必为钱发愁也不错。”

“是呀，”嘎嘎说，它正在为医生烘烤当茶点的松饼呢，“的确如此！”

冬天又来了，厨房窗外雪花飞舞。医生和他的动物们吃过晚饭，总是围坐在温暖的大火炉边。他常常给它们朗读他写的那些书。

而在遥远的非洲，猴子们睡觉前，总是习惯在大大的黄月亮下面的棕榈树上闲聊。它们总是说：“我不知道那个好人此刻在那个遥远的白人国做什么！你认为他还会回来吗？”

这时，波利尼西亚常常会从藤蔓植物里尖声回答道：“我认为他一定会——我猜他一定会——我希望他一定会！”

随后，那条鳄鱼也常常会从河里的污泥中抬起头来，冲它们咕哝道：“我相信他一定会——睡觉吧！”

第一章　最初的家

我能清晰记起的第一个地方是一片宜人的大牧场，其中有一个清澈见底的池塘。绿树成荫，倾身向池，灯心草和睡莲扎根泽中。越过树篱一边，我们可以看到一块耕地，而另一边能望见主人家的大门，主人家就在路边上。牧场的高处有一小片杉树林，低处有一条潺潺流动的小溪，陡峭的河岸悬于小溪之上。

年幼时，我不会吃草，就靠妈妈哺乳。白天我在她身边撒欢，晚上紧偎着她躺着。天热时，我们常常站在池边的树荫下；天冷时，我们就待在树林附近一个温暖舒适的马棚里。

当我长到可以吃草时，妈妈便开始了早出晚归的劳作。

除我以外，牧场上还有六匹马驹。他们都比我年龄大，有些都快有成年马那样高了。我常常跟他们一起奔跑，真好玩儿。我们也经常一起绕着牧场一圈一圈地尽力飞奔。有时我们玩得相当粗野，因为他们疾驰时经常连踢带咬。

一天，我们踢得正欢时，妈妈轻声把我叫到跟前，说道：

“我希望你用心听我要对你说的话。住在这儿的都是很好的马驹，但他们是要去拉货车的马驹，当然他们没有学会礼仪。而你有教养，出身名门。你的爸爸在这一带赫赫有名，你的爷爷在纽马克特赛马比赛中连续两年夺冠，你的奶奶拥有我认识的马匹中最驯良的性格，我想你也从来没有见过我踢咬。我希望你温和善良，永不学坏；用心工作，小跑时蹄子轻抬轻落，即使是在游戏中，也绝不要踢咬。”

我从来没有忘记过妈妈的忠告。我知道她是一匹明理的老马，我家主人非常看重她。妈妈名叫公爵夫人，但是主人常常叫她宝贝儿。

我们的主人是一个善良和蔼的人，他给我们好吃的，给我们提供好的住所，说话也好声好气的，他对我们说话就像跟自家小孩儿说话那样温柔。我们都喜欢他，我的妈妈非常爱他。妈妈在大门边一看到他，就会欢叫，一路小跑到他的身边。主人会轻拍轻抚着她说：“噢，老宝贝儿，你家的小黑怎么样？”因为我毛色黯黑，所以他叫我小黑。随后，他就会给我一片好吃的面包，有时也会给妈妈带一根胡萝卜。所有的马儿都会到他的身边来，但我认为我和妈妈才是他的最爱。赶集那天，妈妈总是独自拉着轻便马车送主人到镇上去。

有一个耕童，名叫迪克，他有时会翻过树篱到我们的田地里摘黑莓。吃饱后，他还要向马驹们扔石子和树枝，让他们飞奔，说是拿马驹们逗乐。我们对他不大介意，因为我们可以跑开，但有时石子会击中并砸伤我们。

一天，他又玩起了这种把戏，不知道主人就在旁边的牧场上；主人就在那儿，瞧了个正着。他立马翻过栅栏，抓住迪克的胳膊，扇了他一耳光，迪克疼得嗷嗷惊叫起来。我们一看见主人，就小跑着靠近些，好看个究竟。

“坏小子！”他说，“坏小子！竟敢撵我的马。这不是第一次，也不是第二次，而是最后一次！给——拿上你的钱滚回家去，我的农场不再需要你了。”于是，我们再也没有见过迪克。负责照料我们的马夫老丹尼尔像我们的主人一样和善，所以我们过得不错。

第二章　一次捕猎

我两岁前，发生了一件我永远难忘的事儿。那是早春时节，夜里下了一点儿霜，树林和牧场上仍然薄雾笼罩。我和其他几匹马驹正在牧场的低洼处吃草，突然从很远的地方传来了狗叫似的声音。那匹最年长的马驹抬起头来，竖起耳朵，一边说：“有猎犬！”一边立刻小跑了起来；我们其他马驹跟着他跑到了牧场的高地，从那儿可以眺望树篱，望见那边的好几块田地。我的妈妈和主人的一匹老坐骑也站在附近，好像他们对这一切都了如指掌。

“他们发现了一只野兔。”妈妈说，“如果他们从这个方向过来，我们就会看到这次捕猎。”

不久，猎狗们全都俯冲进了我们旁边的那块麦苗地。他们发出的那种声音我从来没有听过。他们不吠，不吼，也不哀嚎，而是用最大的嗓门不断地发出“哟！哟嗷嗷！哟！哟嗷嗷！”的声音。一些人骑马尾随他们而来，有的穿着绿大衣，都全速奔跑着。那匹老马喷着鼻息热切地望着那些人的背影，而我们这些小马驹都渴望跟他们一起飞奔而去，但是很快他们就跑进了田地的低洼处，这时他们好像停住了。猎狗也不叫了，一个个鼻子贴地，四散跑开。

“他们闻不到气味了，”那匹老马说，“说不定那只野兔会脱身。”

“什么野兔？”我问。

“噢！我不知道是什么野兔，很可能是从我们的林地里跑出来的本地野兔。任何野兔只要被那些人和狗发现，都肯定会被追赶。”不久，那些狗又开始“哟！哟嗷嗷！”地叫起来，他们都全速折回，径直奔向我们牧场那个陡峭河岸与树篱夹抱的小溪。

“现在我们要看见那只野兔了。”妈妈说。就在这时，一只惊慌失措的野兔飞蹿而过，逃向树林。猎狗们紧随其后，冲过溪岸，跃过小溪，气势汹汹地穿过田间，猎人们紧追不舍。七八个人纵马跃过小溪，紧跟着那些猎狗。那只野兔试图穿过树篱，但是树篱太密了。于是，她急转弯想夺路而逃，却为时已晚。猎狗狂叫着扑向她。我们只听到一声尖叫，她就一命呜呼了。一位猎人策马上前，扬鞭赶走猎犬，不然猎犬们不一会儿就能把兔子撕成碎片。他拎着那只被撕裂后血流不止的兔腿，把兔子举起来，所有的先生们似乎都心满意足。

对我来说，这突如其来的一幕惊心动魄，我最初都没有注意到小溪边发生的一切；而当我真的转头望去时，那儿却已是一幅惨景。两匹上等好马摔倒，一匹在溪流中挣扎，另一匹在草地上痛苦呻吟。一个骑手正从水里爬起来，浑身是泥；另一个骑手躺在那儿，一动不动。

“他的脖子断了。”妈妈说。

“他也是罪有应得。”其中一匹马驹说。

我也这样想，但是妈妈不同意我们的看法。

“噢，不。”她说，“你们不能那样说。不过，尽管我是一匹老马，见多识广，但是我至今都不理解为什么人们如此喜欢这个活动。他们不但常常伤到自己，还常常毁掉好多好马，糟蹋田地，而这一切仅仅是为了捕获一只兔子、一只狐狸或一头雄鹿，这些本可以用别的方法更轻易地得到。而我们只是马儿，不明白。”

妈妈这样说时，我们站在那儿观看。好多骑手都已经走到了那个年轻人的身边，目睹这一切的我们的主人第一个把他抱了起来。他的头耷拉着，胳膊下垂，大家看上去都很严肃。此刻没有嘈杂声，就连猎犬们也安静了下来，好像知道出事了。人们把他抬进我们主人的家。随后，我听说他是小乔治·戈登，是当地乡绅的独子，是一个高大英俊的小伙子，也是他们家的骄傲。

于是，就有人骑马分头行动，有的去请医生，有的去请马医，肯定还有人去戈登先生家，把他儿子出事的消息告诉他。马医邦德先生来看那匹躺在草地上痛苦呻吟的黑马，把他浑身上下摸了个遍，摇了摇头。马的一条腿断了。随后，有人跑到主人家拿回来一杆枪。不一会儿就传来了一声刺耳的枪响和一声可怕的尖叫，之后万籁俱寂。那匹黑马不再动弹了。

妈妈好像神色不安，她说她认识那匹马好多年了，他的名字叫罗布·罗伊。他是一匹良马，身上没有任何恶习。之后，妈妈再也不愿去那片土地了。

没过多少天，我们听到教堂的钟声长鸣。越过大门，我们看到一辆奇怪的黑色四轮大马车，覆盖着黑布，由几匹黑马拉着，后面跟着一辆一辆又一辆的马车，全是黑色的，钟声不停地鸣响着。人们将小戈登送往墓地安葬。他再也不能骑马了。他们是怎么安置罗布·罗伊的，我无从知道，但是这一切仅仅是为了捕获一只小野兔。

第三章　开始受驯

我现在开始渐渐英俊起来了，皮毛优质柔软，乌黑亮泽。我有一只白蹄，前额上还有一颗漂亮的白星。我被公认为骏马。我四岁前，主人不会卖掉我。他说小男孩不用像成年男子那样干活，小马驹长大前也不必像成年马那样干活。

我四岁那年，戈登先生来看我。他仔细查看了我的眼睛、嘴和腿。他从上到下把我摸了一遍。然后，我得在他面前行走、慢跑和飞奔。他似乎很喜欢我，他说：“这匹马好好训练，一定会很棒。”我的主人说他会亲自训练我，因为他不希望我受到惊吓或伤害。他一刻也没有耽误，因为第二天他就开始训练我了。

大家可能不知道什么是训练，所以我要描述一下。训练就是要教一匹马学会戴马鞍，戴笼头，驮男人、女人或小孩；要按照人们的意愿行走，而且要安分行走。除此以外，马儿还得学会戴马轭、牵鞍兜带和臀带，还要在上这些装备时保持不动，然后再在他们身后套一辆大车或轻便马车，这样无论是行走还是慢跑他们都会拉动后面的马车。还有，马儿必须学会按照车夫的意愿或快或慢，绝不能被看见的什么东西惊动，也不能跟其他马儿说话，不能咬，不能踢，也不能有自己的任何意愿，而是要始终按照主人的意愿做事，哪怕他又累又饿。而最糟糕的是，一旦上了马具，他们既不能在高兴时跳跃，也不能在疲倦时躺下。所以，你明白，训练是一件大事。

当然，我过了很久才习惯戴笼头和缰绳，习惯被人牵着在田野或小路上安分地遛弯儿，但是现在我得咬着马嚼子和缰绳。我的主人像往常一样给我一些燕麦，哄了我好一阵子之后，把嚼子放进我的嘴里，套牢缰绳，但这是件让人讨厌的事儿！如果从来没有咬过嚼子，就无法想象那是多么糟糕的感觉。一大块又冷又硬的铁条，像人的手指那样粗，塞进你的嘴里，放在牙齿间，压在舌头上，两头从嘴角出来，由你的头顶上、喉咙边、鼻子旁、下巴上的皮带紧紧扎住，这样你就无法摆脱这个讨厌的硬东西了。这糟糕极了！是的，糟糕极了！至少我这样认为，但是我知道我的妈妈外出时都戴着，所有的成年马也都戴着。所以，考虑到好吃的燕麦，考虑到主人对我的轻轻拍抚、和声细语和优雅举止，我戴上了嚼子和缰绳。

接下来是马鞍，但是这还没有之前那些事儿的一半糟糕。老丹尼尔托住我的头，我的主人非常温柔地把马鞍放在我的背上。随后，主人系紧我身下的肚带，一直轻轻地拍着我，跟我说话，接着喂我吃了一些麦片，牵着我遛了一小会儿。他每天都这样做，直到我主动要求吃燕麦、套马鞍。一天早晨，主人终于骑到了我的背上，在牧场柔软的绿草上遛了一圈。当然，那感觉的确挺怪，但是我必须得说，能驮着主人，我感到相当自豪。他坚持每天都骑我一会儿，这样我很快就习惯了。

下一件讨厌的事儿就是钉马掌。这一开始也很难。主人亲自带我去铁匠铺，以确保我毫发无损，不受任何惊吓。铁匠把我的脚一个接一个地放在他的手里，削掉了蹄子上的一些部分。这没有弄疼我，所以我一动不动地三腿站定，直到他全部削完。随后，他拿出一块跟我的蹄形一样的蹄铁，用力扣上去，并用钉子钉过蹄铁，深深地嵌入我的蹄子里，这样铁掌就钉牢了。我的脚感到硬邦邦、沉甸甸的，但是很快我就习惯了。

现在进展很迅速，主人要进一步训练我戴马具，还有更多的新东西要戴。首先，我的脖子上要戴一个又硬又沉的马轭，缰绳上贴着我眼睛的两侧要有两大片遮光板，叫作眼罩。眼罩真是名副其实，因为戴上去，我就不能往两边看了，只能往前看。接下来，要放上一个小马鞍，上面带着一条绕过我尾巴的讨厌的硬皮带，这就是臀带。我不喜欢那条臀带，把我的长尾巴撩起来把皮带从下面穿过，简直跟咬马嚼子一样难受。我从来没有感到这样想踢人，当然不能踢这么好的一个主人，所以最终如此这般我就习惯了，可以像妈妈那样干活了。

我绝不能忘了提及我的一次训练经历，因为我一向认为这次训练让我受益匪浅。主人把我送到邻近的一个农场主那儿待了两周。那个农场主有一个一侧挨着铁路的牧场。那儿有一些绵羊和奶牛，我跟他们圈养在一起。

我永远也忘不了第一次看见火车开过时的情景。我正在牧场和铁路之间的隔离栏附近静静地吃草，这时听到远处传来一声怪响。我还没有弄清它来自何方，一列长长的黑色火车就呼哧呼哧地喷着烟飞驰而过；几乎还没等我喘过气来，它就消失不见了。我转过身，以最快的速度飞奔到牧场远处，我站在那儿，又惊又怕地喷着鼻息。那天还有好多其他火车经过，有些开得比较慢。这些火车都在附近的车站停下来，有时停车前还发出一阵可怕的尖鸣声和吱嘎声。我觉得这可怕极了，但是那些奶牛却继续非常安静地吃草，那个可怕的黑东西喷着汽轰隆隆地驶过时，他们几乎头都不抬一下。

头几天，我都不能安心地吃草。但是，后来我发现那个可怕的怪物从来不会开进田地里，也不会伤害我，我就不再理会它了。很快，我也像那些牛羊一样，对那呼啸而过的火车不大在意了。

从那以后，我见过好多马因看到蒸汽机或听到它的声响而惊慌不安，多亏好主人对我的照顾，到了火车站我也会像在自己的马厩里那样无所畏惧。

如果有人想调教好一匹马驹，就该遵循这样的方法。

主人经常将我和妈妈套在一起，因为妈妈稳重，可以教会我怎样比一匹生马走得更好。她告诉我说，我表现得越好，就越能得到善待，最明智的做法一向就是尽可能取悦主人。“但是，”她说，“人有多种多样，有的人像我们的主人那样善良体贴，为这种人效力，任何一匹马都会感到自豪；而有的人邪恶残忍，绝不应该有一匹马或一只狗为他效力。除此以外，还有好多愚蠢的人，他们自负、无知、粗心，从来不费心思考，这些人因为缺乏理性而比其他人更糟蹋马儿。尽管他们不是故意的，但是他们会那样做。我希望你会落到好人的手里，但是一匹马永远不知道谁会买他，谁会驾驭他。对我们来说，这一切都是运气。不过，我还是要说，无论在哪儿，你都要竭尽全力，保护好自己的名声。”

第四章　伯特维克庄园

这时，我常常站在马厩里，每天我的皮毛都要被刷到像秃鼻乌鸦的翅膀一样闪亮。五月初，从戈登先生家来了一个人，他把我带到门厅。主人说：“再见，小黑子，做个好马，要竭尽全力！”我无法说“再见”，就把鼻子放在他的手里，他和蔼地轻轻拍了拍我。我离开了第一个家。我跟戈登先生生活了几年，我不妨讲讲那儿的事儿。

戈登先生的庄园在伯特维克村边。进去时要经过一扇大铁门，门边是第一个门房，然后沿着一条两侧长满参天古树的平坦马路一路小跑，就到了另一个门房和另一扇大门。穿过这道门，就到了房子和花园。外面是他的家庭牧场、老果园和马厩。那儿足够安顿好多匹马，停放好多辆马车，而我只需要描述一下我被带进去的那个马厩。那儿非常宽敞，带有四个漂亮的畜栏，一扇向院子敞开的转轴大窗使整个地方既舒适又通风。

第一个畜栏很大，呈正方形，后面关着一扇木门。其他的都是普通畜栏，也都很好，但是没有第一个那么大。第一个畜栏里有一个放干草的底架和一个放谷物的低槽。这种畜栏被称为自由畜栏，因为被安置在里面的马不用拴，他想做什么就做什么。能拥有一个自由畜栏，真是太棒了。

马夫正是要把我安置在这个好畜栏里。这儿干净、可爱又通风。我从来没有住过比这更好的畜栏，四周的围栏不是很高，透过顶端的铁栏杆，我能看到外面发生的一切。

马夫给了我一些非常好吃的燕麦，轻轻地拍了拍我，温和地和我说完话就走了。

吃完燕麦后，我环顾四周，只见我旁边的马厩里站着一匹灰色的小肥马，长着浓密的鬃毛和毛发浓密的尾巴、非常漂亮的脑袋和灵巧别致的小鼻子。

我昂头探过畜栏顶部的铁围栏，问候道：“你好！你叫什么名字？”

他尽可能拉紧缰绳转过身，抬起头来，说道：“我叫快乐腿。我非常漂亮。我驮着那些年轻的小姐，有时还会拉着轻便车带我们的女主人出去。她们非常器重我，詹姆斯也一样。你要住在我隔壁这个畜栏吗？”

我说：“是的。”

“那好。”他说，“我希望你好有个脾气；我不喜欢任何咬人的邻居。”

正在这时，一个马头从那边的畜栏里朝我们这边张望，只见她耳朵向后耷拉着，眼神看上去有些暴躁。这是一匹高大的栗色母马，脖子颀长而美丽。她把目光移向我，说道：

“这么说，是你把我赶出了我的畜栏。来了一匹你这样的小马崽，竟然要把一位女士赶出自己的家，这真是件怪事啊。”

“对不起。”我说，“我没有赶走任何一个人，是那个带我来的人把我安置在这儿的，我跟这件事毫无关系。还有，什么小马崽，我都四岁了，已经长大了。我从来没有跟任何公马或母马争吵过，我希望能平静地生活。”

“好吧。”她说，“我们走着瞧。当然，我也不想跟你这个小东西争吵。”我没有再说什么。

下午，那匹母马出去时，快乐腿把事情的原委都告诉了我。

“事情是这样。”快乐腿说，“姜姐有咬人的坏习惯，所以人们都叫她姜姐。她住在自由畜栏时常常咬人。有一天，她咬了詹姆斯的胳膊，都咬出血了，所以尽管弗罗拉小姐和杰西小姐非常喜欢我，但是她们都怕走进这个马厩。她们常常送给我好吃的东西，像一个苹果、一根胡萝卜或一片面包什么的，但是自从姜姐站在那个畜栏之后，她们就不敢来了。我非常想念她们。如果你不咬人的话，我觉得她们以后还会再来。”

我告诉他说，除了青草、干草和谷粒之外，我从来不咬任何东西，也想不出姜姐能从咬人中找到什么乐趣。

“啊，我认为她的确什么乐趣也找不到。”快乐腿说，“这只是一个坏习惯。她说没有一个人对她好过，所以她为什么不该咬人呢？当然，这是一个很坏的习惯；但是，我确信，如果她说的一切都是真的，她来这儿之前一定受到过严重的虐待。约翰竭尽全力想让她高兴，詹姆斯也竭尽所能，如果马规矩，我们主人就绝不会用鞭子。所以，我认为，她在这儿脾气会变好的。你看，”他带着一副睿智的样子说，“我十二岁了，我知道好多事儿，所以我可以告诉你，对一匹马来说，四里八乡没有比这更好的地方了。约翰是这儿最好的马夫，他在这儿已经有十四年了。你也从来没有见过詹姆斯这样的好孩子，所以，姜姐没能留在那个畜栏里，都是她自己的过错。”

第五章　良好开端

马夫名叫约翰·曼利，他有妻子和一个小孩子，他们住在马厩旁边的小屋里。

第二天早上，他把我带到院子里，给我好好刷洗了一番。正当我带着一身又软又光的皮毛走进自己的畜栏时，戈登先生过来看我，好像非常高兴。“约翰，”他说，“我本来想今天早上试试这匹新马，但是我还有别的事儿。早饭后，你最好带他四处转转，沿着公地和乔木林走，然后顺着水磨坊和小河返回，这样就可以看出他的步速了。”

“我会的，主人。”约翰说。早饭后，他就来了，给我戴上了笼头。为了让我的脑袋舒适，他绑皮带时无论是抽出来还是塞进去，都小心翼翼的。随后，他拿过来马鞍，但是马鞍不够宽，放不到我的背上。他立即就发现了这个问题，又去拿了一个，这个尺寸正好。他骑上我，先是慢慢踱步，然后小跑，接着慢跑。当我们跑进公地时，他用鞭子轻轻地碰了我一下，我们就一路飞奔了起来。

“嗬，嗬！好样的。”他让我停住说，“我想你会喜欢跟着那些猎犬狩猎的。”

穿过庄园往回走时，我们碰见戈登先生和夫人正在散步。他们停下脚步，约翰也跳下了马。

“喂，约翰，他怎么样？”

“好极了，先生。”约翰答道，“他跑得像鹿一样快，精神也不错。只要稍微碰一下缰绳，就可以指挥他。在下面那块公地的尽头，我们遇到了一辆旅行大车，大车上面挂满了篮子、小地毯之类的东西。先生，你知道，好多马儿都无法平静地经过那些大车。他只好好地看了一眼，然后便尽可能从容愉快地继续往前走了。他们正在乔木林附近射猎兔子，附近响了一枪。他小停了一会儿，看了看，但是没有向左右偏移一步。我只是牢牢地抓着缰绳，没有催他，我认为他小时候没有受过惊吓或虐待。”

“那就好。”先生说，“明天我要亲自试试他。”

第二天，我被带到了主人面前。我记得妈妈和好心的老主人的忠告，他要我做什么，我就努力做什么。我发现他是一个很好的骑手，对他的马儿也很体贴。他回家时，夫人在门厅口等着，他骑上前去。

“啊，亲爱的，”她说，“你觉得这匹马怎么样？”

“他完全像约翰说的那样。”他答道，“我从来没有想到会有这么舒适的坐骑。我们叫他什么呢？”

“你喜欢乌木吗？”她说，“他像乌木一样黑。”

“不，不要叫乌木。”

“像你叔叔的那匹老马一样，你叫他黑鸟好吗？”

“不，他比原来那匹老黑鸟英俊多了。”

“是的，”她说，“他的确非常英俊，有一张如此甜美、和蔼的脸庞，还有一双如此漂亮、聪颖的眼睛——叫黑骏马，你说怎么样？”

“黑骏马——啊，不错，我认为这是一个很好的名字。如果你喜欢，这就是他的名字了。”于是，我就有了自己的名字。

约翰走进马厩时，告诉詹姆斯说，主人和夫人已经为我选了一个贴切的好名字，它有意义，不像马伦戈、佩加索斯或阿卜杜拉。他们俩都笑出了声，詹姆斯说：“要不是怕回忆起过去，我就应该给他取名叫罗布·罗伊，因为我从来没有见过两匹马长得这么像。”

“这也难怪。”约翰说，“难道你不知道他们俩都是格雷农场主家老伯爵夫人的孩子吗？”

这我以前从来没有听说过，原来那次狩猎时丧命的可怜的罗布·罗伊是我哥哥。难怪我妈妈那样心神不安。看来马儿没有任何亲属，至少被卖之后，他们就不相识了。

约翰似乎很为我骄傲。他经常把我的鬃毛和尾巴梳得几乎像女士们的头发一样光滑，还会对我说好多话。当然，我听不懂他说的所有的话，但是我越来越了解他的意图，以及他想要我做什么。渐渐地，我也十分喜欢他。他非常温柔善良，好像能了解马儿的感受。他为我梳洗时，知道我哪些地方疼痛、哪些地方怕痒。刷头时，他会小心翼翼地避开我的眼睛，就像那是他自己的眼睛一样。他从来不会惹我发火。

马童詹姆斯·霍华德也用自己的方式尽可能温和愉快地对我，所以我认为自己非常幸运。院子里还有一个帮忙的人，但是他不怎么负责我和姜姐的事儿。

几天之后，我得跟姜姐一起拉着马车出去。我不知道我们该怎么融洽相处。但是，除了我靠近时她后翻耳朵之外，她表现很好。她干活诚实，不遗余力地分担重量，真是一个拉双驾马车的最佳搭档。我们来到小山时，她没有放慢脚步，反而从马轭发力，担起重任，直接向前拉了起来。我们干活时都有同样的勇气，所以约翰往回拉我们的时候，常常比催我们前进的时候还要多。他从来不需要往我俩身上用鞭子。因此，我们的步伐非常一致，我发现在小跑时很容易跟上她的脚步，这使我们十分愉快。主人始终喜欢我们步调一致，约翰也一样。我们一起外出了两三次之后，就变得完全友好随和了，这让我觉得无拘无束。

至于快乐腿，他和我很快变成了好朋友。他是一个如此快乐、勇敢、心平气和的小伙子，人人都喜欢他，尤其是杰西和弗罗拉小姐，她们俩经常骑着他在果园里转悠，跟他和她们那只小狗欢欢玩得不亦乐乎。

我们的主人还有另外两匹马住在另一个马厩里。一匹叫正义，是杂色短腿马，主要用来骑或拉货车；另一匹是褐色老猎马，名叫奥利弗爵士。老猎马现在不再干活了，但是主人格外喜欢他，经常骑着他在庄园跑。他有时会在庄园里拉小型轻便车，或者带着一位年轻的小姐和她的父亲一起外出，因为他非常温顺，所以像快乐腿一样能得到孩子的信任。短腿马强壮、匀称、温顺，有时我们会在小牧场里聊一小会儿。但是，我当然不可能跟他亲密得像跟站在同一个马厩里的姜姐一样。

第六章　自由

我在新家快乐极了。如果说我还缺少一样东西的话，你们千万不要以为我不知足。所有跟我打交道的人都很好，我拥有明亮通风的马厩和最好的饲料。我还能要什么呢？啊，自由！在生命的前三年半，我尽享自由。但是，现在，一周周，一月月，毫无疑问——一年年，除了他们需要我的时候，我都必须夜以继日地站在马厩里，而且必须像那些干了二十年活的老马一样从容、节制。身上到处勒着皮带，嘴上戴着嚼子，眼上蒙着眼罩。我不是在抱怨，因为我知道必须这样。我只是想说，作为一匹充满活力的小马，我以前习惯了在那种大草地或平原上昂首甩尾，全速飞奔，然后再跑回来对着同伴喷鼻息——我是说，要这样永不再有任何随心所欲的自由地生活很难。有时，活动量少于平时的话，我就会感觉浑身有使不完的劲儿，所以约翰带我出去活动时，我实在无法保持安静。我仿佛必须得跳跃、舞动、奔腾，做我愿做的事儿。我知道我一定把约翰晃得够呛，尤其是刚开始。不过，他始终善良而又有耐心。

“稳住，稳住，我的孩子。”他常常说，“等一会儿，我们一定会好好跑动，你的蹄子很快就不会痒痒了。”于是，我们一出村子，他就会让我飞跑几英里，随后我会像以前一样精神抖擞，只是没有了他所说的烦躁。精力充沛的马儿，如果运动量不够，只是去玩，常被人称为轻浮。有些马夫会惩罚他们，但是我们的约翰并不这样。他知道这只是精力旺盛。不过，他有自己的一套方法，他通过说话的声调和缰绳的触摸，让我明白指令。如果他郑重其事，毅然决然，我总能从他的声音中听明白，那声音对我来说比其他任何东西都更有力量，因为我非常喜欢他。

我应该说，我们有时会有几个小时的自由，通常是在夏季天气晴好的礼拜天。因为离教堂不远，所以那天马车从来不出行。

我们被带进家庭牧场或老果园，是一大快事。我们的脚踩在凉爽、柔软的青草上，空气如此芬芳，想做什么就做什么，自由自在，真开心——飞奔、躺下、仰面翻滚或是轻轻细咬甜美的草儿。随后，我们一起站在那棵大栗树的树荫下，聊得好不开心。

第七章　姜姐

一天，我和姜姐站在树荫下，聊了好一阵子。她想知道我成长和受驯的所有情况，我就告诉了她。

“唉，”她说，“如果我的成长经历像你一样，我就会有像你一样好的脾气，但是，现在我相信我永远也不会有了。”

“为什么不会有呢？”我问。

“因为我的经历完全不一样。”她回答说，“从来没有一匹马或一个人善待过我，我也不想讨好谁，因为我一断奶，第一件事就是离开妈妈，跟其他好多小马放在一起。他们都不喜欢我，我也不喜欢他们中的任何一个。没有像你的主人那样和善的人照顾我，跟我说话，给我带好吃的东西。那个照管我们的人从来没有给过我一句好话。我不是说他虐待我，但是，除了确保我们食料充足、冬天有避寒之处外，他对我们再没有一丁点儿的关怀。一条人行道穿过我们的牧场，那些过路的男孩子经常会扔石头追赶我们。尽管我从来没有被击中过，但是有一匹小骏马的脸被严重划伤了，我想那一辈子都会有一道伤疤。我们不喜欢那些男孩子，而这自然让我们更加狂野，而且在我们的心里扎下了这样的观念：男孩子们是我们的敌人。我们也有过非常开心的日子，在自由自在的牧场上时而爬坡，时而俯冲，你追我赶绕着牧场一圈圈地奔跑，然后静静地站在树荫下面。但是，谈到受驯，那对我来说，真是一段难熬的日子。好几个人来抓我，最后他们把我堵到了田地的一个角落，一个人抓住我的额毛，另一个人紧紧拽住我的鼻子，我简直喘不过气来，还有一个人用力抓住我的下巴，掰开我的嘴，就这样强迫地给我套上了笼头，往我的嘴里塞进了衔铁。然后一个人拽住笼头拖着我走，另一个在后面鞭打，这是我第一次领教人类的仁慈——全都是暴力。他们根本没有给我机会去了解他们想怎么样。我是贵族血统，精力非常旺盛，也很狂野，所以毫无疑问，我敢说，我给他们带来了好多麻烦。而可怕的是，日复一日被关在马厩里毫无自由，所以我烦躁痛苦，想要解脱。要知道，有一个和气的主人常常哄着你，你都觉得自己够糟糕了，但是我什么也没有啊。

“以前有过一个名叫赖德先生的老主人，我以为他会让我很快改变想法，他本来可以为我做所有的一切，但是他把所有难事都交给了儿子和另一个有经验的人，他只是偶尔来看看。他的儿子高大、强壮而又莽撞，他们叫他萨姆森，他经常夸口说他从来没有发现一匹马能把他摔下来。他没有他爸爸身上的任何绅士风度，有的只是强硬的声音、强硬的眼神和强硬的手段。从一开始，我就感到他想做的就是耗尽我所有的精力，把我变成安分、卑微、顺从的行尸走肉。行尸走肉！是的，那就是他全部的想法。”说着，姜姐跺了跺脚，好像他的那个想法让她非常生气。随后，她接着说道：

“如果我没有完全按照他的想法去做，他就会恼怒，把我拴在训练场的长缰绳上让我绕着圈跑，直到我跑得筋疲力尽。我想他是喝多了酒，而且我非常清楚他酒喝得越频繁，对我来说就越糟糕。有一天，他想尽办法折腾我，我躺倒在地时，疲惫、痛苦而又生气。那一切看起来真让我难过。第二天一早，他就来找我，又让我绕圈跑了很长时间。我还没有休息一个小时，他就又拿着鞍子、马勒和一副新嚼子来找我了。我一直都说不清那件事是怎么发生的。他就在训练场上骑我，当我做的事儿不对他的脾气时，他就会用缰绳狠狠地驱赶我。新嚼子让我疼痛难忍，于是我突然后腿站立起来，这让他更加恼火，他开始鞭打我。我感到整个灵魂都在跟他对抗，于是我开始踢，开始冲，开始后腿站起，我以前从来没有后腿站起过。我们正面交锋。好一阵子，他都紧紧地夹住马鞍，用鞭子和马刺残酷地惩罚我，但是我热血沸腾，只要能把他撂下来，我毫不在乎他会使什么花招。最后，经过激烈搏斗，我把他向后甩翻在地。我听到他重重地摔在了草地上。我没有回头看他，飞快地跑到了牧场的另一头。到了那儿，我转过身，看到那个迫害我的人从地上慢慢地爬起来，走进了马厩。我站在橡树下看着，但是没有任何人来抓我。时间向前推进，太阳热辣辣的。苍蝇成群地围着我，落在我那被马刺戳得血流不止的侧腹上。我感到饥饿，因为我从早晨起就没有吃过东西，而草地上的草还不够一只鹅填饱肚子的。我想躺下休息，但是鞍子紧紧地绑在身上，无法放松，也没有一滴水喝。下午慢慢地过去了，太阳西沉。我看到其他小马都被带了回去，我知道他们正在美餐。

“最后，就在太阳落下时，我看到老主人手里端着筛子走了出来。他是一位很好的老先生，头发花白。我能从一千个声音里听出他的声音。他的声音不高不低，饱满、清晰、和蔼。他下令时沉稳坚定，每匹马、每个人都明白他期待你服从。他平静地走过来，不时地晃动筛子里的燕麦，高兴温和地对我说道：‘过来，小姑娘，过来，小姑娘。过来，过来。’我站在那儿一动不动，让他走近。他把燕麦递给我，我开始没有恐惧地吃了起来。他的声音带走了我所有的恐惧。他站在我的身边，在我进食时轻轻地拍打和抚摸我，看到我侧面的血块，他好像非常恼怒。‘可怜的小姑娘！糟糕，真糟糕！’随后，他平静地拉起缰绳，把我牵到了马厩。萨姆森就站在门口。我耳朵向后抿，朝他咬去。‘往后站，’主人说，‘别挡着她的路。今天你对这匹小母马做得真糟糕。’他咆哮着骂了恶毒的畜生之类的话。‘你听着，’他的父亲说，‘一个脾气不好的人绝不会驯出一匹好脾气的马。你还没有学会怎么做自己的工作，萨姆森。’随后，他把我牵进了我的畜栏，亲手卸下马鞍和马勒，把我拴好。接着，他要了一桶温水和一块海绵，脱下外套，让马夫拿着桶，在我的两边擦了好一阵子，非常体贴。我相信他知道那些伤口有多么肿痛。‘喔！我的漂亮宝贝儿，’他说，‘站着别动，站着别动。’他的声音的确对我有好处，洗浴也很舒服。我嘴角的皮肤都烂了，不能吃干草，草秆会伤到我。他仔细查看了那儿，摇了摇头，吩咐马夫去拿一些好吃的糠糊糊，把一些饭放进去。这种糊糊味道真好！吃到嘴里既柔软又有疗效。我吃东西时，主人一直都站在旁边，抚摸着我，对那个马夫说着话：‘如果不是用合理的手段来驯服一匹像这样精神饱满的牲口，那她永远都不会变乖。’

“之后，他经常来看我。而当我的嘴痊愈后，被他们叫作乔布的另一名驯马师继续训练我。他稳重体贴，我很快就学会了他想教我的东西。”

第八章　姜姐故事续

接下来的一次，我和姜姐一起待在小围场时，她给我讲了她干活的第一个地方。

“训练结束后，”她说，“我被一个马贩子买走了，和另一匹栗色马做搭档。他让我们一起拉了几个星期的车，然后我们就被卖给了一个时髦先生，被送到伦敦。那个马贩子曾经用马缰驾驭过我，我恨死那种马缰了。但是，在伦敦这个地方，我们被马缰勒得更紧，马夫和他的主人认为这样做能让我们看上去更漂亮。我们经常被赶着去公园或其他时尚场所转悠。你从来没有戴过马缰，不知道那是什么滋味，但是我可以告诉你，那非常可怕。

“我喜欢来回甩头，像其他马一样把头抬得高高的，但是你自己想想，如果你高昂着头，被迫保持那个高度，几个小时根本不能动弹，除了被猛地拽得更高。你的脖子会痛到无法忍受，你不知道该怎么忍受下去。除此以外，我还要戴两个马嚼子，而不是一个——我的马嚼子非常锋利，弄伤了我的舌头和下巴，舌头流出的血染红了从我的嘴唇不断飞溅的白沫，我对马嚼子和缰绳感到恼怒和焦躁。最糟糕的是，当我们的女主人去参加某个盛大宴会或娱乐活动时，我们不得不站着等好几个小时。如果我因为不耐烦而急躁或跺脚，鞭子就会抽在我的身上。这足以把一匹马逼疯！”

“你们的主人没有为你们想过吗？”我问道。

“没有，”她说，“他只关心拥有一个所谓漂亮的亮相。我觉得他对马知之甚少。他把一切都交给了马夫，马夫告诉他说我脾气急躁。我是没有好好受过勒马缰的训练，但是他不是能训好我的料，因为我在马厩里难受生气时，不但没有得到他善意的安抚让我平静，反而得到了一句脏话或一顿毒打。如果他有礼貌，我就会努力承受这一切。我愿意干活，也准备努力工作。但是，他们毫无理由随心所欲地折磨我，这让我生气。他们有什么权利让我这样受苦？除了我嘴里的伤和脖子上的痛之外，我的气管也非常难受。如果我在那儿待久了，我知道那就会损害我的呼吸系统。但是，我越来越烦躁不安，难以自制。无论是谁给我戴马具，我都会猛咬乱踢，为此马夫打过我。有一天，他们刚刚把我套进马车，要用缰绳把我的头拉高，我就开始拼命又冲又踢。我很快就挣坏了好多马具，踢蹬着完全挣脱开来。因此，我在那个地方待到了头。

“之后，我被送到塔特萨尔集市去卖。当然，谁也不能担保我不会有坏脾气，所以都没有说起这事儿。我漂亮的外表和矫健的步伐很快就引来了一位先生为我出价，后来我就被另一个马贩子买走了。他用各种方法和不同的马嚼子测试我，很快就弄清了我不能忍受什么。最后，他用完全不戴勒马缰绳的方式骑我，然后将我作为非常安分的马卖给了一位乡下绅士。他是一位好主人，我生活得很好，但是原来的马夫离开了他，来了一个新马夫。这个马夫像萨姆森一样心狠手辣。他说话的声音总是粗声恶气，很不耐烦。如果他需要我，我在马厩里没有动，他就会用马厩里的扫帚或耙子——拿起什么是什么——打我跗关节以上的部位。他做什么事儿都很粗鲁，所以我开始恨他。他想让我怕他，但是我气性太高了，偏不怕他。有一天，他激怒了我，比以往更厉害，我就咬了他。这当然让他大发雷霆，他就用一条马鞭开始抽我的头。之后，他再也不敢进我的马厩了。我的后蹄和牙齿都为他准备好了，这他知道。跟主人在一起时，我非常安分，主人却听信了马夫说的话，所以我又被卖了。

“还是同一个马贩子听说了我的消息，说他觉得他知道我到一个地方会干得很好。‘真可惜，’他说，‘这么好的一匹马因为缺乏真正的好机会，居然落到了这种糟糕的地步。’最后我在你来之前不久来到了这儿。但是，那时我就已经认定人是我的天敌，我必须自卫。当然这儿截然不同，但是谁知道这会持续多久呢？我希望自己能像你一样思考问题。而在经历了这一切之后，我做不到。”

“那么，”我说，“我认为，如果你还要踢或咬约翰或詹姆斯，那就真不像话了。”

她说：“他们对我好时我也不想。有一次，我的确狠狠地咬了詹姆斯。但是，约翰说：‘尽力对她好点儿。’而不是像我料想的那样惩罚我，詹姆斯包扎着胳膊，来到我的身边，给我端来了麦麸，抚摸我。从那以后，我没再咬过他，将来也不会了。”

我曾为姜姐难过，当然那时我知之甚少，所以我以为很可能是她把事儿搞得一塌糊涂。然而，过了几周，我发现她越来越温和，越来越快乐，任何陌生人走近时她的神情都没有了原来的警惕和傲慢。有一天，詹姆斯说：“我当真认为那匹母马渐渐地喜欢上我了，今天早上我揉摸她的前额后，她在我的身后发出了柔和的嘶鸣。”

“唉，唉，吉姆，这都是伯特维克庄园的疗效。”约翰说，“不久以后，她会像黑骏马一样友好。她需要的所有药物就是善良，可怜的家伙！”主人也注意到了这个变化，一天，他像往常一样走出马车，过来跟我们说话，他抚摸了一下她漂亮的脖子。“啊，我的美人儿，你现在过得怎么样？我想你比刚来时快乐多喽。”

当主人轻轻地抚摸姜姐时，她友善信任地把鼻子凑向了他。

“约翰，我们要治愈她。”他说。

“是的，主人，她进步惊人，不再是刚来时的样子了。先生，这是‘伯特维克庄园药丸’的功劳。”约翰笑着说道。

这是约翰开的一个小玩笑。他总是说，按照常规吃“伯特维克庄园药丸”一个疗程，几乎能治愈任何一匹凶猛的马。他说这些药丸是由耐心、温和、坚定和爱抚制成，每只药丸一磅重，掺入半品脱基本常识，每天喂给马吃。

第九章　快乐腿

教区牧师布罗姆菲尔德先生有好多子女，他们经常过来跟杰西小姐和弗罗拉小姐一起玩。其中的一个姑娘像杰西小姐一样大；两个男孩子年龄较大，还有好几个年龄小的男孩。他们来后，可有快乐腿的活儿干了，因为他们最开心的就是轮流骑在他的身上，在果园或家庭牧场里到处转悠，这样在一起一转就是一个小时。

一天下午，快乐腿跟着他们出去了好长时间。当詹姆斯把他带进来，给他戴上缰绳时，说道：

“好了，你这坏蛋，对你自己的所作所为留点儿神，否则我们都会有麻烦。”

“你都做了什么，快乐腿？”我问道。

“噢！”他甩了甩小脑袋说，“我只是教训了一下那些年轻人。他们不知道什么时候他们已经玩够了，也不知道什么时候我已经受够了，所以我就把他们都从后面尥出去了。只有这样做，他们才能明白。”

“什么！”我说，“你把孩子们尥出去了？我还以为你比这懂事呢。你把杰西小姐或弗罗拉小姐也尥出去了吗？”

看上去他大为生气，说道：

“当然没有。就是给马厩里送来最好的燕麦，我也不会做这种事儿。啊，我像主人一样尽可能关心我们的小姐。至于那些小不点儿，是我教会她们骑马的。当她们骑在我背上受到惊吓或有点儿坐不稳时，我就会像一只追赶小鸟的老猫一样安稳从容。等她们平安无事后，我又会继续加快步伐，你明白，就是为了让她们适应，所以不必费心来说教我。我是那些孩子最好的朋友，也是她们最好的骑术教练。不是她们，是那些男孩子，男孩子们，”他摇晃着鬃毛说，“截然不同，他们必须像我们小时候那样接受驯服。就得有人告诉他们什么是什么。其他孩子骑在我身上转悠将近两个小时，所以男孩子们觉得该轮到他们了，就是这样，我非常愉快。整整一个小时，他们轮流骑着我，我驮着他们到处跑，在地里跑上跑下，跑遍了果园。他们每个人都削了一根大榛树枝做马鞭，下手有点儿太狠了，但是我都欣然接受了。后来我认为他们玩够了，就停下来两三次，作为暗示。你明白，那些男孩子认为马或小型马就像蒸汽机或打谷机一样，可以随他们心意要跑多久就多久，想要跑多快就多快。他们绝不会去想马会疲倦，也绝不会去想马有感情。所以，那个用鞭子抽我的孩子不明白，我就用后腿作为支撑抬起身来，让他从后面滑了下去——仅此而已。他又骑上了我，我又如法炮制。随后，另一个男孩子上来了，他一开始用树枝，我就把他放倒在草地上，如此这般，直到他们能明白为止——仅此而已。他们不是坏孩子，他们并不希望表现得残酷无情。我非常喜欢他们，但是，你明白，我不得不教训他们。当他们把我带到詹姆斯那儿告状时，我想詹姆斯看到那些大树枝后非常生气。他说这些树枝只适合牲口贩子或吉卜赛人用，而不适合年轻绅士。”

“如果我是你，”姜姐说，“我就会狠狠地踢那些男孩子一顿，那会给他们一个教训。”

“你肯定会。”快乐腿说，“但是，当时（恕我直言），我还没有傻到去让主人生气或让詹姆斯蒙羞的地步。此外，那些孩子在骑马时由我照管。我告诉你，他们非常信任我。啊，就在前几天，我听到我们的主人对布罗姆菲尔德夫人说：‘我亲爱的夫人，你不必担心孩子们。我的老快乐腿会像你或我一样照顾他们。我向你保证，我不会用那匹马去卖钱，他是那样心平气和，值得信任。’你以为我会因为几个无知的男孩子对我不好，就忘记五年来我在这儿受到的所有善待，忘记他们对我的所有信任，成为一个忘恩负义的畜牲吗？不，不会！因为你去过的地方从来没有人善待你，所以你不了解，我也为你难过。但是，我可以告诉你，好地方才能出好马。无论如何，我都不会烦扰这儿的人。我爱他们，我真的爱他们。”说着，快乐腿鼻子里发出了低沉的“嗬，嗬，嗬！”声，就像早上他听到门口传来詹姆斯的脚步声时经常做的那样。

“况且，”他接着说道，“如果我喜欢踢人，我会在哪儿呢？啊，会被马上卖掉，没有名誉，我也许会受一个屠夫的孩子奴役，或是在海边的一个地方干活累死，那儿没有人关心我，他们只想弄清我能跑多快，或者像我来这儿之前在住的地方看到的那样，礼拜天被一路鞭打着拉着坐有三四个大人物的马车出去寻欢作乐。不，”他摇着头说，“我希望自己永远不要落到那个地步。”

第十章　果园里的谈话

我和姜姐都不是那种常见的体型高大的拉车马，我们身上更具有赛马血统。我们站起来大约有十五个半手高，所以我们无论当坐骑还是拉车都是好手，我们的主人常说他不喜欢只能做一件事的马或人。他不想在伦敦的公园里炫耀，所以他比较喜欢那种更活跃、更实用的马。对我们来说，最大的快乐就是戴上鞍具去参加一个骑马派对。男主人骑姜姐，女主人骑我，小姐们骑奥利弗爵士和快乐腿。大家在一起时而小跑，时而慢跑，非常开心，这总是让我们兴高采烈。我做的事儿最好，因为我总是驮女主人。她体重很轻，声音甜美，一只手轻轻地拉着缰绳，我在被牵引时几乎感觉不到她在拉缰绳。

噢！如果人们知道由一只轻柔的手牵引对马儿来说有多么惬意，如果他们知道那样做既能让马嘴完好，又能让马儿保持好脾气，肯定就不会再像平日拉缰绳时那样又勒又拖又拽了。我们的嘴很嫩，只要不是因为粗暴无知的对待而受伤或变硬，它们就能感知骑手哪怕最轻微的手部动作。需要我们做什么，我们马上就会知道。我的嘴从来没有受过伤，我相信这就是我们的女主人喜欢我而不喜欢姜姐的原因，尽管她的步伐的确也很好。姜姐经常嫉妒我，她的嘴没有我的那样完美，说这都是因为受驯和在伦敦戴马嚼子造成的。这时，奥利弗爵士常常会说：“好了，好了！不要自寻烦恼了。你最荣耀了，一匹母马能驮我们主人这样重、这样高的男人，而且动作敏捷，弹跳力好，不必因没有驮女主人而垂头丧气。只要人们善待我们，我们就必须安于现状，始终知足听话。”

我经常纳闷奥利弗爵士的尾巴怎么那么短。从上面垂下的流苏般的尾毛，真的只有六七英寸长。一个假日，我们在果园里时，我大胆地问他，是什么事故让他丢了尾巴。“事故？”他狠狠地看了我一眼，轻蔑地哼道，“不是事故！是一次残忍、可耻、无情的行为！小时候，我被带到了一个地方，就是在那儿发生了这些残忍的事儿。我被绑了起来，绑得紧紧的，无法动弹，然后他们过来剪掉了我漂亮的长尾巴，连骨带肉都拿走了。”

“真可怕！”我惊叫道。

“可怕啊！真可怕，而可怕的不仅仅是疼痛，尽管那种疼痛非常可怕，而且持续了很长时间。这不仅仅是夺去我身上最好装饰的无礼举动，尽管那已经很糟了，最重要的是，这样的话，我怎么再去拂掉那些叮在我两侧和后腿上的苍蝇？你们有尾巴的马不用想就能拂去苍蝇，所以你说不出苍蝇落在你身上叮来叮去，而你没有任何东西可以把他们赶走，是何等的折磨！我告诉你这是终生的错误，也是终生的损失。但是，谢天谢地，他们现在不再这样做了。”

“他们当时为什么这样做？”姜姐问道。

“为了时髦！”老马跺了跺脚说，“为了时髦！你知道这是什么意思吧；我那个时代没有一匹良种小马的尾巴不被人以可耻的方式剪短的，就像创造我们的仁慈上帝不知道我们需要什么，也不知道怎么才最好看一样。”

“我想，我在伦敦时，他们用皮带把我的头绑起来，嘴里塞上那种可怕的马嚼子，让我受尽折磨，就是为了时髦。”姜姐说。

“当然是！”他说，“在我看来，时髦是世界上最邪恶的东西之一。比如，现在看看他们是怎么对付那些狗的；为了让他们看上去更勇敢，剪掉他们的尾巴；为了使他们看上去机灵，把他们漂亮的小耳朵剪成尖尖的形状，真是这样。我曾有一个亲密的朋友，那是一只褐色小猎犬，他们叫她匐犬。她非常喜欢我，睡觉从来不离开我的马厩。她把睡觉的地方安在马槽下面，在那儿一窝产下了五只小狗，要多漂亮有多漂亮；没有一只被溺死，因为他们都是珍贵品种，她和孩子们在一起是多么开心啊！当那些小狗睁开眼睛到处爬时，那情景真可爱。但是，有一天，有人过来把他们都带走了。我想也许是担心我会踩到他们吧。但是，并非如此。晚上，可怜的匐犬又把他们一个个叼了回来。他们不再是从前那些开心的小家伙，而是流着血，可怜地哭着。他们的尾巴都被剪掉了一截，漂亮的小耳朵上的柔软耳翼完全被剪掉了。他们的妈妈舔着他们，神色是多么不安，真可怜啊！我永远不会忘记那情景。他们最后都痊愈了，忘记了疼痛。当然，为了使耳朵娇柔部分隔离灰尘及预防伤害的漂亮柔软的耳翼，却一去不复返了。为什么那些人不把自己孩子的耳朵也剪成尖尖的，让他们显得更机灵呢？为什么他们不剪掉自己的鼻尖，让他们显得更勇敢呢？大家都一样有感觉。他们有什么权利折磨和毁坏上帝的生灵呢？”

尽管奥利弗爵士非常温和，但也是一个充满感情的老家伙。他说的一切对我来说都十分新鲜，也很可怕，我发现自己心里对人类产生了一些前所未有的憎恨之情。当然，姜姐非常激动。她仰起头，眼睛闪亮，鼻孔张大，宣称人类既是暴徒又是笨蛋。

“谁说笨蛋呢？”快乐腿说，他刚从老苹果树那边过来，一直在矮枝上蹭着，“谁说笨蛋呢？我想这是坏话。”

“坏话就是用来说坏东西的。”说着，姜姐把奥利弗爵士说的一切告诉了他。

“一点儿没错。”快乐腿伤心地说，“我在当初住的地方经常看到这样的狗。但是，我在这儿不愿谈论这一点。你们知道，主人，还有约翰和詹姆斯，一向对我们很好，在这样的地方对人说三道四好像既不公平又忘恩负义，你们知道，除了我们的主人之外，还有好多好主人和好马夫，当然我们那几位是最好的。”

我们都知道好心的小快乐腿的这番至理名言所言不虚，所以都平静下来，尤其是奥利弗爵士，他对主人情有独钟。为了转变话题，我说：“谁能告诉我眼罩的用处？”

“不能！”奥利弗爵士简短地说，“因为它们没有任何用处。”

“应该是，”杂色矮脚马正义平静地说，“用来防止马儿受惊跳起，也防止马儿受到惊吓引起事故。”

“那他们不给骑的马，尤其是女士骑的马戴眼罩，这是什么原因？”我又问道。

“根本没有任何原因，”他平静地说，“除非也为了时髦。他们说，如果马儿看到了自己拉的或是从后面驶来的马车的轮子，就一定会受惊而逃，尽管街道拥挤时被赶的马儿完全看到了周围的一切。我承认，有时轮子挨得太近，会令人不快，但是我们不会逃跑。我们习惯了，而且明白事理。如果我们从来没有戴过眼罩，我们就永远不需要它。我们应该看到那儿是什么，知道什么是什么，比只看到一点儿我们不明白的东西更能减少恐惧。当然，也许一些马儿小时候受过伤或受过惊吓，戴上眼罩说不定会好些。但是，因为我从来不紧张，所以我无法判断。”

“我认为，”奥利弗爵士说，“夜里戴着眼罩是件危险的事儿。我们马儿在黑暗中比人的视力好得多。如果马能充分利用自己的眼睛，好多事故就绝不会发生。我记得，几年前的一个黑夜，两匹马拉着一辆灵车返回，正好经过斯帕罗农场主家的房子，那儿的池塘紧挨马路，车轮离池边太近了，灵车就翻进了水里，两匹马都淹死了，车夫几乎是死里逃生。当然，这次事故之后，那儿就圈起了一道结实的白色围栏，人们很容易看见。但是，如果那些马没有被蒙住部分眼睛，他们就会自觉远离池边，事故也就不会发生了。你来这儿之前，我们主人的马车就翻倒过。据说，如果左边的灯没有熄灭，约翰就会看到筑路工留下的那个大坑。他也许是这样，而如果老科林没有戴眼罩，无论有没有灯，他都会看见，因为他是一匹老马，完全知道不能去冒险。事实上，他伤得很重，马车也摔坏了，约翰是怎么死里逃生的，谁也不知道。”

“我应该说，”姜姐抽了抽鼻子说，“这些人如此聪明，最好下命令，将来所有的小马生下来，都应该把眼睛长在额头正中央，而不是两边。他们总是认为他们可以改造自然，改善上帝创造的一切。”

气氛又变得紧张起来，这时快乐腿仰起机灵的小脸，说道：“我要告诉你们一个秘密：我相信约翰不赞成眼罩。有一天，我听到他和主人谈起了这个想法。主人说：‘如果马儿已经习惯戴眼罩，再摘去眼罩，就可能会有些危险。’约翰说，他认为，所有小马在受驯时不戴眼罩，将会是一件好事，外国有些地方就是这样。所以，让我们振作起来，跑去果园那头吧。我相信风已经刮掉了一些苹果，我们不妨像那些刺蛾一样吃了它们。”

我们都无法拒绝快乐腿的主意，于是中断了长谈，大快朵颐地吃起了散落在地上的甜甜的苹果，又打起了精神。

第十一章　坦率对话

我在伯特维克住的时间越长，就越为有这个好地方而感到自豪和快乐。我们的男主人和女主人赢得了所有认识他们的人的尊重和爱戴。他们善待每个人、每个事物，不仅善待男男女女，而且善待马、驴、狗、猫、牛和鸟儿。没有一个受过压迫或虐待的动物不是他们的朋友，他们的仆人也是同样的风格。如果村里哪个小孩子残忍地虐待动物，他们很快就会从伯爵府那儿听到。

他们说，先生和农场主格雷共同努力了二十多年，终于去掉了拉货马的勒马缰绳，所以在我们这一带你很少见到那种缰绳。有时，如果女主人碰见一匹负载很重的马儿被拉起脑袋，就会停下马车，走出去，用甜美而又严肃的声音跟车夫理论，尽力向他说明这样做是多么愚蠢和残忍。

我认为没有人能对抗我们女主人的理论。我希望所有的女士都像她一样。我们的男主人有时也十分严厉。我记得，一天早上，他骑着我回家，这时我们看到一个身强力壮的人赶着一辆轻便马车朝我们驶来，拉车的是一匹漂亮的红棕色小马，细细的腿，头和脸都高贵灵敏。就在来到庄园大门时，那个小家伙转向了大门。那个车夫没有命令，也没有警告，突然用力猛地扭回马头，都快让马头挨到屁股了。回过神后，马继续前进，那个人开始狂暴地鞭打他。小马突然冲向前，但是那只强壮有力的手又把漂亮的小东西拽了回来，力气大得几乎足以折断他的下颚，鞭子还在往他的肉里抽。这情景让我心惊肉跳，因为我知道这会让那张细嫩的小嘴多么痛苦。不过，主人向我发令，于是我们立刻追上了他。

“索耶，”他厉声喊道，“那匹小马是血肉做的吗？”

“有血有肉有脾气！”他说，“他太喜欢自作主张了，这不适合我。”他说话时好像带着强烈的情绪。他是一个建筑工，以前因为生意经常来庄园。

“你以为，”主人严厉地说，“这样对他，会让他喜欢顺从你的心意吗？”

“他没有权利转那个弯，他的路是一直向前！”那个人粗鲁地说。

“你经常驾着这匹小马上我这个地方来，”主人说，“这只说明他既有记性又有头脑，他怎么知道你今天不是又要到那儿去呢？不过，这跟那个没有多大关系。索耶先生，我必须说，你惨无人道地虐待一匹小马，我真心疼得看不下去，你这样感情用事，不仅伤害了这匹马，更损害了你自己的品格。记住，人们会根据我们的所作所为，对我们作出评判，无论这些所作所为是针对人还是针对畜牲。”

主人骑着我慢慢地回家，我从他的声音可以听出这件事让他多么伤心。他刚才跟同等地位的绅士说话时，就像是对比他地位低的人说话一样随意。还有一天，我们出门时，遇到了兰利上尉，他是我们主人的一个朋友，正驾着一对英俊的灰马，调教他们拉车。他们聊了一会儿之后，上尉说道：

“你觉得我这个新马队怎么样，道格拉斯先生？你知道，你可是这一带的识马行家，我想听听你的意见。”

主人让我后退一点儿，以便好好看那两匹马。“他们是一对少见的骏马，”他说，“如果他们表里如一的话，我确信，你就不用指望得到更好的马儿了。但是，我看你还是死守着你那个宠物训练方案来折磨你的马儿，削减他们的实力。”

“你什么意思？”另一个人说，“是说马缰？噢，啊！我知道这是你的爱好。那么，实际上，我喜欢看到我的马儿保持昂首的姿态。”

“我也喜欢，”主人说，“和其他人一样喜欢，但是我不希望看到马头被抬高。那会让他们失去所有的光彩。好了，兰利，你是一位军人，肯定想看到你的部队在阅兵时有抬头挺胸之类养眼的表现。但是，如果士兵们的头都绑在一块靠背板上，你就不会为自己的操练得到多少赞扬了。这样做除了让士兵们烦恼和疲劳之外，可能对阅兵没有多大伤害。然而，如果拼刺刀向敌人冲锋陷阵呢？那时，他们需要自由运用每一块肌肉，全力上阵。我想他们取胜的可能性不大。马儿也完全一样：你让他们的性情变得烦躁和焦虑，会削减他们的力量，不能使他们尽力干活，因此他们的关节和肌肉都会过劳，这当然也会加快他们的损耗。放心好了，马儿跟人一样，也需要让脑袋自由活动。如果我们多按照常识行事，少追些时髦，我们就会发现好多事儿都会更加容易。而且，你和我一样了解，如果马儿迈错步子，脑袋和脖子却被紧紧地绑在后面，自行调整的可能性就会大大降低。好了，”主人笑着说道，“我已经让小马跑了好一阵子，你能不能下决心也骑上他呢，上尉？你的范例将会影响深远。”

“我相信你在理论上是对的，”上尉说，“你拿士兵举例非常有力，不过——好吧——我会考虑的。”他们就此别过。

第十二章　暴风雨天

晚秋的一天，我的主人有事要出一趟远门。我被套进了轻便双轮马车，约翰跟主人同行。我一向喜欢拉轻便双轮马车，车子很轻，高高的轮子转起来真带劲儿。大雨过后，现在又刮起了大风，落叶纷纷扬扬地横扫过路面。我们一路上都很开心，直至来到了关卡。那儿有一座矮木桥，河岸相当高。桥不是那种拱桥，而是水平架在河上，因此如果河水满的话，水就会淹到河中央的桥木和踏板。但是，两边的栏杆都非常结实，所以人们都毫不在意。

守关卡的人说河水涨得很快，他担心今天晚上会很糟。好多牧场都淹在了水下，路面上有一个低洼处，河水已经淹到我的膝盖了。但是，底下的桥面不错，主人驾车比较小心，所以过桥没问题。

我们到达镇上后，我当然是好好吃了一顿，主人的生意却占用了他很长时间，所以我们直到傍晚时分才返程回家。这时，风越来越大了，我听到主人对约翰说，他从来没有在这样的暴风天出过门，我也是这样想的。我们沿着树林的边缘走，大树枝像小枝条一样摇来晃去，呼啸而过的风声可怕极了。

“我希望我们能安全驶出这片树林。”主人说。

“是的，先生。”约翰说，“如果一根这样的树枝砸在我们身上，那可就糟了。”

他话刚一出口，就传来了吱嘎声、噼啪声、爆裂声、撕裂声和撞击声。树林中，一棵橡树从根部断裂开来，正好横在我们面前的路上。我绝不能说自己没有被吓倒，因为我真的被吓坏了。我停下来站定，我相信自己在颤抖。当然，我没有转身，也没有逃跑。从小接受的训练不允许我那样做。约翰跳下马车，立刻走到我面前。

“真是死里逃生啊。”主人说，“现在该怎么办呢？”

“唉，先生，我们既无法从那棵树上越过去，也无法绕过去，无可奈何，只能回到那四个岔道口，得足足走上六英里，我们才能回到木桥那儿。这样，我们回去就要晚了，不过这匹马还精神着呢。”

于是，我们就往回走，绕过岔路口，而等我们走到桥边时，天都快黑了。我们只能看到水漫过桥中央。洪水来时，这种事儿时有发生，所以主人没有停车。我们以相当快的速度前进着，而我一踩到桥面，就确信情况不对。我不敢向前走，就纹丝不动地站住了。“继续走啊，美人儿。”说完，主人用鞭子碰了我一下，我却不敢动。他猛地抽了我一鞭子，我前蹄扬起，但还是不敢前进。

“情况不对，先生。”说着，约翰从车上纵身跳下，来到我面前，四处瞧了瞧。他尽力想拉我前进。“快点儿，美人儿，怎么了？”当然，我无法告诉他，但是我非常清楚桥不安全。

就在这时，对面关卡那个人从房子里跑出来，发疯似的晃着手电筒。

“嗬，嗬，嗬！喂！站住！”他喊道。

“出了什么事儿？”主人大声问道。

“桥中间断了，有一部分被冲走了。你们要是继续走的话，就会掉进河里的。”

“谢天谢地！”主人说，“你这美人儿！”说着，约翰拉起缰绳，轻轻地牵着我，转向河边靠右的道路。太阳已经落下一段时间了。狂风大作，刮断了那棵树后，似乎已经暂时停息了。天越来越黑，周围越来越静了。我静静地小跑着，车轮在松软的路上几乎无声无息。好一阵子，主人和约翰都没有说话，后来主人口气严肃地开口说话。他们说的那些话，我大多听不懂。但是，我发现他们都认为，如果我按照主人的吩咐继续走的话，桥十有八九就会坍塌，马儿、马车、主人和仆人都会掉进河里。而且水流湍急，没有灯，附近也没有帮手，十有八九我们会统统被淹死。主人说，上帝给了人类理智，他们可以借此发现事物的规律。然而，他给动物的是不需要推理的知觉，这种知觉要快捷、完美得多，他们常常能借此挽救人的生命。约翰会讲好多马和狗的故事，还会讲他们做过的奇妙事情。他认为，人类没有充分认识到动物的价值，也没有跟他们交朋友，而这些本是人类应该做的。我确信，如果有人跟动物交朋友，那就是他。

我们终于来到了庄园门口，发现园丁正等着我们回来。他说，天黑后，女主人就一直提心吊胆，害怕发生什么意外，还说她已经派詹姆斯骑着杂色短腿马正义向木桥那边打听我们的消息去了。

我们看到门厅和楼上的窗户里都亮着灯。我们走上来时，女主人跑出来，说道：“亲爱的，你真的平安无事吗？噢！我担心死了，一直在胡思乱想。你没有遇到什么意外吧？”

“没有，亲爱的。但是，要不是你的黑骏马比我们明智，我们早就在木桥那边统统被冲进河里去了。”他们走进屋里后，我没有再听到什么。约翰把我牵到了马厩。噢，那天夜里，他给了我一顿美餐，有好吃的糠糊糊和燕麦豆沫，还铺了厚厚的稻草床！我真开心，因为我累了。

第十三章　魔鬼标志

一天，我和约翰出去为主人办事回来，轻快地走在一条漫长笔直的路上，这时我们看到远处一个男孩子正在试图让一匹小马翻越一道栅栏。小马不愿跳，那个男孩子就用鞭子狠狠地抽他，小马只是躲到了一边。男孩子又抽他，小马又躲到了另一边。随后，那个男孩子跳下马，劈头盖脸一阵猛抽。接着，他又骑上马，恬不知耻地一直踢那匹小马，想让小马跃过去，而小马却拒绝起跳。当我们快走到跟前时，小马低下头，扬起蹄子，干净利落地把那个男孩子甩进了宽阔的树篱，一路飞奔跑回了家，缰绳还挂在头上。约翰哈哈大笑。“罪有应得！”他说。

“噢，噢，噢！”那个男孩子在荆棘丛中挣扎着大声叫喊，“我说，过来帮我出去啊。”

“谢天谢地。”约翰说，“我想你完全是罪有应得，也许一点儿擦伤会让你知道，你不该让小马去跃过一道太高的栅栏。”说完，约翰就走了。“也许，”他自言自语道，“那个年轻家伙既是骗子又是暴徒。我们回家正要经过布什比农场主家。美人儿，如果有人想了解情况的话，我和你就可以告诉他们，你明白吧。”于是，我们转向右边，很快就来到了堆谷场，看到了那所房子。那个农场主正匆匆地走向大路，他的妻子正站在大门口，一副万分惊恐的神情。

“你们看到我的孩子了吗？”我们走近时，布什比先生问道，“他一小时前骑着我的那匹小黑马出去，小马刚刚回来了，而马背上却没有人。”

“先生，我认为，”约翰说，“马背上最好没有人，除非有人得体地骑着。”

“你这话什么意思？”农场主问道。

“好了，先生，你的儿子真不像话，我看到他对那匹善良的小马又抽又踢又砸，就因为马儿不愿去跳一道对他来说太高的栅栏。先生，小马表现良好，没有任何缺点。而最终，他只是扬起蹄子把那位年轻的先生抛进了荆棘树篱。那位年轻的先生想让我帮他。但是，我希望你能原谅我，先生，我觉得自己不应该帮他。他没有骨折，先生，只是被刮了几下。我爱马，见到马儿受到虐待，就会恼火。激怒一匹马，让他扬蹄可不是好事儿。通常有了第一次，就不会是最后一次。”

这时，孩子的妈妈开始哭了起来：“噢，我可怜的比尔，我必须去看他。他一定受伤了。”

“老婆，你最好进屋。”农场主说，“比尔需要这样一个教训，我一定要让他明白。他虐待那匹小马可不是一次两次了，我要阻止他。非常感谢你，曼利。再见。”

于是，我们继续前进，一路上约翰格格直笑。后来，他把这事儿告诉了詹姆斯，詹姆斯也大笑着说：“他罪有应得。我在学校时就认识那小子。因为他是农场主的儿子，所以就趾高气扬，经常大摇大摆地走路，欺负小男孩。当然，我们这些比他大的人可不容任何人胡闹，我们让他知道，在学校里、操场上，农场主的儿子和劳工的儿子都是一样的。我清晰记得，一天下午快上课时，我发现他在大窗户边逮苍蝇，拽下他们的翅膀。他没有看见我，我给了他一耳光，让他四仰八叉地躺在了地上。啊，尽管我很生气，但是几乎吓得要死，他煞有介事地吼叫咆哮。男孩子们都从操场上冲过来，男老师也从路上跑过来看看谁在遭受残害。当然，我马上把自己做过的事儿和为什么这样做都一五一十地说了出来。随后，我给那个老师看了那些苍蝇，有些已经粉身碎骨了，有些还在无助地爬着。我还给他看了窗台上的那些苍蝇翅膀。我从来没有见老师生过那么大的气。但是，比尔还在那儿号叫哭诉，就像一个懦夫。老师没有再给他那种惩罚，而是让他整个下午都站在凳子上，说那一周比尔都不能出去玩。接着，老师非常严肃地对所有男孩子谈起了残忍，说伤害弱小无助者是多么无情和懦弱，而让我铭记在心的是这句话，他说残忍是魔鬼特有的标志，如果我们看到谁以残忍为乐，我们就能知道他属于什么样的人，因为魔鬼一开始是谋杀犯，最后是折磨犯。相反，如果我们看到谁爱戴邻居，善待人和畜牲，我们就能知道那是上帝的标志。”

“你们老师教给你们的再正确不过了。”约翰说，“没有爱，就没有宗教信仰。人们可能喜欢大谈宗教信仰，但是，如果宗教不教给他们善待人和畜牲，一切就都是谎言——一切就都是谎言，詹姆斯，当黑白颠倒时，宗教就站不住脚了。”

第十四章　詹姆斯·霍华德

十二月的一天早晨，我做完每天的晨练后，约翰把我牵进马厩，给我绑裹护体防寒的布条，詹姆斯端着燕麦从谷仓那边走进来，这时主人也走进了马厩。他看上去神情相当严肃，手里拿着一封打开的信。约翰关紧我的畜栏门，触帽敬礼，等候吩咐。

“早上好，约翰，”主人说，“我想知道你对詹姆斯是否有什么意见。”

“先生，意见？没有，先生。”

“他干活勤快，对你尊重吗？”

“是的，先生，一向如此。”

“你从来没有发现他在你不在场时干活懈怠吗？”

“从来没有，先生。”

“那就好，但是我必须问另一个问题。当他跟那些马儿一起出去锻炼或送信时，你是否有理由怀疑，他会停下来与他相识的人说话，或者没事儿走进屋里，把马儿留在外面呢？”

“没有，先生，当然没有。如果有人这样说詹姆斯，我不会相信，我也不打算相信，除非有证人对我公正地证实这一点。先生，我不是说谁在企图诋毁詹姆斯的品格，而是要说，在这个马厩里从来没有一个年轻家伙比他稳重、乐观、诚实和机灵。我能够相信他说的话，能够相信他做的事儿。他对马儿温和，人也机智，我宁愿让他掌管这些马，也不愿把他们交给我认识的戴花边帽、穿制服的年轻人照管。无论是谁想了解詹姆斯·霍华德的品格，”约翰坚定地甩了一下脑袋说，“那就让他们来找约翰·曼利。”

主人一直站在那儿，神情严肃专注。但是，等约翰说完时，主人脸上绽开了灿烂的笑容，亲切地看着一直静立在门边的詹姆斯，说道：“詹姆斯，我的伙计，放下燕麦，过来吧。我非常高兴地发现约翰对你品质的认识正好跟我不谋而合。约翰是一个慎重的人，”他带着滑稽的微笑说道，“很少见他对别人发表看法，所以我认为旁敲侧击，鸟儿就会飞出来，我很快就会知道我想知道的事儿了。那现在我们谈正事吧。我收到了我姐夫克利福德·威廉斯爵士从克利福德府寄来的一封信。他想要我帮他找一个值得信任的年轻马夫，大约二十岁到二十一岁，精通业务。老马夫跟他在一起生活了三十年，身体渐渐虚弱，他想找个人跟他一起工作，熟悉他的路数，老人退休后能接替他的工作。他起初每周能获得十八先令，有马厩装、骑马装，卧室在马车房上面，手下有一个马童。克里福德爵士是一位好主人。如果你能得到这个职位，那对你来说将是一个良好的开端。我不想跟你分开，如果你离开我们，我们知道约翰就会失去得力助手。”

“那是，先生。”约翰说，“不过，我不会阻挡他的前途。”

“你多大了，詹姆斯？”主人说。

“明年五月就十九岁了，先生。”

“很年轻，你意下如何，约翰？”

“啊，先生，是很年轻。但是，他像男人一样稳重健壮、发育良好，尽管他在赶车方面经验不多，但是他手疾眼快，小心翼翼，我确信他的马儿绝不会因马蹄或马掌缺乏照顾而被毁掉。”

“约翰，你的话会最有说服力。”主人说，“因为克里福德爵士在附言中补充说：‘如果能找到一个约翰训练出来的人，我就会喜欢不尽。’所以，詹姆斯，伙计，仔细考虑一下，吃饭时跟你的妈妈说说，然后把你的想法告诉我。”

这次谈话后没过几天，事情就完全定了下来，一个月或六周之后，詹姆斯就要去克里福德府了。这样詹姆斯既满足了主人的愿望，同时也会得到所有驾车方面的训练，那都是他可能会用得上的。我以前从来都没见过马车这样频繁地出门，原来女主人不出门时，主人会亲自驾着双轮马车出去，但是，现在无论是主人还是小姐们，或者仅仅是听差要出门，我和姜姐都要被套进马车，由詹姆斯驾驭我们。起先，约翰在驾驶座陪他，对他进行全面指导，后来詹姆斯就独自驾车了。

接着，星期六詹姆斯驾车带着主人逛了城里好多地方，我们穿过好多奇妙的大街，那感觉真棒。正当火车要进站时，主人确定要去火车站，出租马车、载客马车、轻便送货马车和公共马车都在设法过桥。铁路铃响起时，只有好马和好车夫才能过去，因为桥很窄，去火车站还有一个急转弯，如果你眼睛不尖或脑筋不灵，就容易跟其他车辆发生碰撞。

第十五章　老马夫

之后，男主人和女主人决定去拜访住在距离我们家大约四十六英里的几位朋友，这次由詹姆斯驾车。第一天，我们行驶了三十二英里。其中有一些漫长难走的山路，但是詹姆斯驾驶得小心周到，所以我们一点儿也不觉得疲倦。下山时，他绝不会忘记拉住刹车，也不会忘记在适当的地段松开刹车。他总是让我们踩到最平坦的地方。如果上山的路很长，他就让马车轮子稍微横过马路，以免马车向后滑，也好让我们喘口气。所有这些小事都会帮马儿的大忙，尤其是在善言劝诱的前提下。

我们在路上停了一两次。正当太阳要落下时，我们来到了要过夜的那个小镇。我们在集市最大的旅馆前停下来。那是一个很大的旅馆，我们经过一个拱门，进入一个长长的院子，最远端是马厩和车房。两个马夫过来给我们解笼头。打头的是一个小个子，瘸了一条腿，穿着一件黄条纹马甲，和颜悦色，积极能干。我从来没有见过解马具像他这么快的人。他轻轻地拍了拍我，说了一句好话，就把我牵进了一个长马厩，里面有六至八个畜栏和两三匹马。另一个人牵来了姜姐。我们接受刷洗时，詹姆斯站在旁边。

我从来没有被谁像那个小老头那样又轻又快地清洗过。他刷洗完后，詹姆斯走上前把我上下摸了一遍，似乎认为我不可能已被清洗彻底了，但是他发现我的皮毛像丝绸一样光洁。

“好吧，”他说，“我以为自己刷洗得相当快了，我们的约翰比我还快，而你刷得既快又彻底，胜过了我见过的所有马夫。”

“熟能生巧，”那个瘸腿的马夫说，“如果没有达到熟能生巧，那就惭愧了。干了四十年，再不生巧！哈，哈！那就太惭愧了。说到快，啊，上帝保佑你！那只是一种习惯。如果你养成快的习惯，那就跟慢一样容易。我应该说，比慢更容易。事实上，如果我在一件事上拖拖拉拉，需要用两倍的时间，那我的健康状况也不允许。上帝保佑！我可不能像某些人那样磨磨蹭蹭吹着口哨干活！你明白，从十二岁起，我就跟马打交道，不是在狩猎马厩就是在赛马饲养训练场。你明白，因为个子小，我还当了好几年赛马骑师。但是，在古德伍德，你明白，草皮很滑，可怜的‘飞燕’摔倒了，我的膝盖摔伤了，所以我当然在那儿派不上用场了。而没有马，我活不下去，肯定活不下去，所以我就来到了旅馆。我可以告诉你，照管这样有教养、有礼貌、讨人喜欢的动物完全是一件快事。上帝保佑你！我可以看出一匹马受的是何等的待遇。给我二十分钟照管马儿，我就能告诉你这马儿有着什么样的马夫。看这匹马儿，可爱、安分，你要他怎么转，他就怎么转，他抬起蹄子接受清洗，或者说，你让他做什么，他就乐意做什么。然后，你会发现另一匹马，不安、烦躁，不愿走正道。或者你一接近他，他就在马厩那端抬起头，垂下耳朵，好像怕你。要不，就是用蹄后跟摆出要攻击你的样子。可怜的东西！我知道他们有过何种待遇。如果本性腼腆，他们就会易受惊或畏缩。如果本性骁勇，他们就会凶猛可怕。他们的脾气大都是小时候养成的。上帝保佑你！他们就像孩子一样，正如《圣经》所说，应该按章法训练好他们，他们长大后，即使遇到考验，也不会背离那脾气。”

“我喜欢听你说话，”詹姆斯说，“我们在家里就是这样做的，是在我们主人家。”

“你家主人是谁，小伙子？如果方便问的话。据我所见，我应该能断定他是一个好主人。”

“他是灯塔山那边伯特维克庄园的戈登先生。”詹姆斯说。

“啊！原来是这样，我听人说起过他。他相马很准，不是吗？是郡里最好的骑手。”

“我相信他是。”詹姆斯说，“但是，自从我们可怜的小主人夭折以来，他就骑得很少了。”

“啊！可怜的先生。当时我从报纸上全都看到了。还有一匹好马也毙了命，是吗？”

“是的，”詹姆斯说，“那可是一匹骏马，就是这匹骏马的兄弟，长得很像他。”

“可惜！可惜啊！”老人说，“如果我记得没错的话，那个地方不适合马儿跳跃。一道稀疏的栅栏挡在高处，陡峭的河堤下面就是小溪，不是吗？马儿不可能看到他的去向。现在，我还是跟所有男人一样赞成大胆去骑。不过，我仍然认为，有些跳跃只有心领神会的老猎手才能做到。一个人和一匹马的生命比狐狸尾巴值钱。至少，我应该说是这样。”

此时，另一个人已经为姜姐洗完了，给我们端来了谷物。随后，詹姆斯和那位老人一起离开了马厩。

第十六章　大火

那天晚上晚些时候，另一个马夫牵进了旅客的一匹马。他正在给马刷洗时，一个嘴里叼着烟斗的年轻人漫步走进了马厩。

“我说，托勒，”马夫说，“请爬上梯子，到阁楼上拿一些干草，铺在这匹马的饲料架上，好吗？不过，要把烟斗放下。”

“好吧。”那个人说着就钻过活板门上去了，我听到他走过头顶的地板，把干草拿了下来。最后，詹姆斯进来看了我们一眼，就锁上了门。

我说不清我睡了多久，也说不清是夜里几点钟了，但是我感到很不舒服，就醒来了，尽管我几乎不知道为什么。我站起来。空气似乎浓烈而呛鼻。我听见姜姐在咳嗽，另一匹马儿好像也焦躁不安。四周漆黑，我什么也看不见，马厩却仿佛浓烟滚滚，我几乎不知道如何喘气。

活板门是开着的，我想烟是从那个地方钻过来的。我侧耳倾听，听到了一阵轻柔而急促的响声以及低沉的噼啪声和断裂声。我不知道那是什么声音，但那声音中有一种奇怪的魔力让我浑身颤抖。其他马儿也都醒了。有的在扯缰绳，有的在跺脚。

最后，我听到了外面的脚步声，那个之前牵旅客的马进来的马夫提着灯笼冲进了马厩，他开始解马缰，想设法把马儿都牵出去。但是，他好像慌里慌张的，自己都被吓坏了，这让我更加恐惧。第一匹马不愿跟他走，于是他设法牵第二匹和第三匹，但他们也不愿挪动。接下来，他又来到我的身边，想设法用力把我拽出马厩，当然也无济于事。他轮流拉遍了我们所有的马儿，之后就离开了马厩。

毫无疑问，我们都非常愚蠢，但是似乎到处都是危险，我们知道没有人值得信任，一切都陌生、无常。透过敞开的门钻进来的新鲜空气使我们的呼吸变得容易了些，而头顶的呼啸声却越来越响。我抬起头来，透过空架上的木杠看到一道红光在墙上一闪一闪的，然后我听到外面有人喊“着火了！”。那个老马夫平静而又迅速地走进来，把一匹马拉出去，然后又去拉另一匹。火焰却在活板门上蔓延，头上的呼啸声真可怕。

接下来，我听到了詹姆斯的声音，像以往那样从容、愉快。

“来，我的美人儿们，我们该离开这儿了，醒一下，跟我来。”我站得离门最近，所以他先来到我的身边，进来时轻轻地拍了拍我。

“来，美人儿，戴上笼头，我的宝贝儿，我们马上离开这个憋闷的地方。”刻不容缓，于是他从脖子上摘下围巾，轻轻地扎在我的眼睛上，一边拍一边哄地把我牵出了马厩。等我们安全到达了院中，他解下我眼睛上的围巾，大声喊道：“来人！牵走这匹马，我去救另一匹。”

一个高大魁梧的男子走上前拉住我，詹姆斯又冲回了马厩。我望着他离去，发出了一声嘶叫。后来姜姐告诉我说，我的那声嘶叫是我能为她做的最好的事儿，因为如果她没有听到我在外面，她是绝不会有勇气走出来的。

院子里乱成了一锅粥。马儿们正从其他马厩被纷纷放出来，四轮马车和双轮马车也正被拉到房子和棚子外面，以免火势蔓延。院子另一头的窗户也被统统打开了，人们喊着各种各样的话，而我始终盯着马厩门，那儿冒出来的烟比之前更浓了，我还能看见红光闪现。不一会儿，我听到一个响亮清澈的声音，它盖过了所有的骚乱声和喧嚣声，我知道那是主人的声音：

“詹姆斯·霍华德！詹姆斯·霍华德！你在那儿吗？”没有回音，但是我听到马厩里有东西坠落的碰撞声。接下来，我发出一声响亮、快乐的嘶鸣，因为我看到詹姆斯正牵着姜姐穿过浓烟向我们走来。姜姐在剧烈地咳嗽，詹姆斯也说不出话来了。

“我勇敢的小伙子！”主人把手放在他的肩上说，“你受伤了吗？”

詹姆斯摇了摇头，因为他还说不出话来。

“唉，”那个扶住我的大个子说，“他是一个勇敢的小伙子，没错。”

“好了，”主人说，“詹姆斯，等你喘过气来后，我们尽快离开这个地方。”说着，我们向门口走去，这时集市上传来了一阵飞奔的马蹄声和隆隆的车轮声。

“消防车来了！消防车来了！”两三个声音喊道，“往后站，让让路！”只见两匹马拉着一辆沉重的消防车冲进了院子，碾得石头发出了隆隆的响声。消防员纵身跳到了地上。没必要问哪儿发生了火灾——火焰巨大，正从屋顶熊熊升起。

我们尽快出去，来到了宽阔寂静的市场上；繁星闪烁，除了我们后面的喧闹声之外，万籁俱寂。主人领着我们去了另一侧的大旅馆。马夫一出来，主人就说道：“詹姆斯，我现在必须赶到女主人那儿去。我把这些马儿全权委托给你，你需要什么，就吩咐马夫去做。”说完，他就走了。主人没有跑，但是我从来没有见过哪个凡人像他那天夜里走得那么快。

我们还没有走进马厩，就听到了一种可怕的声音。是那些留在马厩里快要被活活烧死的可怜的马儿的尖叫声——那可怕极了！这使我和姜姐都很难过。不过，我们被带进了马厩，得到了善待。

第二天早晨，主人过来看我们怎么样了，他跟詹姆斯说话。我没有听到多少，因为马夫正在给我彻底梳刷，但是我看得出詹姆斯喜气扬扬的，我想主人很为他骄傲。我们的女主人夜里受到了极大的惊吓，所以旅行被推迟到了下午，这样詹姆斯上午就有了空闲。他先去那家旅馆查看我们的马具和马车，然后去打听火灾的更多情况。他回来后，我们听到他向马夫讲明了原委。起初，没有人想到大火是怎么引起的，但是最后有个人说他看见迪克·托勒嘴里叼着烟斗走进了马厩，出来时嘴里的烟斗就没有了，他又去酒吧点了一只。随后，那个打下手的马夫说他请迪克爬上梯子拿下了一些干草，但吩咐迪克先放下烟斗。迪克不承认自己叼着烟斗，但是没有人相信他。我还记得我们约翰·曼利的规矩，绝不允许马厩里有烟斗，所以我认为这应该是所有地方的规矩。

詹姆斯说屋顶和地板都塌了，只有那些黑墙立着。有两匹可怜的马儿没能逃脱，被埋在了烧塌的房椽和碎瓦下面。

第十七章　约翰·曼利的一席话

我们余下的旅程都非常轻松，太阳刚落一小会儿，我们就到达了主人的朋友家里。我们被带进了一个干净、温暖、舒适的马厩。那儿有一个善良的马夫，他让我们舒舒服服的。他听说那场火灾后，好像十分欣赏詹姆斯。

“有一件事儿显而易见，年轻人，”他说，“你的马儿知道谁可以信任。世上最难做的事情之一就是，在发生火灾或洪灾时，把马儿从马厩里牵出来。我不知道他们为什么不出来，但是他们就是不愿出来——只有不到二十分之一的马儿愿意。”

我们在这个地方逗留了两三天，然后就回家了。一路上都很顺利。我们都很高兴又回到了自己的马厩，约翰见到我们同样也很高兴。

在他和詹姆斯离开我们去过夜之前，詹姆斯说道：“我想知道谁会来接替我的位置。”

“住在森林小屋的小乔·格林。”约翰说。

“小乔·格林！啊，他还是一个孩子！”

“他十四岁半了。”约翰说。

“可是，他是这样一个小家伙。”

“是的，他很小，却反应敏捷，心甘情愿，心地也善良，再说他也很想来，他的爸爸也这样想。我知道主人想给他这个机会。他说，如果我认为他做不了，他就会物色一个大一点儿的男孩子。但是，我说我非常乐意试用他六周。”

“六周！”詹姆斯说，“啊，要六个月他才能派上大用场！那会让你大费周折的，约翰。”

“啊，”约翰笑着说道，“我和工作是很好的朋友。我还从来没有怕过干活儿呢。”

“你是一个大好人，”詹姆斯说，“我希望自己能成为你那样的人。”

“我通常不谈我自己的事，”约翰说，“但是，既然你要离开我们到大千世界去脱胎换骨，我就想告诉你，我是怎么看待这些事的。我只有约瑟夫这么大的时候，我的爸爸和妈妈十天内相继死于高烧，只留下了我和瘸腿的妹妹奈丽在这个世界上，我们没有一个亲戚可以投奔。我是农夫的孩子，赚不到足够的钱养活自己，更不要说养活我们俩了。要不是我们的女主人（奈丽把女主人称为她的天使，而且她完全有理由这样叫），我的妹妹一定早就去贫民习艺所了。女主人给她和玛勒寡妇租了一个房间，还给她一些力所能及的编织或针线活。她生病时，女主人还给她送饭，给她送好多漂亮舒适的东西，就像妈妈一样照顾她。而主人则把我带到了马厩，在当时的老马夫诺曼手下干活。我在屋里吃饭，在阁楼上睡觉，还有一套衣服，每周三个先令，这样我就能帮助奈丽了。当时还有诺曼。像他这个年龄，本可以转过身说：我不希望被一个只会在耕犁后面瞎跑的毛孩子打扰，而他却像爸爸一样对我，为我没完没了地受苦。几年后，老人家死了，我就接替了他的位置。所以现在我不仅工资最高，而且雨天或晴天都可以休息，奈丽也快乐得像一只小鸟。所以，你看，詹姆斯，我不是那种瞧不起小男孩、惹我们好心的主人生气的人。不，不是！詹姆斯，我会非常想念你，但是我们会渡过难关，当你受到阻碍时，没有比行善更好的事儿了，所以我很高兴我能这样做。”

“这么说，”詹姆斯说，“你不同意‘人不为己，天诛地灭’这句话了？”

“确实不同意。”约翰说，“如果男主人、女主人和老诺曼都是只顾自身利益，那我和奈丽现在会在哪儿？啊，她在贫民习艺所，而我在挖萝卜！如果你只想着自身利益，黑骏马和姜姐会在哪儿呢？啊，已经被大火烤死喽！不，吉姆，不！不管谁用那句话，那都是自私野蛮的说法。如果他只顾想着自己的利益，那么，他在睁开眼睛之前，没有像小狗或小猫那样被溺死，我只会觉得真遗憾，这就是我的想法。”约翰非常坚定地仰了一下头说。

听到这个，詹姆斯呵呵笑了起来。但是，他说话时的声音有一种厚重感：“除了我的妈妈之外，你是我最好的朋友。我希望你不要忘记我。”

“不会，伙计，不会！”约翰说，“如果有可能我一定帮你。我希望你不会忘记我。”

第二天，在詹姆斯离开之前，乔来到了马厩，尽可能学习他所有的一切。他学会了清扫马厩，抱进稻草和干草。他开始清扫马具，帮助清洗马车。他个子太矮，无法照看我和姜姐，詹姆斯就在快乐腿身上给他示范，因为乔要在约翰手下做事，快乐腿就要完全归他管。他是一个聪明可爱的小家伙，总是吹着口哨来干活。

快乐腿对自己被一个他所说的“一无所知的男孩子”“笨手笨脚地拉来拉去”大为生气。但是，两周快结束时，他悄悄地告诉我说，他认为这个小家伙一定会有出息。

詹姆斯不得不离开我们的日子终于到了。尽管他看上去像以往一样快乐，但是那天早晨他心事重重。

“你明白，”他对约翰说，“我要撇下好多好多。我的妈妈和贝特西，还有你，好心的男主人和女主人，以及这些马和我的老快乐腿。到了新地方，我不认识任何人。要不是我会得到一个更高的职位，能更好地帮助我的妈妈，我想我是不会下定决心去那儿的。这真难受啊，约翰。”

“唉，詹姆斯，小伙子，就是这样。如果你第一次离开家没有这种感觉，我是不会器重你的。打起精神，你在那儿会交到朋友的。如果你过得好——你一定会的——那对你的妈妈来说也是一件好事。她会为你去那样一个好地方而骄傲。”

约翰就这样为他加油，但是人人都为要失去詹姆斯而难过。至于快乐腿，在詹姆斯走后好几天，都神情憔悴，完全没有了食欲。于是，好几个早上约翰在训练我时也用一根引领缰绳把他牵出来，让他在我身边小跑和飞奔，这使小家伙又振作了起来，很快他就没事了。

乔的父亲经常过来帮点儿小忙，因为他懂得这项工作。乔非常努力地学习，约翰也对他倍加鼓励。

第十八章　去请医生

詹姆斯离开几天后的一天夜里，我吃过了干草，正躺在稻草里酣睡，突然马厩里铃声大作，把我惊醒了。我听到约翰的房门打开了，他跑到大厅，很快又折返回来。他打开马厩门的锁，走进来，大声叫道：“醒醒，美人儿！你现在必须保持以往的良好状态。”几乎还没等我来得及想，他就已经把鞍子架到了我的背上，把笼头套到了我的头上。他又跑去拿来了外套，然后一路小跑把我拉到了大厅门口。主人手里提着灯站在那儿。

“好了，约翰，”他说，“为了你的生命——也就是为了女主人的生命——快骑吧，一刻也不能耽误。把这封短信给怀特医生送去。到了旅馆，让马休息一下，尽快赶回。”

约翰说：“是，先生。”随后立刻骑上我的背。住在木屋的园丁听到铃响，早就把门打开了。我们奔出庄园，穿过村子，跑下山，来到了关卡。约翰大声叫喊，咚咚敲门。守门人马上打开了大门。

“好了，”约翰说，“请你把门留着等医生，钱给你。”说完，他便又走了。

我们面前有一条漫长平坦的沿河路。约翰对我说：“现在，美人儿，尽力跑吧。”我就尽力跑了起来。我不需要鞭子，也不需要马刺，尽可能快地飞奔了两英里，我相信就是我赢得过纽马克特比赛的老爷爷当时也不可能跑得比我快。当我们来到桥边时，约翰稍微勒住了我，拍了拍我的脖子，“做得不错，美人儿！好伙计，”他说。他本想让我跑慢些，但是我精神抖擞，于是又像先前一样飞奔而去。空气寒冷，月光明亮，非常舒适。我们先是经过一个村子，然后穿过一片黑树林，接下来上山下山，跑了八英里之后，来到了镇上。我们穿过街道，到达集市。万籁俱寂，只有我踩在石头上发出的嘚嘚声——大家都睡着了。我们来到怀特医生家门口时，教堂的钟敲了三下。约翰拉了两次门铃，然后如响雷一般敲门。一扇窗户打开了，怀特医生戴着睡帽伸出头，问道：“你想干吗？”

“戈登夫人病重了，先生。主人想要你马上去。他认为，如果你不能赶到那儿，她就会死。这里有封短信。”

“等一下，”他说，“我这就来。”

他关上窗户，很快就出现在了门口。

“最糟糕的是，”他说，“我的马出去了一天，早已筋疲力尽了。我的儿子也刚被叫出去，他带走了另一匹马。怎么办呢？我可以骑你的马吗？”

“先生，他这一路差不多都在飞奔。我本想让他在这儿休息一下。但是，我想，如果你认为合适，我们的主人就不会反对，先生。”

“好了，”他说，“我很快就准备好了。”

约翰站在我的身边，抚摸我的脖子。我很热。医生拿着马鞭出来了。

“先生，这你不用带，”约翰说，“黑骏马会一直跑到他趴下为止。先生，尽可能照顾他。我不想让他受到任何伤害。”

“不，不会，约翰，”医生说，“我希望不会。”我们立刻就把约翰远远地抛在了身后。

我不愿说回程那段路。医生比约翰重，也不是一个好骑手。不过，我竭尽全力。关卡的那个人还留着门。当我们来到山边时，医生让我停下来，“好了，我的好伙计，”他说，“歇口气吧。”我很高兴他这样做，因为我快筋疲力尽了，那次歇息后，我继续前进，我们很快就到达了庄园。乔站在木屋门口，我的主人站在大厅门口，因为他已经听到我们来了。他没有说一句话，医生跟着他走进屋子，乔把我牵进了马厩。我很高兴回到了家里。我的腿在身下哆嗦，我只能站在那儿喘息。我身上没有一根干毛，汗水顺着我的腿流下来，我浑身冒着热气，乔以前常常说，我就像炉子上的水壶一样。可怜的乔！他还年小，知之甚少，他的父亲本来可以帮他，却被派到邻村去了。但是，我相信他已经竭尽全力做了自己知道的事儿。他揉着我的腿和胸，他却没有给我盖上暖布。他认为我这么热，一定不喜欢暖布。随后，他给了我一桶水喝。水很冷，很好喝，我全都把它喝完了。接着，他又给了我一些干草和谷物，以为自己干得不错，就走了。不久，我就开始颤抖和战栗，浑身冰冷。我的腿疼，我的腰疼，我的胸疼，我感到浑身都疼。噢！当我站在那儿打战时，我是多么想要那块温暖的厚布啊！我想要约翰，而他要步行八英里才能到这里，于是我躺在稻草里设法让自己入睡。过了好一阵子，我听见约翰来到了门口。我发出了一声低沉的呻吟，因为我非常痛苦。他立刻来到我的身边，弯下腰。尽管我无法把自己的感受告诉他，但是他似乎明白这一切。他给我盖了两三块暖布，然后跑到屋里，端来一些热水。他给我做了一些热粥让我喝，随后我想我就睡着了。

约翰似乎大为恼火。我听到他在一遍又一遍地自言自语道：“笨小子！笨小子！居然没有盖布，我敢说水也是冷的。男孩子真没用。”不过，乔毕竟是一个好孩子。

我现在病得很重，肺部严重感染，呼吸起来都很痛苦。约翰夜以继日地照料我。为了来看我，他夜里要起来两三次。我的主人也经常来看我。“我可怜的美人儿，”有一天，主人对我说，“我的好马儿，你救了女主人的命，美人儿。是的，是你救了她的命。”听到这话，我很高兴，因为好像医生也说过，如果我们再耽搁时间长点儿，就为时已晚了。约翰告诉主人说，他这一生从来没有见过跑得这么快的马儿。这匹马儿好像知道发生了什么事儿。我当然知道，尽管约翰不这样想。至少，我差不多知道——我和约翰必须以最快的速度奔跑，这都是为了女主人。

第十九章　只怪无知

我不知道自己病了多久。马医邦德先生每天都来。有一天，他给我放血治疗，约翰接了一桶。之后，我感觉很晕，以为自己要死了，我相信他们也都是这样想的。

姜姐和快乐腿都被移到了别的马厩，这样我就可以静养了，因为发烧让我的听觉非常灵敏，任何一点儿风吹草动在我听来都格外响亮。我能听得出从房子里走进走出的每个人的脚步声，我知道发生的一切。一天夜里，约翰不得不给我吃药，托马斯·格林进来帮他。我吃过药后，约翰尽可能让我舒服些，他说他会在这儿待半小时看药效如何。托马斯说要陪着他，于是他们就到安放在快乐腿马厩里的长凳上坐下，把灯笼放在他们的脚边，这样我就不会受到光线打扰了。

两人静静地坐了一会儿，随后托马斯·格林低声说道：

“约翰，我希望你能对乔说点儿好话。那个孩子伤心欲裂，他既吃不下饭，也不会笑了。他说，他知道这都是他的过错，尽管他确信自己已经尽力了。他说，如果美人儿死了，没有人会再对他说话。听到他这样说，我真伤心。我想你就跟他说句话吧，他不是一个坏孩子。”

停了一会儿，约翰慢慢地说道：“你不能对我这样苛刻，汤姆。我知道他无意造成伤害，我从来没有说过他是故意的。我知道他不是个坏孩子。不过，你明白，我自己也很痛苦。那匹马是我内心的骄傲，更不要说他是男主人和女主人的心肝宝贝了。一想到他的生命可能会以这种方式被夺去，我真受不了。但是，如果你认为我对那个男孩子苛刻，明天我会尽力对他说句好话——也就是说，如果美人儿好转的话。”

“好的，约翰，谢谢你。我就知道你不希望自己过于苛刻。我很高兴你明白这仅仅是无知。”

约翰回答时的声音差点儿吓了我一跳：

“仅仅是无知！仅仅是无知！你怎么能说这仅仅是无知呢？你不知道这是世界上仅次于邪恶的最坏的事儿吗？只有上天知道无知造成的最严重伤害。如果有人能说出：‘噢！我不知道，我没有任何恶意。’他们觉得这就没事了。我想，玛莎·穆尔沃什开伤风合剂和起镇定作用的糖浆时，并不想杀死那个婴儿，而她的确害死了那个婴儿，因杀人罪受到了审判。”

“她也是罪有应得，”汤姆说，“如果一个女人不知道什么对婴儿有益，什么对婴儿有害，就不该去护理一个娇嫩的小孩子。”

约翰继续说道：“比尔·斯塔基扮成鬼在月光下追他的弟弟，并不想把弟弟吓得魂飞魄散，但是他那样做了。那个聪明英俊的小伙子本来可以成为任何一位母亲心中的骄傲，现在却成了一个白痴，即使他活到八十岁，也绝不会像从前那样聪明了。你自己也深受其害，汤姆。两周前，那些小姐敞开你的温室门，结果一阵严寒的东风正好刮进来。你说，那场风冻死了你的好多植物。”

“好多！”汤姆说，“嫁接的嫩枝条没有一个不被吹折。我不得不再插一遍，最糟糕的是，我都不知道去哪儿找新鲜枝条。当我进来看到她们做的一切时，都快疯了。”

“但是，”约翰说，“我肯定那些小姐不是存心的，那仅仅是无知！”

我没有再听见这番谈话，因为药效良好，让我睡着了。到了第二天早上，我感觉好多了。而当我最终更多地了解了这个世界时，我常常想起约翰说的这番话。

第二十章　乔·格林

乔·格林进展良好。他学得很快，体贴周到，约翰在好多事情上开始信任他了。而正如我所说，他的个子在那个年龄显得矮小，所以他很少能获准来训练我或姜姐。但是，碰巧一天早上，约翰赶着正义拉着行李车出去了，主人想要把一封短信马上送到大约三英里远的一位先生的家里，就吩咐乔给我套上马鞍，把短信送去，同时告诫乔骑马时要小心。

送过短信后，我们静静地走在返程路上。路过砖厂时，我们看到一辆满载砖块的马车，轮子死死地卡在了硬泥地深深的车辙里。马夫大喊大叫着，毫不留情地抽打那两匹马。乔停住了脚步。那真是一幅悲惨的景象。两匹马竭尽全力绷紧身体要把马车拉出来，但是就是拉不动。他们的腿和侧腹都像小溪般流着汗，身体的两边起伏着，每块肌肉都绷紧了，而那个男人却凶神恶煞般地拽着前面那匹马的头，破口大骂，极其野蛮地抽打他们。

“别打了，”乔说，“别再那样抽打这些马了。车轮陷得太深了，他们拉不出来。”那个人毫不理会，继续抽打。

“停下！请停下！”乔说，“我来帮你卸车。现在他们拉不动。”

“管好你自己的事儿，你这个无礼的小坏蛋，我会管好自己的事儿！”那个人正在气头上，更糟糕的是还借着酒劲儿，又将鞭子甩了下来。乔调转我的头，接着我们朝砖石场主人的家全速奔去。我不敢说约翰是不是会同意我们这样跑，我和乔的想法却是一样的，我们都非常生气，所以不可能慢慢腾腾地走。

房子就在路边。乔敲了敲门，大声喊道：“喂！克莱先生在家吗？”门打开了，克莱先生本人走了出来。

“你好，年轻人！你好像很急。主人今天早上有什么吩咐吗？”

“没有，克莱先生，而你的砖厂里却有一个家伙要把两匹马打死了。我让他住手，他不愿住手。我说我愿帮他卸车，他也不愿意。所以，我就来告诉你。先生，请你去一趟吧。”乔的声音因激动而颤抖。

“谢谢你，小伙子，”那个人说着就跑去拿帽子，接着又停了一下，“如果我把那个家伙送到法官那儿，你愿意出庭作证吗？”

“我愿意，”乔说，“也很乐意。”那个人走后，我们就步伐矫健地走在了回家的路上。

“啊，乔，你出了什么事儿？看上去你非常生气。”当这个男孩子从马鞍上跳下时，约翰问。

“我非常生气，我可以告诉你。”说着，男孩子用急切兴奋的话语把发生的一切都告诉了约翰。乔通常是一个文静温和的小家伙，所以看到他被这样激怒，真是让人惊奇。

“对，乔！不管那家伙收没收到传票，你都做得对，我的孩子。好多人都会骑过去，说这不是他们应该干涉的事儿。现在我要说，如果看到有人虐待和压迫，每个人都应该干涉。你做得对，我的孩子。”

此时，乔镇定自如，约翰的赞赏让他自豪。于是，他给我擦蹄子和身体时，手比以往更加坚定有力。

乔和约翰刚要离开马厩回去吃饭，这时男仆来到了马厩，他说主人要乔立即去他的房间。有人被指控虐待马匹，他们需要乔的证词。乔满脸红光，两眼熠熠生辉。“他们会得到证据的。”他说。

“你把自己收拾齐整点儿。”约翰说。乔拉了拉领带，拽了拽夹克，立刻就去了。我们的主人作为郡里的地方法官之一，经常会有案子送给他审理，或者由他说应该怎么判。在马厩里，我们有一段时间都没有再听到什么，因为那是人们吃饭的时间，而当乔又回到马厩时，我看到他兴致高昂，他和善地拍了拍我，说道：“我们再也不会看到这种事儿发生了，对吗，老伙计？”后来，我们听说他非常清晰地提供了证据，那两匹马当时是那样筋疲力尽，身上留下了受虐待的累累伤痕，结果马夫受到了审判，有可能被判两三个月监禁。

乔身上发生这么大的变化，真是喜人。约翰哈哈大笑，说乔那一周长高了一英寸，我相信他已经长高了。他还是像以前那样善良温和，而他做任何事情都更加意志坚定了——好像他一下子从男孩子变成了男子汉。

第二十一章　分别

如今，我已经在这个快乐的地方生活了三年，而凄惨的变化即将来到我们身边。我们不时地听到夫人生病的消息。医生经常来家里，看上去主人神情沉重忧虑。后来，我们听说，夫人必须马上离开家，去一个温暖的国家待两三年。全家人听到这个消息，就像听到丧钟一样。大家都很难过。但是，主人立即就开始着手安排变卖家产离开英国的事儿了。我们经常在马厩里听到人们谈论这个话题。实际上，他们不再提别的话题了。

约翰工作时沉默伤感，乔几乎也不吹口哨了。有好多事儿需要来来回回跑腿，我和姜姐满负荷工作。

第一批走的是杰西小姐和弗罗拉小姐，还有她们的女家庭教师。她们过来跟我们道别。像老朋友一样拥抱了可怜的快乐腿，他的确是她们的老朋友。后来，我们听说了主人对我们的安排。主人把我和姜姐卖给了他的老朋友W勋爵，因为他认为我们在那儿会有一个好归宿。他把快乐腿送给了牧师，那个牧师正为布罗姆菲尔德夫人找一匹小马，而主人的条件是他们永远不能卖掉快乐腿，等他干不动活后，就开枪射杀并埋葬他。

乔应邀照顾快乐腿，帮衬家事，所以我认为快乐腿过得不错。约翰受到好几个好地方的聘请，他却说他还是再等一等、看一看。

他们离开的前一晚，主人走进马厩来给一些叮嘱，也来给他的马儿们最后的爱抚。他似乎情绪非常低落。我能通过他的声音知道这一点。我相信我们马儿比好多人都更能心领神会。

“你已经决定做什么了吗，约翰？”他问，“我发现你没有接受任何聘请。”

“没有，先生。我已经下定决心了，如果我能得到一个跟一流的幼马调教师和驯马师一样的工作，那对我来说是再恰当不过的事了。好多幼马因受到不当的对待而受惊和受伤，如果有合适的人训练他们，就不会有这种事儿了。我总是跟马儿相处得很好，如果我能帮助他们中的一些拥有一个良好的开端，我就会认为自己像是在做善事。你对此有什么看法，先生？”

“我不知道哪儿有这样的人，”主人说，“我想你再合适不过了。你懂马，不晓得什么缘故，马也懂你，你最后会自立门户。我想你的打算再好不过了。如果有任何我可以帮你的地方，就给我写信。我会交代我驻伦敦的代理人，并向他推荐你。”

主人把代理人的姓名和地址告诉了约翰，然后对他长期忠诚的服务表示感谢。这可让约翰承受不起。“求你别说了，先生，我担待不起。你和夫人为我做了这么多，我永远都无法报答。但是，先生，我们永远不会忘记你，如有可能的话，我们有朝一日就会重新看到夫人回来。我们必须心存希望，先生。”主人跟约翰握了握手，却没有说话，他们俩离开了马厩。

悲伤的一天终于来了。男仆和那些重行李前一天已经走了，只剩下主人、夫人和她的女仆。我和姜姐最后一次把马车拉到了大厅门口。仆人从屋里取出了垫子、旅行毛毯和好多其他东西。当一切都安排好后，主人抱着夫人走下楼梯（我就在房子旁边，所以能看到发生的一切）。他小心翼翼地把她放进马车，家仆们都围站在马车四周失声痛哭。

“再见，”他说，“我们不会忘记你们任何人。”说着，他坐进车里——“发车吧，约翰。”

乔跳上车，我们慢慢地小跑着驶出庄园，穿过村子，村里人都站在家门口看主人他们最后一眼，说道：“上帝保佑他们。”

我们到达火车站时，我想夫人下了马车，走到了候车室。我听到她用自己独有的甜美声音说道：“再见，约翰。上帝保佑你。”我感到缰绳骤然一抽，约翰却没有应答，也许他说不出话来。乔刚把马车上的东西卸下来，约翰就让他站在马儿旁边，他则上了月台。可怜的乔！他靠近我们的脑袋站在那儿，遮掩自己的眼泪。火车很快就喷着蒸汽进站了，两三分钟后，车门砰地关上，列车员吹响了哨子，火车滑行而去，只留下了一团团白烟和几颗十分沉重的心。

等完全看不见火车后，约翰才回来。

“我们再也见不到她了，”他说，“再也见不到了。”他拿起缰绳，坐上驾驶座，跟乔一起慢慢地驾车回家，而现在那已经不是我们的家了。

第二十二章　伯爵府

第二天早饭后，乔把快乐腿套进夫人那辆低矮的轻便马车，要赶他到牧师家去。乔先来跟我们道别，快乐腿从院子里向我们嘶叫了一声。之后，约翰给姜姐套上马鞍，给我套上牵引缰绳，驾着我们越过田野，走了大概十五英里，来到了伯爵府庄园，这就是W伯爵生活的地方。那是一座非常漂亮的房子，有好多马厩。我们穿过石门，走进院子。约翰求见约克先生。过了一段时间，约克先生才出来。他是一个相貌英俊的中年男人，他的声音立刻透露出他期望别人服从他。他对约翰非常友好，彬彬有礼。他微微看了我和姜姐一眼后，叫一个马夫把我们牵到了马厩，然后邀请约翰去吃点心。

我们被牵到了一个明亮通风的马厩，并被安置在了相邻的两个畜栏里，在那儿接受刷洗和喂食。大约半小时后，约翰和即将成为我们新马夫的约克先生进来看我们。

“那么，曼利先生，”他在仔细相看过我俩后说，“我看这两匹马没有任何毛病。不过，我们都知道，马儿也像人一样有自己的特性，有时他们需要不同的待遇。我想知道，这两匹马有没有什么你想提的特别之处？”

“噢，”约翰说，“我相信，在乡下再也找不出比这两匹马更好的一对搭档了。要跟他们分开，我真伤心，而他们并非一模一样。那匹黑马是我见过的性情最好的马儿。我想，他从小时候起就从来不知道什么是难听的话、什么是殴打，他所有的乐趣好像就是做你想要做的事儿。不过，我想，那匹红棕马以前一定受过虐待。我们从马贩子那儿也听到了好多。她刚来时暴躁多疑，而当她发现我们这儿是何种地方时，她的坏脾气就渐渐地消失了。我三年都没有见她有过一丁点儿发脾气的迹象。如果好好对她，就再没有比她更出色、更顺从的动物了。但是，她天生比那匹黑马更易怒。同样面对苍蝇，她比黑马更烦躁，同样面对有哪儿不舒服的马具她也比黑马更焦急。如果被虐待或受到不公正待遇，她肯定会针锋相对。你知道好多骁勇的马儿都会这样做。”

“当然，”约克说，“我完全理解。不过，你知道，在这样的马厩里，要让所有马夫都以恰当的方式工作并不容易。我会尽全力。我必须走了。你对那匹母马的介绍，我会记住的。”

他们正要离开马厩，这时约翰停下来，说道：“我最好提一下，我们从来不给这两匹马用勒马缰绳。黑马从来没有戴过，马贩子说过，衔铁搞坏了另一匹马的脾气。”

“好了，”约克说，“如果他们来这儿，那就必须戴勒马缰绳。我自己喜欢放松缰绳，主人总是对马儿通情达理。但是，我家夫人——则是另一回事。她喜欢时尚，如果她的拉车马没有紧紧地勒高马头，她就不会看他们一眼。我总是反对给马戴衔铁，还会继续反对，而夫人骑马时，则必须勒高系牢！”

“我对此表示遗憾，非常遗憾。”约翰说，“但是，我现在必须走了，否则我就赶不上火车了。”

他绕过来，逐一走到我们的身边，最后一次拍了拍我们，对我们说了说话，他的声音听上去非常悲伤。

我把脸凑向他，我只能这样做来道别。随后，他就走了，我从此再也没有见过他。

第二天，W勋爵来看我们，他好像对我们的外表非常满意。

“我对这两匹马大有信心，”他说，“我的朋友戈登先生已经向我介绍过他们的性格。当然，他们在毛色上并不搭配，而我的想法是，他们在乡下拉拉马车倒是挺不错。在去伦敦之前，我必须设法找一匹跟男爵搭配的马儿。我相信，驾那匹黑马再合适不过了。”

于是，约克把约翰对他说的关于我们的信息都告诉了他。

“好吧，”他说，“你一定要留意那匹母马，让导向缰绳放松。我敢说，开始时稍微迁就一下，他们会做得非常出色。这事儿我会对夫人说的。”

下午，我们被戴上了马具，套上了马车。马厩里的钟刚敲了三下，我们就被牵着绕到了房子前面。房子都非常宽大，有伯特维克庄园老房子的三四倍大。但是，如果马儿可以发表意见的话，那就是，不如以前庄园的一半惬意。两个男仆穿着土褐色制服、鲜红色马裤和白色长袜，站在那儿严阵以待。

不一会儿，我们就听到了夫人走下石阶楼梯时传来的丝绸裙的飒飒声。她绕圈打量了我们一番。她个子高挑，样子傲慢，好像对什么事儿感到不满，却一言不发，直接坐进了马车。这是第一次戴勒马缰绳，我必须说，尽管不能让我的头偶尔低下来确实讨厌，但是它也没有把我的头拉得比我习惯支撑的更高。我为姜姐感到担忧，而她似乎从容满足。

第二天三点钟，我们又来到了门口，还是先前那两个男仆。我们听到了丝绸裙的飒飒声，夫人走下了台阶，以命令的口气说道：“约克，你必须把这些马的脑袋再抬高些，他们让人看着不顺眼。”

约克鞠了一躬，毕恭毕敬地说：“请原谅，夫人，这两匹马可都有三年没上过勒马缰绳了。主人说，为了更安全，还是让他们逐步适应吧。不过，如果您乐意的话，我可以让他们再抬高点儿。”

“就这样做。”她说。

约克绕到我们的头边，亲自把缰绳勒短了些——我想，勒进去了一个孔眼。无论如何，每勒进去一点儿，感觉都会大不一样。那天，我们要爬一段陡峭的山路。这时，我开始明白了我曾经听到过的一切。当然，我想把头往前伸，像以前经常做的那样努力把马车拉上去。但是，不行，我现在不得不抬高脑袋，这让我耗尽了精力，发力全靠背部和腿部。我们到达后，姜姐说：“现在你明白是什么滋味了吧，而这还不算糟。只要情况不会大大恶化，我就什么也不会说，因为我们在这儿受到了优待。但是，如果想紧紧勒高我的头，他们就要当心了！我可受不了，也不愿忍受。”

一天天，一个孔眼一个孔眼，我们的导向缰绳越来越短了，我不再像从前那样愉快地期盼戴上马具了，而是开始害怕它了。姜姐也显得烦躁不安，尽管她话语不多。最后，我想最糟糕的已经结束了，好几天都没有再缩短缰绳，我决定将就着尽职尽责，尽管现在工作成了一种持续不断的伤害，而非快事，但最糟糕的还没有到来。

第二十三章　为自由而战

一天，夫人比平常下来晚了些，丝绸裙的飒飒声比以往更响了。

“赶车去B公爵夫人家。”她说，停了一下后，又说道，“你永远都不打算抬高这些马的脑袋了吗，约克？立刻抬高他们的脑袋，不要让我们再看到这种迁就和胡闹了。”

约克先来到我的身边，马夫站在姜姐的头边。约克把我的脑袋向后拽，把缰绳勒得紧紧的，我都快受不了了。随后，他走到姜姐的身边，姜姐正不耐烦地上下甩头跟嚼子较劲儿，似乎现在她又回到老做派了。她对将要发生的事儿心生妙计，为了收紧缰绳，约克刚把缰绳从鞍环上取下来，她就趁机突然扬起前蹄，后腿立起，狂暴地踢在了约克的鼻子上，踢掉了他的帽子。马夫也差点儿被踢倒。他们俩立即飞奔到她的身前，她却跟他们对抗，继续猛烈前冲，后腿站起，不顾一切地踢蹬。最后，她在我左后腿上踢了一下后，正好踢到了车辕上，摔倒在地。要不是约克迅速坐到她的头上，不让她挣扎，还不知道下一步她会搞什么鬼呢。与此同时，约克大声喊道：“解开黑马！快去拿摇柄，拧掉车辕上的螺丝。如果你们解不开，就来一个人割断这缰绳！”一个男仆跑去拿摇柄，另一个从屋里拿来了刀子。马夫很快就把我从姜姐和马车那儿解救了出来，牵进了畜栏。他刚把我放进去，就跑回了约克那儿。我对发生的一切非常激动。如果说我过去习惯踢人或后腿站立的话，我相信当时我也会那样做，而我从来没有那样做过，所以我就站在那儿生气，腿部疼痛，头仍被紧勒到了鞍环上，无法低头。我万分痛苦，无论是谁第一个靠近我，我都很想踢上一脚。

然而，不久以后，姜姐总算被两个马夫牵了进来，身上被打得青一块紫一块。约克跟她一起来的，他吩咐了几句，然后过来看我。他立刻放下我的头。

“该死的勒马缰绳！”他自言自语说，“我想我们很快就会倒霉了——主人会大为恼火。但是，在这儿，如果女人的丈夫都不能管教她，仆人当然就做不到了。所以，我也洗手不干了。如果她到不了公爵夫人的游园会，我也就无能为力了。”

约克没有在人前说过这一点。当有人在场时，他说话总是毕恭毕敬。现在，他抚摸我的全身，很快找到了我被踢到的后腿跗关节上方的那个地方，那儿非常肿痛。他吩咐用热水给我擦洗一下，然后上了一些药剂。

得知发生的一切后，W勋爵非常恼火。他责怪约克向夫人让步，约克回答说他今后更喜欢只接受先生的命令。而我认为这没有任何作用，因为情况还是像从前那样持续下去。我还以为约克可以更好地保护他的马儿们，也许我没有判断力。

姜姐再也没有被套进马车，而当她伤好后，伯爵的一个小儿子说想要她，他确信姜姐一定会是一匹好猎马。而我仍旧被迫拉车，而且有了一个新搭档，名叫马克斯。他始终习惯绷紧的缰绳。我问他是怎么忍受这一切的。

“噢，”他说，“我之所以忍受，是因为我必须这样。但是，这种缰绳会缩短我的生命。如果你不得不戴下去的话，那也会缩短你的生命。”

“你认为，”我问，“我们的主人知道这对我们有多么糟糕吗？”

“我说不上来。”他说，“但是，马贩子和马医都非常清楚。我当时还在马贩子那儿，他正训练我和另一匹马搭档。他要我们抬高头，像他说的那样，每天高一点儿高一点儿。当时那儿有一位先生问他为什么这样做。‘因为，’他说，‘如果我们不这样做，别人就不买他们。伦敦人总是想要他们的马儿把头抬高，把腿抬高。当然，这样对马来说非常糟糕，却有利于交易。马儿很快就会疲惫或得病，他们就会来再买一对。’”马克斯说，“这就是我亲耳听他说的。你可以自己判断。”

我给夫人拉车的漫长的四个月遭受的痛苦，真是难以形容。我完全相信，如果这种痛苦再持续更久的话，我的健康或好脾气就会垮掉。此前，我从来不知道什么是口吐白沫，而现在锋利的嚼子在我的舌头和下颚活动，头部和喉咙深受压迫，总会让我的嘴巴泛起或多或少的白沫。看到这个，有些人认为很好，说：“多么出色、多么精神的牲口！”然而，就像人口吐白沫一样，马口吐白沫也是不正常的，这是一种不适的确切征兆，说明马儿应该得到照顾。除此以外，我的气管也有压迫感，常常让我的呼吸很不舒服。我干完活儿回来后，脖子和胸部都紧张痛苦，嘴和舌头都很疼，感觉疲惫沮丧。

在原来那个家，我始终知道约翰和我的主人是我的朋友。然而，在这儿，尽管我在好多方面都受到优待，但是我没有朋友。约克也许已经知道，很有可能真的知道缰绳对我是何等的折磨。不过，我想他把这当成理所当然却又无能为力的事儿。无论如何，什么也解救不了我。

第二十四章　安妮小姐

早春时节，W伯爵和一部分家庭成员去了伦敦，还带去了约克。我和姜姐，还有其他几匹马，都被留在家里备用，马夫领班留下来照料。

留在庄园里的哈丽特小姐是一个重病患者，从来不坐马车出门。安妮小姐喜欢跟她的兄弟或堂兄弟们一道骑马。她是一个无可挑剔的女骑手，不仅漂亮，而且快乐、温和。她选我作她的坐骑，还给我起名叫黑风。我非常喜欢这样兜风，在清爽的空气中跟姜姐或莉齐一起奔跑。这个莉齐是一匹机灵的红棕色母马，几乎是纯种马，因为动作优雅、性情活泼，所以颇受男士们宠爱。但是，姜姐比我更了解她，她告诉我说莉齐相当胆怯。

庄园里住有一个名叫布兰泰尔的先生，他总是骑莉齐，对她赞不绝口。有一天，安妮小姐吩咐把女鞍架到莉齐的身上，另一副鞍子架到我的身上。当我们来到门口时，那位先生似乎非常不安。

“这是怎么回事？”他问，“你对你的好黑风厌倦了吗？”

“噢，不，一点儿也不，”她答道，“我可是善心大发，让你也骑他一次，我来试骑你的迷人的莉齐。我必须承认，她在尺寸和外观上都比我最爱的黑风更有女士坐骑的样子。”

“请让我忠告你，不要骑她，”他说，“她是一匹迷人的马儿，可对女士来说她过于紧张。我确切地告诉你，她很不安全，我还是求你把马鞍换过来吧。”

“亲爱的表兄，”安妮小姐笑道，“请善良体贴的你不要为我费心了。我从孩提时就已经开始骑马了，尽管我知道你不赞成姑娘们打猎，但是我已经跟着马队狩猎好几次了。这可是事实，你们男士们都这样喜欢这个莉齐，我就想试试。请你帮我骑上去吧，好朋友就要有好朋友的样子。”

他没再说什么，小心翼翼地把她扶上马鞍，看了看嚼子和马勒，把缰绳轻轻地放进她的手里，随后骑到了我的身上。我们正要离开，一个男仆带着一片纸以及哈丽特小姐的口信走了出来——“他们能帮她去阿什利医生家问问这个问题，然后带来回复吗？”

村子大概有一英里远，医生家是村里的最后一家。我们一路兴高采烈地来到了他家大门口。他的房子坐落在高大的常青树丛中，离大门还有一小段车程。

布兰泰尔在大门口下马，正要为安妮小姐开门，她却说道：“我在这儿等你，你可以把黑风的缰绳拴在大门上。”

他怀疑地看着她。“我不到五分钟就回来。”他说。

“噢，别着急。我和莉齐是不会从你这儿逃跑的。”

他把我的缰绳拴在一根铁钉上，很快就消失在了树丛中。莉齐静静地站在路边，背对着我，离我有几步远。我的年轻小姐手挽着松弛的缰绳，悠然自得地坐在那儿，哼着小曲。我一直听着布兰泰尔先生的脚步声，直到他到了房前，我还听到他敲门的声音。大路的另一边是一片牧场，大门敞开着。就在此时，一些拉车马和几匹小马毫无秩序地跑了出来，后面一个男孩子正啪啪地抽着一根大鞭子。那些小马野性调皮，其中一匹跑过大路，踉踉跄跄地撞在了莉齐的后腿上。我说不清，是怪那匹愚笨的小马，还是怪响亮的甩鞭声，或者是两者兼而有之，反正莉齐猛地踢了一脚，飞快地狂奔而去。这一切突如其来，安妮小姐差点儿从马上摔下来，她却又很快坐稳了身子。我发出了响亮尖锐的嘶叫，进行求救。我一遍又一遍地嘶叫，焦急地刨着地面，甩着脑袋，想挣脱缰绳。我早就等不及了。布兰泰尔先生跑到大门边，他神情忧虑地环顾四周，当时只看到大路的远处有飞驰而去的身影。他立即翻身上马。我无需他策马扬鞭，因为我和骑手一样迫不及待。他看出了这一点，放松缰绳，微微前倾，我们向她们追去。

我们跑了大约一英里半的直路，然后向右转，接着路分成了两条。我们还远没有跑到拐弯处，她就从视野中消失了。她拐向哪条路了呢？一个女人正站在花园门口，手搭凉棚，急切地望着大路。布兰泰尔先生几乎没有勒缰减速就大声喊道：“哪边？”“右边。”那女人手指着右边大声说道，我们沿着右边的路继续追赶。随后，曾有一刻，我们看见了安妮小姐。又一个拐弯，她再次失去了影踪。有好几次，我们都是瞥见人影，随即又跟丢了，好像根本接近不了她们。一个老修路工站在一堆石头近旁，铁锹掉落，两手举起。我们走近时，他做出要说话的手势。布兰泰尔稍微拉了一下缰绳。“去公地了，先生，去公地了。她拐到那儿去了。”我非常熟悉这个公地；大部分地面都很不平坦，长满了石南丛和深绿色的荆豆灌木丛，到处都是灌木丛生的老荆棘树；还有一些长着茂密矮草的空地，到处都是蚁山和鼹鼠洞。据我所知，这是最不适宜急速飞奔的地方。

我们还没追到公地那儿，便又看见那身绿色骑装在我们前方飞奔。小姐的帽子不见了，棕色长发在身后飘动。她的头和身体后仰，好像正用剩下的全部体力拽着缰绳，而这力量似乎也快要耗尽了。显而易见，路面的起伏已经让莉齐大大减速，看来我们有机会追上她了。

刚才我们在大路上奔跑时，布兰泰尔放开了我的头。但是，现在他凭借轻柔的手和训练有素的眼睛引领我前进，颇具大师风范。我们的速度丝毫没有放慢，我们正在果断地逼近她们。

大约在石南丛生的荒地的半道上，有一条刚挖的宽沟，挖出来的泥土胡乱地堆在另一边。这肯定会让她们停下来！但是，没有。莉齐几乎没有停顿，就纵身跳起，绊在了那些粗硬的土块上，摔倒在地。布兰泰尔低吟道：“哎，黑风，竭尽全力啊！”他牢牢地拉住我的缰绳。我振作精神，果断一跃，跳过了沟岸。

可怜的小姐脸朝下趴在灌木丛中，一动不动。布兰泰尔跪下来，叫她的名字，却没有任何声音。他轻轻地扳起她的脸，只见她脸色惨白，眼睛闭合。“安妮，亲爱的安妮，请说话！”但是，没有回答。他解开她的骑装，松开她的领口，摸着她的手和手腕，然后突然站起，疯狂地环顾四周想要求救。

不远处有两个人在割草皮，他们看到莉齐狂奔着，背上没有骑手，就放下手里的活儿去追她。

布兰泰尔的呼唤声很快把他们引到了现场。最先赶到的男子见此情景显得非常不安，问他能做什么。

“你会骑马吗？”

“啊，先生，我不大会骑。但是，为了安妮小姐，我愿意冒断脖子的危险。她那年冬天对我的妻子好极了。”

“那就骑上这匹马，我的朋友——你的脖子会相当安全——骑马去医生那儿，叫他立刻过来——然后去庄园——把你知道的一切都告诉他们，让他们把那辆马车送过来，带上安妮小姐的女仆和帮手。我就留在这儿。”

“好吧，先生。我会竭尽全力，我恳求上帝让我可爱的年轻小姐立刻睁开眼睛。”随后，他望着赶来的第二个人大声喊道：“嗨，乔，跑去端些水来，叫我的妻子尽快到安妮小姐这儿来。”

随后，他总算爬上了马鞍，两腿一夹我的两侧，“驾”的一声，稍微绕开那个沟渠，开始上路。他手里没有鞭子，这好像让他感到不安。但是，我的脚步很快就消除了他的不安，他发现他能做的最好的事儿就是紧紧地贴住马鞍，夹住我，他果断地这样做了。我尽可能少晃他，而在崎岖的地面上，他大声叫道：“稳住！喔！稳住！”到了大路上，我们就平安无事了。在医生家和在庄园里，他跑腿的活儿做得诚实可靠。他们请他喝点儿东西。“不，不，”他说，“我要穿过田地抄近路返回他们那儿，要赶在马车之前回到那儿。”

得知消息后，家里好一阵忙乱和骚动。我刚被带进畜栏，就被摘下了马鞍和笼头，身上盖上了一块布。

姜姐被套上鞍子后，就匆匆忙忙出发了，她要去找乔治勋爵。我不久便听到马车驶出了院子。

好像过了很久，姜姐才回来，又过了很久，畜栏中才只剩我们两个。她把自己看到的一切都告诉了我。

“我能说得不多，”她说，“我们差不多是一路飞奔，到那儿时，医生刚好骑马赶到。只见一个女人坐在地上，小姐的头枕在她的腿上。医生向她嘴里倒了些东西，而我听见的一切就是‘她没死’。随后，我被一个人牵到了不远处。过了一会儿，她被抬进了马车，我们就一起回家了。我听到主人对一个拦住他询问的人说，他希望没有骨折，但是她还没有开口说话。”

当乔治勋爵带姜姐去打猎时，约克摇了摇头。他说，猎马的第一个训练季，应该找一个稳妥的人驯马，而不是像乔治勋爵这样随意的骑手。

姜姐过去非常喜欢打猎，而有时她回来后，我能看出她非常疲惫，她偶尔会短暂地咳嗽一下。她兴致勃勃，没有抱怨，我却还是禁不住为她感到担忧。

事发两天后，布兰泰尔先生过来看我。他拍了拍我，对我大加赞扬。他告诉乔治勋爵说，他相信那匹马像他一样知道安妮的危险。“我就是想挡都挡不住他，”他说，“她绝不应该骑任何其他的马。”从他们的对话中，我得知我的年轻小姐现在脱离了危险，不久又能骑马了。这对我来说是一个喜讯，我盼望幸福的生活。

第二十五章　鲁宾·史密斯

现在，我必须说说鲁宾·史密斯。约克去伦敦后，鲁宾·史密斯留下来接管了马厩。没有人比他更精通业务了。当他一切正常时，没有一个人能比他更忠诚、更有价值。他管马时性情温和，十分机智，因为他曾跟一个外科兽医合住过两年，所以他差不多还可以给马看病。他驾车一流，无论是四马马车还是两马马车，他都能轻松驾驶。他相貌英俊，学识渊博，举止非常文雅。我相信大家都喜欢他，当然，马也喜欢他。唯一让人惊讶的是，他竟然处在一种低下的地位，而不是像约克一样处在马夫头儿的位置。不过，他有一个极大的缺点，那就是爱喝酒。他不像有些男人那样总是喝个不停，他总是几个星期或几个月保持节制，之后酒瘾就会爆发，像约克所说的那样，狂喝一阵，既丢自己的脸，又让他的妻子胆战心惊，还会给跟他有关的一切带来麻烦。然而，他非常得力，所以约克把这件事隐瞒了两三次，没有让伯爵知道。但是，一天夜里，当鲁宾不得不驾车把一群人从舞会上送回家时，他喝得酩酊大醉，握不住缰绳，所以其中一位先生不得不登上马车驾车把那些女士送回家。当然，事儿瞒不住了，鲁宾马上就被辞退了。他可怜的妻子和小孩子们不得不离开庄园大门边漂亮的小木屋，能去哪儿就去哪儿。这一切都是老马克斯告诉我的，因为那是好久以前发生的事儿了。但是，在我和姜姐到来之前不久，史密斯又被召了回来。约克向非常好心的伯爵求了情，史密斯信誓旦旦，只要他住在那儿，就绝不再沾一滴酒。史密斯信守承诺，所以约克认为自己不在时能放心让他顶替自己的位置，而且他非常聪明诚实，好像没有人比他更合适了。

此时是四月初，伯爵一家预期五月份回来。那辆轻便的四轮马车将被重新组装，因为布兰泰尔上校必须返回部队。根据安排，史密斯要驾车把他送到镇上，然后再骑马回来。因此，史密斯带上了马鞍，此行我被选中。在车站，上校在史密斯的手里放了一些钱，跟他道别说：“鲁宾，照顾好你年轻的妻子，不要让任何想骑黑风的冒失小伙子随便乱骑——让他为女士服务。”

我们把马车留在了车铺，史密斯骑着我去了白狮旅馆，他吩咐马夫好好喂我，四点钟为他备好马。我一条前腿蹄铁的螺丝在来时路上就已经松动了。但是，马夫大约四点钟才发现。五点钟时，史密斯走进院子，说他六点钟才会离开，因为他遇见了一些老朋友。于是，马夫把螺丝松动的事儿告诉了他，问他是不是要检查一下蹄铁。

“不，”史密斯说，“到我们回家都不会有问题。”

他说话声非常响亮，随随便便，我认为不察看一下我的铁蹄很不像他的做法，因为他向来都十分重视我们脚掌上松动的钉子。他六点钟没有来，七点钟没有来，八点钟也没有来，快九点时他才叫我，声音响亮粗鲁。他似乎脾气很糟，还骂了看马人，尽管我说不清为什么。

店老板站在门口，说道：“小心，史密斯先生！”而他却骂骂咧咧，生气地回答，几乎还没有跑出镇子，他就开始策马飞奔。尽管当时我已经在全速前进，但他还是常常用鞭子狠狠地抽打我。月亮还没有升起，天色很黑。大路最近刚刚修过，上面都是石子。我以这样的速度奔跑在上面，蹄铁越来越松了，我们临近收费公路关卡时，蹄铁就脱落了。

如果史密斯神志清醒，就会感觉到我的步伐出了毛病；但是，他酩酊大醉，注意不到。

关卡那边是一段长路，刚铺上石子——又长又尖的石子，任何马儿被骑到这样的路上快跑，都是一种冒险。就是在这种路上，而且掉了一块蹄铁，我还被迫全速快跑，同时骑手用鞭子狠狠地抽打着我，嘴里骂骂咧咧，催我再快些。当然，我那只掉了铁掌的蹄子遭受了巨大的痛苦。那只蹄子裂开，裂到了活肉部分，里面被尖锐的石子扎得生疼。

不能再向前跑了。在这种情况下，没有一匹马还能再跑下去。我疼痛难忍，趔趄一下，猛地跪倒在地。史密斯因我跌倒而被甩了出去，而且因为我跑的速度很快，所以他一定是重重地摔倒了。我很快就站了起来，一瘸一拐地走到路边，那儿没有石子。月亮刚刚爬上了树篱梢。我借着月光可以看到史密斯躺在离我几码远的地方。他没有站起来。他稍微努力了一下想站起来，随后是一声沉重的呻吟。我本也可以呻吟，因为我的一只蹄子和两个膝盖都在遭受剧痛。但是，马儿习惯默默地忍受痛苦。我没有发出任何声音，而是站在那儿倾听。史密斯又发出了一声沉重的呻吟。不过，尽管此刻他躺在皎洁的月光下，但是我看不见任何姿势的变化。我对他、对自己都无能为力，可是，噢！我是多么渴望听到马声、车轮声或脚步声啊！路上走过的人不多。夜里这个时候，我们要等救援的人来，可能要等上好几个小时。我在那儿张望、倾听。这是一个宁静甜蜜的四月的夜晚，只有夜莺的几声低鸣，只有月亮旁边的朵朵白云，只有一只在树篱上方飞来飞去的褐色猫头鹰。这让我想起了很久以前的那些夏夜，当时在格雷农场主翠绿宜人的草地上，我常常躺在妈妈的身边。

第二十六章　如此结局

我听到大老远传来了马蹄声，一定是将近半夜时分。声音时隐时现，然后越来越清晰，越来越近了。到伯爵府要先穿过伯爵家的树林。声音就是从那个方向传来的，我希望那会是来寻找我们的。随着那声音越来越近，我几乎可以确信那是姜姐的蹄声。再靠近一点儿时，我可以听出她拉着一辆轻便双轮马车。我大声嘶叫。听到姜姐的回应和人们的声音，我喜出望外。他们从石子路上慢慢地驶过来，在路上躺着的那个黑影边停下。

其中一个人跳下车，俯身查看。“是鲁宾，”他说，“他不动了！”

另一个人跟过来，也向他弯下腰。“他死了，”他说，“感觉一下，他的两只手是多么凉！”

他们把他抱起来，却没有任何生命迹象，他的头发浸满了血。他们又把他放下来，过来看我。他们很快就看到了我受伤的膝盖。

“啊，是这匹马跌倒，把他甩了出去！谁会想到这匹黑马会这样做呢？没有人相信他会摔倒。鲁宾一定在这儿躺了好几个小时！说也奇怪，这匹马竟然没有离开现场。”

随后，罗伯特想把我向前拉。我迈了一步，却差点儿又摔倒。

“喂！他的这只蹄子像两个膝盖一样伤得很重。瞧这儿——他的蹄子完全被划成了碎片。他很可能残废了，可怜的家伙！奈德，我告诉你，我怀疑鲁宾不对劲儿。试想一下，他骑着掉了一块蹄铁的马过那些石子路的情景吧！唉，如果他神志清醒的话，他就会宁愿尽力从月亮上骑过去。我担心他是又犯病了。可怜的苏珊！她来我家问他是否回来时脸色惨白。她假装自己毫不担忧，谈到了好多可能耽误他行程的事儿。不过，尽管如此，但她还是恳求我去迎迎他——可是，我们必须怎么办呢？带一匹马和一具遗体回去，这绝非易事。”

接下来，他们商量了一下决定，罗伯特作马夫，负责牵我，而奈德必须扛遗体。把遗体放进马车并非易事，因为没有人去牵姜姐，而她和我一样知道他们正在干什么，站在那儿一动不动。我之所以注意到这一点，是因为，如果说姜姐有缺点的话，那就是她站着时会急躁。

奈德拉着鲁宾的遗体慢慢地上路了。罗伯特又过来看了看我的脚，然后拿出手帕，紧紧绑住，他就这样牵着我回家。我永远不会忘记那次夜行。有三英里多的路程。罗伯特牵着我慢慢走着。我忍着剧痛，一瘸一拐，尽可能走好路。我相信，罗伯特为我难过，因为他经常爱抚和鼓励我，和颜悦色地对我说着话。

我终于回到了自己的畜栏，吃了一些谷物。罗伯特用湿布裹住我的膝盖，把糠泥敷剂绑到我的蹄子上，这可以在明天早上马医到来之前帮我先去热、清洁。我不顾疼痛，设法让自己躺在稻草上睡觉。

第二天，马医给我检查过伤口后说，他希望我的关节没有受伤，这样的话，我以后还可以继续工作，而我身上却永远都留有伤疤。我相信，他们已竭尽全力给我良好的治疗了，那可是一个漫长痛苦的治疗。我的膝盖上长了他们所谓的疤瘤，用腐蚀剂烧掉了。最终愈合后，他们在我两个膝关节前面涂上了一种灼热的液体来彻底脱毛。他们这样做是有原因的，而且我认为也应该这么做。

因为史密斯的死突如其来，而且没有目击者在场，所以他们进行了调查。白狮旅馆的老板、马夫，还有其他好几个人都举证说，史密斯从旅馆出来时就喝醉了；关卡的看守说他通过关卡时快马加鞭；而我的蹄铁也在石子间找到了，所以这个案子真相大白，我被洗刷了所有的罪责。

大家都同情苏珊。她快疯了，总是翻来覆去地说着：“噢！他真好啊——真好啊！这都是该死的酒。他们为什么要卖那该死的酒啊？噢，鲁宾，鲁宾！”她就这样喊着，直到鲁宾安葬。当时，因为她既没有家，也没有亲戚，所以她和她的六个小孩子被迫再次离开了高大橡树旁边那个舒适的家，进了阴暗的大济贫所。

第二十七章　糟蹋和衰落

膝盖一充分痊愈，我就被送到一个小牧场待了一两个月。那儿没有任何其他动物。尽管我可以享受自由和甜美的草儿，但是我早已习惯了群居，所以感到非常孤独。我和姜姐已经成为忠实的朋友，现在我特别想念她的陪伴。听到过路的马蹄声，我常常嘶叫，却很少能得到回应。直到一天早晨，大门被打开。除了亲爱的老姜姐之外，谁会进来呢？那个人解开她的缰绳，把她留在了那儿。我高兴地嘶叫了一声，小跑到她的身边。我们俩见面都很高兴，我却很快发现，他们把她带过来跟我在一起，并不是为了让我们高兴。她的故事太长了，讲不过来，一句话，她被残酷的骑乘毁了，现在被送到这儿是看她剩下还会做什么。

乔治勋爵年轻，不愿接受任何警告。他是一个无情的骑手，只要有机会，就会去打猎。他对他的马儿漠不关心。我离开马厩不久之后，就有一场越野障碍赛马，他决定骑马参加比赛。尽管马夫告诉他说姜姐有点儿紧张，不适合参加这种比赛，但是他不相信，所以比赛那天他催促姜姐跟上最前面的骑手。姜姐精神抖擞，竭尽全力，随着前三名冲过了终点，她的气管却受了伤，而且乔治勋爵对她来说太重了，所以她的背也受了伤。“就这样，”她说，“我们就到了这儿，在我们年富力强时被糟蹋了，你是被一个醉鬼，我是被一个傻瓜。真难受啊！”我们俩都由衷地感到已不是从前的自己了。然而，这也没有破坏我们彼此相伴时的那种乐趣。我们不再像过去那样飞奔，但是我们常常一起进食，一起躺下，一起在那棵婆娑的菩提树下头挨着头站立好几个小时。我们就这样度过了那段时光，直到家里人从城里回来。

一天，我们看见伯爵走进牧场，约克跟他一起。我们认出了是谁，但还是静静地站在菩提树下，让他们走到我们身边。他们仔细查看我们。伯爵好像非常恼火。

“就是扔掉三百英镑，也毫无用处，”他说，“不过，我最关心的是我老朋友的这些马，他以为他们在我这儿会找到一个好归宿，结果他们却被毁了。那匹母马会再跑十二个月，我们看看这对她会不会有用。不过，那匹黑马必须卖掉。尽管非常可惜，但是我的马厩里不能收留膝盖伤成这样的马儿。”

“是的，主人，当然不能。”约克说，“不过，他可能会有一个不注重相貌、还会受到优待的去处。我认识巴思的一个人，他开有几家马行，常常想低价买一匹好马。我知道他对马照顾得非常周到。那次审讯澄清了这匹马的品质，而且主人或我的推荐也足以为他担保。”

“你最好给他写封信，约克。我关心的不是他能卖多少钱，而是那个地方。”

之后，他们就离开了我们。

“他们很快就会带你走，”姜姐说，“我就要失去自己唯一的朋友了，十有八九我们再也不能相见了。这个冷酷的世界啊！”

之后大约一周，罗伯特拿着笼头来到了这个地方，套在了我的头上，就把我牵走了。姜姐没有临别寄语。我要被牵走时，我们彼此嘶叫了一声，她顺着树篱焦急地小跑，对我呼唤，直到听不到我的蹄声。

通过约克的推荐，我被马行的主人买走了。我不得不坐火车去，我对这不熟悉，第一次坐火车需要极大的勇气。但是，后来我发现火车的喷气声、呼啸声、吹哨声，尤其是我站立的运马货车的颤抖，都没有对我造成真正的伤害，所以我很快就默默地接受了。

到达旅程终点后，我发现自己来到了一个还算舒适的马厩，而且受到了细心照顾。这些马厩不像我过去常常待的那些马厩一样通风舒适。这些畜栏地面不平，处在斜坡上，因为我的头总是被拴在马槽上，所以我不得不总是站在斜坡上，这令我疲乏不堪。人们好像还不知道，如果马儿能站得舒服，并且可以转身的话，就能干更多的活儿。不过，我吃得很好，还被擦得干干净净的。总的来说，我认为，我们的主人总是尽可能地照顾我们。他养了好多马儿，还有用来出租的各种马车。有时，他自己的马夫来驾车；有时，马儿和马车被租给先生或小姐们驾驶。

第二十八章　打工马和赶马人

迄今为止，至少总是由会骑马的人来骑我。但是，在这个地方，我将会体验到我们马儿遭受的各种各样的坏把式和无知驾驭。因为我是一匹“打工马”，所以会被出租给各种想租用我的人。因为我心平气和，靠得住，所以常常比其他马儿更多地被租给无知骑手。尽管要讲述所有的驾驭方式得用很长时间，但我还是要提上几种。

首先，有一种紧拉缰绳的赶车人——他们似乎认为一切全靠尽力握紧缰绳，从来不放松勒着马嘴的绳子，也从来不给马儿一点儿活动自由。他们总是在谈的就是“完全掌控马儿”和“拉高马头”，好像马生来不会自己抬头一样。

一些可怜衰弱的马儿，嘴巴已经被这样的车夫弄得僵硬、没有感觉了，他们也许能从这样的驾驭方式中得到一些帮助。但是，对一匹能靠自己的腿站立、嘴巴敏感、容易引导的马儿来说，这不仅是痛苦的折磨，而且愚蠢。

然后，还有放松缰绳的赶车人，他们让缰绳松垮地躺在我们的背上，他们自己的手懒洋洋地放在膝盖上。当然，如果突然发生什么事儿，这些先生就对马儿没有任何控制力了。如果马儿受惊、惊跳或踉跄，他们就会无所作为，既帮不了马儿，也帮不了自己，直至酿成惨祸。当然，我自己对这样的驾驭方式没有意见，因为我不习惯惊跳，也不习惯踉跄，只习惯依靠赶车人的引导和鼓励行动。尽管如此，但是马儿喜欢下山时能感觉到有缰绳稍微拉着，喜欢知道赶车人没有睡着。

此外，赶车懒散会让马儿养成坏的、通常是懒惰的习惯，这样的马转手后，不得不通过挨鞭子，或多或少地忍受痛苦和麻烦，来改掉那些习惯。戈登先生总是让我们保持最佳的步伐和最好的举止。他说要毁掉一匹马让他养成坏习惯，就像宠坏一个孩子一样残酷，以后二者都不得不为此受苦。

还有，这些车夫常常都很粗心，对任何别的事儿都很关心，唯独对他们的马儿不行。一天，我拉着四轮敞篷轻便马车跟这样一个车夫出去，后面坐着一位女士和两个孩子。我们在动身之前，他笨拙地动了动缰绳，尽管我已经动身了，但他还是理所当然、毫无意义地狠狠抽了我几鞭。那儿一直都在大面积修路，即使那些没有新铺石子的地方，到处也有好多散落的石子。车夫在跟夫人和孩子们谈笑风生，谈东说西，却从来不认为他的马儿值得密切注视，值得行驶在最平坦的路上。所以，我的一只前脚掌很容易就踩进了一个石子。

现在，如果戈登先生或约翰在，事实上任何一个好车夫在，他都会在我三步之内看到有不对劲儿的地方。即使是在夜里，老把式也会从缰绳上感觉到步伐不对劲儿，下车取出那个石子。但是，这个人却继续谈笑风生，而每走一步，石子就会更加牢固地嵌进我的脚掌和蹄叉之间。石子尖的一面插在里面，圆的一面留在外面。大家都知道，这是马儿能碰上的最危险的石子，既能划伤马蹄，又能让马儿踉跄跌倒。

我说不清这个人到底是半瞎还是粗心大意，他就这样让我的蹄子里塞了石子足足走了半英里，什么都没有看见。到我疼得一瘸一拐，他才终于看到了，大声叫道：“喂，走啊！唉，他们居然给我们派了一匹瘸马！真不像话！”

随后，他扔下缰绳，拿起鞭子，一边劈头盖脸地抽，一边说道：“好了，跟我摆老资格没用。还要赶路，装瘸偷懒都没用。”

就在这时，一个农场主骑着一匹棕色短腿马走过来。他抬了抬帽子，停了下来。

“对不起，先生，”他说，“不过，我认为你的马有毛病。从它走路的样子看，我认为它的蹄铁里面好像有石子。如果你允许的话，我想看看他的蹄子。这些散落的石子对马儿来说是该死的危险东西。”

“他是一匹雇来的马。”车夫说，“我不知道他有什么毛病，他们派了这样一匹瘸马，可真不像话。”

农场主下了马，把缰绳挽在胳膊上，立刻抬起我离他最近的那只蹄子。

“我的天哪，有石子！瘸！我想也是！”

起先，他想用手把石子抠出来。但是，因为现在卡得很紧，所以他从口袋里掏出取石器，小心翼翼也很费劲地把石子取了出来。随后，他举起石子，说道：“瞧，这就是你的马踩进的石子。他没有摔倒跌破膝盖，真是奇迹！”

“噢，当然！”车夫说，“真是怪事！以前我从来不知道马蹄踩进石子这种事儿。”

“你不知道？”农场主相当轻蔑地说。“不过，马蹄是会踩进石子的，即使最好的马儿也会，在这样的路上有时难免。如果你不想让你的马儿变成瘸子，就必须留神，马蹄一踩进石子就马上取出来。这只蹄子已经严重受伤了。”他把我的那只蹄子轻轻地放下，拍了拍我说，“先生，我劝你，最好让他悠着走一会儿。这只蹄子严重受伤，一瘸一拐的情况不会马上消失。”

说完，他骑上马，向女士抬抬帽子，就策马而去了。

他走后，我的车夫开始抖缰绳拽马具，我明白我必须前进，我当然明白这一点，我很高兴石子没有了，但还是很疼。

这就是我们打工马经常经受的考验。

第二十九章　伦敦佬

还有就是像开蒸汽机一样的赶车方式。这些车夫大都是城里人，他们从来没有养过马儿，通常乘火车出行。

他们似乎总认为马儿跟蒸汽机差不多，只是比较小。无论如何，他们都认为，只要他们花了钱，马儿就一定要按照他们的意愿，要他跑多快就得跑多快，要他跑多远就得跑多远，要他驮多重就得驮多重。不管道路是泥泞难走还是干燥好走，不管是多石还是平坦，不管是上坡还是下坡，都是一样——前进，前进，前进，必须前进，保持同样的步幅，既没有安慰，也没有体谅。

这些人从来不考虑下车自己走上陡坡。噢，不，他们已经付钱了就要坐车，他们一定要坐车！马儿呢？噢，他已经习惯了！如果不把人们拉上山，马儿生下来做什么呢？走路！真是好笑！所以，鞭子抽起来，缰绳抖起来，常常还会有一阵粗暴的责骂声：“快走啊，你这懒畜生！”紧接着又是狠狠一鞭，这时我们始终在竭尽全力向前赶路，没有怨言，乖乖听话，尽管内心常常厌烦、痛苦和沮丧。

这种开蒸汽机式的驾车风格比任何其他类型的驾驶方法都更快地耗尽我们的体力。我宁愿为一个体贴的好车夫跑二十英里，也不愿为这种人跑十英里，这会让我事倍功半。

还有一点，无论下坡路多么陡，他们几乎都不拉刹车，因此严重事故时有发生。要么就是拉住刹车，到了坡底常常忘记松开，我不止一次不得不拉着刹住一只轮子的马车爬上另一个陡坡，到了半坡上，我的车夫才想到这一点，这会让一匹马非常疲劳。

因此，这些伦敦佬不会像绅士那样以从容的步伐开始，常常在马厩院时就全速动身。当他们想停下时，会先鞭打我们，然后突然停下，我们差点儿摔坐在地上，我们的嘴巴会被马嚼子弄得参差不齐——他们把这称为急刹车。拐弯时，他们那样急转，就像路上没有正行逆行似的。

我清楚记得一个春天的夜晚，我和罗里已经出去一天了（罗里是跟我搭档拉车的主力马，是一个诚实的好小伙子）。我们有自己的车夫，他总是对我们体贴友善，所以我们那天非常开心。黄昏时分，我们正以敏捷的步伐飞快地走在回家的路上。我们的路突然转向了左边。但是，我们离自己这一侧的树篱很近，而且有足够的空间可以通过，所以我们的车夫没有让我们靠边。就在我们接近拐角时，我听到一匹马正拉着两轮马车朝我们的方向冲下坡来。树篱很高，我什么也看不见，紧接着我们就撞在了一起。幸运的是，我站在靠近树篱的那侧。罗里站在车辕的左侧，甚至没有辕杆保护他。那个赶车人一直冲这个拐角赶来，当看到我们时，他已经来不及靠到他自己那边了。所有的冲击力都撞在了罗里身上。车辕正好撞到了他的胸部，他大叫一声，踉跄后退，这叫声我永远难忘。另一匹马跌坐下去，一根辕杆被撞断了。原来那也是我们马厩里的一匹马，他拉着年轻人们非常喜欢的轻便高轮马车。

赶车人是那种漫无目的的无知之徒，他们甚至不知道自己应该走路的哪一边，或者，即使他们知道，也满不在乎。可怜的罗里皮开肉绽，鲜血直流。他们说，如果再靠边一点点儿，就会要了他的命。如果真是那样，对这个可怜的家伙来说也是一件好事。

事实上，过了很久，他的伤才痊愈，随后他就被卖去拉煤车了。那是什么滋味，只有马儿知道，就是在那些陡峭的山路上上上下下地拉车。我在那儿看到过一些这样的景象，就是一匹马后面拉着沉重的两轮车走下坡路，马车上连刹车装置都没有安。这样的景象至今我想起来都难过。

罗里受伤之后，我经常跟一匹名叫佩吉的母马一起拉车。她住在我旁边的畜栏里，健壮匀称，皮毛呈鲜亮的暗褐色，长着美丽的斑点，鬃毛和尾巴呈深棕色。尽管她的血统并不高贵，但是她非常漂亮，性情温和，积极肯干。尽管如此，但是她的眼里有一种焦虑的神情，我知道她有某种烦恼。我们第一次出去时，我认为她的步伐很怪。她好像时而小跑，时而慢跑三四步，然后向前跳一小步。

跟她一起拉车的马都很不愉快，我也非常烦躁。我们到家后，我问她是什么让她以这样奇怪难堪的方式走路。

“啊，”她不安地说，“我知道我的步伐很糟，但我又能怎样呢？这真不是我的过错，就是因为我的腿很短。尽管我站着几乎跟你一样高，但是你膝盖以上的腿却要比我长足足三英寸，所以你当然能比我跨得远、走得快。你明白我不是由自己制造的。我希望我能自己改造自己，那样我就会有长腿了。所有的麻烦都来自我的短腿。”佩吉以沮丧的语调说道。

“可那又怎样呢？”我说，“你这样强壮，性情和蔼，积极肯干。”

“啊，你知道，”她说，“人们喜欢走得快，如果你跟不上其他的马儿，那等待你的就始终只有鞭子、鞭子、鞭子。所以，我不得不尽可能跟上，才会走得这样蹩脚、拖拉。情况并不总是这样，当我跟第一个主人生活在一起时，我总是匀速小跑，那时他可不会那么急。他是乡下的一个年轻牧师，一个善良和蔼的主人。他有两座教堂，相距很远，他工作很多，却从来没有因我跑得不快而骂我或抽我。他非常喜欢我。我只希望我现在能跟他在一起。然而，他不得不离开，到一个大城市去，于是我被卖给了一个农场主。

“你知道，一些农场主是资本家，我却认为他是层次很低的人。他从来不在乎马好不好，也从来不在乎自己赶得好不好，只喜欢快跑。我尽力快跑，但还是不行，他总是抽我，所以我就养成了跃步向前赶的习惯。赶集的夜晚，他常常在客栈待到很晚，然后以最快的速度赶车回家。

“一个黑夜，他像往常一样飞驰回家，这时车轮突然撞到路上一个又大又重的东西上，马车立刻就翻倒了。他被甩了出去，一只胳膊摔断，我想肋骨也断了几根。不管怎样，我跟他在一起的生活结束了，我并不难过。不过，你明白，如果人们必须走得快，对我来说哪里都一样。如果我的腿再长些，该多好啊！”

可怜的佩吉！尽管我为她非常难过，但是我却无法安慰她，因为我知道慢马跟快马套在一起拉车是多么难受。所有的鞭子最终会抽到他们的身上，他们却无能为力。

她经常被用来拉四轮敞篷轻便马车，因为她非常温和，所以颇受一些女士喜欢。之后，过了一段时间，她被卖给了两位女士，她们自己赶车，想找一匹安全的好马。

我在乡下遇见过她好几次，只见她脚步稳健，一副快乐、满足的神情。见到她我非常高兴，因为她值得拥有一个好归宿。

她离开我们之后，另一匹马来顶替了她。他非常年轻，但是，因为容易惊跳而名声不好，所以失去了一个好去处。我问他是什么让他受惊的。

“啊，我不大知道，”他说，“我小时候非常腼腆，受过好几次惊吓。如果我见到什么怪事儿，就常常会转身去看——你明白，我们戴着眼罩，看不见，除非环顾四周，才能明白是怎么回事——这时，我的主人总会给我一鞭子，这当然会使我继续前进，而这并没有减轻我的恐惧。我想，如果他能让我平静地去看一切，明白没有什么会伤害我，就会万事大吉，我也会习以为常。一天，一位老先生跟他一起骑马，一大张白纸或破布正好吹到了我的一侧。我前闪后躲。主人像往常那样狠狠地抽打我，而那位老先生却大声叫道：‘你错了！你错了！你绝不该抽打一匹惊退的马。他之所以惊退，是因为他害怕。你这样做，只会让他更害怕，这个习惯会变得更糟。’所以，我认为并不是所有人都这样做。我肯定也不想因这样一个原因而惊退。但是，如果你从来没有获准去习惯什么，你怎么知道什么危险、什么不危险呢？我从来不怕我知道的一切。我当时是在一个有鹿的地方长大的。我当然了解他们，就像我了解牛羊一样，但是他们并不寻常，我知道好多敏感的马看到他们就会害怕，在经过养鹿的围场之前会骚动不安。”

我知道我的同伴说得没错，我也希望每一匹小马都有像格雷农场主和戈登先生这样好的主人。

当然我们有时在这儿也会碰上好把式。我记得，一天早上，我被套上了一辆轻便双轮马车，带到了普尔特尼街上的一座房子。两位先生走出来，个子较高的那个走到我头边，看了看马嚼子和马勒，一只手动了动项圈，看是不是套得舒适。

“你认为这匹马需要马勒吗？”他对马夫说。

“啊，”那个人说，“应该说，他没有马勒也无妨。他有一张难得的好嘴，尽管精神饱满，但是他没有任何恶习。只是我们经常发现人们喜欢用马勒。”

“我不喜欢，”先生说，“请行行好取掉它，把缰绳套在脸颊边吧。一张轻松舒适的嘴巴是长途旅行的一件大事，难道不是吗，老伙计？”他拍了拍我的脖子说。

随后，他拿起缰绳，他们俩都上了车。我现在还能记得他让我转弯时是多么悄无声息，他轻触缰绳，在我的背上轻扬马鞭，我们就出发了。

我弓起脖子，以最佳的步速动身了。我发现我身后的那个人知道应该怎么赶一匹好马。好像昔日重来似的，这让我非常开心。

这位先生非常喜欢我，坐上马鞍试了好几次之后，他劝说我的主人把我卖给他的一位朋友，他的朋友想要一匹安全舒适的马儿。于是，那年夏天我最终被卖给了巴里先生。

第三十章　小偷

我的新主人是一个未婚男人。他住在巴思，大多时间忙于生意。他的医生建议他进行骑马运动，因此他才买了我。他在距离住所不远处租了一个马厩，聘用了一个名叫费尔彻的人当马夫。主人对马儿知之甚少，但是待我很好，我本来可以有一个安逸的好地方，他却对周围的情况一无所知。他吩咐用最好的干草，充足的燕麦、碎豆子、谷糠，还有野豌豆或黑麦，想要多少就给多少。我听到主人这样吩咐过，所以我知道有好多美食，我想我会过得很好的。

有几天一切顺利。我发现马夫懂行。他始终让马厩干净通风，把我也刷洗得非常彻底，一直都性情温和。他曾在巴思一家大酒店当过马夫。他已经放弃了那份工作，现在自己种水果和蔬菜卖到集市。他的妻子养肥家禽和兔子卖钱。过了一段时间，我好像觉得燕麦非常短缺。我吃的是豆子，麸皮里掺的可不是燕麦，而是豆子，就是有燕麦也寥寥无几，肯定不到应有量的四分之一。两三周后，这开始影响我的力气和精神。尽管草料很好，但是没有谷物，无法维持我的健康。然而，我不能抱怨，也无法让他们知道我的需要。就这样过了大约两个月，我纳闷我的主人怎么看不出问题呢。但是，一天下午，他骑着我到乡下去看一位朋友，那位农场主先生住在通向威尔斯的路上，看马是火眼金睛。迎接过朋友之后，他看了我一眼，说道：

“巴里，在我看来，你的马看上去没有你当初买他时气色好；他身体好吗？”

“是的，我想是的，”我的主人说，“他现在大不如从前那样活泼了。马夫告诉我说，马儿秋天总是无精打采、有气无力，所以我必须料到这一点。”

“秋天，胡说！”农场主说，“啊，现在才到八月份，你的活儿轻，吃得又好，即使是秋天，他也不应该这样掉膘。你是怎么喂他的呢？”

主人告诉了他。他慢慢地摇了摇头，开始抚摸我的全身。

“亲爱的伙计，我说不清是谁吃了你的谷物，但是，如果是你的马吃的话，那我就大错特错了。你骑得很快吗？”

“不是，很缓。”

“那请把你的手放在这儿，”他把手伸到我的脖子和肩上说。“他就像刚从草地上出来的马一样温暖潮湿。我建议你多去观察一下马厩。我不喜欢多疑，谢天谢地，我也没有理由多疑，因为无论我在不在，我都信得过我的那些手下。不过，也有一些卑鄙小人，会邪恶到从不会说话的牲口那儿抢夺食物。你必须调查一下。”说完，他转向那个过来牵我的手下人说，“好好给这匹马喂磨碎的燕麦，不要给他定量。”

“不会说话的牲口！”是的，我们就是。但是，如果我能说话，我就会告诉主人他的燕麦到哪儿去了。每天早上大约六点钟，我的马夫常常带一个小男孩过来，小男孩总是提一只带盖的篮子。他常常跟着他的父亲走进马具房，那儿放有燕麦。当门半开时，我能看到他们把料箱里的燕麦装进一只小袋子，然后小男孩就会离开。

这之后过了五六个早上，正当小男孩离开马厩时，门被推开了，一名警察走了进来，紧紧地抓住了小男孩的胳膊，另一位警察跟了进来，从里面锁上门，说道：“带我去看你的父亲放兔食的地方。”

看上去小男孩非常害怕，开始哭了起来。但是，无路可逃，所以他带路去了谷仓。警察在那儿找到了另一个空袋子，就像小男孩篮子里装满燕麦的那个袋子。

费尔彻当时正在给我擦洗蹄子，而他们很快就发现了他。尽管他大呼小叫了好一阵子，但还是被带到了拘留所，他的儿子也被带走了。后来，我听说他的儿子没有被定罪，而他却被判了两个月的监禁。

第三十一章　骗子

主人没有马上找到合适的人。然而，没过几天，新马夫就来了。他是一个身材高大、模样英俊的家伙。但是，如果有骗子扮成马夫的话，阿尔弗雷德·斯莫克就是这种人。他对我非常文明，从来不虐待我，事实上，当主人在场看着时，他总是摸摸我、拍拍我。为了让我好看，他总会在带我出门前用水刷我的鬃毛和尾巴，用油刷我的蹄子，甚至为我清洗蹄子、检查铁掌或清洗全身。他常常把我当成一头奶牛。他任凭我的嚼子生锈，马鞍潮湿，兜带僵硬。

阿尔弗雷德·斯莫克认为自己很帅，他会在马具房的小镜子前花好多时间整理自己的头发、胡须和领带。主人对他说话时，他总是说：“是，先生。是，先生。”每说一句话，他都要碰下自己的帽子。大家都认为他是一个很好的小伙子，认为巴里先生遇到他真幸运。我要说他是我接触过的最懒惰、最自负的家伙。当然，不被虐待已经是万幸了，但是马儿要的不止于此。我有一个宽松的畜栏，要不是他懒惰从来不清扫，我本可以非常舒适。他从来不清完所有的稻草，下面的稻草发出的气味非常难闻。同时，升上来的浓浓的气体，使我的眼睛刺痛发炎，我连食欲都没有了。

一天，他的主人进来，说道：“阿尔弗雷德，马厩气味有些重。你就不能把那个马厩好好刷洗一下，多倒些水冲一下吗？”

“好，先生。”他碰了一下帽子说，“先生，如果你喜欢的话，我就会这样做。但是，在马栏里倒水有些危险，先生，马儿非常容易感冒，先生。我不想伤害他。但是，如果你喜欢的话，我就会这样做，先生。”

“噢。”他的主人说，“我不想让他感冒，但是，我不喜欢这马厩里的气味。你认为排水沟正常吗？”

“噢，先生，既然你提到了这一点，我认为排水沟的确有时会反味儿，也许出了什么毛病，先生。”

“那就叫砖匠过来看看。”他的主人说。

“好，先生，我会叫的。”

砖匠来了，揭起了好多砖头，却没有发现什么毛病。于是，他撒了一些石灰，向主人收了五先令，而我的畜栏里的气味还是像以往一样糟。不过，这还不算完——因为我站在一些潮湿的稻草上，我的蹄子开始变得不健康、易过敏，主人常常说：

“我不知道这匹马是怎么回事，他总是用蹄子摸索着走路。我有时担心他会绊倒。”

“是的，先生。”阿尔弗雷德说，“我在训练他时就已经注意到了。”

事实上，他几乎从来没有训练过我。主人忙时，我常常在马厩里一待就是好几天，根本没有伸展过腿，喂食量却跟我干重活时一样多。这经常使我的身体机能失调，有时让我难以消化，反应迟钝，更多的时候是焦躁不安。他从来不给我吃青草或谷糠，这些会让我降温，因为他既无知又自负。回来，他不训练我，也不给我换食，我只好吃药丸和汤药，这些东西除了难以下咽之外，常常让我感到恶心和不适。

一天，我的蹄子非常乏力，所以我驮着主人在一些新铺的石子路上小跑时，严重踉跄了两次。于是，他在从兰斯顿进城的路上，在一个马医那儿停下来，请他看看我是怎么回事。那个人把我的蹄子一个个抬起来仔细查看，然后站起来，拍了拍手上的灰尘，说道：

“你的马得了蹄叉腐疽，而且非常严重。他的蹄子非常乏力，没有摔倒真是幸运。我纳闷，你的马夫以前居然没有注意到。这种情况，我们经常会在一些垃圾从来不适当清除的脏马厩里发现。如果你明天把你的马夫送到这儿，我就给你的马治蹄子，我还会教你的马夫怎么涂抹我给他的擦剂。”

第二天，我的蹄子被彻底清洗了一遍，塞满了一些在浓药水里泡过的粗麻屑。这滋味可真不好受。

马医吩咐每天清除我畜栏里的所有垃圾，地面要保持干干净净。然后，我要吃谷糠，吃一些青草，不要吃太多的谷物，直到我的蹄子康复。经过这次治疗，我很快就恢复了精神。但是，两次被马夫欺骗后，巴里先生非常愤慨，决定不再养马，需要用马时就去租一匹。因此，我被养到蹄子彻底痊愈之后，便又被卖掉了。

第三十二章　马市

毫无疑问，对那些一无所知的人来说，马市是一个非常有趣的地方。至少，那儿有好多可看的东西。

那儿有一长溜一长溜来自乡下、刚从湿地牵来的小马；有一群一群毛发蓬松、没有快乐腿个子高的威尔士小马；有几百匹各种各样的拉车马，其中有些马的长尾巴被编了起来，用鲜红的绳子扎得高高的；还有好多像我一样相貌英俊、出身高贵，但因事故、损伤、呼吸不畅或其他毛病而降为中等马的马儿。那儿有一些朝气蓬勃、做什么都合适的好马，他们由在一侧奔跑的马夫牵着导引缰绳，小跑时大秀美腿，高炫步伐。但是，周围有好多可怜的马儿，因繁重劳动而不幸垮掉，膝盖弯曲，后腿每走一步都朝外甩动。还有一些看上去非常沮丧的老马，下唇耷拉，耳朵沉重后翻，好像生活再无乐趣，也再无希望了。还有一些马儿瘦得你能看见他们的所有肋骨，有些背上和臀部都是旧伤。在马看来，这些都是凄惨的景象，因为他不知道自己会不会落到同样的境地。

时而抬价，时而砍价，讨价还价声此起彼伏。如果一匹马尽其所能说出自己的想法，应该说那个马市上的谎言和骗局要比聪明人所能讲述的还要多。我跟其他两三匹强壮中用的马儿放在一起，好多人过来看我们。那些先生总是一看到我受过伤的膝盖就转过身，尽管卖我的人发誓说那只是在畜栏里滑倒造成的。

相马的第一件事就是掰开我的嘴巴，然后看我的眼睛，接着顺着我的腿一路向下摸，用劲儿摸我的皮肉，最后还要试试我的步幅。奇妙的是，人们做这些事儿的方式是多么不同。有些人做得粗鲁随便，就像那只是一块木头似的；有些人常常轻轻地将手滑过你的身体，偶尔拍拍，好像是要说：“承蒙许可。”当然，从这些买家对我的态度，我就能断定好多东西。

我想，有一个人，如果他愿意买我，我就会幸福。他不是什么绅士，也不是虚张声势自称绅士的那种人。他是一个有些矮小的人，但是体格健美，行动敏捷。从他触摸我的方式，我立刻知道他对马儿在行。他说话温和，灰色的眼睛里流露出和蔼愉悦的神色。说来可能奇怪——但却仍是真的——让我喜欢他的是，他身上有股干净清新的气味，不是我原来讨厌的那种酒味和烟味，而是一种清香，就像他刚从干草仓出来一样。他为我出价二十三英镑，却遭到了拒绝，于是他就走了。我注视着他，而他还是走了。这时，一个长相凶猛、粗声大气的人走了过来。我心惊胆战，生怕他会把我买走，还好他走开了。又来过一两个无意购买的人。随后，那个长相凶猛的人又折回来，出价二十三英镑。买卖双方展开了一场势均力敌的讨价还价，因为我的卖家开始以为自己拿不到他要求的价钱，他必须降价。但是，就在这时，那个灰色眼睛的人又折了回来。我情不自禁地向他伸出头，他和善地爱抚我的脸。

“好吧，老伙计。”他说，“我想，我们彼此都满意算了。我出二十四英镑买他。”

“假如出二十五，他就归你了。”

“二十四英镑十先令，”我的朋友以非常果断的语气说，“我就不说六便士了——行不行？”

“成交。”卖家说，“你放心好了，这匹马大有潜质。你买他拉车，稳赚不亏。”

钱当场付清，我的新主人牵住我的缰绳，把我牵出了市场，去了一家客栈。在那儿，他准备有一套马鞍和马勒。他喂我好好吃了一顿燕麦，我吃时他站在旁边，既自言自语，又对我说着话。半小时后，我们走在了去伦敦的路上，穿过惬意的小巷和乡间路，直至来到了伦敦的康庄大道。我们稳步走在大道上，黄昏时分终于到达了大城市。煤气灯已经点起，一英里又一英里，既有街道左右相随，又有街道相互交叉。我想，我们永远都走不到尽头了。最后，我们穿过一条街，来到了一个长长的马车站，这时骑我的主人欢快地大声叫道：“晚安，老板！”

“你好啊！”一个声音叫道，“你买到好马了吗？”

“我想是吧。”我的主人答道。

“我希望他带给你好运。”

“谢谢你，老板。”说完，他继续前行。我们不久走上了一条边道，大约走到一半时，拐进了一条非常狭窄的街道，一边是有些破旧的房子，另一边好像是马车房和马厩。

主人在一个房子前停住，吹了一声口哨。门飞快地打开了，一个年轻女人带着一个小女孩和一个小男孩跑了出来。下马后，主人受到了非常热烈的迎接。

“喂，哈里，我的儿子，打开大门，让妈妈把灯笼提过来。”

接下来，他们都在那个小小的马厩院子里围站在我的身边。

“爸爸，他温驯吗？”

“是的，多莉，像你自己的小猫咪一样温驯。过来拍拍他。”

那只小手马上毫不畏惧地在我的肩上拍来拍去。这种感觉真好！

“你给他刷洗，我去给他端糠糊糊。”妈妈说。

“去端吧，波莉，这正是他想要的东西。我知道你为我准备好了美味的糊糊。”

“是香肠布丁和苹果小馅饼！”小男孩大声喊道，这让大家哈哈大笑。我被牵进了一个安逸舒适、气味清新的畜栏，里面铺有好多干稻草。美餐之后，我就躺下来，心里想着自己会幸福的。

第三十三章　伦敦拉出租马车的马

我的新主人名叫杰里迈亚·巴克，但是人人都叫他杰里，所以我也这样叫他。他的妻子波莉正是男性能找到的最佳配偶。她是一个丰满端庄、娇小整洁的女人，一头柔顺的黑发，一双黑眼睛，一张有趣的小嘴。男孩子十二岁了，是一个高大、坦率、和蔼的小伙子。小多萝西（他们叫她多莉）是母亲的翻版，今年八岁了。他们都非常相亲相爱。我在这之前和之后都没有见过这么幸福快乐的一家人。杰里有一辆自己的出租马车，还有两匹马，他自己驾车，也自己照管马儿。他的另一匹马高大雪白，骨架相当大，被称为上尉。他现在老了，年轻时，一定了不起。他仍然骄傲地抬头弓脖。事实上，他是一匹血统优良、举止得体的贵族老马，彻彻底底的贵族老马。他告诉我说，他早年参加过克里米亚战争，他那时属于一名骑兵军官，常常引领军团。这件事我以后再作详述。

第二天早上，我洗刷停当后，波莉和多莉走进院子来看我，想跟我交朋友。哈里从早晨起就一直在帮他的爸爸，而且已经声明了自己的观点，就是我最终会成为“正儿八经的好汉”。波莉给我拿来了一片苹果，多莉拿了一块面包，使我以为自己好像又变回了从前的黑骏马。又有人爱抚，悄声细语地说话，真是一大快事。我也竭尽全力让他们看到我希望和他们友好相处。波莉认为我非常英俊，要不是膝盖受伤，拉出租车真是大材小用了。

“当然，没有人告诉我们这是谁的过错。”杰里说，“只要我不知道，我就要给他有利的判断。我从来没有骑过这样坚定利落的马儿。我们就按照老马的名字还叫他杰克吧——好吗，波莉？”

“好，”她说，“我喜欢好名字能传下去。”

上尉整个上午都在外面拉车。哈里放学后来喂我，给我水喝。下午我被套上车。杰里不厌其烦地检查项圈和马勒套得是否舒适，好像约翰·曼利又回来了。兜带放松一两个孔眼，一切都正好。没有马缰，没有马勒，只有普通的环形嚼子。这是多么幸运的事儿啊！

穿过边道后，我们来到了大出租车站，就是杰里说过“晚安”的那个地方。这个宽阔街道的一边是带有奇妙店面的高房，另一边是铁栅栏围着的老教堂和教堂墓地。沿着这些铁栅栏停有好多等待乘客的出租马车。地上到处散放着一些干草，有些人站在一起聊天，有些人坐在驾驶座上看报纸，还有一两个人正给他们的马喂干草，喂水。我们在最后一辆马车后面停下来。两三个人围过来，开始看我，评头论足。

“拉灵车很好。”有个人说。

“长得太帅了。”另一个人煞有介事地摇了摇头说，“过几个晴天早上，你就会发现毛病的，否则我就不叫琼斯。”

“噢。”杰里和颜悦色地说，“我想我不用找毛病，毛病就会被发现的，对吗？如果是这样的话，我还可以多保留一会儿好兴致。”

随后来了一个宽脸男人，只见他穿着灰色大衣，大衣上面缀有白色大纽扣，披一件灰色大斗篷，戴一顶灰色帽子，脖子上松散地系着一条蓝色羊毛围巾，他的头发也是灰色的。但是，他样子乐呵呵的，其他人都纷纷为他让路。他把我上下打量了一遍，就像他要买我似的。接着，他挺直身子，咕哝道：“他对你来说正合适，杰里。你付多少钱我都不会介意，他物有所值。”就这样，我的品相在这个站台上得到了肯定。

这个人名叫格兰特，而别人却叫他“灰色格兰特”或“格兰特老板”。他在这个站台上资历最老，会主动处理事务和解决纷争。他通常是一个快乐明理的人。但是，如果他犯点儿脾气，就像他有时喝高了一样，没有人喜欢离他的拳头太近，因为他可能会狠狠地给你一拳。

有生以来，我第一次拉出租车，这第一周可真难熬啊。我对伦敦根本不习惯，也不习惯喧闹、匆忙和车水马龙，我不得不一路穿行，这让我感到忧虑和厌烦。但是，我很快发现我可以完全信任我的车夫，于是我变得轻松，也渐渐地习惯了。

杰里是我认识的最好的车夫，更值得夸赞的是，他为马儿考虑得像为自己考虑得一样多。他很快发现我工作积极、竭尽全力，所以从来不抽打我，除非要出发时才会用鞭梢轻轻地撩一下我的背部。但是，一般来说，我通过他拿起缰绳的方式就完全明白这一点了，所以我相信他把鞭子放在一侧的时间常常多于拿在手里的时间。

不久，我和主人就互相了解了，就像人、马能够互通一样。在马厩里，他也尽可能让我们舒服。围栏是老款式，好多都是在斜坡上。但是，他在我们畜栏后面装有两个可以移动的栅栏，这样夜里我们休息时，他就会取掉我们的笼头，插上栅栏，我们就可以自由转动，想站哪儿就站哪儿，这真舒服。

杰里总是让我们干干净净的，他尽可能地给我们变换食物，供给量总是很大。不仅如此，他还总是给我们喝好多干净、新鲜的水，白天黑夜都把水放在我们的身边，当然我们浑身发热进来时除外。有些人说马儿不应该想喝多少就喝多少。但是，我知道，如果我们需要时就能获准喝水，一次只喝一点点儿，这比一口气喝下半桶对我们好得多，因为我们都曾被置于无水可喝、口渴难耐的境地。有些马夫会回家喝啤酒，撇下我们吃干草和燕麦，好几个小时连润嗓子的东西都不给我们。这时，我们当然一次要喝好多，这会加速我们呼吸系统的损伤，有时还会让我们的胃受寒。在这儿我们最幸福的事儿就是礼拜天可以休息。我们一周工作都非常辛苦，要不是有这么一天，我想我们不可能坚持下来。此外，这时我们才有时间享受彼此相处的时光。就是在这些日子里，我听说了同伴的往事。

第三十四章　一匹老战马

上尉曾被调教、驯养作军马之用。他的第一位主人是一名出征克里米亚战争的骑兵军官。他说，他非常喜欢跟所有其他马一起训练，一起小跑，一起左转右转，听到命令一起立定，听到号声或军官的指令全速前冲。年轻时，他毛色黝黑，是那种带斑点的铁灰色，可以说非常英俊。主人是一名意气风发的年轻绅士，非常喜欢他，从一开始就怀着极大的关怀和善意来对待他。他告诉我说，他认为军马生涯非常愉快。但是，说到坐上大轮船漂洋过海被派往国外时，他几乎改变了这种想法。

他说：“那段时间真可怕啊！当然，我们无法从陆地走到船上，所以他们不得不在我们身上套上粗绳，无论我们怎么挣扎，还是被抬了起来，越过水面，送到了大船的甲板上。在那儿，我们被放进了封闭的小畜栏。从来没有这么久看不到天空，从来没有这么久伸不开腿。轮船有时遇到大风会摇来晃去，我们连碰带撞还带摔，感觉真够糟的。然而，最后这一切都结束了，我们被用力拖起，晃回到了陆地上。我们都很高兴，再次踩到坚实的地面时，大家都纷纷喷鼻欢叫。

“很快，我们就发现我们来到的这个国家和我们自己的国家截然不同，除了战斗之外，我们还要忍受好多艰难困苦。但是，好多人都非常喜欢他们的马儿，所以他们竭尽所能让马儿在寒冷、潮湿，以及乱了章法的万物面前怡然自得。”

“但是，打仗怎样？”我说，“那不是比其他任何事儿都更糟吗？”

“啊，”他说，“我几乎不知道。我们总是喜欢听到号声响起，喜欢被派出去，迫不及待地出发，尽管有时为了等待命令不得不站好几个小时。当命令发出后，我们就会开开心心、迫不及待地跃步向前，好像根本没有炮弹、刺刀或子弹似的。我相信，只要我们感觉自己的骑手在马鞍上坐稳，他的手牢牢地抓住缰绳，我们就没有谁会害怕，即使空中有可怕的炸弹飞过，被炸成上千片，我们也不怕。

“我跟高贵的主人一起参加过好多行动，都没有受伤。尽管我也见过马儿中弹倒下，被长矛扎穿，被可怕的军刀砍伤，尽管我们任由他们死在战场，或者死于伤痛，但是我想我自己并不害怕。我的主人鼓舞他的士兵时声音欢快，让我认为他和我不可能被杀死。我对他完全信任，当他指挥我时，我就准备好去冲锋陷阵，堵住那个炮眼。我看到好多勇士都被砍倒，好多人摔下马鞍受了重伤。我听见过那些垂死的人发出的哭喊声和呻吟声。我曾经慢跑过鲜血流淌的地面，常常为了不踩到受伤的人或马而不停地腾挪，而却从来没有感到过恐惧。直到那可怕的一天到来——那是我永远难忘的一天。”

这时，老上尉暂停了一会儿，长吸了口气。我等着，他继续说了起来：

“那是一个秋天的早上，像平常一样，无论是要打仗还是要等候命令，拂晓前一小时，我们的骑兵团早已出来，披挂完毕。士兵们站在马旁，严阵以待。随着天色渐亮，军官们好像有些激动。天还没有完全亮，我们就听到敌人开火了。

“这时，一位军官骑过来，下令士兵们上马。于是大家纷纷上马，每一匹马都等着缰绳被触及，或被骑兵鞋跟压紧，我们一个个生龙活虎，跃跃欲试。但是，我们都受过良好的训练，除了时而咬咬嚼子，以及时不时不安地甩甩头之外，看不出我们焦躁。

“我和亲爱的主人站在队伍的最前面，大家都一动不动，目不转睛，他把我一小绺错位的鬃毛捋正，用手抚平，然后拍了拍我的脖子，说道：‘今天我们要打一天仗，巴亚德（骁勇者），我的美人儿。但是，我们会像以前那样尽职尽责。’那天早上，他拍我脖子的次数，比以前任何时候都多，他就这样一直静静地拍着，好像他在想其他事。我喜欢感受他的手放在我的脖子上，我骄傲而又高兴地弓起颈脊。不过，我站在那儿一动不动，因为我知道他所有的情绪，知道他什么时候想让我安静，什么时候想让我欢快。

“我说不清那天发生的一切，但是我可以讲述我们一块儿发起的最后一次冲锋。那就是穿越敌人炮火正前方的一个山谷。此时，我们完全习惯了附近隆隆的炮声、滑膛枪的嘎嘎声，以及子弹的嗖嗖声，而那天我们穿越的炮火却是我从来没有经历过的。子弹和炮弹从右边、左边、前面向我们倾泻而来。好多勇士纷纷倒下来，好多马纷纷倒下来，把骑兵摔倒在地。好多背上失去了骑手的马从队伍里狂奔出来。然而，因为害怕落单，加上没有人指挥，所以又跑回到了以前的伙伴中，跟他们一起冲锋陷阵。

“尽管非常可怕，但是谁都没有停下来，也没有后退。队伍人数每时每刻都在减少，而当我们的战友倒下时，我们就会围拢、团结在一起。当我们越来越接近大炮时，我们的步伐不仅没有动摇和犹豫，反而越来越快了。

“我的主人，我亲爱的主人正高举右手鼓舞他的战友们，这时一颗子弹从我的头边嗖地飞过，打中了他。尽管他没有发出喊叫，但是我感觉他受到打击摇晃了一下。我尽力控制速度，剑还是从他的右手里掉下，缰绳也从左手脱落，他在马鞍上向后一仰，摔落在地。其他骑兵从我们身边横扫而过，我被他们的冲力推离了现场。

“我想站在他的身边，不让飞驰而过的马蹄踩住他，却无济于事。我这时既没有主人，也没有朋友，孤零零地站在那个大杀戮场上，恐惧攫住了我，我浑身发抖，以前从来没有那样发抖过。就像我看到其他马儿做的那样，我也想尽力加入到队伍中，跟他们一起飞奔，但是我被士兵们的剑击退了。就在此时，一个失去战马的士兵一把抓住我的缰绳骑上了我，我和这个新主人一起又向前冲去。然而，我们英勇的连队寡不敌众，被打得惨败，那些从枪林弹雨中活下来的人又纷纷跑回了原地。有些马已经严重受伤了，因为失血过多几乎跑不动了，其他意志坚强的马儿设法靠三条腿拖行，还有一些马儿后腿被子弹打烂了，正挣扎着靠前蹄站起来。战斗结束后，伤员们被带了回去，牺牲的都被埋葬了。”

“那些受伤的马呢？”我问，“他们都留下来等死吗？”

“不是，部队的马医带着手枪走过来，射杀了所有受重伤的马。一些只受点儿轻伤的被抬带回去治疗，而早上出去的那些高贵、温驯的马儿大部分再也没有回来。我们马厩里回来的大约只有四分之一。

“我再也没有见到亲爱的主人。我相信他已经摔下马鞍倒地身亡了。我从来没有这样深爱过一个主人。我还参加了好多其他战斗，只受过一次伤，却并不严重。战争结束后，我又回到了英国，还像出国时一样健康强壮。”

我说：“我听别人说起过战争，就像那是一件非常美好的事儿。”

“啊！”他说，“我想他们从来没有见过战争。毫无疑问，没有敌人，仅仅训练训练，列队行进，演习一下，是很好。是的，那真不错。但是，当有成千上万的出色勇士和好马战死或终身残疾时，那就另当别论了。”

“你知道他们为什么打仗吗？”我问。

“不知道，”他说，“那不是一匹马所能明白的。但是，如果一路漂洋过海杀敌正确的话，那敌人一定是罪大恶极。”

第三十五章　杰里·巴克

我从来没有见过比新主人更好的人了。他和蔼善良，像约翰·曼利一样具有强烈的正义感；他心平气和，性情乐观，不大会有人寻衅跟他吵架。他非常喜欢编一些小曲，唱给自己听。他非常喜欢的是这首歌：

来吧，爸爸妈妈，
还有兄弟姐妹，
来啊，一起来吧，
你帮我来我帮你。

他们就是这样。哈里像年龄大的男孩子一样擅长干马厩里的活儿，而且总想去做力所能及的事儿。于是，波莉和多莉早上常常来帮忙收拾马车，刷刷和拍拍坐垫，擦擦玻璃，同时杰里在院子里给我们清洗，哈里在刷马具。他们之间常常有好多欢笑和乐趣，这比那些责骂或难听的话更能让我和上尉精神振奋。他们早上早早起来，因为杰里常常会唱：

假如你早上，
扔掉十分钟，
你整整一天，
都捡不回来。
你仓促匆忙，
忧虑又慌张，
你永远失去，
永远都泡汤。

他受不了毫无目的的闲逛和浪费时间，最让他生气的就是发现一些人总是迟到，为了弥补自己的懒散，他们要出租马拼命奔跑。

一天，两个看上去野里野气的年轻人从车站附近的酒馆里出来，召唤杰里。

“喂，车夫！赶快，我们有些晚了。加油，你把我们送到维多利亚车站，及时赶上一点钟的火车好吗？你会多得一先令。”

“先生们，我会以正常的速度送你们。像那样拼命，先令是赔偿不了的。”

拉里的马车就在我们的旁边。他猛地打开门，说道：“先生，我是你们需要的人！坐我的车，我的马儿会让你们正点到达那儿。”他为他们关好车门时，向杰里使了个眼色，说道：“超速快跑，违背良心。”随后，他狠狠地抽打自己疲惫不堪的马儿，拼命出发了。杰里拍了拍我的脖子说：“不，杰克，一先令补偿不了那种事儿，对吗，老伙计？”

尽管杰里坚决反对为讨好一些草率的人而拼命驾驶，但是他赶车一向不错，也不反对马力全开，他说只要他知道是为什么就行。

我清楚记得，一天早上，我们正在车站等乘客时，一个提着沉重旅行皮箱的年轻人踩到了人行道上的一块橘子皮，重重地摔倒在地。

杰里第一个跑过去，扶他站起来。他看起来好像很惊讶，他们把他扶进一家商店，他走起路来好像非常痛苦。当然，杰里又回到了站台。但是，大约十分钟后，一个店员大声叫他。于是，我们就停到了人行道上。

“你能把我送到东南火车站吗？”年轻人说，“我怕，这不幸的一跤已经让我误点了。但是，我不能错过十二点的火车，这对我至关重要。如果你能及时把我送到那儿，我会感激不尽，而且非常乐意多付你一些车费。”

杰里诚恳地说：“先生，如果你认为身体过得去的话，我会竭尽全力的。”因为看上去他脸色惨白，病恹恹的。

“我必须走，”他认真地说，“请打开门，让我们一刻也不要耽误。”

杰里立刻登上了驾驶座，向我愉悦地吆喝了一声，缰绳一拉，我就心领神会。

“喂，杰克，我的伙计，”他说，“飞跑吧，只要我们知道为什么，我们就要让他们看看我们是怎么飞过地面的。”

中午时分要在城里把车赶快总是很难，这时街上车水马龙。不过，我们还是竭尽所能。一个好车夫和一匹好马相互了解，同心协力，肯定能做得非常出色。我有一张很好的嘴巴——也就是说，稍微碰一下缰绳，我就能听从指挥。如果你想在中午时分快速穿过伦敦，就需要好多实践经验。

我和杰里习惯了这一点。如果我们下定决心穿过去，谁都快不过我们。我敏捷胆大，总能相信我的车夫；杰里动作快，同时又有耐心，相信自己的马儿。他很少用鞭子。当他想加快速度时，我会从他的语气和“驾驾”声中知道，也会通过缰绳知道要去哪儿，所以不用鞭打。不过，我必须言归正传。

那天街上水泄不通，而我们却一路走得相当顺畅，但是到了齐普赛街路口，却堵了三四分钟。年轻人伸出头，焦急地说：“我想我最好还是下车走吧。如果这样继续下去，我就永远赶不到那儿了。”

“先生，我会竭尽所能，”杰里说，“我认为我们还来得及。这次堵车不可能太久。再说，你的行李很重，你提不动的，先生。”

就在这时，我们前面的敞篷双轮车开始向前移动，随后我们漂亮转弯，穿街过巷，进进出出，拼命奔跑。说来奇怪，伦敦桥上居然畅通无阻，因为出租马车和四轮马车整个儿排成长队都跟着我们一路飞奔，也许都想去赶那趟火车。不管怎样，当大钟的指针指向十二点差八分时，我们和其他好多马车一起飞快地驶进了车站。

“谢天谢地！我们终于赶上了。”年轻人说，“感谢你，我的朋友，还有你的好马。你救了我，这是金钱无法回报的。收下这额外的二先令六便士。”

“不，先生，不，感谢你的美意。很高兴我们赶上了时间，先生。现在不要耽搁了，先生，铃响了。喂，搬运工！把这位先生的行李搬到——多佛线——十二点的火车上——就这样。”没等对方再说一个字，杰里就飞快地让我调过头，给其他在最后时刻冲过来的马车让路，我们停在一边，直到车流高峰期过去。

“真高兴！他说，“真高兴！可怜的小伙子！我不知道是什么让他这样焦急！”

杰里经常大声自言自语，我们不是在行进途中时，我都能听清他的话。

杰里回到站点后，大家对他拼命赶火车捞外快好一阵子嘲笑，他们说这一切违背了他的原则，他们想知道他捞了多少外快。

“比我平时赚的要多得多，”他狡黠地点了点头说，“他给我的能让我回去以后稍微舒服好几天。”

“胡说八道！”有个人说。

“他骗人，”另一个人说，“一边告诫我们，一边自己还是那样做。”

“喂，伙计们，”杰里说，“那位先生给了我两个半先令外快，但是我没有接。看到他赶上火车时欢天喜地的样子，对我就足够了。如果我和杰克想不时快跑一下自得其乐，那是我们自己的事儿，不是你们的事儿。”

“啊，”拉里说，“你永远都成不了富人。”

“很可能不会，”杰里说，“但是，我知道我不会因此而不快。我听人读过好多次戒律，但是我从来没有注意到任何一条说：‘你要做富人。’《新约》里有好多关于富人的新奇事儿。我想，如果我像他们那样，我认为那一定会让我感到有些不舒服。”

“如果你真的富有，”格兰特老板从他的马车顶上回过头说，“这是你应得的，杰里。你不会因财富而受到诅咒。至于你，拉里，你到死都会很穷。你鞭子用得太多了。”

“那么，”拉里说，“马不挨鞭子就不愿走，该怎么办？”

“你从来不费心去看看没有鞭子马儿会不会走路，你挥鞭的样子始终像胳膊得了小舞蹈病似的。如果这不让你筋疲力尽，就会让你的马筋疲力尽。你总是在换马，知道为什么吗？因为你从来不给他们任何安宁或鼓励。”

“唉，我运气不好，”拉里说，“这才是症结所在。”

“你永远不会好运，”老板说，“好运特别关照与她并驾齐驱的人，她通常喜欢那些有判断力、心肠好的人，至少这是我的经验。”

格兰特老板又转过去看起了报纸，其他人也回到了自己的车上。

第三十六章　礼拜天的出租马车

一天早上，杰里刚把我套进车辕，正在系挽绳时，一位先生走进了院子。“愿为你效劳，先生。”杰里说。

“早上好，巴克先生。”那位先生说，“我很高兴跟你商议礼拜天早上送布利格斯夫人去教堂一事。我们现在去新教堂，有些远，她无法步行去。”

“谢谢你，先生。”杰里说，“但是，我只取得了六天制营运执照(1)，所以礼拜天我不能载客，那是非法的。”

“噢！”那个人说，“我不知道你的是六天制马车，但是，变更一下执照肯定非常容易。我看这样做，你也不会有什么损失。事实上，布里格斯夫人非常喜欢由你为她驾车。”

“先生，我很高兴帮夫人的忙，而我也有过七天制执照，那活儿对我和我的马儿都太辛苦了。年复一年，没有一天休息，从来没有陪妻子和孩子们过过一个礼拜天，而且从来没有时间去做礼拜。我开始赶出租马车前，已经习惯礼拜天去教堂了。所以，最近五年，我只持六天制执照，发现这样在各方面都更好。”

“啊，当然。”布里格斯先生答道，“每个人都应该休息，礼拜天能去教堂，这合情合理，但是我想你不会介意这匹马跑这短短的一段路，再说一天只有一次。整个下午和晚上都是你的，你知道我们是很好的顾客。”

“是的，先生，这没错，我的确很感激所有的帮助，我可以为你和夫人效劳的任何事儿，我都应该自豪和高兴地去做。不过，先生，我不能放弃我的星期天，真的不能。我在书上读过，上帝造人，他也造了马和其他所有动物。一造好这些生灵，他就定下了一个休息日，还下令七天里大家都要休息一天。所以，先生，我认为上帝一定知道这对他们有什么好处，我也相信这对我有好处。因为我有一天休息，所以我更加强壮、健康了。马儿也精神抖擞，不会很快就筋疲力尽。六天制赶车人都这样对我说，我在银行里的存款也比以前多了。至于妻子和孩子们，先生——啊，都很开心！他们无论如何也不愿我再回到七天制工作状态了。”

“噢，很好。”那位先生说，“别再费心了，巴克先生。我到别处去打听一下。”说完，他就走了。

“唉，”杰里对我说，“我们无能为力，杰克，老伙计。我们必须有自己的礼拜天。”

“波莉！”他叫道，“波莉！过来。”

波莉立马就来了。

“这一切是怎么回事，杰里？”

“啊，亲爱的，布里格斯先生想要我每个礼拜天上午都送布里格斯夫人去做礼拜。我说我只有六天制营运执照。他说：‘办个七天制营运执照，我会酬谢你。’波莉，你知道，他们是我们很好的顾客。布里格斯夫人经常出去买东西或拜访，一去就是几个小时，然后当场付钱，公平体面，像个淑女。从来不会杀价，也不会像有些人那样把三个小时说成是两个半小时，对马儿来说也轻松自在，不用为那些迟到十五分钟的人一路狂奔去赶火车。如果我在这件事上不帮她的忙，我们很可能就会完全做不成他们的生意。你说说看，老婆？”

“我说，杰里，”她缓缓地说，“我说，即使布里格斯夫人每个礼拜天早上给你一枚金币，我也不愿你再做七天制车夫。我们早已知道没有礼拜天是什么滋味了，现在我们才知道有自己的礼拜天是什么样子。谢天谢地，你赚的钱够养活我们了，尽管有时买燕麦、干草，再加上交营运执照年费和租金等等日子紧巴巴的，但是，哈里很快就能赚钱了，所以我宁愿再辛苦点儿，也不愿回到那些可怕的日子了。你差不多连看一眼自己孩子的时间都没有，我们也从来不能一起去做礼拜，不能有一天快乐安宁的日子。我们千万不要再回到那些日子了，我就说这些，杰里。”

“我就是这样告诉布里格斯先生的，亲爱的，”杰里说，“这也是我想要坚持的。所以，波莉，别再去烦恼了，”因为她已经开始哭了，“就是赚两倍的钱，我也不会再回到从前的日子了，所以放心吧，老婆。好了，打起精神，我要去车站了。”

这次对话后，三周已经过去了，布里格斯夫人没有再订过车，所以只有从车站接活。杰里对此非常痛心，因为人和马肯定更辛苦。但是，波莉总是给他鼓劲，说：“不用担心，他爸，不用担心：

竭尽全力，
不及其余，
有朝一日，
万事顺利。”

很快，大家就知道杰里是因为什么失去了他最好的顾客。大多数人都说他是傻瓜，但还是有两三个人支持他。

“如果劳工们都不坚守自己的礼拜天，”杜鲁门说，“那他们很快就会一无所有。这是每个人的权利，也是每个动物的权利。根据上帝的法律，我们要有一天休息；根据英国的法律，我们也要有一天休息。我要说，我们应该坚持这些法律赋予我们的权利，并为我们的孩子们保住这些权利。”

“你们这些信教的家伙这样说顶好，”拉里说，“但是，我能赚一先令就会去赚一先令。我不相信宗教，因为我看你们这些信教的人比其他人好不到哪儿去。”

“如果他们好不到哪儿去，”杰里插话说，“那是因为他们并不虔诚。你也许会说我们国家的法律不健全，因为有人会违法。如果一个人爱发脾气，诽谤邻居，欠债不还，不管他做多少次礼拜，都不是虔诚的教徒。就是有些人弄虚作假，那也不会把宗教变成假的。真正的宗教是世界上最好、最真的东西，也是唯一能让人感到真正快乐和让我们生活的世界变得更好的东西。”

“无论如何，如果说宗教有好处的话，”琼斯说，“那它就会阻止你们那些教徒迫使我们礼拜天工作，你们知道他们当中好多人都这样做，这就是我说宗教只是骗人的原因——啊，要不是有人去教堂礼拜，我们根本不值得礼拜天出门。但是，他们有他们所谓的特权，而我却没有。如果我没有机会拯救自己的灵魂，那就指望他们为我的灵魂负责了。”

好几个人为此鼓起了掌，随后杰里说道：

“尽管这听上去没错，但却行不通。每个人必须照顾自己的灵魂，你不能把它像弃婴一样放在别人的门口，指望别人来照顾它。你不明白，如果你总是坐在驾驶座上等乘客，他们就会说：‘如果我们不坐他的马车，别人就会坐，他也不希望有什么礼拜天。’当然，他们没有弄清事情的真相，否则他们就会明白，如果他们从来不坐马车，你站在那儿是不会有用的。然而，人们总是不想弄清事情的真相。这样做也许不便。但是，如果你们礼拜天工作的车夫都罢工要求休息一天，事情不就搞定了嘛。”

“如果所有的好人都去不了他们中意的传教士那儿，他们该怎么办？”拉里说。

“我不能为别人制订计划，”杰里说，“但是，如果他们走不了很远，他们可以去较近的地方；如果下雨，他们就可以像平日那样穿上雨衣。如果一件事正确，就可以去做；如果一件事错误，就可以不做。一个好人总会找到办法。这无论是对我们马车夫还是对去教堂礼拜的人都像真理一样。”

————————————————————

(1) 由于出租马车的年费急剧减少，近年，六天制马车和七天制马车之间的差异被废除。——作者原注

第三十七章　金科玉律

之后，又过了两三周，一天深夜，我们走进院子时，波莉提着灯笼穿过大路跑了过来（如果天不下雨，她总是提着灯笼给杰里照明）。

“杰里，一切都好起来了，布里格斯夫人今天下午派仆人过来让你明天十一点送她出去。我说：‘行，我想可以，我们还以为她现在雇用别人了呢。’

“‘啊，’他说，‘真实情况是，巴克先生拒绝礼拜天出车，主人非常生气。他一直在尝试用别的出租马车，但是他们都有毛病，有的驾得太快，有些驾得太慢，夫人说没有一个像你的马车一样漂亮干净，只有巴克先生的马车最适合她。’”

波莉快要喘不过气来了，杰里突然欢笑了起来。

“‘有朝一日，万事顺利。’你说得对，亲爱的，你一向说得对。跑进去把晚饭端来，我要取下杰克的马具，让他立刻舒适、开心一下。”

这之后，布里格斯夫人像以前一样频繁地乘坐杰里的车，却从来没有在礼拜天乘坐过。不过，有一天，我们在礼拜天也干了活，情况是这样的：星期六夜里，我们回到家里，都很累，但是想到第二天可以好好休息就非常高兴，而情况并不是这样。

礼拜天早上，杰里正在院子里给我清洗，这时波莉走到他的身边，看上去忧心忡忡。

“怎么了？”杰里说。

“噢，亲爱的，”她说，“可怜的戴娜·布朗刚让人送来一封信，说她的妈妈病危，如果她还想见到活着的她的话，就必须马上去。那个地方距离这儿有十多英里，是在乡下。她说，如果她坐火车去，还要步行四英里。她身体非常虚弱，婴儿才四个星期大，那肯定不可能，所以她想知道你愿不愿拉她去，她承诺她一有钱就会如数付给你。”

“啧，啧！我们看看再说吧。我想的不是钱，而是想会失去礼拜天。马很累，我也很累——这才是症结所在。”

“这件事非常棘手，”波莉说，“不过你不在，礼拜天就没了一半。你也知道，我们想要别人怎么对待我们，就应该怎么对待别人。我非常清楚，如果我的母亲奄奄一息，我就会想要什么。所以，杰里，亲爱的，我相信那不是不守安息日，因为如果我们把一头可怜的动物或驴子拉出陷阱，不会破坏安息日的话，我就完全相信送可怜的戴娜也不会破坏安息日。”

“啊，波莉，你像牧师一样善良。这样吧，既然今天我已经听过礼拜天早晨的布道，你可以去告诉戴娜，我会在大钟敲响十下时为她准备停当。不过，等一下——请顺路带去我对布雷顿肉铺的问候，问他能不能把他那辆双轮轻便马车借给我，我知道他礼拜天从来不用它。这对那匹马来说将会截然不同，大有裨益。”

她去了，很快就返回来，说他可以随意使用那辆双轮轻便马车。

“好吧，”他说，“现在给我准备一点儿面包和奶酪，我会尽可能下午回来。”

“我会准备好早茶吃的肉馅饼，而不是晚餐。”说完，波莉就走了。这时，杰里哼起《波莉真有女人味》的小曲，他非常喜欢这个小曲。

他选我来跑这趟路，十点钟我们就拉着一辆轻便高轮马车出发了，高轮马车拉起来轻松自如，跟四轮马车相比仿佛再好不过了。

那是五月的一个晴天，我们一出城，芬芳的空气、鲜草的气息和松软的乡路都让我心旷神怡，好像回到了过去的岁月，所以我很快就开始感到精神抖擞。

戴娜的家人住在一个小农舍里，农舍位于一条绿色小路的尽头，靠近一个绿树成荫的牧场。那儿有两头牛正在吃草。一个年轻人让杰里把马车赶进牧场，拴在牛棚里，他说他真希望能提供一个更好的马厩。

“如果你的奶牛不会受到冒犯的话，”杰里说，“没有什么比在你这美丽的牧场上待一两个小时更让我的马儿欢喜的了。他很安分，而这也是对他少有的款待。”

“牵来吧，别客气。”年轻人说，“你对我的姐姐这样好，我们最乐意帮助你。我们一小时后就要吃饭，我希望你进来跟我们一起吃，尽管妈妈病情严重，我们全家都不开心。”

杰里对他表示衷心的感谢，说自己随身带有吃的，他最想做的就是在牧场四处走走。

我身上的马具取下后，我不知道应该先做什么——是吃草还是打滚儿，是躺下休息还是自由自在地尽情奔跑在草地上。这一切我都轮流做了一遍。杰里看上去跟我一样非常高兴，他在岸边的一棵成荫的树下坐下来，听着鸟鸣，然后自己也唱了起来，接着读起了那本他非常喜欢的棕色封面的小书，随后绕着牧场漫步，沿着小溪走，在那儿他摘了一些鲜花和山楂果，用长长的常青藤条束起来。接下来，他让我好好吃了一顿随身带来的燕麦。但是，时间好像太短了——自从离开伯爵府和可怜的姜姐，我就没有到过田野。

我们慢悠悠地回家了。当我们走到院子里时，杰里首先这样说道：“啊，波莉，我终究没有失去礼拜天，因为每一片灌木丛中都总有鸟儿在唱圣歌，我也一起做了礼拜。至于杰克，他就像一匹小马驹似的。”

当他把鲜花递给多莉时，她开心地跳起舞来。

第三十八章　多莉和真君子

冬天早早地来了，天气非常寒冷潮湿。一连几个星期，每天不是下雪就是下雨，要么就是雨夹雪，就是有所变化，也只是刺骨的大风天或是凛冽的霜冻。马儿们都切身体会到了这一点。当天气干冷时，两块厚旅行毛毯就会让我们保暖，而当大雨袭来时，这些毯子很快就会湿透，盖着反而没有任何好处。有些车夫会在我们的身上盖一块防水布，那是一个好东西，但是，有些马夫很穷，既没有能力保护自己，也没有能力保护他们的马儿。那年冬天，马夫中的好多人都饱受煎熬。工作半天之后，我们马儿就可以到干燥的马厩休息，而他们马夫还得坐在驾驶座上等，如果是等一个宴会的话，有时就要等到凌晨一两点钟。

冰天雪地街上很滑，那对我们马儿来说最糟糕。这样负重走一英里，蹄踩不坚实，比在好路上跑四英里还要费劲儿。为了保持平衡，我们身体的每根神经和每块肌肉都绷得紧紧的。此外，对摔跤的忧虑比其他任何东西都更让马儿耗力。如果路面真的很糟，我们的蹄铁就会装防滑钉，而刚开始这让我们神经紧张。

天气很差时，好多人常常会坐在附近的酒馆里，让别人替他们守候。但是，那样他们往往会错过乘客，而且，就像杰里说的那样，在那儿不可能不花钱。他从来不去日出酒家，附近有一家咖啡店，他偶尔去那儿，或者向一个来我们这儿卖热咖啡和馅饼的老头购买。他认为，烈酒和啤酒过后会让人更冷，让车夫保暖的最好的东西是干爽的衣服、可口的食物、快乐的心情和家里体贴的妻子。他不能回家时，波莉就会给他提供吃的，有时他会看到小多莉从街角那边偷看，以确定爸爸在不在车站。如果看到了爸爸，她就会飞快地跑开，很快拿着罐子或提着篮子跑回来，里面盛着波莉准备好的热汤或布丁。这么一个小东西能安全穿过常常车马成群的街道，真是令人惊奇。然而，她是一个勇敢的小姑娘，感到给爸爸送他所谓的“第一道菜”是她的无上光荣。她在车站上很受欢迎，如果杰里不能送她安全过街，所有人都愿代劳。

一个寒冷的风天，多莉给杰里送来了一盆热气腾腾的东西，他吃时她站在旁边。他刚要开始吃，一位先生飞快地走向我们，举起了伞。杰里也碰了碰帽子作为回应，把盆递给了多莉，正要拿掉我身上的布，这时那位先生赶紧走上来，叫道：“不，不，喝完汤，我的朋友。尽管我抽不出多少时间，但是我可以等你把汤喝完，再把你的小姑娘送到人行道上。”这样说着，他自己坐进了马车。杰里向他表示了衷心的感谢，然后又回到了多莉的身边。

“你瞧，多莉，这是一位绅士，一位真正的绅士，多莉。他还有时间为一位穷车夫和一个小女孩的舒适考虑。”

杰里喝完汤，把孩子送过街道，然后按照吩咐，驱车去了克拉珀姆高地。这之后，这位先生又坐了好几次我们的车。我想他非常喜欢狗和马，因为每当我们把他送到家门口时，两三条狗就会跳出来迎接他。有时他会走过来拍拍我，用平静愉悦的口吻说道：“这马儿有一个好主人，他也应该有一个好主人。”很少有人会注意到一匹一直为他做事的马儿。我知道女士们偶尔会这样做，这位先生，以及其他一两位也曾拍过我，对我说过体贴的话，但是，百分之九十九的人宁愿想起去拍一台拉火车的蒸汽机。

那位先生不大年轻了，肩膀向前倾，就像他总是扑向什么东西似的。他的嘴唇薄薄的，紧闭着，但是脸上带着非常愉快的微笑。他的眼神敏锐，下巴和头部的动作让人觉得他做任何事情都非常坚决。他的声音亲切悦耳，任何马儿都会信任那种声音，尽管那声音像和他有关的其他一切那样坚定。

一天，他和另一位先生一起坐我们的车。他们在R街的一家商店前停下来，他的朋友进去时，他站在门口。在我们街对面稍靠前一点儿的地方，两匹非常漂亮的马拉着一辆车，正站在酒店前。车夫没有跟他们在一起，我说不清他们已经站了多久，但是他们好像以为自己等的时间已经够长了，就准备离开。他们还没走几步，车夫就跑出来，抓住了他们。看到他们移动，车夫好像勃然大怒，拿起鞭子和缰绳狠狠地惩罚他们，甚至还打他们的脑袋。我们的那位先生看到这一切，快步走过街道，声音果断地说道：

“如果你不立即住手，我就要以你离开自己的马和行为粗暴让人逮捕你。”

那个人明显是喝醉了，滔滔不绝地骂了一些脏话，但是不再打马，他拉起缰绳，上了马车。与此同时，我们的朋友面色平静地从口袋里掏出笔记本，看了看马车上的名字和地址，记下了什么。

“你记那个干吗？”车夫一边挥鞭前进，一边吼道。他得到的回应只是点头和冷笑。

返回马车时，我们的朋友和他的同伴走到一起，他的同伴大声笑道：“赖特，我本以为你自己操心的事儿够多了，不会费心去管别人的马和仆人了呢。”

我们的朋友一动不动站了一会儿，头稍微后仰：“你知道这个世界为什么像现在这样糟糕吗？”

“不知道。”另一个人说。

“那我告诉你。那是因为人们只想着自己的事儿，不愿费心去支持受压迫者，也不愿揭露那些作恶者。看到这种坏事，我绝不会袖手旁观，好多主人感谢我让他们知道自己的马受到了怎样的虐待。”

“先生，我真希望有更多像你一样的绅士，”杰里说，“因为这个城市迫切需要你们。”

之后，我们继续赶路。当他们下车时，他说：“这就是我的原则，如果我们看到残忍或错误之事，有能力阻止却毫无作为，那我们自己也会成为罪人。”

第三十九章　破衣萨姆

应该说，作为一匹拉出租车的马，我的确处境很好。我的车夫是我的主人，即使他不是那么好的人，善待我、不让我过分劳累也符合他的利益。但是，好多马都是那些马车大老板的，他们以每天很高的价格把马车租给车夫。因为那些马不属于这些车夫，所以他们只想着从马身上赚钱，先付给老板，然后养家糊口。其中一些马的日子非常艰难。当然，我只理解一点点儿，但是车站上常常讨论这件事儿。老板是一个心地善良而又喜欢马儿的人，如果看到马筋疲力尽或受到虐待，他就会大声呼吁。

一天，一个名叫“破衣萨姆”的车夫牵马过来，他衣衫褴褛，可怜巴巴，看上去那匹马受到过狠狠的抽打。老板说：

“你和你的马更适合去警察局，而不是来这个地方。”

那个人把他那块破毯子扔在马身上，完全转向老板，以听上去近乎绝望的声音说：

“如果警察跟这件事儿有关的话，那应该是跟向我们要价太高的老板们有关，或者是跟定得太低的车费有关。如果一个人不得不像当下我们中的好多人一样每天得付十八先令才能使用一辆车和两匹马，而且必须付清这些钱，我们才会为自己赚钱，那我要说这就不仅仅是辛苦了。每天开始谋生之前，要先从每匹马身上赚九先令。你知道那是实情，如果马儿不工作，我们就一定会饿死，我和孩子们之前都已经知道那意味着什么。我有六个孩子，只有一个能赚点钱。我每天要在车站待十四或十六个小时，有十或十二周没有歇过一个礼拜天了。你知道斯金纳只要掌势就从来不给一天休息时间，如果我不辛苦工作，告诉我谁辛苦工作！我想要保暖外套和雨衣，但是我要养活这么多张嘴，怎么能买得起呢？一周前，为了付给斯金纳租金，我不得不典当自己的钟表，所以我再也见不到它了。”

其他一些站在四周的车夫都点头称是。那个人继续说道：

“如果你们有自己的马和车，或者为好心的车主驾车，就有机会过好日子，也有机会做对事情；我却没有。在四英里范围内，跑完一英里后的每英里，我们收费不能超过六便士。今天早上我不得不跑了整整六英里，就赚了三先令。我返程没有乘客，只好一路空车回来。马儿跑了十二英里，我就赚了三先令。这之后，我有一笔三英里的生意，如果提包和箱子放在外面，我足足可以多赚两便士之多。但是，你知道人们是怎么做的。所有能放在前座上的东西都堆了进来，三只沉甸甸的箱子压在最上面。东西是六便士，车费是一先令六便士。后来，我回程时赚了一先令。现在马儿跑了十八英里，我赚了六先令。那匹马还要赚三先令，下午的马再赚九先令，我才能摸到一便士。当然，也并不总是那样糟糕，但是你知道经常是这样。所以我说告诉一个人不要让马儿劳累过度是一个笑柄，因为当一头畜生筋疲力尽时，只有鞭子会使他抬腿前进。你无能为力——你必须先考虑妻子和孩子，再考虑马儿，车主们必须注意这一点，我们不能。我不是为了这个而虐马。你们谁也不能说我虐待马。某个地方不妥——从来没有休息一天——没有跟妻子和孩子们安生过过一个小时。我常常觉得自己垂垂老矣，尽管我才四十五岁。你知道有些贵族多么性急，他们怀疑我们骗人，多收费。唉，他们手里拿着钱包，站在那儿一便士一便士地数钱，拿眼看着我们，就像我们是扒手似的。我真希望他们有些人每天都能风雨无阻地在我的车上坐十六个小时，这样赚的钱除了交十八先令，才能谋生，这样他们就不会做出从来不多付六便士或把所有行李都塞进车里这种稀罕事了。还好，有些人会不时给我们一些相当可观的小费，否则我们就活不下去。但是，你不能总指望这个。”

那些站在四周的人都非常赞成这个说法，其中一个人说：“这种辛苦真让人绝望。一个人偶尔做错事，倒也不奇怪，但是如果他喝多了，谁会去对他发脾气呢？”

杰里没有加入这次谈话，但是我以前从来没有看到他的脸色如此悲伤。老板刚才站在那儿两手插进口袋，现在从帽子里拿出手帕擦了擦前额。

“你驳倒了我，萨姆，”他说，“因为这都是事实，我再也不会拿警察来跟你说事儿了。刚才是那匹马的眼神刺激了我。这是人的不幸，也是马的不幸，我不知道谁会改正这一点。但是不管怎样，你可以告诉这个可怜的马儿，这样使唤他，你感到难过。有时，一句好话就是我们能给这些可怜的畜生的一切，如果他们真正明白，那就太好了。”

这次谈话几天后的一天早上，一个新人拉着萨姆的马车来到车站。

“喂！”有个人说，“破衣萨姆怎么了？”

“他卧病在床，”那个人说，“他昨晚在院子里病倒了，几乎爬不回家。他的妻子今天早上派一个男孩子来说他的爸爸在发高烧，出不了车，所以我就来替他。”

第二天早上，那个人又来了。

“萨姆怎么样了？”老板问。

“他走了。”那个人说。

“什么，走了？你不是说他死了吧？”

“刚断气，”那个人说，“他是今天凌晨四点死的。昨天一整天他都在说胡话——语无伦次地说斯金纳，说没有礼拜天。‘我从来没有休过一个礼拜天。’这就是他临终的话。”

好一阵子，谁都没有说话。随后，老板说道：“伙计们，我告诉你们什么呢，这就是对我们的警告。”

第四十章　可怜的姜姐

一天，我们的马车和好多其他马车一起在一个音乐表演的公园外等候，这时一辆破旧马车停到了我们的车边。拉车的是一匹疲惫不堪的栗色老马，毛皮保养得很差，瘦骨嶙峋，膝盖弯曲，前腿摇摇晃晃。我一直在吃干草，风把一小簇干草卷到了那个方向，可怜的老马伸出瘦长的脖子衔起，然后转过头，环顾四周想再找一些。她黯然无神的眼睛充满绝望，我不禁注意起她来。这时，我在想着我以前曾在哪儿见过这匹马，她仔细打量着我，说：“黑骏马，是你吗？”

是姜姐！可是，变化真大啊！原来优美弯曲、富有光泽的脖子现在平直、细瘦、凹陷；原来整齐挺拔的腿和精致的球节肿胀了起来，关节部位因辛苦劳作而变形；原来意气风发的脸现在饱经沧桑，而且从她上下起伏的肋部和频繁的咳嗽声中，我可以看出她的呼吸是多么糟糕。

我们的车夫们一起站在一小段距离开外。于是，我悄悄地向她走了一两步，这样我们就可以小声说话了。她讲述的是一段悲惨的故事。

在伯爵府进行了十二个月的跑步康复训练之后，他们认为她又适合去干活了，就把她卖给了一位先生。有一小阵子，她过得很好，但是跑得比平时久了，她就会旧病复发，所以经过休息和治疗之后，她又被卖了。就这样，她被转了好几次手，但一次不如一次。

“就这样，最后，”她说，“我被一个拥有好多车马做出租之用的人买下了。看上去你身体健康，我很高兴，但是我过的日子无法跟你说啊。当他们发现我的毛病时，他们就说我不值他们出的价，所以我必须去拉低等级的马车，就是要让我筋疲力尽。他们就是这样干的，他们拿鞭子抽我，让我干活，从来没有一个人想过我遭受的痛苦——他们说他们花钱买我，必须把这个钱从我的身上赚回来。那个现在租我的人每天都要向老板付一大笔钱，所以他必须得把这钱从我的身上赚回来。就这样，一周又一周，礼拜天我从来没有休息过。”

我说：“你过去一向是一受到虐待就捍卫自己的啊。”

“啊！”她说，“我做过一次，但是那没用。人最强大，如果他们冷酷无情，我们就只能忍受，忍啊忍，直到死去。我真希望死期来临，我真希望自己死去。我见过死马，我相信他们不受苦了。我真希望我在干活时倒地身亡，而不是被送到屠马场。”

我非常难过，把鼻子凑到她的鼻子上，但是我说不出一句安慰她的话来。我想她见到我很高兴，因为她说：“你是我有生以来唯一的朋友。”

就在这时，她的车夫走过来，一把拽住她的嘴，将她牵离了马车队伍，驱车而去，留下我难过不已。

不久之后，一辆载着一头死马的双轮马车经过我们的出租车停车场。马头耷拉在车尾，毫无生气的舌头慢慢地滴着血，眼睛凹陷。但是，我难以诉说，那情景是多么可怕。那是一匹脖子瘦长的栗色马。我看到额头下面有一道白色条纹。我相信那是姜姐，我希望是她，因为那样的话，她的痛苦就会结束了。噢！如果人们更仁慈的话，他们就应该在我们沦落到如此惨境之前开枪打死我们。

第四十一章　肉铺

我看到的那些伦敦马当中的好多麻烦，大多是可以靠一点儿常识来避免的。如果我们马儿受到合理的对待，就不会介意辛苦工作。我相信，好多给穷人拉车的马儿比我过去常常佩戴着镶银马具、吃着高级食物给W伯爵夫人拉车时开心。

看到那些小马吃力地拉着重物或在粗俗残忍的男孩子的重击下蹒跚而行，常常让我伤心。有一次，我看到一匹小灰马，只见他长着浓密的鬃毛和漂亮的脑袋，酷似快乐腿，如果我的身上没有马具，我就会对他嘶叫。他正在竭尽全力拉一辆重车，而一个强壮粗鲁的男孩子正用鞭子狠狠地抽打他的腹部，残忍地敲他的小嘴。这会是快乐腿吗？就是像他。不过，布罗姆菲尔德先生绝不会卖他，我想他不会这样做。但是，这匹马很可能是一匹好马，小时候也有一个快乐的成长环境。

我常常注意到肉铺的马被赶得飞快，尽管我不知道为什么，直到有一天，我们在圣约翰林场等了一段时间，才明白是怎么回事。隔壁是一家肉铺，我们正站在那儿时，肉铺的一辆马车飞奔而来。那匹马热汗淋淋，筋疲力尽，耷拉着脑袋，他上下起伏的肋部和颤抖的腿表明，他被赶得是多么猛烈。那个小伙子跳下马车，拿出篮子，老板从店里走出来，一脸不快。他看了看马之后，生气地转向小伙子。

“我对你说多少次了，不要这样赶车？你毁了上一匹马，损坏了他的呼吸系统，你又要以同样的方式毁了这匹马。你要不是我的亲生儿子，我就会当场解雇你。你把一匹赶成这种状况的马带回店里，真丢人。你这样驾驶很可能会被警察带走，你要是被带走，不要指望我保你，因为我对你说已经说烦了，你必须自己当心。”

说这话时，那个男孩子站在旁边，脸色阴沉，态度顽固，而他的父亲一停住话头，他就突然发起了火。这不是他的过错，他不应该承担过错。他始终只是在奉命行事。

“你总是说：‘喂，快点；喂，赶快！’我去那些人家时，一家想要一条羊腿早做晚饭，我必须十五分钟内赶回来；另一家厨师忘了订牛肉，我必须取来送去，然后立刻赶回，否则夫人就要责骂；那个主妇说，他们家里来了不速之客，必须马上送去一些排骨；住在新月街四号的那位女士，不等到午餐肉送到，就从来不订晚餐肉。所以，一直就是匆匆忙忙赶来赶去。如果那些贵族事先想好他们要什么，提前一天预订好他们要的肉，你就不用这样斥责我了！”

“但愿他们会，”屠夫说，“如果事先知道，我就不用这样莫名其妙地烦恼，还能更好地让顾客满意——可是，你看——说有什么用——谁会考虑一个卖肉的方便，谁会考虑肉铺的马呢？得了，把他牵进来，好好照顾他，记住，他今天不能再出去了。如果他们还要别的什么，你就提着篮子自己去。”说完，他就走了进去，马被牵走了。

不过，并不是所有的男孩子都冷酷无情。我见过一些男孩子喜欢他们的马驹或驴子，就像宠爱小狗一样，而且那些小家伙为他们的年轻车夫不停地连续工作，就像我现在为杰里工作一样心甘情愿、高高兴兴。尽管有时干活很苦，但是朋友的抚摸和话语会让一切轻松自如。

有一个年轻小贩拉着青菜和土豆来到我们的街上，他有一匹老矮种马，长得不很好看，但却是我见过的最快乐、最勇敢的矮种马，看到他们俩相互那样喜欢，真让人高兴。那匹马像狗一样跟着他的主人。男孩子坐上马车后，不用鞭子，不用说话，小马就会一路小跑，快乐地穿街而过，好像他是从王后的马厩里出来似的。杰里喜欢那个男孩子，叫他“查理王子”，因为他说他有朝一日会成为车夫王。

还有一位老人以前常常拉着一辆小煤车来到我们的街上，他戴着一顶运煤工的帽子，看上去粗糙黝黑。他和他的老马常常一起沿街慢行，就像两个互相了解的好伴侣。那匹马常常会主动在门口停下来，让他们卸煤。他常常让一只耳朵弯向主人。老人还没走近，整条街就能听到他的喊声。我从来不知道他说的是什么，但是小孩子们都叫他“老巴呼”，因为他的声音听上去像是那样。波莉非常友好地从他那儿买煤，杰里说想到一匹老马能在一个穷地方这样快乐，真是一种安慰。

第四十二章　选举

一天下午，我们进院子时，波莉走了出来。“杰里！B先生来我这儿问你选票的事儿，他想租你的马车去选举，他要等你的回话。”

“啊，波莉，你可以说我的马车另有用场。我不喜欢马车上贴满他们的大海报，还要让杰克和上尉跑到那些酒馆去接那些喝得半醉的投票人，啊，我认为那对马儿是一种侮辱。不，我不会那样做。”

“我想你会给那位先生投票吧？他说他跟你的政治立场一致。”

“在有些事儿上是一致的，但我不会为他投票，波莉。你知道他是做什么生意的吗？”

“知道。”

“那么，一个靠做这一行致富的人在有些方面好倒是好，但是他对劳动人民的需要视而不见。照我的良心，我不能推举他去制定法律。我敢说他们会生气，但是每个人都必须做他认为对国家最好的事儿。”

选举前的那天早上，杰里正把我套进车辕，这时多莉呜呜哭着走进院子，她的蓝色小上衣和白围裙上溅满了泥点。

“啊，多莉，怎么了？”

“那些顽皮的男孩子，”她哭诉道，“朝我身上扔泥土，还叫我小邋——遢——”

“爸爸，他们都叫她‘蓝色小邋遢’。”哈里非常生气地跑进来说，“不过，我已经回敬他们了。他们不会再侮辱妹妹了。我痛打了他们一顿，他们一定会记住的。一伙胆小、无赖的橙色流氓。”

杰里亲了亲孩子，说道：“宝贝儿，跑去妈妈那儿，告诉她，我觉得今天你最好待在家里帮她。”

随后，杰里神情严肃地转向哈里：

“我的孩子，我希望你会永远保护你的妹妹，无论是谁侮辱她，你都要狠狠地揍他一顿——就应该这样。但是，记住，我不会让人在我的地皮上耍流氓选举。世界上有好多蓝色流氓、橙色流氓，也有白色流氓、紫色流氓或其他颜色的流氓，但是我不会让自己的家人掺和进去。哪怕是妇女和孩子都乐意因一种颜色而跟别人争吵，但是他们中知道那颜色代表什么的人不到十分之一。”

“啊，爸爸，我还以为蓝色代表自由。”

“我的孩子，自由并非来自颜色，颜色只代表政党。你们从这些颜色中能得到的所有自由，就是有花别人的钱喝醉的自由，有坐着一辆肮脏旧马车去投选票的自由，有谩骂任何不穿你们党派颜色衣服的人、声嘶力竭地呼喊你似懂非懂的话语的自由——这就是你的自由！”

“噢，爸爸，你在开玩笑吧。”

“不，哈里，我是认真的，看到人们本不该上当却继续上当，真让人感到害臊。选举是一件非常严肃的事儿。至少应该如此，每个人都应该凭良心投票，并让他的邻居也这样做。”

第四十三章　患难之交

选举日终于到来了，我和杰里不缺活干。起初，来了一个身体矮胖、手提毛毡提包的先生，他想去主教门车站。随后，我们被一群想让我们送去摄政者公园的人叫住。接下来，我们在一条小巷里受到征用，因为那儿有一位胆怯、焦虑的老太太正在等着被送去银行，我们不得不又停下来，把她送回原地。我们刚让她下车，一位满面通红的先生就拿着一沓纸气喘吁吁地跑过来。还没等杰里下车，他就已经打开了门，突然坐进来，大声喊道：“弓街警察局，快！”于是，我们载他而去，又送了一两趟后，回到了车站，车站上没有其他马车。杰里给我戴上粮袋，因为就像他所说：“在像这样的日子，我们必须伺机吃东西，杰克，就这样用力咀嚼吧，充分利用时间，老伙计。”

我发现我吃的是用糠兑湿的碎燕麦的好料。这在任何时候都会是一种款待，而另一方面在当时还非常提神。杰里是那样体贴、善良——哪匹马不愿为这样的主人竭尽全力呢？随后，他拿出波莉准备的一张肉馅饼，站在我的旁边，开始吃了起来。街上水泄不通，那些涂有候选人颜色的马车在人群中横冲直撞，好像人的性命无足轻重似的。那天，我们看到有两个人被撞倒，其中一个是妇女。那些马是在遭罪，可怜的牲畜！但是，那些坐在车里的投票人根本没有想到这一点。其中好多人喝得半醉，如果他们自己党派的人经过，他们就会从马车窗里伸出头来欢呼。那是我见到的第一次选举，尽管我听说现在情况有所好转，但我还是不想再参加第二次。

我和杰里还没吃几口，一个可怜的年轻女人就沿街走来，只见她抱着一个沉甸甸的孩子。她左顾右盼，好像手足无措。不一会儿，她向杰里走来，问他能否告诉她去圣托马斯医院的路，到那儿有多远。她说，她那天早上坐着赶集的马车从乡下来，不知道选举的事儿，对伦敦完全不熟悉。医生吩咐她带小男孩去那家医院。孩子难受，哭得有气无力。

“可怜的小家伙！”她说，“他疼得受不了了。他四岁了，走路还像婴儿一样，不过，医生说，如果我能把他送进那家医院，他就可能会康复。求求你，先生，有多远，走哪条路？”

“唉，夫人，”杰里说，“你不可能步行穿过这样的人群到那儿的！唉，距离有三英里，这孩子很沉。”

“是的，哎呀，他很沉，但是，我强壮，感谢上帝，只要我知道路，我想我都会设法前进。请把路告诉我吧。”

“你做不到，”杰里说，“你可能会被撞倒，孩子也可能会被轧到。听我说，请上这辆车吧，我会把你安全送到医院。你没看见天要下雨了吗？”

“不，先生，不，我不能这样做，谢谢你，我带的钱只够回去用的。请告诉我路吧。”

“听我说，夫人，”杰里说，“我家里也有妻子和可爱的孩子，我知道一位父亲的感受。现在你坐上车，我免费送你去那儿。让一个女人和一个生病的孩子冒这样的险，我会为自己感到惭愧。”

“上天保佑你！”女人说着，放声大哭。

“好了，好了，打起精神，亲爱的，我会很快把你们送到那儿；来，让我扶你上车吧。”

杰里去开门时，两个男人——帽子和纽扣孔都标上了颜色——跑过来叫道：“马车！”

“有人订了。”杰里叫道。但是，其中一个男人从那个女人的身边挤过来，跳进马车，另一个人也跟着跳了进去。看上去杰里像警察一样严厉。“这辆马车已经被那位女士预订了，先生们。”

“女士！”其中一个人说，“噢！她可以等。我们的事儿非常重要，再说我们先坐进来，这是我们的权利，我们就待在里面。”

杰里关上车门，脸上掠过一丝滑稽的微笑。“好吧，先生们，请待在里面吧，想待多久就待多久。你们自己休息吧，我可以等。”说完，他对他们置之不理，走到年轻女人的跟前，她站在我的身边。“他们很快就会走的。”他笑道，“别烦恼，亲爱的。”

他们很快就走了，他们明白杰里的搪塞意图之后，就下了车，对他骂着各种难听的话，大声叫喊着他的车牌号，还说要让法院传唤他。这个小小的停顿之后，我们很快走在了去医院的路上，尽可能走背街小巷。杰里按响了大门铃，帮年轻女人下了马车。

“万分感谢。”她说，“我一个人绝不可能赶到这儿。”

“不用客气，我希望这个可爱的孩子会很快好转。”

他在门口望着她进去，轻轻地对自己说道：“你已经对一个最卑微的人那样做了。”随后，他拍了拍我的脖子。有什么事儿让他高兴时，他总是这样做。

当时，雨下得很紧。我们正要离开医院，门又打开了，门房大声叫道：“马车！”我们停了下来，一位女士走下台阶。杰里好像立刻认出了她。她向后移了移面纱，说道：“巴克！杰里迈亚·巴克，是你吗？很高兴在这儿遇到你。你正是我想要的朋友，因为今天在伦敦这一带租车很难。”

“为你服务，非常荣幸，夫人。我很高兴正巧在这儿。我送你去哪儿，夫人？”

“去帕丁顿车站，然后，如果我们来得及的话，我想我们来得及，你就把玛丽和孩子们的情况都告诉我吧。”

我们及时赶到了车站，那位女士站在候车棚下面，跟杰里聊了好一会儿。我发现她原来是波莉的女主人，打听了好多之后，她说：“你怎么觉得冬天拉车这活儿适合你呢？我知道玛丽去年很为你担忧。”

“是的，夫人，她是很担忧，我当时严重咳嗽，一直咳嗽到天气转暖。现在我在外面待得晚了，她的确非常担忧。夫人，你明白，这需要时时刻刻风雨无阻，的确考验一个男人的体质。但是，现在我过得相当不错，如果我没有马儿要照顾，就会感到空落落的。我从小就干这事儿，恐怕也干不好任何其他事儿。”

“好了，巴克，”她说，“如果你当真要拿自己的健康冒险干这工作，那将会非常遗憾，不仅仅是为你自己，也是为玛丽和孩子们。有好多地方需要好车夫或好马夫，如果你认为自己应该放弃拉出租马车这活儿，就告诉我。”

随后，她要巴克代她问玛丽好，并在他的手里放了一些什么，说道：“给两个孩子各五先令，玛丽会知道怎么花。”

杰里对她表示感谢，一副非常高兴的样子。我们走出车站，终于回到了家。不管怎样，我累了。

第四十四章　老上尉和接班人

我和上尉成了好朋友。他是一位出身高贵的老伙计，也是很好的伙伴。我从来没有想过他会不得不离开家，走下坡路，但还是轮到了他，事情就是这样。我当时不在场，不过，我后来听说了所有的一切。

他和杰里把一伙人送过伦敦桥，送到大火车站，正要回来。他们行至大桥和纪念碑之间的某个地方，杰里看到两匹身强力壮的马正拉着酿酒商的一辆空货车。车夫用皮鞭重重地抽打他的马。车很轻，马开始狂飙起来，那个人对马儿失去了控制。当时街上车水马龙，一个年轻女孩被撞倒，马车碾了过去，接下来他们朝杰里的马车撞过来，杰里的马车被掀翻在地，两个轮子都被撞掉了。上尉被拖倒在地，车辕裂成了碎片，其中一个碎片扎进了他的肋部。杰里也被摔倒在地，只是受了点儿擦伤。谁也说不清上尉是怎么脱离危险的，他总是说这是一个奇迹。人们扶起可怜的上尉时，才发现他遭到了碰撞，身负重伤。杰里慢慢地把他牵回了家，鲜血从他的肋部和肩膀滴下来，浸透了雪白的皮毛，真是一幅凄惨景象。原来那个酿酒商驾车时已喝得酩酊大醉，他因此受到了处罚，不得不赔偿了我们主人的损失。但是，没有一个人赔偿可怜的上尉的损失。

马医和杰里竭尽所能缓解他的痛苦，让他舒适。马车不得不修理，所以我好几天都没有出去，杰里没有赚一分钱。事后，我们第一次来到车站时，老板格兰特过来听听上尉的情况。

“他永远也恢复不过来了，”杰里说，“至少干不成我这活儿了，马医今天早上这样说。他说这马儿可以干驮运东西这类活儿。这让我非常生气。驮运，真的！我见过伦敦附近干这活儿的那些马的惨景。我唯一的希望就是所有的酒鬼都能被关进疯人院，而不是允许他们冲撞清醒的人。如果他们摔断自己的骨头，撞碎自己的马车，弄残自己的马，那就是他们自己的事儿，我们不会管，而在我看来，总是无辜者受苦。然后，他们谈什么赔偿！你不可能赔偿。除了失去了一匹像老朋友一样的好马之外，还有种种问题、烦恼和时间损失——说什么补偿，那都是无稽之谈！如果我要在无底深渊里再看到有一个什么魔鬼的话，那就是酒鬼。”

“我说，杰里，”老板说，“你可说到了我的痛处了，你知道，我没有你这样好，这对我来说更丢人。我真希望我能戒酒。”

“那么，”杰里说，“你为什么不戒酒，老板？你这么好的一个人，不应该成为这种东西的奴隶。”

“杰里，我是一个大傻瓜，我试过一次，戒了两天，但是我想我会死的。你是怎么做的？”

“为了戒酒，我也努力了好几周，你明白我从来没有真正醉过，但是我发现我不能主宰自己，酒瘾上来时，真难拒绝。我明白，我们其中一个必须服输——酒鬼或杰里·巴克，我说不应该是杰里·巴克，上帝在帮我。然而，这是一种挣扎，我需要尽可能得到所有帮助，因为直到我设法戒酒时才知道这习惯是多么根深蒂固。不过，波莉煞费苦心，我才会有好食物，而当酒瘾上来时，我常常喝咖啡或吃些薄荷，要么看点儿书，这对我是一种帮助。我不得不一遍遍地对自己说：‘戒酒，否则你就会失去灵魂！戒酒，否则你会伤波莉的心！’感谢上帝，感谢我的爱妻，我挣脱了枷锁，现在我已经十年没有沾过一滴酒了，也从来没有想过。”

“我有很大决心去试，”格兰特说，“因为不能主宰自己的人非常可怜。”

“做吧，老板，做吧，你绝不会后悔，如果我们车队里的一些可怜家伙看到你也可以不喝酒，那将会对他们有多大帮助啊！我知道，如果可能的话，有两三个人就会不想去酒馆。”

起初，上尉好像做得不错，但他是一匹老态龙钟的马儿，拉这么久的出租车仅仅是缘于他极好的体质和杰里的照顾，现在他完全垮了。马医说，如果他能够康复的话，足可以卖几英镑。但是，杰里说，不！把一个可靠的老仆人卖掉，让他辛劳、痛苦，得到的几英镑会腐蚀他所有剩下的钱。杰里认为，他对这个老伙计能做的最仁慈的事儿，就是将一颗子弹坚定地射进他的脑袋，这样他就再也不受罪了，因为他不知道到哪儿去找一个善良的主人让他度过最后的日子。

作出这个决定后的第二天，哈里把我牵到铁匠铺做了几个新脚掌，等我回来时，上尉已经去了。我和家人都难过极了。

现在，杰里不得不物色另一匹马，很快他就从一个在贵族马厩当马夫副手的人那儿得知了一匹马的信息。他是一匹年轻、珍贵的马儿，但是，他曾经逃跑，撞上了另一辆马车，把主人摔了出去，自己也被划伤了，还败坏了自己的名声，不适合再待在一位绅士的马厩里了。马夫正奉命四处打听，尽可能把他卖个好人家。

杰里说：“只要一匹马不凶恶，不难驾驭，我就有很高的兴致。”

“他没有一点儿恶习，”那个人说，“他的嘴也很嫩，我自己认为这也是事故发生的原因。你看他刚被剪过毛，天气糟糕，他也没有得到足够的训练，所以他一出去，就像气球一样充满弹性。我们的老板——我是说我们的马夫——给他上马具时尽可能拉得很紧，还要加上颌缰、勒马缰绳和一个尖尖的马勒，而且那些缰绳是套在底杆上的。我相信，就是这把这匹嘴嫩、浑身是劲的马逼疯的。”

“很有可能。我会来看他的。”杰里说。

第二天，“急性子”——这就是他的名字——来到了家里，他是一匹棕色骏马，才五岁，身上没有一根白毛，像上尉一样高，脑袋非常好看。我非常友好地跟他打招呼，但是没有问他任何问题。第一天夜里，他非常不安，没有躺下，而是不停地绕着圈子猛拽缰绳，用脑袋撞马槽，吵得我难以入睡。然而，第二天，他拉了五六个小时车后，进来时安安静静、规规矩矩。杰里拍着他，跟他说了好多话，他们很快就相互了解了。杰里说，只要配上舒服的嚼子、派上好多活儿，他就会温顺得像羊羔一样。使人人都遭殃的风才是恶风，因为如果他的贵族主人丢失了一百基尼的最爱，车夫却倾其所有地从中得到了一匹好马。

急性子觉得拉车大大掉价，而且讨厌站在那儿排队。但是，一周过完时，他向我承认说，嘴巴舒适、脑袋自由是极大的补偿，毕竟，这活儿不比把脑袋和尾巴一起拴在马鞍上那样掉价。事实上，他过得不错，杰里也非常喜欢他。

第四十五章　杰里的新年

对一些人来说，圣诞节和新年都是非常快乐的时光。但是，对车夫和他们的马来说，尽管那是旺季，但那绝不是什么节日。有那么多宴会、舞会，还有好多娱乐场所开张，所以他们工作辛苦，经常干到很晚。有时，车夫和马不得不在雨天或严寒中等好几个小时，冻得浑身哆嗦，而里面的人却在随着音乐翩翩起舞。我不知道那些美丽的女士是否想过在驾驶座上等候的疲惫车夫，是否想过那匹一直忍耐着站在那儿，冻得腿都僵硬的马儿。

我现在大多在晚上干活，因为我完全习惯了久站，杰里也更担心急性子感冒。圣诞那一周，我们拉了好多夜活儿。杰里咳嗽得厉害，无论我们干到多晚，波莉都会坐在那儿等他，提着灯笼出来迎接他，一副焦虑不安的样子。

新年之夜，我们不得不把两位先生送到伦敦西区广场的一座房子。九点钟，我们把他们送到，奉命十一点再来接他们。“但是，”有个人说，“因为这是一个牌局，所以你们可能得等几分钟，可不要迟到啊。”

十一点的钟声敲响时，我们站在了门口，因为杰里一向准时。时钟十五分钟报一次时——一刻钟、两刻钟、三刻钟，然后十二点的钟声敲响了，门却还没有开。

风变化不定，白天狂风暴雨，而现在却下起了刺骨猛烈的雨夹雪，好像从四面八方袭来。天气很冷，我们没有任何遮挡。杰里下了车，过来把我的一块布往脖子上拉了一点儿，随后，他来回转了一两圈，跺着脚，接下来，他开始敲打自己的胳膊，但是这样却使他咳嗽了起来。于是，他打开车门，坐在底板上，两只脚放在人行道上，总算有了一点儿遮挡。时钟还是每隔十五分钟鸣响一次，却没有人来。十二点半时，他按了门铃，问仆人那天夜里还要不要他的车。

“噢！要，肯定要你的车，”那个人说，“你不能走，很快就结束了。”杰里又坐下来，他的声音非常嘶哑，我几乎听不见。

一点十五分，门开了，两位先生走了出来。他们一句话没说就坐上了车，告诉杰里往哪儿走，差不多有两英里。我的腿都冻木了，我还以为自己会摔跤的。这两个人下车时，没有对让我们久等表示道歉，而是对杰里的收费生气。不过，杰里从来不向别人多收费，也绝不少收，所以他们必须得支付让我们等那两个小时十五分钟的等时费，那对杰里来说可是辛苦钱。

我们终于回到了家。他简直说不出话来，咳嗽得特别厉害。波莉没有问任何问题，而是打开门，为他举着灯笼。

“我不能做点儿什么吗？”她说。

“能，给杰克弄点暖和的东西，然后给我煮些粥。”

这是他声音嘶哑低声说出来的，他几乎都喘不过气来了。而他还是照常给我擦身子，甚至还去干草棚多抱了一捆稻草让我睡觉。波莉给我端来了暖呼呼的饲料，让我感到很舒服，然后他们就锁上了门。

第二天早上，很晚才有人来，当时只有哈里。他给我们刷身子，喂我们吃的，清扫畜栏，然后又把稻草放了回去，就像是礼拜天一样。他一声不吭，既不吹口哨，也不唱歌。中午时分，他又来了，喂我们吃喝。这次是波莉跟他一起来的，她在痛哭，我可以从他们的对话中推测出杰里病情严重，医生说他的病非常严重。就这样，过了两天，家里麻烦重重。我们只看到哈里，有时会见到多莉。我想，她是来陪伴哈里的，因为波莉总是陪着杰里，而杰里必须静养。

第三天，哈里在马厩里时，外面传来了敲门声，格兰特老板走了进来。

“孩子，我不想进屋，”他说，“但是，我想知道你的父亲怎么样了。”

“他很糟，”哈里说，“糟得不能再糟了。他们称这病是‘支气管炎’，医生认为今晚是好转与否的一个坎儿。”

“真不幸，太不幸了，”格兰特摇了摇头说，“我知道上周就有两个人死于这种病。这个病会立马夺命。但是，哪儿有生命，哪儿就有希望，所以你必须振作精神。”

“是的，”哈里马上说道，“医生说，我的父亲比大多数人运气好，因为他不曾饮酒。医生说昨天他发那么高的烧，如果曾喝过酒的话，他就会像一张纸一样被烧掉。但是，我相信他一定会挺过去的。你不觉得他会挺过去吗，格兰特先生？”

老板一脸迷惑。

“如果有任何‘吉人天相’的说法，我相信他一定会的，我的孩子。他是我认识的最好的人。明天一早我再来看看。”

第二天一早，他就来了。

“怎么样？”他说。

“父亲好些了，”哈里说，“妈妈希望他会挺过去。”

“感谢上帝！”老板说，“现在你们必须为他保暖，让他心情轻松，这会使我想起那些马。你看这一周杰克待在暖烘烘的马厩里反而更好，你可以轻松地带他到街上来回走走、伸伸腿。但是，这匹小马，如果他不干活的话，很快就会完蛋的，可以说，会有你受的，当他真要出去干活时，就会出事。”

“现在就是这样，”哈里说，“我已经给他减少谷物了，但他还是精神抖擞，我不知道该怎么对付他。”

“正是这样，”格兰特说，“听着，告诉你的妈妈，看她是否同意我每天来看他，直到一切安顿好为止，然后让他拉一段时间车，无论他赚多少，我都会给你的妈妈一半，这样可以贴补马饲料的费用。我知道你的爸爸参加了一个出色的俱乐部，而俱乐部不会养马，这段时间马儿会无所事事。我中午会来，到时候听听你的妈妈怎么说。”还没等哈里感谢，他就走了。

中午，我想他去见了波莉，因为他和哈里一起走进马厩，给急性子戴上马具，把他牵了出去。

他来看过急性子有一周多时间。当哈里感谢他或说起他的恩情时，他一笑置之，说那都是他的运气好，因为他的马正需要休息一小段时间，否则他们还休息不了呢。

尽管杰里持续好转，但是医生说如果他想活到老年，就绝不能再干拉车的活儿了。孩子们一起商量过多次爸爸妈妈将来做什么，他们可以怎么帮忙赚钱。

一天下午，急性子被牵了进来，浑身又湿又脏。

“街上净是烂泥，”老板说，“我的孩子，让他清洁干爽一下，这会让你暖和起来的。”

“好的，老板，”哈里说，“我会让他清洁干爽的。你知道我受过父亲的训练。”

“我希望所有的男孩子都像你一样受过训练。”老板说。

当哈里正用海绵擦去急性子身上和腿上的泥浆时，多莉走了进来，看上去心事重重。

“谁住在菲尔斯托，哈里？妈妈收到了一封菲尔斯托的来信，她好像非常高兴，拿着跑上楼给父亲看。”

“你不知道？啊，那是福勒夫人住地的名字——是妈妈以前的女主人，你知道——就是爸爸去年夏天遇见的那位女士，她还分别给了你和我五先令。”

“噢！是福勒夫人。我当然知道她所有的一切。我想知道她给妈妈写的是什么。”

“妈妈上周给她写了信，”哈里说，“你知道她对爸爸说过，如果他不想再拉车，就要告诉她。我不知道她说了什么。跑去看看，多莉。”

哈里像老马夫那样唰唰唰地擦洗着急性子！几分钟后，多莉就蹦跳着走进了马厩。

“噢！哈里，这可是再美不过的事儿了。福勒夫人说我们都可以去跟她做邻居。她有一套农舍空着，正适合我们住，有花园，有鸡舍，有苹果树，应有尽有！她的马车夫春天就要走了，到时候她想要爸爸接替他。周围都是好人家，你可以在他们的花园或马厩里找个活儿，要么当个小听差。那儿也有适合我的好学校。妈妈一会儿哭一会儿笑，爸爸看上去也很高兴！”

“这真是少有的高兴事儿，”哈里说，“我应该说这正合适，这对爸爸妈妈都合适。但是，我不想穿着双排扣紧身衣当小听差。我要当马夫或园丁。”

杰里身体一好，他们就马上决定搬到乡下，马车和马要尽快卖掉。

对我来说，这是一个不幸的消息，因为我现在不再年轻了，也不能指望自己的状况有任何改善。自从离开伯特维克庄园以来，我跟亲爱的主人杰里在一起再开心不过了。但是，拉了三年出租车，即使条件再好，也会筋疲力尽。我觉得自己不再是以前的那匹马了。

格兰特马上说他想要急性子，车站上会有人买我，但是，杰里说我不应该再跟什么人去拉马车，格兰特答应为我找一个舒适的地方。

离别的日子到了。杰里还不能出门，新年之夜过后，我就从来没有见过他。波莉和孩子们来向我告别。“可怜的老杰克！亲爱的老杰克！我真希望我们能带你一起走。”说着，她把一只手放在我的鬃毛上，脸贴近我的脖子，亲了亲我。多莉呜呜哭着也亲了亲我。哈里抚摸了我好一阵子，一言不发，看上去非常伤心。就这样我被带去了新的地方。

第四十六章　杰克斯和女士

我被卖给了一个粮食贩子兼面包师，杰里认识他。杰里觉得我跟他在一起应该吃得好，活儿也公道。最初他说的完全没错，如果我的主人总是在家里的话，我想我不会超负荷工作，但是有一个工头对每匹马都总是催赶，常常在我装满货物时还下令再装点儿别的东西。我的车夫名叫杰克斯，他经常说我不应该拉那么多，而那个工头却总是压制他：“一次能干完的事儿，就不用分两次去干。他就喜欢往前赶。”

杰克斯像其他车夫一样总是拉起马缰，这样我就无法拉得轻松了。到那儿三四个月后，我发现干活会让我筋疲力尽。

一天，我拉的东西比往常更多，部分路段是陡坡。我用尽全力，却还是上不去，不得不走走停停。这让我的车夫感到不快，他狠狠地抽了一鞭。“快走，你这懒家伙，”他说，“否则我就收拾你。”

我又开始拉起了重负，又向前挣扎了几码远，鞭子又抽了下来，我又向前挣扎。大车的鞭子抽在身上火辣辣的疼，我的心像可怜的肋部一样疼痛难忍。我竭尽全力，还是受到这样的惩罚和虐待，这真让我伤心啊。他要第三次残忍地鞭打我，这时一位女士快步走到他的身边，用甜美、诚恳的声音说道：

“噢！请不要再打你这匹好马了，我相信他是全力以赴，这条路很陡，我相信他是竭尽全力了。”

“如果他竭尽全力还不能把这货物拉上去，那他就必须尽更大的努力，夫人，我就知道这些。”杰克斯说。

“可这不是重负吗？”她说。

“是的，是的，太重了，”他说，“可那不是我的过错。我们正要出发时，工头过来了，他为了省事，多装了三英担，所以我必须尽可能继续做好。”

他又要举起鞭子，这时那位女士说道：

“请住手！我想，如果你愿意的话，我可以帮你。”

那个人放声大笑。

“你明白，”她说，“你并没有给他一个公平的机会。他被马缰牵制着脑袋，用不上全力，如果你取掉马缰，我相信他就会做得更好——请试试吧。”她循循善诱地说，“如果你愿意试试，我会非常开心的。”

“好，好，”杰克斯短促地笑了一下说，“能让一位女士开心，当然做什么都行。你想把缰绳放下多长，夫人？”

“完全放下，把他的头完全放开。”

缰绳取掉后，我立刻把脑袋低到了膝盖的位置。这真舒服啊！随后，我上下摇晃了好几次，想摆脱脖子的疼痛僵硬感。

“可怜的家伙！你要的就是这个。”她一边用温柔的手轻轻拍我和抚摸我，一边说道，“现在，如果你能对他和声细语，领他向前，我相信他就能做得更好。”

杰克斯牵住了缰绳：“快点儿，小黑。”我低下头，把我全身的重量都压在了马轭上，我不遗余力。货车继续前进，我稳健地把它拉上了坡，然后停下来歇了口气。

那位女士顺着人行道向前走，此刻穿过去，走到了大路上。她抚摸和轻拍我的脖子，我已经很久没有被人拍过了。

“你明白，你给他机会，他就会心甘情愿。我相信他是一匹脾气不错的马，而且我敢说他以前有过较好的日子。你不要再给他上缰绳了，好吗？”因为他正要按照老方法套上缰绳。

“好吧，夫人，我无法否认，是放开他的脑袋助他爬上了坡，下次我会记住的，谢谢你，夫人。但是，如果他不戴导向马缰出去，我就会成为所有车夫的笑柄，你明白，这是时尚。”

她说：“不跟随坏时尚，而是引导好风尚，不是更好吗？现在，好多先生都不用导向马缰了。我们的拉车马已经十五年没有戴过了，干起活来要比那些戴导向马缰的马轻松好多。此外，”她非常认真地补充说，“如果我们没有很好的理由，就无权摧残上帝创造的任何生灵。我们称他们是不会说话的动物，他们就是这样，因为他们不能把自己的感受告诉我们，但是他们并没有因不会说话而减少痛苦。不过，我现在不能耽误你了。谢谢你在这匹好马身上试用了我的方法，我相信你会发现这远比鞭子要好。再见。”说完，她又轻轻地拍了拍我，脚步轻快地穿过了小路，我再也没有见到过她。

“那是一位真正的女士，我敢肯定，”杰克斯自言自语说，“她说话彬彬有礼，就像我是绅士一样。无论如何，我要上坡时会尝试她的方法。”我必须为他说一句公道话，他让我的缰绳后退了好几个孔眼，之后要上坡的话，也总是让我的头活动自如。不过，负重还在继续。尽管吃得好、休息得好可以让你工作时有体力，但是没有一匹马受得了超载。我很快就因为这个彻底垮了，主人买了一匹比较年轻的马接替我。我不妨在这儿提一下这段时间另一个让我受苦的原因。尽管我听同伴们说起过，但是从来没有亲历过这种不幸：这是一个光线糟糕的马厩，后面只有一扇很小的窗户，结果畜栏几乎都是黑黢黢的。

除了让我精神压抑之外，这也大大地损害了我的视力，当我突然从黑暗中被牵到耀眼的阳光下时，我的眼睛生疼生疼的。好几次我都绊在了门槛上，几乎看不清自己要去哪儿。

我相信，如果在那儿待很久的话，我早就变得半盲了。那将会是极大的不幸，因为我听人说过赶一匹全瞎的马要比赶一匹视力不佳的马安全，因为视力不佳常常会使他们变得非常胆怯。然而，我躲过了一劫，视力上没有受到持久的伤害。我被卖给了一个大马车主。

第四十七章　艰难岁月

我永远忘不了自己的新主人，他有一双黑眼睛、一只鹰钩鼻、一口像斗牛犬那样的牙齿，他的声音就像车轮碾过砾石发出的摩擦声一样刺耳。他名叫尼古拉斯·斯金纳，我相信他就是可怜的“破衣萨姆”的车老板。

我听人说过眼见为实，而我应该说是身受为实，因为尽管我以前见过好多，但是直到现在，我才知道出租车役马的生活是多么悲惨。

斯金纳有一批低级马车和一批低级车夫，他对那些人非常苛刻，那些人对马也非常苛刻。在这个地方，我们没有礼拜天可以休息，当时正是酷热的夏天。

礼拜天早上，有时会有一群放荡不羁的人租一天马车，四个人坐在里面，另一个人和车夫坐在一起，我必须得把他们送到十几英里外的乡下，然后再返回来。无论上坡路多么陡峭，无论天气多么炎热，他们没有人会下车走上坡去——除非车夫担心我实在应付不了。有时我非常燥热和疲惫，简直连饭都不想碰。我是多么想念以前热天杰里星期六夜里给我们的加了硝石的美味的糠糊糊啊，那常常会让我们凉快下来，浑身舒服。随后，我们有两个晚上和一个白天的连续休息，星期一早上我们就像返老还童似的精神抖擞。但是，这儿没有休息，我的车夫和他的主人一样冷酷无情。他有一根无情的鞭子，鞭梢上有一个东西非常锋利，有时会把我抽出血来，他甚至会抽打我的肚子，还会劈头盖脸地打我。这样的侮辱让我伤心极了，我却仍然竭尽全力，从不退却，因为正如可怜的姜姐所说：无济于事，人最强大。

我的生活现在是绝对的不幸，我真希望自己能像姜姐一样在干活时倒地身亡，脱离苦海。有一天，我这个愿望差点儿变成现实。

早上八点，我到出租车站。我拉了好几趟乘客，然后要送一个乘客去火车站。一列长长的火车就要开进来了，所以我的车夫停在站外的马车后面，想碰碰运气，在返程路上捎个客人。那是一辆满载乘客的火车，所有的马车很快就都有人坐了，而我们的车也受到了召唤。那是一行四人：一个大声嚷嚷、咋咋呼呼的男人带着一位女士、一个小男孩和一个年轻姑娘，还有一大堆行李。女士和小男孩坐进了马车，当男人吩咐抬行李时，年轻姑娘走过来看着我。

“爸爸，”她说，“我肯定这匹可怜的马儿拉我们和所有行李跑不了那么远，他有气无力、疲惫不堪。请看看他！”

“噢！小姐，他没事儿，”我的车夫说，“他够壮的。”

那个搬运一些重箱子的搬运工向那位先生建议，行李这么多，他要不要再叫一辆车。

“你的马能不能拉？”那个咋咋呼呼的男人问道。

“噢！他能做好。把箱子搬上来吧，搬运工，再多些他也能拉。”他帮着拖上来一只沉甸甸的箱子，我感觉到弹簧都压了下去。

“爸爸，爸爸，请再叫一辆车吧，”年轻姑娘用恳求的语气说道，“我相信我们错了，我相信这很残忍。”

“胡说，格蕾丝，马上进去，不要这样大惊小怪。如果生意人雇车之前都要检查一下拉出租车的马，那就太糟了——那个人肯定懂行。得了，进来吧，住嘴！”

我的友善的朋友只好服从，箱子一个接一个地被拖上来，放在车顶或车夫身边。最后一切就绪，他像往常一样猛拉缰绳，挥鞭驶出了车站。

车子很沉，从早上起，我既没有吃过东西，也没有休息过，但我还是不顾残酷和不公，像往常一样竭尽全力。

我一路走得还算顺利，直至我们来到路德门山。然而，车子太沉了，我自己也筋疲力尽了。我在缰绳和皮鞭的不断驱赶下挣扎前进，霎时间——我说不清是怎么回事——我的蹄子在身下一滑，我重重地侧翻在地，我摔得猛，摔得狠，仿佛把我所有的气息都摔了出去。我躺在那儿，一动不动，事实上，我无力动弹，我想我现在要死了。我听到自己周围一片混乱，有响亮愤怒的声音，有卸行李的声音，但是这都像做梦一样。我想我听到了那个甜美、怜悯的声音说：“噢！那匹可怜的马儿！这都是我们的过错。”有人走过来，解开我笼头上的喉带，松开紧绑马轭的挽绳。有人说：“他死了，他再也起不来了。”随后，我听到一个警察在下令，但是我睁不开眼睛，只能偶尔喘口气。一些冷水浇在了我的头上，一些兴奋剂灌进了我的嘴里，一些东西盖在了我的身上。我说不清在那儿躺了多久，不过，我发现自己又起死回生了。一个声音和蔼的男人拍着我，鼓励我站起来。他又灌了我一些兴奋剂，我努力了一两次之后，终于摇摇晃晃地站了起来，然后被轻轻地牵到了附近的马厩。到了这儿，我被安排进了一个铺好干草的畜栏里，有人给我送来了热粥，我感激地喝了。

晚上，我恢复到了足以被牵回斯金纳的马厩的程度，我想他们为我尽力了。第二天早上，斯金纳带着马医来看我。他非常仔细地给我检查了一遍，说道：

“这是过劳症，而不是患病。如果你能让他放养六个月，他就还能再干活，但是，现在他身上连一点儿力气也没有了。”

“那他肯定就完了，”斯金纳说，“我没有什么牧场来养病马——他可能好转，也可能好转不了，我的生意容不下那种事儿。我的办法是，只要他们能走，就让他们干活，最后把他们卖给屠宰场或别的地方换钱。”

“如果他患气喘，”马医说，“你最好立即把他杀了，但他现在不是。再过十来天有一个马匹拍卖会，如果你让他休息，给他吃的，他就可以恢复精神，至少你可以拿到比他的皮囊高的价钱。”

听了这个建议，我想斯金纳有些不情愿地下令，要给我好吃的，好好照顾我。让我高兴的是，那个马夫执行命令比主人下令要心甘情愿得多。十天的彻底休息，大量好吃的燕麦、干草和里面拌有煮熟的亚麻籽的糠糊糊，比其他任何东西都更能让我恢复状态，那些亚麻籽糠糊糊香喷喷的，我开始想，毕竟，活着要比死了好。事发后的第十二天，我被牵到了离伦敦城几英里的拍卖会上。我觉得，对我目前处境的任何改变都一定会是好转，所以我抬起头来，希望有最好的结果。

第四十八章　大好人农场主和孙子威利

在这次拍卖会上，我发现自己当然是跟那些衰老的马在一起——有的瘸了，有的得了气喘，有的老了，有的我想开枪打死会更受其欢迎。

买家，还有卖家，他们中的好多人看上去境况并不比他们正在为其讨价还价的可怜牲口好多少。都是一些贫穷的老男人，他们想花几英镑买一匹马或马驹来帮他们拉一些小木头或煤车。有些贫穷的男人想把一匹衰老的马卖两三个英镑，这比把他打死损失要小。看上去有些人好像已经完全让贫困和艰难岁月变得铁石心肠。不过，还有些人我愿意用尽最后的力气去效劳，尽管他们贫困，衣衫褴褛，但是他们友好、人道，他们的声音让我信任。其中有一位走路摇摇晃晃的老人，他非常喜欢我，我也非常喜欢他，但是我不够强壮——那是焦虑一刻啊！我注意到从集市好马区走过来一个男人，看上去这个人像是绅士模样的农场主，身边带着一个小男孩，他后背宽阔，肩膀浑圆，脸庞和蔼红润，头戴一顶宽边帽。他来到我和同伴们的身边时，站在那儿一动不动，用同情的目光来回打量着我们。我看到他的目光落在我的身上，我还有不错的鬃毛和尾巴，这为我的外貌增添了光彩。我竖起耳朵，看着他。

“威利，这儿有一匹马，他有过比较美好的日子。”

“可怜的老家伙！”男孩子说，“爷爷，你觉得他拉过马车吗？”

“噢，是的！我的孩子，”农场主又凑近了些说，“他年轻时可能挺不错。看他的鼻孔和耳朵，看他脖子和肩膀的形状。这匹马饲养得不错。”他伸出一只手，在我的脖子上亲切地拍了一下，我伸出鼻子，对他的善意作出回应，男孩子抚摸着我的脸。

“可怜的老家伙！看到了吧，爷爷，他是多么善解人意！你能不能买下他，就像你对瓢虫那样让他重新焕发青春呢？”

“亲爱的孩子，我不可能让所有的老马都变年轻，再说，瓢虫并不是很老，她是因为身体虚弱，受到了虐待。”

“好吧，爷爷，我不相信这匹马老了，看看他的鬃毛和尾巴。我希望你看看他的嘴巴，然后你就清楚了，尽管他也很瘦，但是他的眼睛并不像一些老马那样凹陷。”

老先生朗声大笑：“上帝保佑这个孩子！他像他的老爷爷一样熟悉马儿。”

“爷爷，请看看他的嘴巴，然后问问价钱，我相信他在我们的牧场上会变年轻的。”

这时，那个把我带来卖的人插话了。

“小先生真懂行。先生，事实上，这匹马只是因为拉车过度被累垮了，他并不老。我听马医说，他的呼吸系统没有损坏，只要放养六个月，他就会恢复精神。过去这十天，我都照顾他，从来没有碰到过像他这样感恩可人的动物，肯定值得一位先生为他付五英镑，让他有一个机会。我保证明年春天他会值二十英镑。”

老人笑出了声，小男孩子急切地抬起头来。

“噢，爷爷，你刚才不是说那匹小公马卖五英镑超出了你的预期吗？如果你真的买下这匹马，你也不会更穷的。”

农场主慢慢地摸着我的腿，我的腿肿胀疲劳，随后，他看了看我的嘴巴：“大概有十三四岁了吧，请让他小跑一下，好吗？”

我弓起可怜的瘦脖子，微微抬起尾巴，尽可能甩出腿，因为它们非常僵硬。

“你为他要的最低价是多少？”我回来后，农场主问。

“五英镑，先生，那是我们主人定的最低价。”

“这是一个投机买卖，”老先生摇摇头说，而与此同时又慢慢地掏出钱包；“完全是投机买卖！你这儿还有别的生意吗？”他一边说，一边数着金币，放进那个人的手里。

“没有，先生。如果你乐意，我可以把马给你牵到客栈。”

“那就牵吧，我现在正准备去那儿。”

他们向前走，我被牵在后面。男孩子抑制不住喜悦之情，老先生好像也很高兴。我在客栈好好吃了一顿，随后就被新主人的一个仆人轻轻地骑回了家。我们走进一个大牧场，其中一个角落有一个棚。

大好人先生就是我恩人的名字，他吩咐我每天早晚都要有干草和燕麦，白天让我在牧场跑跑。“你，威利，”他说，“必须小心照顾他，我把他交给你看管。”

男孩子对这个职责非常自豪，一丝不苟地承担下来。他没有一天不过来看我，有时会把我从别的马中间挑出来，给我一点儿胡萝卜或好吃的东西，要么就在我吃燕麦时站在我身边。他总是带着亲切的话语和爱抚而来，所以我当然渐渐地喜欢上了他。他叫我老朋友，只要他在田地里，我总是来到他的身边，跟着他四处跑。有时他叫来他的爷爷，他的爷爷总是仔细查看我的腿。

“威利，这是我们要注意的一点，”他会说，“而他正在持续好转，我想明年春天我们会看到好转。”

极好的休息、好吃的食物、柔软的草皮和温和的运动，很快就开始对我的健康状况和精神产生了影响。我从母亲那儿继承了良好的体质，小时候从来没有扭伤过，所以我比其他好多干过活的马更有机会养足力气。冬天里，我的腿大大好转，我开始感觉自己又一次完全年轻了。春天来临，三月的一天，大好人先生决定让我试拉一下四轮敞篷轻便马车。我非常高兴，他和威利驾着我走了几英里。我的腿现在不再僵硬了，我干起活来轻松自如。

“威利，他变年轻了，我们现在必须让他干点儿轻活儿，到仲夏时，他就会像瓢虫一样了。他的嘴巴漂亮，步速也不错，好得不能再好了。”

“噢，爷爷，我真高兴你买了他！”

“我也很高兴，我的孩子，不过，他更要感谢你，而不是我。我们现在必须为他物色一个安静优雅、受到重视的地方。”

第四十九章　最后的家

那年的一个夏日，马夫格外仔细地为我清洗梳刷，我觉得肯定有某种新变化即将到来。他修剪了我的距毛和腿毛，用焦油毛刷刷了刷我的蹄子，甚至分开了我的额毛。我觉得马具也擦得格外亮。威利跟爷爷一起坐上马车时好像喜忧参半。

“只要小姐们喜欢他，”老先生说，“她们将适合他，他也会适合她们。我们只能试试。”

出村一两英里地，我们来到了一所漂亮的矮房前，门前是草坪和灌木丛，一条车道通到门口。威利按了门铃，问布罗姆菲尔德小姐或埃伦小姐是否在家。是的，她们在家。于是，我和威利待在一起，大好人先生走进了房子。十分钟左右，他就回来了，后面跟着三位小姐：一位个子高挑、脸色苍白、裹着白色披肩的女士，她靠在一位比较年轻、眼睛乌黑、一脸微笑的女士身上，另一位模样非常端庄的女士是布罗姆菲尔德小姐。她们都过来看我，问了一些问题。那个比较年轻的女士——就是埃伦小姐——非常喜欢我，她说她相信会喜欢我，我有一张如此好看的脸庞。那位个子高挑、脸色苍白的小姐说，如果马以前摔倒过，她乘坐这种马拉的车总会紧张，怕我会再次跌倒，如果那样，她永远也克服不了那种恐惧。

“你们明白，小姐们，”大好人先生说，“好多一流马摔破膝盖不是他们自己的过错，而是因为车夫粗心大意，在我看来，应该说这匹马也一样。当然，我不希望影响你。如果你喜欢，你可以试用他一下，然后你的马夫就会对他有判断了。”

“说到马的事儿，你一向是我们的好顾问，”那位端庄的小姐说，“你的推荐对我大有帮助。如果我的姐姐拉维尼娅不反对的话，我们就会同意试用一下，多谢。”

于是，她们就安排让我第二天过去。

第二天早上，一个模样机灵的年轻人过来牵我。起初，他看上去非常高兴，而当看到我的膝盖时，他用一种失望的声音说道：

“先生，我觉得，你不应该把这样一匹受到损伤的马推荐给女士们。”

“‘品德优美才是真美’，”我的主人说，“你就带他试一下，我相信，你会公平对待他，年轻人。如果他不如你以前骑过的马安全，那就把他送回来。”

我被牵到了新家，安置在一个舒适的马厩里，吃过饭后，就独自待着。第二天，马夫给我清洗脸时，说道：

“这就像黑骏马的那颗星星，他也有这么高。我不知道他如今在哪儿。”

又过了一小会儿，他清洗到了我的脖子上流过血、皮肤上留有一个小疙瘩的地方。他简直吃了一惊，一边开始仔细地查看我，一边自言自语。

“额头上有白星，右侧一只白脚，这个小疙瘩就在那个地方。”随后，看着我的后背中央，“哎呀，还有那一小片白毛，约翰以前经常称它是‘黑骏马的三便士银币’。这一定是黑骏马！啊，黑骏马！黑骏马！你还认识我吗？差点儿害死你的小乔·格林？”说完，他开始对我拍来拍去，好像高兴极了。

我不能说我还认得他，因为现在他长成了英俊的小伙子，黑色的络腮胡，男子汉的声音，但是我相信他认识我，他就是乔·格林，我非常高兴。我把鼻子凑到他的近前，想说我们是朋友。我从来没有见过哪个人这么高兴。

“给你一次公正的试用！我想的确应该这样！我不知道是哪个无赖弄伤了你的膝盖，我的老骏马！你一定是在什么地方受过虐待。好了，好了，就是你现在过得不好，也不会是我的过错了。我真希望约翰·曼利也能在这儿看到你。”

下午，我被套进了一辆低矮的游园车，带到了门口。埃伦小姐打算试我，格林跟她一道去。我很快就发现她是一个好把式，好像对我的步速也很满意。我听到乔在对她说我的事儿，他确信我就是戈登先生家以前的那匹黑骏马。

当我们返回时，其他姐妹都出来打听我表现如何。她把她刚才听到的都告诉了她们，然后说道：

“我肯定会给戈登夫人写信告诉她，她最喜欢的马儿已经来到了我们这儿。她会多么高兴啊！”

之后，我每天都拉车，拉了一周左右，因为我看上去非常安全，所以拉维尼娅小姐最后也坐上小马车冒险出行。之后，她们决定留下我并叫我的原名黑骏马。

如今，我已经在这个快乐的地方住了整整一年。乔是最出色、最善良的马夫。我工作轻松愉快，感觉自己所有的力量和精神全都恢复如初了。前几天，大好人先生对乔说道：

“在你这个地方，他会活到二十岁——说不定更久。”

威利总是得空就跟我说话，把我当成是特别亲密的朋友。小姐们已经承诺绝不会把我卖掉，所以我没有什么害怕的。我的故事到这儿就结束了。我的烦恼都结束了，我无拘无束。我经常在早晨完全清醒之前，想象自己还在伯特维克庄园的果园里，跟老朋友们一起站在那些苹果树下。

20　Joe Green

Joe Green went on very well; he learned quickly, and was so attentive and careful that John began to trust him in many things; but, as I have said, he was small of his age, and it was seldom that he was allowed to exercise either Ginger or me; but it so happened one morning that John was out with Justice in the luggage cart, and the master wanted a note to be taken immediately to a gentleman's house, about three miles distant, and sent his orders for Joe to saddle me and take it; adding the caution that he was to ride steadily.

The note was delivered, and we were quietly returning till we came to the brickfield. Here we saw a cart heavily laden with bricks; the wheels had stuck fast in the stiff mud of some deep ruts, and the carter was shouting and fiogging the two horses unmercifully. Joe pulled up. It was a sad sight. There were the two horses straining and struggling with all their might to drag the cart out, but they could not move it; the sweat streamed from their legs and fianks, their sides heaved, and every muscle was strained, while the man, fiercely pulling at the head of the forehorse, swore and lashed most brutally.

“Hold hard,”said Joe,“don't go on fiogging the horses like that; the wheels are so stuck that they cannot move the cart.”The man took no heed, but went on lashing.

“Stop! pray stop,”said Joe;“I'll help you to lighten the cart; they can't move it now.”

“Mind your own business, you impudent young rascal, and I'll mind mine.”The man was in a towering passion, and the worse for drink, and laid on the whip again. Joe turned my head, and the next moment we were going at a round gallop towards the house of the master brickmaker. I cannot say if John would have approved of our pace, but Joe and I were both of one mind, and so angry that we could not have gone slower.

The house stood close by the roadside. Joe knocked at the door and shouted,“Halloo! Is Mr. Clay at home?”The door was opened, and Mr. Clay himself came out.

“Halloo, young man! you seem in a hurry; any orders from the Squire this morning?”

“No, Mr. Clay, but there's a fellow in your brickyard fiogging two horses to death. I told him to stop, and he wouldn't; I said I'd help him to lighten the cart, and he wouldn't; so I have come to tell you. Pray, sir, go.”Joe's voice shook with excitement.

“Thank ye, my lad,”said the man, running in for his hat; then pausing for a moment,“Will you give evidence of what you saw if I should bring the fellow up before a magistrate?”

“That I will,”said Joe,“and glad too.”The man was gone, and we were on our way home at a smart trot.

“Why, what's the matter with you, Joe? You look angry all over,”said John, as the boy fiung himself from the saddle.

“I am angry all over, I can tell you,”said the boy, and then in hurried, excited words he told all that had happened. Joe was usually such a quiet, gentle little fellow that it was wonderful to see him so roused.

“Right, Joe! you did right, my boy, whether the fellow gets a summons or not. Many folks would have ridden by and said it was not their business to interfere. Now, I say that with cruelty and oppression it is everybody's business to interfere when they see it; you did right, my boy.”

Joe was quite calm by this time, and proud that John approved of him, and he cleaned out my feet, and rubbed me down with a firmer hand than usual.

They were just going home to dinner when the footman came down to the stable to say that Joe was wanted directly in master's private room; there was a man brought up for ill-using horses, and Joe's evidence was wanted. The boy fiushed up to his forehead, and his eyes sparkled.“They shall have it,”said he.

“Put yourself a bit straight,”said John. Joe gave a pull at his necktie and a twitch at his jacket, and was off in a moment. Our master being one of the county magistrates, cases were often brought to him to settle, or say what should be done. In the stable we heard no more for some time, as it was the men's dinner hour, but when Joe came next into the stable I saw he was in high spirits; he gave me a good-natured slap and said,“We won't see such things done, will we, old fellow?”We heard afterwards that he had given his evidence so clearly, and the horses were in such an exhausted state, bearing marks of such brutal usage, that the carter was committed to take his trial, and might possibly be sentenced to two or three months in prison.

It was wonderful what a change had come over Joe. John laughed, and said he had grown an inch taller in that week, and I believe he had. He was just as kind and gentle as before, but there was more purpose and determination in all that he did—as if he had jumped at once from a boy into a man.

译本序

伊·谢·屠格涅夫（1818—1883）是十九世纪俄国杰出作家。他一生四十余年的笔耕生涯中，创作了被誉为“艺术编年史”的六部长篇小说，以及大量的中短篇小说、特写、戏剧、抒情诗、叙事诗、散文诗等各种体裁的作品，并撰写了相当数量的文学评论、回忆录、文学书简，等等，他的创作极大地丰富了俄国文学的宝库，为俄国文学的发展做出了巨大贡献。他的作品也深受世界各国人民的喜爱，如今已成了人类的共同文化遗产。

《猎人笔记》是屠格涅夫的成名作，也是他第一部现实主义力作，在他整个文学创作中占有相当重要的位置。

《猎人笔记》是一部形式独特的特写集。其第一篇特写《霍里和卡利内奇》最初发表于俄国《现代人》杂志1847年第一期。后面的绝大部分篇章也都是陆续发表于同一杂志。直至1852年，作者将先后刊出的二十一篇特写汇编在一起，外加一篇未曾发表的新作《两地主》，以《猎人笔记》为书名，出版了单行本。至1880年，作者又加进了后来创作的三篇《切尔托普哈诺夫的末路》（1872）、《车轱辘响》（1874）、《枯萎了的女人》（1874），共计二十五篇，这便成了作者生前最后的定本。今天我们所据以译出的就是这样的定本。

十九世纪三四十年代，俄国的资本主义经济有了相当程度的发展，俄国农村中农奴制的存在已成了经济发展和社会进步的严重障碍，因此，农奴制的改革问题便被提上了日程，成了当时社会最关注的迫切问题。

屠格涅夫出身于奥廖尔省的一个贵族家庭，他的母亲就是一位残暴的农奴主。他自幼目睹地主阶级的凶残专横，早就产生了对农民悲惨处境的深切同情。上大学后，又受到了进步思想的熏陶，下定决心要与农奴制度作不倦的斗争。1843年他结识了著名批评家别林斯基，在别林斯基的思想影响下，他更坚定了与农奴制作斗争的决心。

《猎人笔记》就是他以反农奴制为中心思想的第一部重要作品，在这里他以敏锐的观察力提供了自己的新题材，发出了自己的呐喊。所以《猎人笔记》一出版，便引起举世瞩目，其影响所至远远超过了文艺界而扩及于整个社会。不同阶级的人们对它做出了不同的反应。它的思想内容立刻激起沙皇政府及统治阶级的惊恐和愤怒。当时沙皇政府中那位颇具政治嗅觉的教育大臣很快便嗅出了书中的反农奴制气息，他向尼古拉一世报告说，此书的大部分篇章都“带有侮辱地主的绝对倾向”，说书中的地主“不是被表现得滑稽可笑，就是常常被弄得极不体面而有损于他们名誉的样子”。随后不久，屠格涅夫便受到了沙皇政府的迫害，被遣返故里监管一年。而在广大人民群众中，此书则受到普遍的欢迎。作家有一次在一个小车站上遇到两位不相识的青年农民，当他们得知他就是《猎人笔记》的作者时，便脱帽向他致敬。其中一位还以“俄罗斯大众的名义”向他表示“敬意和感谢”。进步的文艺界人士更给予此书以很高的评价。尤其是别林斯基，当此书的第一篇特写《霍里和卡利内奇》刚发表时，便立即给了作者以极大的鼓励。别林斯基写信对作家说：你大概还不清楚自己的作品具有何等的价值，你找到了适合自己的创作形式，你走上了出色的道路，你的前程远大。著名作家赫尔岑也称赞此书是一部“反农奴制的控诉书”。

这部作品反农奴制的思想倾向明显地表现在对作为农奴制社会基础的地主阶级的揭露和批判上，表现在对农民命运的深切同情上，表现在对农民的才能和精神世界的热情赞美上。

在揭露和批判地主阶级方面，俄国“自然派”文学奠基者、杰出作家果戈理已率先做出了出色的贡献，他在《死魂灵》中已成功地刻画了从玛尼洛夫到普柳什金等系列的典型地主形象。屠格涅夫继承并发展了果戈理的现实主义文学传统，在《猎人笔记》中以不同于前者的风格，向读者展示了一系列新旧地主的画像。

沙皇政府中那位教育大臣所说的这部作品把地主不是表现得“滑稽可笑”，就是被弄得“极不体面”。从表面粗粗看来，所写的似乎就是如此而已。当你细细地品味书中的内容时，你就可发现，书中所写的地主不仅仅是“滑稽可笑”，他们的行为也远不止是“极不体面”。在农奴制的旧俄国，地主与农民的关系是压迫者与被压迫者、剥削者与被剥削者的关系。在这样的关系中，地主必然会表现出诸如残暴、狠毒、贪婪以及虚伪、愚蠢、空虚、无耻等卑劣的性格和行为。这些正是作家要揭露和批判的对象。不过，作家在这本书中一般没有直接描写地主们凶残狰狞的面孔，没有直接描写他们残酷迫害农民的张牙舞爪的举动，没有直接描写他们最丑恶的表现。在不得不写的地方，也显得特别的小心，主要是通过间接的暗示和启发，让读者通过联想去认识他们卑劣的行为和品性。这固然是为了使作品易于通过书刊审查，更主要的是这位作家对自己的作品持有特殊的审美要求。

地主佩诺奇金是书中刻画得最出色的典型形象。此人受过“良好”教育，颇有“文明”风度。他仪表堂堂，衣着时髦，举止文雅，“为人正派”，“通情达理”。他家里收拾得既干净又舒适，他又饮食讲究，待客热情。但即使这样，客人还是不乐意登门，原因是他家里总是弥漫着可怕的气氛，令人窒息。他对奴仆虽然说话和气，貌似仁慈，但实际上非常冷酷无情，奴仆们偶有伺候不周之处（如侍仆费多尔忘了把他的酒烫热），便会受到严厉惩罚。即便在这种场合，这位老爷仍然显得文质彬彬，既没有表现出怒气冲冲，也没有厉声呵斥，更不用亲自动手打人，他只是坦然地、低声地吩咐旁边的奴仆“去处理一下”就行了。

佩诺奇金还善于利用总管、村长之类爪牙去经管各处的田庄。索夫龙就是他手下一名很得宠的总管，佩诺奇金得意地夸赞这位总管有“治国安邦”之才。索夫龙主管下的什比洛夫村就是老爷的田庄的样板。当老爷光临该村时，村长（总管的儿子）早就在村口迎候。老爷的车子进入村子时，几个坐着大车、一面唱着歌从打谷场上归来的庄稼人一见到老爷前来，马上就闭口不唱了，都摘下了帽子，低下了头。老爷的到来立刻使全村“震惊”了。不仅吓得娃娃哭着朝家里跑，连鸡也吓得直往大门底下钻。要说索夫龙的“管理”才能，确实有两下子：在他的治下，庄稼人都乖乖地按期向东家缴佃租。凡缴不起租的，索夫龙可给代缴，但这庄稼人就得给索夫龙当牛做马，凡欠了一些租的，就得给索夫龙当长工。凡是顶撞过索夫龙的（如安季普），就会被他折腾得家破人亡：几个儿子全被送去当兵，最后连母牛也被牵走，婆娘还挨一顿毒打。若还敢向东家告状（安季普真的告了状），就得彻底完蛋。所以在庄稼人眼里，索夫龙不是人，而是“一条恶狗”。作家无疑是想通过这些情节向社会启示：一个“文明”“有教养的”地主的统治尚且如此，更何况其他地主的统治了。

《两地主》也是一篇讽刺性很强的特写，讲的是两个性格各异的地主。一个姓赫瓦伦斯基，是个退伍军官，好像没有打过仗。此人“心地善良”，但有一些“奇怪的见解和习惯”。他瞧不起无钱无势的贵族，对他们“决不肯平等相待”，至于对那些地位卑微的人，更是“不瞧一眼”，要是需要同这些人说句话，他的声音便变得“像公鹌鹑”。他还没有娶妻，很好色，在路上一看见漂亮的女人，便穷追不舍。他喜欢打牌，但只愿同身份低的人打，这样他可以随意呵斥。等到同省长或其他高官打牌时，他那态度便发生惊人的变化：满脸堆笑，整个人变得像蜜一样甜。他还喜欢抛头露面，在各种庄严的公共场合上表现不凡。他很吝啬，所以竟不愿意接受贵族长这样的荣誉头衔。他大概怕开销大，不合算。

另一个地主是斯捷古诺夫。他自称是“老实人”，办事“按老规矩”，生活中的一切都保持古风。可有时也会赶新潮：为了显示自己不落后于时代，十年前便从莫斯科买来一台脱粒机，可是一直把它锁在棚子里不用，心里便很满足。他待客十分热情，显得是个“好心肠的人”，然而对附近的庄稼人却很不客气：例如近邻的农家有几只鸡跑进了他的花园，他便大喊大叫，不仅把鸡没收，还要抓住那个进来赶鸡回去的小姑娘鞭打一顿。他对奴仆也很残酷无情。他吩咐人鞭挞奴仆，自己坐在凉台上一边喝茶，一边随着鞭打声的节奏喊：“啪啪啪！啪啪！啪啪！”他对那些不够听话的庄稼人就更狠心了，把他们“送去当兵，把他们东一个西一个地拆散开来”，即使这样，他仍感到不解气，因为这样“也根除不了”。他还总结出一套理论：“老爷终究是老爷，庄稼人终究是庄稼人”；“如果老子是贼，儿子必定也是贼”。

在其他一些篇章中还描写了各种类型的地主，如蛮横地抢占他人土地的地主（“猎人”的祖父）；精神空虚、变着法子折磨庄稼人和家仆的科莫夫；穿着像马车夫，表面上对农民客客气气，可又使他们心里害怕的柳博兹沃诺夫；设立庄园“办事处”，通过一批爪牙进行管理的女地主洛斯尼亚科娃，等等。通过对这些地主乖僻行为和习性的描写，自然使读者联想到，在他们主宰下的黑暗王国里，广大的农民会有什么样的命运。

揭示农民的悲惨命运，也是《猎人笔记》的基本主题之一。在屠格涅夫之前，利戈罗维奇的《乡村》和《苦命人安东》对此已做过一定程度的反映。在《猎人笔记》中我们也看到了一些因农奴制的长期压迫而变得极其可怜猥琐的旧式俄罗斯农民。例如《莓泉》中那个斯捷普什卡，他原先曾是地主的家仆，后来被主人完全抛弃了，结果落到“不被当人看”的地步，在人口调查簿上都找不到他的名字，连一份“口粮”也没有。他为了糊口，整天“像蚂蚁似的”到处觅食充饥。《利戈夫村》中绰号“小树枝”（即苏乔克）的库兹马，也是个家仆，在众多的地主手里被转来转去，被主人当一件东西似的任意摆布，先后充当过几个地主家的厨子、车夫、鞋匠、戏子、渔夫等角色，他被扭曲成一个毫无个性、胆小如鼠的可怜虫，以至于在那次涉水过河面临灭顶之灾时，竟不敢伸出手去抓住走在前面的“老爷”的衣襟。还有《两地主》中那个管餐室的仆役瓦夏，受了鞭打之后仍认为主子是个好人，是自己罪有应得，说主子是“不会平白无故惩罚人的”。书中的这类描写，显然是对农奴制的严厉控诉。

然而，书中最引人注目的则是作家从前人没有接触过的角度去发现农民生活的新的方面，那就是去表现农民的才干、创造力、优良品性和丰富的精神世界。

深受别林斯基重视和赞扬的第一篇特写《霍里和卡利内奇》率先为读者提供了两个别开生面的农民形象。一个叫霍里，为人精明、务实，有进取心和自信，他凭自己的勤劳和才智，为自己创建了较为独立富裕的生活。他思想开放，求知欲强，对国外的社会民生都感兴趣。他使人想起了彼得大帝，他也体现出俄罗斯人的精神特征：“相信自己的力量和刚强”，“勇敢地面对未来”。另一个是与他性格迥异的卡利内奇。这是个颇具天赋和丰富内心世界的农民。他不像霍里那样务实，不善于安排个人生活。他是个理想派、浪漫派一类的人，热情而好幻想，爱好大自然。他有多种特长：养蜂、治病、念咒语、识天时，又能弹会唱，还识得字。他很尊重霍里，霍里也很喜欢他，他俩之间洋溢着友谊的“温情”：他有时给霍里献上一束草莓，霍里很欣赏他的歌喉，有时与他一起动情地唱起伤感的歌。有时他们也互相逗趣，友好地争论。这是作家为俄罗斯农民唱出的第一首赞歌，并为全书定下了主旋律。诚然，作家是在向世人宣告：在俄罗斯农民的身上“蕴藏着并成熟着伟大事业的未来的萌芽，伟大的民族发展的萌芽”！

《美丽的梅恰河畔的卡西扬》中的卡西扬也是一个令人喜爱的农民形象。他身体矮小瘦弱，不善于干活，可他充满着生命的活力。他在大自然的怀抱中显得那么灵活、自在、惬意，确像是个大自然的宠儿。他能与各种鸟儿对歌、争鸣，能利用野草为人治病。他头脑聪明，善于思考，平常沉默寡言，但一旦打开话匣子，便滔滔不绝，活像个哲学家，说出一套套绝非一般农民所能说得出的哲理。他爱大自然中的一切生灵，认为一切飞禽走兽都有权享受自己的生命，有权活尽自己的天年。射猎它们是罪过的。他认为人类有自己吃喝的东西，那就是上帝所恩赐的粮食和水，还有祖宗传下来的家禽家畜。他自己却喜欢去捕捉夜莺，但他不是为了杀害它、食用它，而是让它使人们开心快乐。他说鱼是可以捕食的，因为鱼的血“是冷的，不是活的”。他认为做人“必须正直，这是最要紧的”。他感到“人间无公道”，他打算去“寻找真理”！在这里作家是何等热情地赞叹农民的纯真和善良，赞叹他们的道德力量。

《歌手》更像是一首赞歌，它既直接地赞美山沟里的农民歌手雅科夫的艺术天赋，同时也间接地赞美歌手身边那群农人的音乐鉴赏力。作家借猎人之口说，这位农民的歌声“蕴有真挚深沉的情感、青春的气息、力量、甜美，以及一种淡淡的哀愁”，说那歌声里跳跃着“一颗俄罗斯正义的炽热灵魂”，它紧紧地“抓住人们的心，直接扣动俄罗斯人的心弦”。接着作家描写了在场听众的反应作为印证。你看，猎人的心弦被“扣动”了，“涌上了热泪”，酒馆老板娘禁不住“发出低沉的、压抑的哭声”，老成持重的老板感动得“垂下了头”，眨巴眼压制着内心的激动而“扭过头去”，笨瓜“深深动情了，笨相地张着嘴巴，呆呆地站着”，穿破长袍的庄稼人“在角落里低声抽泣”，那沉着冷静的“怪老爷”也“涌出大颗的泪珠”，连雅科夫的竞赛对手包工头都听得“发愣”了。作家似乎在告诉人们：在俄罗斯农民中不仅有艺术天才，更有广大的能够欣赏艺术美的群众。可是作家又在后面描写了一幅令人“很不愉快的”画面，表现了这群农人醉酒后使人懊丧的丑态。这无疑是要发人深思：农奴制下的现实生活无情地扭曲了这些具有才华和美好心灵的农人，他们理应有一种文明的、适合于他们美好心灵的生活！

屠格涅夫还以相当的篇幅描绘了女性的农民，如聪明美丽的渴求爱情和自由而又勇于做自我牺牲的马特廖娜（《彼·彼·卡拉塔叶夫》），纯真、温柔而又痴情的阿库丽娜（《幽会》）。特别是在《枯萎了的女人》中，作家以整章篇幅深情而细腻地刻画了卢克丽娅的形象。卢克丽娅原先是一个能歌善舞、笑声朗朗的美丽姑娘，曾是众多小伙子爱慕的对象。可是她后来不幸地从高台阶上重重摔了下来，由于没有得到适当的治疗而瘫痪，枯萎了，成了一具“活尸首”，虽然她外形的美丧失了，可是她那心灵的美反显得更为动人：她是那样坚强地忍受着病痛的折磨，她竟能以女英雄贞德的精神鼓舞自己。在长期的僵卧状态中仍表现出她对生命、对大自然的热爱；她不去抱怨个人的不幸，很能体谅别人，还惦记着农民兄弟的贫苦。从这些章节中我们已可发现，屠格涅夫确是一位描写女性心灵美的高手，这些描写也为全书增添了不少诗趣。

作家在这部书中也没有忽略对农民后生的刻画。在开篇中他就为读者勾勒了几个小霍里的画像，他们看起来是那样健康、开朗、富于幽默感，它给人以这样的印象：这些小霍里将比老霍里更强，他们更有能力去开拓自己的未来。在《别任草地》中专门描写了五个天真稚气的农家孩子。作家把他们置于暮色笼罩下的草地的背景里，似乎是有意烘托他们的纯真和可爱。然而他们毕竟是些穷孩子，小小年纪便分担着生活的担子，显然他们是没有机会上学，接受科学的教育的，他们受到的是民间的神话传说的熏陶。他们讲的传说故事里都带有恐怖凄凉的色彩，这反映了现实生活的苦痛已在孩子们心灵上留下了阴影，作家对他们倾注了深深的同情。在对勇敢的帕夫卢沙的热情赞叹里，更表现了作者对农民后生的希望和信心。

屠格涅夫的这些人物形象都是以现实生活中人物为原型的，而非凭概念随心所欲“创造”的，他的笔法是“诚挚而公正”的，对地主没有恶意丑化，对农民也没有任意美化，都能准确地抓住这两类人物性格的本质特征。作者也没有就这些人物做出直接的评价，这样的评价是留给读者自己去做的。

再来谈一下书中的风景描写吧。

如果说《猎人笔记》中猎人的形象是贯穿全书各篇的形象，那么，俄罗斯中部的大自然景色也可说是贯穿全书的第二形象，它与前者一样，成为统一全书结构的一个重要因素，同时它也为全书平添了诗情画意。

屠格涅夫极擅长描写自然风景。日月星辰、天空白云、晨光暮霭、雨露风霜等自然现象以及自然界中的湖光山色、树林原野、香花野草、禽兽虫鱼，在他的神奇画笔下无不显得诗趣盎然，情味无穷。难怪托尔斯泰赞叹他的风景描写说：“只要他描上三笔两笔，自然景物就会冒出芬芳。”

风景描写在此书中具有多方面的重要作用：有时是标示故事发生时环境气氛和时间地点，有时烘托或反衬人物的内心世界，有时对情节的发展或结局起着象征作用。比如《幽会》中那位纯真少女阿库丽娜在树林中等待情郎前来幽会的时候，那树林中的景色也显得那么欢快，“到处洒满阳光，透过那些欢腾嬉闹的树叶，看得见浅蓝色的天空，它仿佛在闪闪发亮……空气中弥漫着一种特殊的干爽的新鲜气息，令人心旷神怡，精神焕发”，这显然是少女此时心境的外投。待到那个薄情郎冷淡地抛下她而离去的时候，这位少女异常地伤心、失望，此时林中的景色亦随之大变，那阳光“似乎也变淡了，变冷了”，那些“蜷曲的小树叶急急地飞腾起来”，一只乌鸦在上空“时断时续地啼喊着”……一切都标志着“冬天的凄凉可怕的景象似乎已在悄然逼近了”。由此也可看到，屠格涅夫对自然景色的描写不是冷漠的、纯客观的，而是融入了主观的情感，使自然也染上了浓浓的情感色彩，达到情景的交融。所以书中的景色描写便成了作品的有机组成部分。

当然，在《猎人笔记》中我们不但可看到屠格涅夫长于写景，而且也可看到他在刻画人物性格方面的非凡功力。这里我们不妨顺便稍谈一下他在刻画人物方面的几个特点：

一、善于选择有代表性的细节。例如《总管》中的侍仆费多尔因一点小过失（忘了给主人热酒），主人佩诺奇金便低声下令要惩罚他，这一细节即深刻地暴露了这位地主对待下人的冷酷无情。又如佩诺奇金去他的田庄，全村的庄稼人顿时惶惶不安，连孩子都吓得往屋里跑，母鸡也吓得往大门底下钻。这细节也有力地烘托出这位地主在庄稼人心目中的印象。

二、善于运用鲜明的对比手法。例如在开篇便以两个聪明可爱的农民霍里和卡利内奇同那个平庸可笑的地主波卢特金作了强烈对比，一下给读者留下深刻的印象；在这两个农民之间也进行细致的对比，表现了他们各自的性格特征。在地主与地主之间也作对比（如《两地主》中两个地主的不同表现）。而且在同一人物身上也进行表里的对比，如佩诺奇金温文尔雅的风度与他冷酷残暴内心的对比，等等。

三、善于运用动物形象去比喻人物的性格。例如把那个胆小窝囊、一见到上司便浑身发抖的涅多皮尤斯金比喻成“像一只被抓住的小鸟”；把希格雷县的哈姆莱特那位有心灵创伤的妻子比喻为“被猫抓伤了的可怜的黄雀”，等等。有时干脆把这类比喻直接变成人物的绰号，例如，把那个懦弱渺小的老奴仆库兹马称为“小树枝”（即苏乔克），把那个沉默、孤独而又坚强的护林人福马称为“孤狼”，把那个性格好动而不安分的卡西扬称为“跳蚤”，等等。这些手法使作家在刻画人物性格时节约了大量笔墨，同时又起了画龙点睛的作用。

屠格涅夫又是一位语言大师，他创作中的语言总是显得那么的简洁、明快、清新、优美，读起来确实是一种美的享受。列宁就非常欣赏这位作家的语言，列宁在提到几位俄罗斯语言大师的名字时，首先便提到了他。

屠格涅夫不止一次地表明自己是一个现实主义作家，他把“准确而有力地再现真实”视为自己的“莫大幸福”。托尔斯泰也称赞屠格涅夫创作的最主要特点就是它的“真实性”。读了《猎人笔记》，你就可感到：全书的内容都是俄罗斯生活的真实写照，是地道的俄罗斯的东西，每一篇都散发着俄罗斯泥土的芳香。

但是屠格涅夫并不满足于描写生活的真实。在他看来，“把生活提高到理想”才是艺术家的崇高使命。然而所谓提高不是人为的随便拔高，不是把现实生活加以任意的美化，而是要求作家从现实生活中的理想事物方面去提炼自己的材料。换言之，就是要从生活的散文中看到生活的诗意。法国作家德·沃盖说，屠格涅夫的才华“正好表现于保持现实和理想之间的惊人的匀称，每个细节都停留在现实主义的领域……而整个说来却飘浮在理想的领域”。法国作家莫洛亚更干脆地称屠格涅夫的现实主义为“诗意的现实主义”。我想，用这个词来评价《猎人笔记》的创作风格也是恰如其分的。

霍里和卡利内奇

奥廖尔省人跟卡卢加省人有着气质上的明显差异，这也许会让那些从波尔霍夫县前来日兹德拉县的人大为吃惊。奥廖尔省的庄稼人个头不大，略显驼背，郁郁寡欢，老是愁眉不展。他们住的是窄小的白杨木屋，身服劳役，不事经商，饮食粗劣，穿的是树皮鞋；而卡卢加省的交田租的庄稼人可就大不一样了，他们住的是宽绰的松木房子，个子高高的，神情快活而胆大，脸孔白白净净，做奶油和柏油买卖，逢年过节便穿起长筒靴。奥廖尔省的村庄（我们说的是奥廖尔省的东部）一般都坐落在耕地中间，在那种稀里糊涂变成了污水塘的溪谷边上。除了寥寥几棵随时供人派用场的爆竹柳以及三两棵瘦巴巴的白桦，方圆一俄里内不见树木。房子鳞次栉比，房顶铺的是烂麦秸……卡卢加省的村庄恰好相反，大部分都是林木四绕；房子的间距显得较为宽松，排列得也较为齐整，房顶是用木板盖的，大门锁得严严实实，后院的篱笆也不见东歪西倒，不往外倾斜，不会招那些过往的猪来登门做客……对于猎人来说，卡卢加省也比较称心。过上五年六载，奥廖尔省最后一批森林和茂密的灌木丛将会荡然无存，沼泽地亦将无处可寻；相反，在卡卢加省，几百俄里内林木连绵不绝，沼泽地也占几十俄里，依然有高雅的松鸡在此栖息，和善的大鹬也常常光临，忙忙碌碌的山鹑猛地腾空而起，令射手和猎犬又惊又喜。

我曾以猎人身份去过日兹德拉县，在那边野外遇到了卡卢加省的一位小地主，并跟他混得挺熟。他姓波卢特金，是个猎迷，所以也是个有头有脸的人。说实话，他还是有一些弱点的。比如说吧，凡是省里富裕人家的闺秀，他全求过婚，结果到处遭人拒绝，被逐出门外，因此，他常怀着一颗破碎的心向各个朋友和相识苦诉衷肠，可是照旧把自家果园出产的酸桃子和其他不熟的果子当作礼品奉赠给那些被追求对象的高堂。他对趣闻非常津津乐道，叨咕个没完，尽管波卢特金先生认为自己说的多么情趣盎然，可惜从未赢得人家一笑。他叹赏阿基姆·纳希莫夫[1]的文章和小说《平娜》[2]。他说话结巴；将自家的狗美其名曰“天文学家”。他把“可是”念成“可希”，他家里吃的是法式菜肴，据他家的厨子的理解，烹调这类菜肴的奥秘就在于把各种各样食物的原汁原味来个彻里彻外的改造：肉食一经这位巧手料理，其味便变得像鱼，鱼变得像蘑菇，而通心粉则煮出了火药味；可是放进汤里的胡萝卜又全成了菱形或梯形的玩意儿。不过，撇开这些屈指可数的而又无伤大雅的缺点不谈，波卢特金，如同上边所说，算得上是个有头有脸的人。

我跟波卢特金相识的当天，他便邀我前去他家过夜。

“离我家大概有五俄里地，”他说，“步行去很远；我们先去霍里家吧。”（读者谅必会允许我不照他的口吃方式来转述吧。）

“霍里是什么人？”

“是我家的佃户……他家离这儿挺近的。”

于是我们便前去霍里家。在林子中间的一块经精心清理和整治过的空地上，耸立着霍里的独家宅院。院里有几间松木建造的房子，用篱笆圈在一起；正房前方有一敞棚，是由几根细柱子支撑起来的。我们步入院内。迎接我们的是一个年轻小伙，二十来岁，高高的个子，相貌堂堂。

“喂，费佳！霍里在家吗？”波卢特金先生问他。

“不在，他进城去了，”那小伙答道，一边微笑着，露出一排雪白的牙齿，“吩咐备车吗？”

“对，伙计，备车吧。还给我们拿些格瓦斯来。”

我们进了房子。由洁净的圆木组装的墙壁上没有挂一张苏兹达尔[3]的画；房角处摆着一尊沉甸甸的裹着银服饰的圣像，圣像前燃着一盏神灯；有一张前不久被刮洗得干干净净的椴木桌子；在圆木间的隙缝里，在窗子的边框上，既无机灵的茶婆虫在那里游荡，也无疑虑重重的蟑螂在那里藏身。那个年轻小伙拿着一只盛满爽口格瓦斯的大号白杯子，一大块小麦粉面包和放有十多根腌黄瓜的木盘快捷地出来了。他将这些食品在桌子上通通摆好，然后倚身门上，面露笑容，打量起我们来。我们还没来得及把这些小吃打扫光，台阶前已传来马车的响声。我们起身出来。驾车的是一个十五六岁的孩子，一头鬈发，两腮绯红，他使大劲勒住了那匹肥实的花斑牡马。马车四边围着六个大个子的年轻人，他们彼此很相像，而且都像费佳。“全是霍里的孩子！”波卢特金说。“全是小霍里，”费佳接过话说，他也跟着我们来到台阶上，“还没有到齐呢：波塔普正在林子里，西多尔跟着老爸进城去了……要小心，瓦夏，”他转向驾车的孩子继续说，“尽量跟快点，送的是老爷呢。不过，到了高坡那儿可得留神，悠着点儿。别把车子搞坏了，不能惊扰老爷的肚皮！”旁的几个小霍里听了费佳这句有点越轨的逗趣话都轻轻地笑了。“把天文学家放上车！”波卢特金先生威严地喊了一声。费佳开心地把那只强露笑容的狗举了起来，放到马车底板上。瓦夏松一下缰绳。我们的马车轱辘便滚动了。“这是我们的办事处，”波卢特金忽然指着一所低矮的小平房对我说，“要不要去瞧瞧？“好的。”“目前它已撤了，”他说，一边下了车，“不过还值得一瞧。”说是办事处，不过是两个空房间而已。看守人是个独眼老头，他从后院跑来了。“你好，米尼亚伊奇，”波卢特金先生说，“哪儿有水？”独眼老头跑了开去，不一会儿就拿了一瓶水和两个杯子回来。“尝尝吧，”波卢特金对我说，“我这里的水可是上好的泉水呀。”我们各饮了一杯，这时候老头向我躬身施礼。“喂，看来现在我们可以动身了，”我的这位新朋友说，“在这个办事处里我卖出四俄亩林子给了商人阿利卢耶夫，还算卖了个好价钱。”我们坐进了马车，过了半小时，我们已经抵达主人的宅院了。

“请问，”晚餐时我问波卢特金，“为什么您的这位霍里跟您的其他佃户分开住呢？”

“原因嘛是这样的：他是我的一个挺有头脑的庄稼汉。大概二十五年前吧，他家的房子烧了；于是他前来对先父说：‘尼古拉·库济米奇[4]，请让我搬到您的林子里的沼泽地上住吧。我会给您付高额租金的。’‘你为什么要迁到沼泽地上住呢？’‘我思谋着这样好；只是请您，尼古拉·库济米奇老爷，别派我去干任何活了，而租金嘛，由您来定。’‘一年五十卢布！’‘行。’‘当心，我可不许拖欠！’‘那当然，我不会拖欠的……’就这样他搬到沼泽地住下了。打那时候起，大家都管他叫霍里[5]。”

“那么，他发了吧？”我问。

“发了。如今他付我的租金是一百卢布。我也许还要提价呢。我曾对他说过好几遍这样的话。我说：‘赎身吧，霍里，哎，赎了吧……’可是他这个老滑头硬是咬定赎不起，说是没有钱……这怎么可能呢……”

第二天，我们一喝过茶马上就去打猎了。马车经过林子的时候，波卢特金先生吩咐车夫在一所矮房子旁停一下车，并大喊一声：“卡利内奇！”“就来，老爷，马上来，”院子里传来答话声，“我在系鞋子呢。”我们的马车慢慢地向前赶着；一个四十来岁的汉子在村外赶上了我们，他是位瘦高个子，小脑袋稍稍后仰。这就是卡利内奇。他那张和善的、带点麻斑的黝黑脸孔，我一见就感到喜欢。卡利内奇天天都陪伴老爷去打猎（这是我后来听说的），背着他的袋子，有时还扛着枪，探察鸟儿在何处栖息，打水、采草莓、搭棚子、跟在马车后面跑；离开他，波卢特金真可谓寸步难行。卡利内奇这个人的性格是顶乐呵的，也是顶和顺的，他不断地低声哼唱歌曲，无所思虑地向四处东张西望，说话带点鼻音，微笑的时候便眯起那双浅蓝色的眼睛，不时地捋捋那稀疏的楔形胡子。他走起路来不急不忙，可步子迈得老大，还拄着一根又长又细的拐棍。这一天他跟我聊了好几回，伺候我时不见他低三下四，然而他照料老爷真像照料孩子一般。中午时分，天气酷热不堪，我们不得不找个蔽荫地方，这时候他领我们到他设在林子深处的养蜂房去。卡利内奇给我们打开了那间挂着一捆捆冒着香气的干草的小屋的门，让我们躺在新鲜的干草上，他在自己头上戴了一个袋状的网罩，拿起一把刀子、瓦罐和一块木片，到养蜂房去给我们割蜂蜜。我们喝着掺和泉水的透亮的温蜜汁，在蜜蜂单调的嗡嗡声和树叶的不停的簌簌声中睡着了。一阵清风吹醒了我……我睁开眼睛，看见卡利内奇坐在那扇半开半掩的门的门槛上，用刀在削一柄木勺。我盯着他的脸欣赏了好一阵子，那是一张如傍晚天空一般温和而明朗的脸。波卢特金先生也醒来了。我们没有立即起来。在走了很久的路和一阵酣睡之后，安然不动地躺在干草堆上是颇为惬意的：身体显得既舒坦又疲倦。脸上冒着轻微的热气，甜蜜的困倦使人懒得睁眼。最后我们起来了，又一直闲逛到傍晚。晚餐时我们又谈起了霍里和卡利内奇。“卡利内奇是个善良的庄稼人，”波卢特金对我说，“他又热心又殷勤，可希他没法正经八百地干农活，因为我老拖着他。他天天要陪我去打猎……哪还干得了农活呢，您想想看。”我很同意他的话，接着我们都睡着了。

到了第二天，波卢特金先生要进趟城，是为同邻居皮丘可夫打官司去的，听说那个叫皮丘可夫的邻居抢耕了他的田地，还在这块耕地上殴打了他的一个农妇……我便独自前去打猎，傍晚前拐到了霍里家。一个老头在门口接待了我，他谢顶、矮个、宽肩膀、身体壮实，这就是霍里本人。我怀着好奇心打量了这个霍里。他那面容活像苏格拉底：同样的带点疙瘩的高额门，同样的小眼睛，同样的翘鼻子。我们一同进了屋。上回见过的那个费佳给我端上牛奶和黑面包。霍里在凳子上坐下来，安详地抚摩着他那拳曲的胡子，同我攀谈起来。他显得很自尊，言谈举止慢条斯理，不时地从他那长长的小胡子下露出微笑。

我跟他聊播种，聊收成，聊农家生活……他对我说的话似乎处处认同；只是后来我感到不好意思，我觉得自己说得并非样样恰当……于是情况变得有点令人纳闷。霍里有时谈得难以捉摸，大概是由于谨慎的缘故吧……以下便是我们谈话中的一个例子：

“你说说，霍里，”我对他说，“你为什么不向老爷赎身呢？”

“我要赎身干吗？如今我很了解老爷，也付得起租金……我家老爷人很好。”

“得到自由总是更好些吧。”我说。

霍里斜瞥了我一眼。

“那当然。”他说。

“既然这样，那你为什么不赎身呢？”

霍里摇了摇头。

“老爷，让我拿什么去赎呀？”

“唉，得了，老头……”

“霍里要是成了自由人，”他低声地继续说，好像在自言自语，“那种不留胡子的人[6]，就会来向霍里发号施令了。”

“那你自己也剃掉胡子嘛。”

“胡子算什么？胡子是把草，可以割的。”

“那还说什么呢？”

“看来，霍里干脆去做生意人得了；生意人日子过得好，也可留胡子。”

“你不是已经在做生意了吗？”我问他。

“我只搞点奶油和柏油方面的小买卖……怎么，老爷，要不要备辆马车？”

“你这人嘴好严哪，心里可有主意啦。”我心里想。

“不用，”我大声说，“我不需要马车。明天我要在你家近处转转，如果允许的话，我想在你家干草棚里过一夜。”

“欢迎呀。不过，你在干草棚里睡得踏实吗？我吩咐娘儿们给你铺上床单，放上枕头。喂，娘儿们！”他喊道，一面站起身来，“过来，娘儿们……你，费佳，跟她们一块去。她们都是些饭桶。”

过了一刻钟，费佳提着灯笼领我到干草棚去。我扑倒在干草上，狗蜷缩在我的脚旁；费佳向我道了晚安，门嘎的一响，又砰的一声关上了。我久久没有睡着。一头母牛走近门边，大声地喷了两口气。狗自尊地朝它汪汪地大叫起来；一头猪从棚边走过，沉思地哼哼着；有匹马也在附近某处嚼着干草，打着响鼻……我终于打起盹来。

一大早费佳唤醒了我。这个快活而机灵的小伙子很让我喜欢；据我所见，他也是老霍里的心肝宝贝。他们爷儿俩常常相互逗闷子，亲热极了。老头出来问候了我。不知是因为我在他家过了夜，或是其他什么原因，霍里比昨天对我的态度更亲切多了。

“茶炊为你准备好了，”他微笑着对我说，“我们去喝茶吧。”

我们在桌子旁坐下来。一个壮健的女人，即他的一位儿媳，送上了一罐牛奶。他的儿子们全挨个地来到屋里。

“你有这么一大家子呀！”我对老头说。

“是呀，”他咬了一小块糖，一边说，“对我和我的老伴来说他们看来没有什么好抱怨的。”

“全都跟你住在一起吗？”

“全住在一起。他们自己愿意这样，就这样住了。”

“都娶媳妇了吗？”

“就这个淘气鬼还没有成亲，”他指了指依旧靠在门上的费佳回答我说，“瓦西卡年纪还小，可以再等等。”

“我干吗结婚？”费佳回嘴说，“我这样蛮好。老婆对我有什么用？好跟她吵架，是吗？”

“哼，你呀……我还不知道你！戴上银戒指……想整天跟那班丫头片子胡混……‘得了，真不要脸！’”老头滑稽地模仿那些丫头们说话的口气说，“我可知道你，你这懒虫！”

“老婆有什么好？”

“老婆就是劳力嘛，”霍里严肃地说，“老婆会侍候男人。”

“我要劳力做什么？”

“得了，你就喜欢别人替你白干活。你这种家伙我可知道。”

“既然这样，就给我娶一个吧，啊？怎么啦！你为什么不说话？”

“唉，得了，得了，调皮鬼。你瞧，咱们打扰老爷了。会给你娶的，别担心……老爷，你别生气，孩子还小，不懂规矩。”

费佳摇摇头……

“霍里在家吗？”门外响起一个熟悉的声音，卡利内奇进了屋，手里拿着一束草莓，那是他为自己的朋友霍里采的。老头欢欣地迎接他。我惊奇地瞅了瞅卡利内奇，说真的，我没料到庄稼人也有这种“温情”。

这一天我比平常约晚了四小时才去打猎，随后三天我都住在霍里家里。我的这两位新相识令我颇感兴趣。我不清楚我拿什么博得了他们的信任，他们都无拘无束地跟我聊这聊那。我愉快地听着他们的谈话，并不断观察他们。这两位朋友彼此没什么相似之处。霍里是个正派的、务实的人，有经营管理的头脑，重理性；相反，卡利内奇是属于理想派、浪漫派一类的人，他热情洋溢，好幻想。霍里懂得实际生活，所以他要修建房屋，积蓄钱财，跟主人和其他有权有势的人融洽相处；卡利内奇则是脚穿草鞋走路，凑凑合合度日。霍里养育了一群孩子，有一个对他服服帖帖、团结一心的家庭；卡利内奇也曾有过媳妇，可他惧内，未养得一儿半女。霍里对波卢特金先生其人看得一清二楚；而卡利内奇则很崇拜主人。霍里喜欢卡利内奇，对他时加袒护；卡利内奇也喜欢并尊敬霍里。霍里话语不多，笑颜常开，而心里可颇有主意；卡利内奇很爱说话，但不像机灵的花言巧语者那样，说得像夜莺歌唱一般……不过，卡利内奇很有一些天赋，霍里对此就很赏识；比如说，他会用咒语止血、镇惊、制疯、驱虫；蜜蜂都服他调教，他是很有好手气的。霍里曾当着我的面请他把一匹新买来的马牵进马厩[7]，卡利内奇便认认真真、正经八百地去执行这个多疑的老头的托付。卡利内奇更接近于大自然；而霍里更接近于人和社会。卡利内奇不喜欢深入思考，他盲目相信一切；霍里站得高，以至对人生持有嘲弄的眼光。他见多识广，我从他那里学到不少东西；比如说，我从他口里知道了这样的事，他说，每年夏天，在麦收季节前，常有一辆式样特别的小马车来到各个村庄。车上坐着一个穿长外衫的人，他在销售大镰刀。用现金购买的话，每把卖一卢布二十五戈比至一个半卢布；若是赊账，每把则卖三个卢布纸币至一个银卢布。不用说，所有的庄稼人向他买的时候都要赊账。过不了两三星期，他又来了，是为讨账来的。庄稼人刚割了燕麦，都付得起账；庄稼人与商人一起去了小酒店，在那里付清了赊账。有一些地主思谋着用现金购进镰刀，然后用同一价格赊账给庄稼人；可是庄稼人觉得不过瘾，甚至有些丧气；因为他们失掉了不少乐趣，比如用手指弹弹镰刀，听听声响，把镰刀拿在手里翻来覆去地查看，无数遍地探问那个骗人的商贩子：“喂，伙计，这镰刀不怎么行吧？”在买小镰刀的时候，也会出现同样的把戏。不过不同的是，这样场合往往有女人们掺和进去，有时候弄得那商人不得不动手打人，这样一来反而对女人们有利了。然而，最让女人们吃亏上当的是以下情况。造纸厂的原料采办人员委托那些在一些县里被称为“鹰”的专门人员去收购废布。这种“鹰”从商人手里领到二百卢布左右的纸币，然后就去寻找猎物。可是他和自己因以得名的那种高尚的鸟大不相同，他不是明目张胆地去进攻，相反，这种“鹰”要耍滑头，弄诡计。他把马车停在村子近旁某处丛林里，自己窜到各家的后院或后门，装成过路的人或装成无事闲逛的人。娘儿们凭感觉就猜到他来了，便悄悄地向他跑去。买卖匆匆地就成交了。为了几个铜子，娘儿们不仅把各种不要的破衣烂布卖给“鹰”，而且把丈夫的衬衫和自己的裙子都给卖了。近来娘儿们发现有些交易是挺来钱的，那就是把自家的大麻，尤其是把一些大麻布偷出来，以同样方式卖出去——这样一来，“鹰”们的生意可就一下红火了。可是村里的爷们儿也变聪明了，一觉得可疑，远远一听到“鹰”到来的消息，便立即采取措施，认真防备。说真的，这不可气吗？卖大麻本是他们的事，他们是实实在在地去卖——不是拿到城里去卖，去城里卖得自己运去，而是卖给前来采购的商人，他们由于没有秤，就规定四十把算一普特[8]——可您知道，什么是一把，什么是俄国人的手掌，特别是在他“存心多拿”的时候！我这个阅历浅、对农村生活不“识门道”（如我们奥廖尔省人所说的）的人听了很多这类的故事。不过霍里不是自己一个劲儿去讲，他也问了我许多问题。他听说我到过外国，这大大引起了他的好奇心……卡利内奇的好奇心也不比他的差，可是卡利内奇更感兴趣的是有关大自然、高山、瀑布、非凡的建筑、大城市等的描述；霍里所关心的则是国家和管理方面的问题。他对一切事情都逐个儿进行分析思考：“这种事在他们那儿跟咱们这儿一样，或是不一样？……说说吧，老爷，是怎么回事？……”“啊，天哪，真玄呀！”在我讲述的时候，卡利内奇不时地这样感叹；霍里则默不作声，浓眉紧蹙，只是偶尔说：“这在咱们这儿可能行不通，不过这很好，很得当。”我不能将他的种种提问都向你们转述，也没有必要；但从我们的谈话里，我得出一种信念，读者对它也许怎么也料想不到，这信念就是：彼得大帝主要是表现出俄罗斯人的特性，俄罗斯人的特性正表现于他的革新精神中。俄罗斯人是如此的相信自己的力量和坚强，以至自己受折磨也在所不顾：他们很少迷恋过去，总是大胆地向前看。凡是好的他们便喜欢，合理的他们便吸取，至于它来自何处，他们觉得无所谓。他们那健全的头脑喜欢嘲笑德国人的乏味的理性；但是，用霍里的话说，德国人是挺好奇的人，他准备向他们学习。由于自己处境的特殊性，由于他实际上的独立性，霍里对我谈了许多，这在别的人那里，就像庄稼人所说的，那是用杠杆转不出，用磨也磨不出的。他的确很了解自己的地位。我同霍里聊天时，是头一回听到俄国庄稼人的那种纯朴而深含智慧的言谈。作为一个庄稼人，他的知识是相当渊博的，但是他不会读书识字；而卡利内奇会。“这个鬼家伙识得字，”霍里说，“他养蜂也挺棒，蜂从来不死。”“你让自己的孩子学识字吗？”霍里沉默了一下。“费佳识字。”“其他几个呢？”“其他几个不识。”“为什么呀？”老头置之不答，并换了话题。然而，不管他多么聪明，他也有许多偏见和成见。他打心眼深处就瞧不起女人，他开心的时候就拿她们逗乐，嘲笑她们。他那老伴又老又爱唠叨，整天不下炕，不停地怨这怨那，骂不绝口；儿子们都不搭理她，可是儿媳们对她却怕得要命。难怪俄罗斯小曲中的婆婆这样唱：“你算我什么儿子，算什么成家的人！你不揍老婆，不揍新媳妇……”有一回我打算替那几个儿媳鸣不平，想引起霍里的同情；可是他坦然地反驳我说：“您去管这些……小事何苦呢——让娘儿们吵去好啦……劝解她们反而更糟，也犯不着惹那份麻烦。”有时候这个凶恶的老太婆爬下炕，从穿堂里唤出那只看家狗，她喊道：“来，来，小狗！”接着抡起火钩子照着那狗的瘦脊背直打，或者站在敞棚下朝所有过路的人，如霍里所形容那样，“骂街”。然而，她怕自己的丈夫，他一声令下，她便乖乖地回到她的炕上。可特别有趣的是听卡利内奇与霍里在谈及有关波卢特金先生事时的拌嘴。“你呀，霍里，别当我的面招惹他。”卡利内奇说。“那为什么他不给你置双靴子呢？”霍里反驳说。“哼，靴子……我要靴子干什么？我是庄稼人……”“我也是庄稼人，可是你瞧……”说到这儿，霍里抬起自己的脚，把那双可能是象皮制的靴子给卡利内奇看。“哼，我哪能跟你比呀！”卡利内奇回答说。“哪怕给你点钱买树皮鞋也好嘛：你是老陪他去打猎的呀；也许一天就得一双树皮鞋吧。”“他是给我买树皮鞋钱的。”“可不，去年就赏了你一个十戈比银币。”卡利内奇懊丧地转过脸去，霍里哈哈地大笑起来，这时候他那双小眼睛眯得全看不见了。

卡利内奇唱歌唱得非常动听，他还弹了一会儿三弦琴。霍里听着听着，忽然把头侧向一边，以悲怆的声音与他伴唱起来。霍里特别喜欢《我的命运啊，命运！》这首歌曲。费佳趁机取笑父亲。“老爷子，怎么悲伤起来啦？”而霍里只顾手托脸颊，闭起眼睛，继续悲歌自己的命运……可是在别的时候，没有人比他更勤奋的了，他老是在鼓捣着什么：修修马车，整整篱笆，查查挽具。然而他不大讲究卫生，有一次我提了一下，他回答说：“房子嘛得有些住家的气味。”

“你看，”我反驳他说，“卡利内奇的蜂房里多干净。”

“蜂房若不干净，蜜蜂就不肯待了，老爷。”他叹口气说。

有一次他问我：“你家有世袭领地吗？”“有。”“离这儿远吗？”“约有一百俄里吧。”“那么你是住在自家领地上？”“是的。”“想必常常玩枪打猎吧？”“的确是。”“那挺好；为了身体，多去打打松鸡吧，不过得常换换村长。”

到了第四天傍晚，波卢特金先生派人来接我。跟霍里老头告别，我有点依依不舍。我同卡利内奇一起坐上马车。“再见吧，霍里，祝你健康。”我说……“再见，费佳。”“再见，老爷，再见，别忘了我们。”我们动身了；晚霞刚刚燃红。“明天会是好天气。”我望着明亮的天空说。“不，要下雨啦，”卡利内奇反驳我说，“鸭子在那边使劲拍水，再说，青草散发出浓烈的气味。”我们的马车跑进了丛林。卡利内奇在车夫的座位上颠簸着，低声地哼起歌曲，一面不断地瞧着晚霞……

第二天，我离开了波卢特金先生的好客之家。

[1]阿·纳希莫夫（一七八二——一八一四），俄国诗人。

[2]《平娜》系俄国作家马尔科夫（一八一〇——一八七六）的小说，曾受到别林斯基的严厉批评。

[3]苏兹达尔系弗拉基米尔省的一个县，该县出产简陋的木版画。

[4]波卢特金的父亲的名字和父名。

[5]俄语中“霍里”是“黄鼠狼”的意思。

[6]指官吏、士绅们，当时是不许他们蓄胡子的。

[7]这是旧俄农村中的一种风俗，认为有人有好手气，办事吉利。

[8]俄国的重量单位，相当于16.38公斤。

县城的大夫

秋天的时候，有一回我从很远的野外打猎归来，途中着了凉，病了。我发起烧来，幸好这时候已到了县城，在一家客店住下了。我打发人去请医生。半小时后来了一位县城的大夫。此人个头不大，瘦巴巴的，头发乌黑。他给我开了普通的退烧药，要我贴上芥末膏，挺麻利地把一张五卢布钞票塞进他那翻袖口里，而同时干咳了一声，瞧了瞧旁边，本来想要立即打道回府，不知怎的，跟我聊了起来，于是留了下来。我受着高烧的折磨；我料想夜里会睡不着，巴不得有个人同我侃侃大山。茶端上来了。我的医生便打开了话匣子。他这个人不笨，口齿伶俐，说话颇有风趣。世上有些事好奇怪：你同有的人相处很久，关系也挺融洽，可是你从来不向他披肝沥胆，倾吐心曲；而跟有的人刚刚结识，便视为知己，彼此把心里的全部隐私像忏悔似的掏给对方。我不清楚我是凭什么博得了我这位新朋友的信任，不知出于什么原因，他便把一件相当动人的事，如常言说的，“拿来”说给我听了。现在我就把他讲的事说给我知音的读者听听。我尽量用那位大夫的原话叙述。

“您知不知道，”他开始说了，嗓音显得乏力而发颤（这是因为抽了纯别列佐夫烟草的缘故），“您知不知道本地的法官帕韦尔·卢基奇·梅洛夫？……不知道吧……那没关系。（他咳几下清清嗓子，擦擦眼睛。）您看，怎么说好呢，就照实对您说吧，事情是发生在大斋期里，那正是冰雪消融的时节。我坐在他——我们的法官——家里，在玩普列费兰斯纸牌。我们这位法官是个好人，对玩这种牌很着迷。突然（我的大夫常常用‘突然’这个词）有人对我说：‘有人找您。’我说：‘有什么事？’那人说：‘他带来一张条子，也许是病家写的。’我说：‘把条子拿来。’果然是一个病家写的……那是好事——您明白，这就是我们的饭碗嘛……是这么一回事：那条子是一位守寡的女地主写给我的；她说：‘我女儿病危，看上帝的面上，劳您驾来一趟，我派马车接您。’嗯，这倒没有什么……可是她家离城有二十俄里地，当时已是深更半夜，而且道路又是那么糟！再说啦，她那家又穷，很难指望出两个银卢布以上的诊费，就连这点钱还未必有，没准只给些粗麻布或者旁的一点儿什么。可是您明白，职责重于一切嘛，人家快要丧命了。我突然把纸牌交给那位每场必到的牌友卡利奥宾，就赶回家去。一瞧，一辆小马车已停在台阶前；那几匹马是农家的马——是些大肚子马，肚子特别大，身上的毛简直像毡子一样，那车夫为了表示崇敬，脱了帽坐在那里。我心想，一看就知道，老兄，你的主人不是家财万贯的主呀……您笑了，对您直说吧，我们这些穷哥们，凡事都要掂量掂量……要是车夫像个公爵似的坐着，不脱帽子，还从胡子底下冒出几声冷笑，一边摇晃着鞭子——我敢说准能拿到双倍的诊金！而这一回，我知道不会有那样的运气。不过，我心想，没法子，还是救人要紧嘛。我带上一些最必需的药品，就动身了。您信吗，我费了老劲才勉强到达的。道路糟透了：又是小河，又是雪，又是烂泥，又是水坑，突然有一处堤坝还决了口——多糟糕呀！可我还是到了。病家的房子很小，房顶是麦秸铺的。窗子里亮着灯，想必是在等我。一个恭恭敬敬的老太太戴着便帽出来迎接我。她说：‘救救命吧，她快不行了。’我说：‘请别着急……病人在哪儿呢？’‘请到这边来。’我一看，是一个干干净净的小房间，角落里亮着一盏神灯，床上躺着一位二十来岁的女子，处于昏迷状态。她体温很高，呼吸困难——患的是热病。房间里还另有两位女子，是她的姐妹，她们甚是惊恐，眼泪汪汪的。她们说：‘昨天她还好好的，吃东西也有胃口；今天一早便说头痛，到晚上就这样了。’我再次说：‘请别着急。’您知道，这是医生必须说的话，接着我便开始给病人诊治。我给她放了血，吩咐给她抹上芥末膏，开了药。这时候我瞧了瞧她，瞧着瞧着——我的天，我从来没有见过这样标致的脸蛋……简直可说是个绝色美妞！我的怜惜之情便油然而生。那容貌真招人喜欢，那双眼睛……过了一会儿，感谢上帝，她安静些了；她发了汗，似乎清醒过来了，向周围瞧了瞧，微微一笑，用手摸摸脸……两位姐妹向她俯身问道：‘你怎么样啦？’‘没什么。’她说，身子转了过去……我一瞧，她睡着了。于是我说，现在该让病人安静一会儿。我们便蹑手蹑脚地走出去，留下一个丫头在那里随时侍候。客厅的桌子上已摆好了茶炊，旁边还放着牙买加酒：干我们这一行是少不了它的。给我上了茶，并请我留下过夜……我同意了，这时候还能去哪儿呀！老太太叹气不已。我说：‘您何必这样呢？她会好的。请别担心，您自己去好好休息一下，已经一点多钟了。’‘要是有事，请您叫人喊醒我好吗？’‘好的，好的。’老太太出去了，两位姐妹也回到自己房里去；已经给我在客厅里铺好了床。我躺下来，可就是睡不着——多么奇怪呀！我心里老是翻腾着。我总是想着我的病人。我终于忍耐不住，突然起来了；心里想，去看看病人怎么样了？她的卧室就在客厅隔壁。于是我下了床，轻轻地推开门，而我的心怦怦直跳。我一瞧，那个丫头已经睡着了，张着嘴，还打着鼾，这个狡猾丫头！病人脸朝外躺着，两手伸开，可怜的姑娘！我走近她……她突然睁开眼睛凝视着我……‘谁呀？谁呀？’我有些发窘。我说：‘别害怕，小姐，我是医生，来看看您怎么样了。’‘您是医生？’‘是医生……是令堂派人到城里请我来的；我已经给您放过血，小姐；现在您好好睡吧，过上三两天，上帝保佑，我们会让您康复的。’‘唉，好呀，好呀，医生。别让我死去呀……求求您，求求您啦。’‘您这是怎么啦，上帝会保佑您的！’我心想，她又发烧了。我给她号了下脉，的确，又在发烧。她瞧了我一会儿，突然抓过我的手。‘我要告诉您，我为什么不愿意死，我要告诉您，我要告诉您……现在只有咱们两个人；可是请您别告诉任何人……请听我说……’我弯下身子；她的嘴唇凑到我的耳边，她的头发触到我的脸——说真的，我脑袋都晕了——她喃喃地说了起来……我什么也听不明白……唉，她是在说胡话呢……她低声地说呀，说呀，话说得很快，似乎说的不是俄国话，她说完了，身子颤了一下，把头倒在枕头上，用手指威吓我说：‘当心，医生，不能对任何人说……’我好歹让她安静下来，给她喝了水，叫醒那个丫头，就出来了。”

说到这儿，大夫又使劲地嗅了嗅鼻烟，发了一会儿呆。

“可是，”他接下去说，“到了第二天，同我的期望相反，她的病情不见减轻。我想来想去，突然决定留下来，虽然还有别的病人在等着我……您也知道，对病家可随便不得，不然，以后的业务会大受影响。但是，第一，这病人确实处于危急状态；第二，应说实话，我对她大有好感。再说，这全家人我都喜欢。她们虽然很穷，可很有教养，可以说是很难得的……她们的父亲是个有学问的人，是作家；当然，他死于贫困，然而已经让子女们受到了良好教育；又留下了许多书。是不是因为我在病人身旁热心照料，还是别的原因，我敢说，她们都很喜欢我，对我像亲人似的……再说，路又泥泞得可怕，交通可以说完全中断了；去城里买药也困难得很……病人的病况还未见好转……日子一天又一天地过去……但是……这样一来（大夫沉默了一会儿。）我真不知怎么对您讲好……（他又嗅了下鼻烟，咳了一声，喝了一口茶。）对您直说吧，我的病人……这怎么说呢……也许是爱上了我……或者不是，不是爱上……可是……真的，这怎么说好呢……”（大夫低下了头，脸红了。）

“不，”他很兴奋地接下说，“怎么能说爱上呀！人总该知道自己的身价嘛。她是个有教养的、聪明博学的女子，而我连拉丁文可以说都忘光了。至于模样嘛（大夫微笑着瞧了瞧自己），看起来也没有什么好自夸的。然而上帝也没有让我生成了傻瓜：我不会把白的叫作黑的；我也懂得些什么的。比如说，我心里很清楚，亚历山德拉·安德列叶夫娜——她名叫亚历山德拉·安德列叶夫娜——对我产生的不是爱情，而可以说是一种友好的情谊、敬重什么的。虽然她自己也许在这方面搞错了，要知道她的地位是怎样的，您自己想想看……然而，”大夫带点慌张地一口气说完这些断断续续的话，以后又补充说，“我似乎有点说乱了……这样说您会一点听不明白……这样吧，我还是照顺序给您说吧。”

他喝干了一杯茶，以较平静的音调说起来。

“事情是这样的。我的病人的病情越来越糟了，越来越糟了。您不当大夫，亲爱的先生，您可能体会不了我们这些当大夫的心情，特别是当他最初料到他敌不过病魔时的心情。自信心不知哪儿去啦！你突然会害怕起来，怕得没法说。你似乎感到你把自己的所有医术全给忘了，病人也不相信你了，别的人也发现你惊慌失措了，不大乐意地告诉你症状，皱着眉头瞧着，在一旁嘀嘀咕咕……唉，糟透了！你心里定是在想，会有对症的药的，只要找得到就好。看，是这药不是？试试吧——不对，不是这药！不等药力有起作用的时间……一会儿用这种药，一会儿又用那种药。有时就拿起药学书来翻翻……心想，就是它，就是这种药！实际上有时是随便翻翻书，心想或许运气好能找到什么……可是病人这时候快不行了；也许别的大夫能够救治他。于是你就说，需要会诊；我不能把责任揽给自己。在这种场合下你多么像个傻瓜！不过，时间一长，就习惯了，觉得没有什么。人死了，不是你的过错，你是照章办事嘛。常常还有更令人窝心的事：看到人家盲目地信任你，而你自己则感到无力帮人一把。亚历山德拉·安德列叶夫娜一家正是这样信任我的：她们家的姑娘已危在旦夕。而我这方面呢，则让她们相信，这病不大要紧，可是心里却担心得要命。特别难办的是，道路那么泥泞难行，车夫去买药，往返得好几天。我待在病人房间出不来，我离不开，您知道，我给她讲各种各样好笑的事，同她玩纸牌。夜里都坐在那里守着。老太太噙着泪感谢我；而我心想：‘我不值得你谢。’我坦率地跟您说吧——如今也不必隐瞒了——我爱上了这位女病人。亚历山德拉·安德列叶夫娜对我也情意绵绵；除了我，一般她不让任何别人进她的房间。她跟我一聊起来，便向我问长问短，问我在哪儿上的学，日子过得怎么样，亲人有些谁，同哪些人交往？我觉得不能让她多说话，需要劝阻她，但您知道，完全不让她说说话——我办不到。我常常抱着头在想：‘你是在干什么呀，你这强盗？……’然而她握住我的手不放，打量着我，久久地打量着我，然后转过脸去，叹口气说：‘您是多好的人哪！’她那双手烧得多么烫，眼睛大大的，显得无精打采。她说：“是的，您很善良，您是个好人，您不像我们这里的一些街坊……是的，您不是那种人……我以前怎么不认识您呀！’‘亚历山德拉·安得列叶夫娜，您安静些吧，’我说，‘……说真的，我觉得，我不知道有什么值得您夸奖的……看上帝面上，请您安静些吧，安静些吧……一切都会好的，您会康复的。’不过我应该告诉您，”大夫向前弯弯身，耸起眉头，继续说，“她们跟街坊来往很少，因为寒微人家跟她们身份不大相称，而傲气又使她们不愿去高攀那些富人阔佬。对您说吧，这是一个非常有教养的家庭，所以，您知道，我很引以为荣。她只吃由我亲手递给的药……这可怜的人由我帮她坐起来服药，然后凝望着我……我的心跳得可厉害啦。这期间，她的病情越来越恶化，越来越糟了，我想，她就要死了，一定要死了。您信吗，哪怕让我进棺材也好；这时候她的母亲和两位姐妹都在一旁打量着，直盯着我的眼睛……对我渐渐失去了信任。‘什么？怎么样呀？’‘没什么，没什么！’神志都不清了，怎么是没什么呢。有一天夜里我又是一个人坐在病人旁边。那丫头也坐在那里，鼾声如雷……可是也不能怪这个可怜的丫头，她也累得够呛了。亚历山德拉·安德列叶夫娜整个晚上都感到非常难受，烧得很苦。她一直辗转反侧地折腾到半夜；最后似乎睡着了，至少躺着不动了。屋角里圣像亮着神灯。我坐在那里，耷拉下脑袋，打起盹来。突然，像是有人从旁捅了我一下，我转过头……我的天！亚历山德拉·安德列叶夫娜睁着眼睛在瞅我……嘴张着，两颊烧得通红。‘您怎么啦？’‘医生，我要死了吗？’‘哪会呢！’‘不，医生，不，请不要说我会好起来……不要这样说啦……如果您知道……您听我说，看在上帝面上，不要对我隐瞒病情啦！’她呼吸得非常急速。‘要是我确切知道我定要死去……那我要把一切都告诉您，全告诉您！’亚历山德拉·安德列叶夫娜，请别这样想！’‘请听我说，我一点也没睡着，我对您看了好久……看在上帝面上……我信得过您，您这个人很善良、很诚实，为了世上神圣的一切，我恳求您对我说实话吧！要是您能明白，这对于我是多么的重要。……医生，看在上帝面上，请告诉我，我的病很危险吗？’‘我对您说什么呢，亚历山德拉·安德列叶夫娜——别那么想！’‘请行行好，我求您了！’‘我不能瞒您，亚历山德拉·安德列叶夫娜，您的病确实很危险，但上帝会保佑的……’‘我要死了，我要死了……’她似乎高兴起来，脸上显得非常快乐；我很吃惊。‘您别害怕，别害怕，死一点儿也不让我畏惧。’她突然欠起身来，支在胳膊肘上。“现在……嗯，现在我可以对您说了，我真心实意地感谢您，您很善良，是个好人，我爱您……’我呆了似的瞧着她；您知道，我害怕极了……‘听见了吗，我爱您……’‘亚历山德拉·安德列叶夫娜，我哪儿配呢！’‘不，不，您不理解我……您不理解我……’突然她伸过双手，抱住我的头，吻了一下……真的，我几乎喊了起来……我猛地跪下来，把头埋在枕头里。她默不作声；她的手指在我的头发上颤动着；我听见她在呜咽。我开始安慰她，要她放宽心……我真不知道对她说了些什么。我说：‘您会把那丫头吵醒的，亚历山德拉·安德列叶夫娜……我很感谢您……请相信我……安静些吧。’‘得了，得了，’她一再地说，‘别去管她们啦，她们醒来也好，进来也好，都无所谓：反正我要死……而你有什么好羞的，好怕的呢？抬起头来吧……也许您不爱我，也许我搞错了……若是这样的话，请原谅我。’‘亚历山德拉·安德列叶夫娜，您说的什么呀？……我爱您，亚历山德拉·安德列叶夫娜。’她直对我的眼睛盯了一下，张开双臂。‘那就拥抱我吧……’对您坦率地说，我搞不懂我在那一夜怎么没有发疯。我感到我的病人是在毁灭自己；我看得出，她不完全清醒；我也明白，要是她不认为自己快要死去，她大概就想不到我了；您想想看，她活到二十五岁了，还没有爱过什么人，可就要死去，岂不遗憾？正因为如此，她痛苦极了，所以，出于绝望，她连我这样的人也抓住不放——这一下您明白了吧？她那双手搂着我不放。我说：‘请顾惜顾惜我吧，亚历山德拉·安德列叶夫娜，也顾惜顾惜您自己。’她说：‘为什么呀，有什么好顾惜的呢？反正我要死了……’她不断地叨咕这句话。‘要是我知道我还会活下去，还要做个体面的小姐，那我就会害臊的，真的害臊的……而现在还有什么呢？’‘谁对您说，您要死了？’‘唉，得了，你骗不了我，你连说谎也不会，瞧瞧你自己吧。’‘您会好的，亚历山德拉·安德列叶夫娜，我会把您治好的；我们要求得到令堂的祝福……我们将结为夫妇，我们会幸福的。’‘不，不，我记住您说的话，我会死的……你答应过我……你对我说过……’我很难过，有许多原因令我难过。您想想，有时有些小事，看起来没什么，其实令人痛苦得很。她突然想到问我叫什么名字，她问的不是姓，而是名字。可惜我的名字不怎么的，叫特里丰。是呀，是呀，叫特里丰，特里丰·伊万内奇。在她家里大家都称呼我医生。我没办法，只得实告：‘叫特里丰，小姐。’她眯眯眼睛，摇摇头，用法语嘟哝句什么——大概是句不好听的话吧——随后她笑了起来，也笑得不大好听。就这样我跟她一起过了几乎一整夜。清早我出来像疯了似的；我再去她的房间时已是白天用过茶之后。我的天，我的天哪！都认不出她来了，比死人只多一口气了。我对您绝对说实话，到现在我都不明白，压根儿不明白，我当时怎么受得了那样的折磨。我的病人又苦挣苦扎地活了三天三夜……多么难熬的三个夜晚啊！她对我说了些什么呀！……最后的那一夜，您想象一下吧——我坐在她身旁，只求上帝一样事：快点带她走吧，把我也一起带上吧……突然她的老母亲一下闯进房间里……我在头天晚上就对她——这位老母亲——说过，我说情况不妙，希望不大了，请牧师来吧。病人一见到母亲就说：‘正好，你来了……你看看我们吧，我们相爱了，我们相爱了，我们相互起了誓。’‘她这是怎么啦，医生，她怎么啦？’我已面无人色。我说：‘她发高烧，在说胡话……’而她却说：‘得了，得了，你刚才对我说的完全是另一番话，你还接受了我的戒指呢……你干吗装假呢？我母亲心好，她会原谅的，会理解的，我就要死了——我用不到说谎；把手给我……’我跳了起来，跑掉了。老太太当然已猜到了。

“不过，我就不多打扰了，说真的，我自己一想起这一切，心里真难受。我的病人到第二天就死了。愿她进天国（大夫快速地补说了这句，叹了一口气）！她临终前要求家里人都出去，单留下我一个人在身旁。她说：‘请原谅我吧，也许，我对不起您……有病嘛……不过请您相信，我没有比爱您更深地爱过任何人……请不要把我忘了……保存好我的戒指吧……’”

大夫转过脸去；我握住他的手。

“唉！”他说，“聊聊别的什么吧，要不，想不想玩一玩小输赢的普列费兰斯牌？知道吗，我们这号人是不该陷到那种高尚情感中去的。我们这号人该考虑的只有，怎么让孩子不哭不闹，让老婆不骂街。打那以后，我结婚了，即缔结了所谓的合法婚姻……可不是吗……我娶了一位商人的女儿，有七千卢布的陪嫁。她叫阿库丽娜，跟我特里丰正好门当户对。我告诉您吧，这婆娘挺凶，好在她整天睡大觉……怎么，玩普列费兰斯吗？”

我们坐下来，玩起一戈比一局的普列费兰斯。特里丰·伊万内奇赢了我两个半卢布——他很晚才走，对自己的赢钱极为得意。

我的邻里拉季洛夫

秋天里山鹬常常栖息在那些老椴树园里。在我们奥廖尔省有许许多多这样的园子。我们的先人在选择定居地方时必定辟出两三俄亩好地用来营建带椴树林荫道的果园。经过五十来年，多则七十来年，这些庄园，即所谓的“贵族之家”渐渐从地面上消失了；房子倒塌了，或被卖掉后给拆运走了，石建杂用房也变成了一堆堆废墟。苹果树枯死了，被当作了柴火，栅栏和篱笆都消失殆尽了。唯有椴树依旧欣欣向荣，如今在它们的周围已整出一片片耕地，它们正向我们这些轻浮的后人诉说“早已长眠的父兄”的往事。这样的老椴树是一种非常美好的树……连俄国庄稼汉的无情的斧头也怜惜它呢。它的叶子很小，强劲的树枝宽宽地覆盖四方，树下永是一片浓荫。

我和叶尔莫莱有一回在野外游猎山鹑，我看到旁边有一个荒芜了的园子，就向它走去。我刚刚踏进林子，一只山鹬啪的一声从灌木丛里腾空而起；我放了一枪，就在那一瞬间，离我没几步远的地方有人喊了一声：一位年轻姑娘惊慌的脸从树后露了一下，当即便躲开了。叶尔莫莱向我跑来。“您怎么在这儿开枪呀：这儿住着一个地主呢。”

我还没来得及回答，我的狗也没来得及神采飞扬地把射死的山鹬叼给我，便听到一阵急促的脚步声，一个高个的蓄小胡子的人从密林里走了出来，他一副不高兴的样子站到我跟前。我再三表示歉意，并报了自己的姓名，还把那只在他领地上射下的鸟送给他。

“那好，”他带着微笑对我说，“我就收下您的野禽，但是有一个条件：您要留下来在我家吃顿饭。”

说心里话，我不大乐意接受他的邀请，可是却之不恭。

“我是这儿的地主，是您的邻里，我姓拉季洛夫，您可能听说过，”我的新相识继续说，“今天是星期天，我家的伙食大概会像点样，不然，我就不敢请您了。”

我做了这种场合下得体的回答，便随之前往。一条清扫过不久的小路很快把我们引出了椴树林；我们走进一座菜园。在一些老苹果树和茂盛的醋栗丛之间，长满一棵棵圆圆的浅绿色白菜；蛇醉草弯弯绕绕地缠在高高的杆子上；菜畦上密匝匝地插着小枝条，上面缠着干枯了的豌豆藤；一个个扁平的大南瓜宛如躺在地上；在那些沾满尘土、带棱带角的叶子下露出黄灿灿的黄瓜；高高的荨麻沿着篱笆一溜地摇晃着；有两三处长着一丛鞑靼忍冬、接骨木、野蔷薇，这都是往昔“花坛”的遗物。有一个小鱼池，里面灌满淡红色的含黏液的水，鱼池旁有一口水井，周围尽是小水坑；一些鸭子就在那些水坑里拍水游玩；有只狗全身颤动着，眯着眼睛在草地上啃骨头；一头花斑色母牛也在那边懒洋洋地吃草，不时地用尾巴甩打瘦瘦的脊背。小路拐向了一边；在粗大的爆竹柳和白桦树后面映出了一幢老式小屋，屋顶是松木盖的，屋前有个歪斜的台阶。拉季洛夫在这里停下步。

“不过，”他善意地直对着我的脸瞧了瞧，说，“我刚才细想了一下，也许您根本不愿意上我家来，要是那样的话……”

我没等他把话说完，便极力向他表示：恰好相反，我很高兴在他家用餐。

“那好，请吧。”

我们进了屋。一个身穿蓝色厚呢长外衣的年轻仆人在台阶上迎接我们。拉季洛夫立即让他拿伏特加酒招待叶尔莫莱；我的猎伴朝着这位慷慨施主毕恭毕敬地鞠了个躬。我们经过那个贴有形形色色图画，挂有许多鸟笼的前室，走进一个不很大的房间——这是拉季洛夫的办事室。我脱下了猎装，把枪搁到房角里；一个穿长襟衣服的侍仆忙手忙脚地清掉我身上的尘土。

“好，咱们就到客厅去吧，”拉季洛夫亲切地说，“让您会会家母。”

我跟着他走。客厅中央摆着一个长沙发，那里坐着一位身材不高的老太太，她身穿一件深棕色衣服，戴一顶白色便帽，有一张慈祥而瘦削的脸，眼神畏怯而忧伤。

“妈，我来介绍一下：这位是咱们的邻里×××。”

老太太欠欠身子，向我施下礼，没有从她那双干瘦的手中放下口袋似的粗毛线手提包。

“您光临我们这地方已很久了吗？”她眨了眨眼睛，有气无力地低声问道。

“不，不很久。”

“打算在这儿久住吗？”

“我想住到冬天吧。”

老太太不言语了。

“还有这一位，”拉季洛夫向我指指一个又高又瘦的人说，我进客厅时没有注意到他，“这是费多尔·米赫伊奇……喂，费佳[1]，把你的技艺对客人露一手。你干吗躲到角落里呀？”

费多尔·米赫伊奇立刻从椅子上站起来，从窗台上取过一把破提琴，拿起弓子——不是按规矩握着弓的一头，而是握着弓的中段，把小提琴抵在胸前，闭拢眼睛，跳起舞来，一边哼着歌，把琴弦拉得吱吱直响。看样子他大概有七十来岁，长长的粗布外套在他那干瘦的肢体上可悲地晃荡着，他跳着舞；时而大胆地摇晃着他那光秃的小脑袋，时而似乎要停住不动，把那青筋嶙嶙的脖子伸得直直的，两只脚在原地踩着，有时显然很费劲地屈起双膝。他那掉光牙的嘴巴发出苍老的声音。拉季洛夫大概从我脸上的表情猜到，费佳的“技艺”没有给我带来多大的快乐。

“好了，老爷子，够了，”他说，“你可以去犒劳一下自己了。”

费多尔·米赫伊奇立即把小提琴搁到窗台上，先向我这个客人鞠个躬，接着向老太太，再向拉季洛夫鞠了躬，随后就出去了。

“他原先也是个地主，”我的新朋友接着说，“本来挺有钱的，可是破产了，所以现在就住在我家里……当年他在省里可算是头号的风流汉呢：夺走过两个男人的老婆，家里养着一些歌手，他自己也挺能跳能唱的……要不要来点伏特加？饭菜都摆好了。”

一位年轻姑娘，就是我在园子里见到一眼的那一位，走进房间里来。

“这位就是奥丽雅！”拉季洛夫稍稍转过头说，“请多多关照……好，咱们就去吃饭吧。”

我们去到餐室就了座。当我们从客厅出来，到这边坐定后，那个因受到“犒劳”而两眼发亮，鼻子也微微发红的费多尔·米赫伊奇便唱起《让胜利之雷响起吧！》。屋角里已放着一张没铺桌布的小桌子，上面为他单摆了一份餐具。这个可怜老头的邋遢相令人不敢恭维，所以经常让他离大家远一点。他画了十字，叹口气，然后如鲨鱼似的吞食起来。饭菜确实不错，由于是星期天，所以少不了有颤动的果子冻和那种名为“西班牙之风”的甜点心。这个曾在陆军步兵团干过十来年并到过土耳其的拉季洛夫在餐席上便天南地北地聊开了。我留意地听着，并悄悄地观察起奥丽加[2]。她不算很漂亮；可是她那坚毅而沉着的表情，她那宽阔而白皙的额门、浓密的头发，特别是那双虽然不很大，但显得聪明、清晰、水灵的褐色眼睛，无论谁处在我此时的位置上，都会感到惊讶的。她似乎很专心地倾听拉季洛夫的每句话；她脸上显露的不是兴趣，而是热情的关注。论岁数拉季洛夫可做她的父亲；他称呼她为“你”，然而我立刻猜她不是他的女儿。在谈话中他提到自己已故的妻子——“就是她姐”，他指着奥丽加这样说。她脸一下子红了，垂下了眼睛。拉季洛夫沉默了一会儿，并换了话题。老太太在用餐的整段时间里没有说一句话，几乎什么也没有吃，也没有客气地招呼我多吃菜。她那脸上流露出某种畏缩的、失望的期待和一种老年的忧伤，使人看了感到非常难受。快散席的时候，费多尔·米赫伊奇本来要唱支歌来“赞颂”主人和客人，然而拉季洛夫瞧了我一眼，便叫他不要唱了；老头用手抹抹嘴唇，眨眨眼睛，行了个礼，又坐下了，可坐到了椅子的边上。饭后我和拉季洛夫去到他的办事室。

凡是心里强烈地怀有一种念头或一种欲望的人，在待人接物上都有某种共同点，某种表面上的相似之处，不论他们的品性、能力、社会地位和所受的教育是多么的不同。我越是留意观察拉季洛夫，就越感到他就是属于这一类人。他谈农事、收成、刈草、战争、县里的流言蜚语、近期的选举等时，谈得头头是道，顺畅自如，甚至相当投入，但突然间却叹起气来，像一个被繁忙工作搞得疲累不堪的人一样倒在安乐椅里，用手抹抹脸。他那既善良又温情的整个心灵似乎浸透着、充溢着某种情感。令我惊讶的是，我从他身上看不出他对什么有强烈的爱好，比如对吃喝、对行猎、对库尔斯克的夜莺、对患癫痫病的鸽子、对俄罗斯文学、对溜蹄马、对匈牙利舞、对纸牌和台球游戏、对舞蹈晚会、对省城或大都市的旅游、对造纸厂和制糖厂、对豪华的亭阁、对茶、对娇惯坏了的拉梢马、对胖得把腰带系到胳肢窝下的马车夫、对那些穿着讲究但不知为什么脖子一动眼睛就歪斜和往外翻的马车夫……“这究竟是个什么样的地主呢？”我这样想。而且他绝没有装得像个闷闷不乐的人，像个怨天尤命的人；他对别人总是显出一样的感情和热忱，几乎想要去结交每一个随便相遇的人。其实，您同时会感到，他跟任何人都不可能成为朋友，都不可能真正地深交，这并不是因为他一概不需要别人，而是因为他把一切都埋入内心。我细细观察了拉季洛夫，简直想象不出他无论现在或过去什么时候会是幸福的人。他也不算是个美男子；然而在他的眼神里、微笑里，他的整个身上都蕴含着某种非凡的魅力，的确如此。所以，我很想好好地了解他，喜欢他。当然，有时他也暴露出地主和乡下人的本性，然而他终究是个相当不错的人。

我刚刚同他聊起新任的县长，忽然门口传来奥丽加的声音：“茶备好了。”我们来到客厅。费多尔·米赫伊奇仍然坐在窗子和门之间的那个角落里，谦卑地缩起脚。拉季洛夫的母亲在一边织袜子。窗子是开着的，从园子里飘来秋天的清爽气息和苹果的芳香。奥丽加忙着为我们斟茶。我这会儿比用餐时更加仔细地打量她。她很少说话，像一般的县城姑娘一样，可是至少我从她身上看不出她在痛苦地感到空虚无聊的同时想要说些好听的话，不翻白眼，也不做带幻想味道的、用意不明的微笑。她显得既文静又坦然，如同一个经历过大喜或大悲后歇息下来的人。她的步态、举止又坚定又洒脱。她很让我喜欢。

我跟拉季洛夫又侃了起来。我已经记不清我们是怎样得出一个人所共知的见解：一些最无关紧要的小事往往比一些极其重要的事给人的印象更深。

“是呀，”拉季洛夫说，“我常有这种体会。您知道，我有过妻子。共同生活不很久……三年，我妻子便死于难产。我想，我活不下去了；我悲伤极了，痛苦得要死，可是又哭不出来——成了呆子似的。我们照规矩给她穿好衣服，放到灵床上——就在这间屋子里。神甫来了，几位教堂执事也来了，开始唱赞美诗、祈祷、焚香；我鞠躬磕头，可是掉不出一滴泪来。我的心仿佛变成石头，头脑也是这样——全身沉重极了。头一天就这样过去。您信吗？夜里我甚至睡着了。第二天一早我来到妻子身旁——那时候是夏天，她从头到脚都被阳光照射着，而且被照得亮亮的。突然我看到……（拉季洛夫说到这儿不由得颤抖了一下。）您猜怎么着？她的一只眼睛没有全闭上，有一只苍蝇就在那只眼睛上爬……我一下就栽倒在地了。苏醒后就开始哭呀，哭呀，已抑制不住自己了……”

拉季洛夫不说话了。我瞧了瞧他，又瞧了瞧奥丽加……我永远忘不了她那脸上的表情。老太太把袜子搁在膝上，从手提包里掏出手绢，偷偷地擦擦眼泪，费多尔·米赫伊奇蓦地站起身来，抓过他的小提琴，用嘶哑而古怪的嗓音唱了起来。他大概是想让我们快乐，可是一听他那声音，我们全打战了。拉季洛夫就请他别唱了。

“不过，”他接下去说，“过去的事已经过去了，过去的事是挽回不了的，而且终归……人世上的一切都会好起来的，这话似乎是伏尔泰说的吧。”他连忙补充说。

“是的，”我回答说，“当然是这样的。而且各种不幸都可忍受过去，没有摆脱不了的逆境。”

“您这样想吗？”拉季洛夫说，“怎么说呢，也许您是对的。记得我在土耳其的时候，有一次躺在医院里，人已半死不活的了：我因创口感染而发起热病。唉，那时的住院条件当然没法说是好的，战争时期嘛，有个地方躺就得感谢老天爷了！突然又送来一批伤病员——把他们往哪儿安置呀？大夫跑东跑西，就是找不到地方。后来他走到我身边，问助理医生：‘他还活着吗？’助理医生回答说：‘早上还活着的。’大夫弯下身听了听我还在喘气。这位仁兄就不耐烦了，说：‘这小子真差劲，他反正就要死的，必定死的，却在这儿苟延残喘，拖时间，不过是白占地方，妨碍别人。’我心里想：‘完了，你要完蛋，米海洛·米海雷奇呀……’可我还是病好了，您瞧瞧，还一直活到现在呢。可见您说的是对的。”

“在任何情况下我这样说都是对的，”我回答说，“假如您那时真的死了，那终归也算是摆脱了逆境。”

“那当然是，那当然是，”他用手在桌上拍了一下，补充说……“只要下决心……在逆境里待着有什么出息？……干吗要耽搁、拖延呢……”

奥丽加一下站了起来，往园子里走去。

“喂，费佳，跳个舞吧！”拉季洛夫喊道。

费佳腾地站起来，用一种华丽别致的舞步在房间里跳开了，犹如那出名的“山羊”在训练有素的狗熊身边表演一样，并唱起那首《在我家大门旁……》来。

大门外传来一辆赛跑用的二轮马车的响声，过不多一会儿，一位高身材、宽肩膀、体格结实的老头——独院地主奥夫夏尼科夫——走进这房间里来……不过，奥夫夏尼科夫是一位出色的独特人物，所以请读者许我在另一篇里去谈他。眼前我只补充说一下：翌日，我和叶尔莫莱在天亮前一同去打猎，打过猎就回家了。过了一星期我再次去拉季洛夫家，可是既见不到他，也见不到奥丽加。又过了两星期我便听说，他突然失踪了，抛下母亲，带着那位小姨子不知何处去了。全省都轰动了，对这件事议论纷纷，只有这时候我才彻底领悟奥丽加在拉季洛夫谈到妻子时脸上的那种表情。当时那种表情不单单是同情，它还是一种醋劲儿呢。

我在离开乡下之前去拜望了拉季洛夫的老母。我在那间客厅里见到了她；她正在同费多尔·米赫伊奇玩“傻瓜”牌。

“您有令郎的消息吗？”最后我还是问她。

老太太哭起来了。我就不再向她打听拉季洛夫的消息了。

[1]费多尔的小称。

[2]奥丽雅的小称。

独院地主[1]奥夫夏尼科夫

亲爱的读者，有这样一个人，他身材魁梧，年约七十，脸有点像克雷洛夫[2]，双眉低垂，眉下有一双明亮睿智的眼睛，器宇轩昂，谈吐稳重，步履迟缓，这就是我要向诸位介绍的奥夫夏尼科夫。他穿的是一件肥肥大大的长袖蓝外衣，衣扣直扣到脖下，脖子上围有一条淡紫色绸围巾，脚蹬一双擦得锃亮的带穗子的长筒靴，从大体上看，很像一个殷实的生意人。他的手又软又白，甚为好看，在说话的时候，常常去摸摸外衣上的扣子。奥夫夏尼科夫的傲气和古板、机灵和懒散、直爽和固执使我想起彼得大帝以前时代的俄罗斯贵族……他要是穿上古代的无领大袍，那会很相称的。这是一位旧时代的遗老。乡亲们对他异常尊敬，认为与他交往是件体面事。他的那些独院地主弟兄对他可崇拜啦，老远望见他便脱帽致敬，并以他为骄傲。一般说来，在我们这一带，独院地主跟庄稼人至今很难区分：他们的家业恐怕还比不上庄稼人的，小牛长得不及荞麦高，马匹勉强地活着，挽具也很蹩脚。奥夫夏尼科夫可算是这通常情况中的一个例外，虽然也说不上有钱。他和老伴两人住在一幢舒适整洁的小房子里，仆人不多，让他们穿俄罗斯式服装，称他们为用人。仆人们也替他耕田种地。他不冒称贵族，也不以地主自居，从来不像常言所说的那样“忘乎所以”：头遍请他入席，他不会立即就座，有新的客人到来时他定然起立，然而又显得那样庄重、尊严而亲切，使客人不由得向他深深鞠躬。奥夫夏尼科夫保持古风旧习不是出自迷信（他的心灵是相当自由开放的），而是出自习惯。比如说，他不喜欢带弹簧座的马车，因为他觉得这种马车坐得并不舒坦，他要么乘坐赛跑马车，要么乘坐带皮垫的漂亮小马车，亲自驾驭自己的良种枣红色跑马（他养的马全是枣红色的）。马车夫是一个脸颊红润的年轻小伙子，头发理成圆弧形，穿一件浅蓝呢上衣，头戴低低的羊皮帽，腰系皮带，毕恭毕敬地与主人并肩而坐。奥夫夏尼科夫每天都要睡一会儿午觉，每逢星期六洗一次澡，只读一些宗教的书（而且神气地戴上那副圆形银框眼镜），每天都早起早睡。可是他不蓄胡子，头发理成德国式发型。他待客极为亲切诚挚，但不对客人低三下四。不忙前忙后，也不拿什么干的和腌的东西去款待客人。“老伴！”他慢条斯理地说，身体不站起来，只是稍稍向她转过头，“拿些好吃的来请客人尝尝。”他认为粮食是上帝所赐，销售粮食是罪孽的。一八四〇年，在发生大饥荒和物价狂涨之时。他把自家的全部存粮拿出来赈济附近的地主和农民；来年时他们都很感激地把粮食归还给他。常常有乡亲们跑来请奥夫夏尼科夫去为他们评理、调解，他们几乎都能服从他的评判，听从他的劝解……许多人多亏有他帮助而最终划清了田界……可是有两三次同一些女地主发生龃龉，这以后他便声称，决不为妇道人家之间的纠纷居中调解了。如今他受不了忙乱、受不了惊慌着急，更受不了娘儿们的长嘴长舌和“瞎忙”。有一次他家的房子着了火。有个雇工慌里慌张地向他跑来，一边大喊大叫：“失火了！失火了！”奥夫夏尼科夫镇定自若地说：“你嚷嚷什么呀？递给我帽子和手杖……”他喜欢亲自训练马。有一回，一匹冲劲十足的比秋克马[3]拉着他下山，奔向峡谷。“嘿，得了，得了，年轻的小马驹，你会摔死的。”奥夫夏尼科夫好心地关照它，可说时迟那时快，他连同所乘的赛跑马车、坐在后边的小厮和那匹马一起全滚到峡谷里了。幸亏谷底尽是一堆堆沙子。没有伤着人，只有那比秋克马把一只腿摔脱臼了。“唉，你瞧瞧，”奥夫夏尼科夫从地上爬起来，仍然语气平和地说，“我对你说过的呀。”他按自己的心意找了一位配偶。他的妻子塔季雅娜·伊利尼奇娜是位高个子女人，端庄而寡言少语，老是系着栗色的绸头巾。她显得神情冷漠，可是没有人怨她严厉，相反，有许多穷人称她为好大娘和恩人。端正的容颜、乌黑的大眼睛、薄薄的嘴唇至今仍能证明她当年的出众姿色。奥夫夏尼科夫没有子女。

读者已经知道，我是在拉季洛夫家里认识他的，没过几天我就去他家拜访了。正巧他在家。他坐在皮制的大安乐椅上阅读经文。一只灰猫待在他肩上打呼噜。他按平素习惯亲切而庄重地接待了我。我们攀谈起来。

“请您照实说，卢卡·彼得罗维奇，”谈话中我这样问，“早先在你们那个年月里是不是较好一些？”

“跟您说吧，有些方面确实好一些，”奥夫夏尼科夫说，“那时候我们日子过得比较安定，也比较宽裕，确实……不过还是现在好；到你们的孩子们长大了，那时候一定会更好。”

“卢卡·彼得罗维奇，我原以为您会夸耀旧时代呢。”

“不，旧时代我认为没什么可夸耀的。举个例说吧，如今您是地主，同您已经去世的祖父一样是地主，可您没有他那样的权势啦！而您也不是那一号人。就连当今还有一些地主在挤压我们；看来这也在所难免。也许将来事情会变好的。可不是嘛，我年轻时司空见惯的事，眼前就见不到了。”

“举个例子说吧，是什么事呢？”

“那就再举您爷爷的例子说说吧。他是个好耍权势的人！他常常欺侮我们这类百姓。说来您可能知道——您怎么会不知道自家的地呢——从切普雷金到马利宁的那片地吧？……如今这片地已成了您家的燕麦田……唉，按说这地本来是我家的，整片都是我家的。您爷爷把它从我家霸占了去；他骑着马，手指了指说‘这是我的土地’——就霸占过去了。先父（愿他进天堂！）是个正直人，也是个火暴性子的人，他忍不下这口气——谁甘愿丢掉自家的田产呢？——就去法院上告。可是只有他一人去上告，旁的人都不去告，因为他们都害怕。有人去向您爷爷告密说，彼得·奥夫夏尼科夫去告您了，说您夺走他的地……您爷爷马上就派手下的猎师巴乌什带上一伙人闯到我家来了……他们逮住我的父亲，押到你们家的领地上。那时候我还是个毛孩子，光着脚丫跟在父亲后面跑。您猜怎么着……他们把他押到你们家的窗子下，就用棍子揍他。您爷爷站在凉台上瞅着；您奶奶坐在窗前，也在瞅着。我父亲就喊道：‘大娘，马丽雅·瓦西利叶夫娜，可怜可怜我，替我说句公道话吧！’可是她只是欠欠身子，观看着。就这样逼着我父亲答应交出土地，还要他向你们家表示感谢，感谢放他一条活命。这块地就这样成了你们家的了。您去问问您家的佃户看，这块地叫什么？它就叫棍棒地，因为是用棍棒夺来的。所以说，我们这些小人物就不喜那老一套规矩。”

我不知道如何对奥夫夏尼科夫说才好，我不敢瞧他的脸。

“当时我家还有一位邻里，他姓科莫夫，名叫斯捷潘·尼克托波利昂内奇。他使尽各种花招来刁难我父亲。他是个酒鬼，喜欢请人喝酒，酒喝足时就用法文说一句‘塞邦’[4]，又把嘴巴舔了舔，然后就闹腾开了！他叫人去把所有的左邻右舍都请了来。他的马车都准备好了，停在门前；你要是不去，他马上亲自闯来……真是一个怪人！他在所谓‘清醒’的时候不大瞎说；可是一喝醉酒，就胡吹起来了，说他在彼得堡的丰坦卡街上有三幢房子，一幢是带一个烟囱的红房子，另一幢是带两个烟囱的黄房子，第三幢是蓝的，不带烟囱；他说他有三个儿子（实际上他没有结过婚），一个当步兵，另一个当骑兵，老三在家过日子……又说，三个儿子各住一幢房子，老大家常有海军将官来访，老二家常有陆军将官来访，而到老三家来的尽是英国人！说着说着便站了起来，说：‘为我家老大的健康干杯，他是最孝敬我的孩子！’接着便哭了起来。要是有谁不举杯祝酒，那就糟了。他就要说：‘毙了你！他不许埋葬你！……’有时候他会蹦起来大喊：‘大伙都来跳舞吧，让自个儿乐一乐，也让我高兴高兴！’那你就得跳，哪怕死了也得跳。他把家里的农奴丫头们折磨得可苦啦。经常让她们通宵达旦地唱歌，谁唱得最响亮，就奖赏谁。当她们唱累了——他就抱着脑袋哀叹道：‘哎呀，我这孤苦伶仃的人啊！大家都抛下我这可怜的人了！’于是马夫们赶紧就来给丫头们打气。我父亲也被他看中了，有啥法子呢？他差点把我父亲打发进了棺材，真的快被他折腾死了，幸亏他自己先死了，是喝醉了从鸽子棚上跌下来摔死的……瞧，我家有过一些什么样的邻里啊！”

“时代已经变多了！”我说。

“是呀，是呀，”奥夫夏尼科夫赞同地说道，“可以这样说吧，在那些旧年月贵族们活得可奢侈了。至于那些达官显要就更不用提了：我在莫斯科时见得多啦。据说，这种人如今在那边也不见了。”

“您去过莫斯科？”

“去过，那早啦，很早很早啦。如今我七十三了，我是在十六岁那一年去的莫斯科。”

奥夫夏尼科夫叹了口气。

“您在那边见到过一些什么人呢？”

“许许多多的达官显贵都见到过，什么样的都见过；他们真是荣华富贵，令人惊叹呀。可是没有人比得上已故的伯爵阿列克塞·格里戈列维奇·奥洛夫—切斯明斯基。阿列克塞·格里戈列维奇我经常见到；我的一位叔叔在他家里当管家。伯爵家就住在卡卢加门附近的沙波洛夫卡街。他真是显贵人物呢！他的那种风度仪表，那种宽宏大度，你根本想象不出，也无法形容。单是身材别提多魁梧了，而且身强力壮，目光炯炯！当你还没有熟悉他，没有接近他的时候，的确会感到害怕，会感到胆怯；可是一旦与他接近之后，他就会像太阳一样使你感到浑身温暖，非常愉快。他容许每个人去见他，他对什么事情都感兴趣。他亲自参加赛马，不论什么人都可以同他竞赛；他从来不立即一马当先，他不愿让别人难堪，不挡着别人，只是到最后才超越过去；他显得那样和蔼可亲：他安慰对手，夸奖对手的马。他养了一批善翻筋斗的优种鸽子。常常来到院子里，坐在安乐椅上，吩咐放鸽子飞；仆人们站在周围的房顶上，拿着枪防止老鹰的袭击。伯爵的脚边放了一个大银盆，里面盛着水，他就朝水里观赏那些鸽子。许许多多穷苦人、乞丐都靠他救济过日子……他献出了多少钱财啊！他一旦发怒，简直像是打雷，可怕极了，不过你用不到哭鼻子，过一会儿再瞧，他已笑容满面了。他一举办宴会，准教全莫斯科人喝个醉……要知道他还是个好聪明的人哪！他打败过土耳其人。他还喜欢角力；他从图拉，从哈尔科夫，从唐波夫，从全国各地请来一大批大力士。谁被他摔倒了，便奖赏谁；要是谁赢了他，他更是给以厚赏，还要亲吻他……我还待在莫斯科那一会儿，他曾发起过一次猎犬比赛，这样的比赛在俄国从未有过：他邀请全国所有的猎人前来，并规定了日期，限期三个月。这样，猎人们都来会集了。把猎狗、雇用的猎手都运来了——嚯，到的人可多了，真是千军万马！先是设宴款待，然后大家前去城外。观众来得多极了，真是海了去啦……您猜怎么着？……您爷爷的那只狗跑得最快，一举夺魁。”

“是那只米洛维特卡吗？”我问。

“是米洛维特卡，那只米洛维特卡……这样一来伯爵就向您爷爷请求说：‘把您的狗卖给我吧，你要多少，就给多少。’您爷爷回答说：‘不，伯爵，我不是买卖人：没用的破烂也不卖，若是为了表示敬意，即使老婆也可让人，唯独这只米洛维特卡不能让……我倒宁肯让出自己。’阿列克塞·格里戈列维奇很赞赏他，说：‘好，佩服。’您爷爷就用马车把这只狗送回家了；后来米洛维特卡死了，您爷爷让人奏乐为它送葬，把它葬在花园里，在坟前立了块碑，并刻上墓志铭。”

“这么说来，阿列克塞·格里戈列维奇没有得罪过任何人。”我说。

“事情往往是这样的：谁越没能耐，谁就越翘尾巴。”

“那个巴乌什是个什么样的人呢？”沉默了一会儿之后，我问。

“您听说过米洛维特卡，怎么会不知道巴乌什呢？……他是您爷爷手下主要猎师和驯猎狗的人。您爷爷喜欢他不次于喜欢米洛维特卡。这是个什么都敢干的人，只要您爷爷一声令下，他会立即照办，哪怕是上刀山下火海……他朝猎狗吆喝一声，林子里就会闹得天翻地覆。有时他一下闹起倔脾气来，就跳下马，躺倒不干……猎狗一旦听不到他的吆喝声，那就完了！那些狗就不再去闻新留下的猎物足迹，什么猎物也不去追了。这一下让您爷爷气得要命！‘我不吊死这个无赖，就不活了！我要剥这个坏蛋的皮！我要让这个坏家伙不得好死！’但是到头来还是派人去询问他有什么要求，探问他不吆喝狗去捕猎的原因。巴乌什在这种情况下一般只要求喝酒，一当喝够了酒，就会起身上马，又高高兴兴地去指挥那群猎狗了。”

“您好像也喜欢打猎，卢卡·彼得罗维奇？”

“可算喜欢吧……确是如此，但不是现在，现在我的好时光已经过去了，那是在年轻的时候……可是您知道，由于身份的关系，不大好搞，像我们这些人是不能跟在贵族们屁股后头的。的确，我们这类人中也有一些嗜酒成性的没出息的人，常常去同那些老爷们一起胡混……这有什么乐趣呢……不过是让自己丢脸罢了。人家让他骑蹩脚的、跌跌绊绊的马；动不动揪下他的帽子往地上扔，有时还用鞭子抽他一下，像抽马似的；而他老得赔着笑脸，让人家开心。不行呀，我对您说，越是身份低，就越要自重，否则，只会自讨羞辱。”

“是呀，”奥夫夏尼科夫叹口气，继续说，“许多时光像水似的流过去了。世道已经变了。特别是在那些贵族中间，我看到的变化可大啦。田产少的要么去当差，要么不住在原地了；那些田产多的，更叫人认不出来了。那些有大产业的人，在那阵划分地界的时候，我见得多了。我可以这样跟您说吧，瞅着他们，心里的确很喜欢：他们又和气，又有礼貌。只有一点很使我惊奇，他们学识渊博，说话有条有理，令人心悦诚服，可是对于实际的事却一窍不通，连自己的利益是否受损也搞不明白：他们的农奴管家就如折轭具似的摆弄他们。说起来您可能知道亚历山大·弗拉季米罗维奇·科罗廖夫吧？他算得上是个地道的贵族吧？长相帅气，家产殷实，又受过高等教育，似乎出过国，谈吐稳重、谦虚，见了我们总要握握手。您认识吗？……那好，请听我说一说。上星期我们应中介人尼基福尔·伊利奇的邀请前去别廖佐夫卡聚会。中介人尼基福尔·伊利奇对我们说：‘诸位，该把地界划一划清了；比起所有其他地区来，我们这地区落后啦，这多丢脸呀。我们就开始干吧。’于是我们就干起来了。照例是磋商、争论；我们的代理人发起性子来。但最先带头吵闹的是钦尼科夫·波尔菲里……而这个人为什么要闹呢？……他本人地无一垄，他是受兄弟之托来办事的。他大喊道：‘不行！你们糊弄不了我！不行！不能那样搞！把测量图拿来！把测量员给我叫来，叫那坏小子上这儿来！’‘您到底要怎么样呢？’‘别把人当傻瓜！哼，你们以为我马上会把我的要求说给你们听吗？……不行，你们还是把测量图拿来，就这样！’他的手在图上直敲。马尔法·德米特列夫娜被他气得要死。她喊道：‘您怎么敢败坏我的名誉？’他回答说：‘把您的名誉给我的栗色母马我都不要。’好说歹说，总算用马杰拉酒让他消了气。他平静下来了，可别的人又闹开了。亚历山大·弗拉季米罗维奇·科罗廖夫坐在角落里，咬着手杖上的镶头，只是不住地摇头。我感到很不好意思，真想溜了出去。人家对我们会怎么想呢？一瞧，我的亚历山大·弗拉季米雷奇[5]站了起来，装出要说话的样子。中介人慌忙地说：‘诸位，诸位，亚历山大·弗拉季米雷奇要讲话了。’不能不夸这些贵族：大家立即停下不吵了。于是亚历山大·弗拉季米雷奇开始讲了，他说：我们似乎忘记了我们是为了什么会集到这儿的；虽然划分地界无疑是对土地拥有者有利的，但实质上它为的是什么呢？为的是使农民负担轻一些，使他们劳作起来方便一些，承担得起赋役；而不要像现在这样，自己都搞不清自己的土地，常常要跑到五俄里外去耕种，再说对他们也很难处罚。随后亚历山大·弗拉季米罗维奇又说：地主不去关心农民的利益是罪过的；如果冷静地想一想，最终就会明白，农民的利益和我们的利益是一致的：他们好，我们也好，他们不好过，我们也不好过……所以，为了一些鸡毛蒜皮的事而争来争去，那是罪过的、糊涂的……他说呀，说呀……说得多在理呀！很打动人的心……贵族们听了个个垂下了头；我也差点掉了泪。说实话，古书里也没有说过这样的话……而到头来怎么样呢？他那四俄亩长满青苔的沼地却死活不愿让出来，也不愿意卖。他说：‘我叫人把这块沼地的水排干，在那儿建一座设备完善的毛纺厂。’又说：‘我已选定这块地做厂址，这方面我有我的考虑……’如果真是这样，倒也罢了，然而事情并非如此，只不过是因为他的乡邻安东·卡拉西科夫舍不得花一百卢布票子去疏通他的那位管家老爷。事情一件也没办成，我们就散了。直到现在亚历山大·弗拉季米雷奇还认为自己是对的，还老是去谈毛纺厂的事，可是并没有叫人去给那沼地排水。

“他对自己的产业是怎样经营的呢？”

“他采用全套新办法。农民们不赞赏，不过也用不着听他们的。亚历山大·弗拉季米雷奇搞得不错。”

“这是怎么啦，卢卡·彼得罗维奇？我以为您是老保守呢。”

“我嘛，是另一码事了。我既不是贵族，也不是地主。我的产业算得了啥？……干别的我也不会。我力求做得公道，合法——这就谢天谢地了！年轻的老爷们不喜欢老的一套，我很赞赏他们……该是动动脑筋的时候了。只有一点差劲：年轻的老爷们太自作聪明了。对待庄稼人就像玩木偶似的，转过来，转过去，搞坏了一丢了之。这样一来，农奴出身的管家，或德国籍的管事又把庄稼人抓在自己的手心里了。哪怕有一个年轻老爷做出个榜样也好，让人看看，应该怎样经营才对……这结果又会怎样呢？难道我就这样死去，看不到新的局面了吗？……什么样的怪事呀？老的东西死了，新的东西还没有出生！”

我不知道怎样回答奥夫夏尼科夫才好。他环顾了一下，向我更挪近一点，低声往下说：

“您听说过瓦西利·尼科拉伊奇·柳博兹沃诺夫的事吗？”

“没有，没有听说。”

“请您说说，这是什么怪事，我搞不明白。是他那些佃户说的，可我弄不懂他们说的是什么意思。您知道，他是个年轻人，不久前他母亲去世了，他得到了一笔遗产。于是来到自己的领地上。庄稼人一齐前来，想瞧瞧自家老爷的风采。瓦西利·尼科拉伊奇向他们迎了过来。庄稼人一瞧——好奇怪呀！——老爷穿着一件棉毛裤，像个马车夫，脚上穿的是一双镶边的靴子；他穿的衬衫是红色的，上衣也是像马车夫穿的；蓄着大胡子，头上戴的是顶样式古怪的小帽，那张脸也很怪，似醉非醉，像是精神不正常。他说：‘你们好，伙计们！愿上帝保佑你们。’庄稼人向他鞠躬，只是不吭声，大概有些胆怯。他本人似乎也显得胆怯。他向众人讲了几句话，他说：‘我是俄罗斯人，你们也是俄罗斯人；我爱俄罗斯的一切……我的心是俄罗斯的，血也是俄罗斯的……’突然他下令说：‘来，乡亲们，唱一首俄罗斯民歌吧！’庄稼人的双腿哆嗦起来，都发愣了。有一个胆子大一些的人开始唱了，立刻又蹲下地去，藏到别人的背后了……令人惊奇的是，我们这儿确实有一些落拓不羁的地主，行为放荡，穿得像马车夫一样，又跳舞，又弹吉他，跟仆人们一起唱歌、饮酒，跟农人们一起吃吃喝喝；可是这位瓦西利·尼古拉伊奇却像位大家闺秀，老是在读书写字，要么就唱赞美诗，不跟人聊天，腼腼腆腆，经常独自一人在花园里徘徊漫步，像是有苦闷或忧伤。原有的那个管家在开头一些日子显得惶惶不安；在瓦西利·尼古拉伊奇到来之前，他跑遍了各家农户，向大家鞠躬作揖——这馋猫心里明白，它吃了谁家的鱼肉！庄稼人有了盼头，心里想：‘你溜不掉，伙计！马上有人来收拾你啦；当心吧，你这贪心鬼！……’可结果呀——怎么对您说好呢？连上帝也弄不明白是怎么回事！瓦西利·尼古拉伊奇叫管家前来，他一开口，自己倒先脸红了，连呼吸也急促起来，说：‘你在我这儿办事要公道，不要欺压人，听见了吗？’打那以后就没有再叫管家前来听吩咐了。他待在自家领地上就像个陌生人。这样一来，管家便放宽心了，庄稼人都不敢去找瓦西利·尼古拉伊奇，因为他们害怕。还有令人奇怪的事呢：这位老爷向他们鞠躬问候，亲切地望着他们，他们却反而吓得发抖。多么怪呀，先生，您说说？……或许是我糊涂了，老了，还怎么的——我搞不明白。”

我回答奥夫夏尼科夫说，这位柳博兹沃诺夫先生也许有病。

“有什么病！别看他年轻轻的，身子已肥得滚圆，脸也胖嘟嘟的……真是天晓得！”（奥夫夏尼科夫深深叹了口气。）

“好，不谈贵族了，”我说，“您给我讲讲独院地主的事好吗，卢卡·彼得罗维奇？”

“不，不说这个吧，”他连忙说，“的确……也该对您说说说……可是说什么呢！（奥夫夏尼科夫挥一下手。）咱们还是用茶吧……他们是庄稼人，的确就是庄稼人；不过说真的，我们这类人还能怎么样呢？”

他沉默起来了。茶端上来了。塔季雅娜·伊利尼奇娜从座位上站起，坐得更靠近我们些。这个晚上她悄悄地出去几趟，又悄悄地回来。房间里寂然无声。奥夫夏尼科夫庄重地一杯接一杯地慢慢喝着。

“米佳今天来了。”塔季雅娜·伊利尼奇娜低声地说。

“他来干什么？”

“来赔不是。”

奥夫夏尼科夫摇摇头。

“唉，您说说看，”他朝向我说，“拿这些亲戚怎么办呢？不能把他们拒之门外……这不，上帝赐给我一个侄儿。这孩子人很聪明，很机灵，这没得说；学习也棒，只是我对他什么也指望不上。他本来任了公职，可他撂下不干了：说是没什么发展前途……难道他是个贵族？即使是个贵族，也不能立刻当上将军嘛。目前他没事闲着……这倒没什么——谁知道他竟干起替人提刀代笔的事！替农人写状子，拟呈文，给乡警出点子，告发土地测量员，出入大小酒馆，结交一些无业人员、小市民、旅店的勤杂工。这不是迟早得惹祸吗？这警察局长和县警察局长警告过他不止一次了。好在他能花言巧语，插科打诨，逗得他们哈哈大笑，可后来又给他们添麻烦……得了，他还坐在你的小屋子里吗？”他转身对妻子说，“我可知道你，你可是那副菩萨心肠，总护着他。”

塔季雅娜·伊利尼奇娜低下头，笑了笑，脸也红了。

“哼，就是这样嘛，”奥夫夏尼科夫继续说……“你呀，就会宠他！好了，叫他过来吧——那就这样吧，看在贵客面上，我饶了这傻瓜蛋……好，叫他过来，叫他过来……”

塔季雅娜·伊利尼奇娜走到门口喊了一声：“米佳！”

米佳是个二十七八岁的青年人，身材高挑挺拔，一头鬈发。他进房间时一看见我，便停在门边。他穿的是德国式服装，但单是肩部大得不相称的褶子就明显地证明，这服装无论是裁剪或做工都是出自俄国裁缝的手。

“嘿，过来吧，过来吧，”老头子说，“为啥害臊呀？要谢谢你婶，是她说的情……好，我来介绍一下，”他指着米佳说，“这是我的亲侄儿，可我怎么也管教不了他。他混到头啦！（我和他相互鞠个躬。）你说说，你在那边又胡搞什么啦？他们为啥告你，你说呀。”

米佳显然不愿当着我的面进行解释和辩白。

“以后再说吧，叔。”他咕哝说。

“不，别以后啦，现在就说吧，”老头子继续说道……“我知道，你呀，在这位先生面前感到难为情，这样更好——你就痛悔吧。你说，你说……我们来听听。”

“我没什么可难为情的，”米佳激动地开始说，晃了晃头，“叔，您自己评断一下吧。列舍季洛夫的几个独院地主来对我说：‘替我们说说理吧，老弟。’我问：‘怎么一回事？’‘事情是这样的：我们的粮库管理得好好的，可以说再好不过了；突然有位当官的来到我们这儿，说是奉命来检查仓库的。他检查一通之后就说：“你们的粮库管理紊乱，有严重纰漏，我必须向上级汇报。”那我们问：“纰漏何在呢？”他说：“这我心里有数。”……于是我们便一起商量出一个办法：给那个官老爷烧把香，孝敬孝敬他，可是普罗霍雷奇那老家伙却不赞成，他说，这样只能使那些官老爷更贪得无厌。实际上这算什么呢？我们就毫无办法对付？……我们听了这老家伙的话，可是那位官老爷生气了，真的打了报告指控我们了。如今要传我们上法庭了。’我问：‘那么你们的粮库确实管理得好吗？’‘苍天可做证，管理得很好，而且存有法定数量的粮食……’我说：‘既然如此，你们就不必害怕。’于是我就替他们写了状子……现在谁胜谁负还不清楚……为什么有人为这件事上您这儿来指责我——道理是很明显的：无论什么人，自己的衬衫总是最贴近自身。”

“任何人都是这样，显然，你不是这样，”老头低声地说……“那么你跟舒托洛莫夫的庄稼人在那边搞什么鬼？”

“您怎么知道的？”

“我当然知道。”

“这事儿我也没做错——您再好好评断评断。舒托洛莫夫的庄稼人有位乡邻叫别斯潘金，他种了他们的四俄亩地，他说这块地是属于他自己的。舒托洛莫夫的庄稼人是付了代役租的，他们的东家已出国去了，您想想，还有谁替他们辩护呢？这块地毫无疑问历来都是他们承租的。所以他们来找我，请我替他们写份申诉书。我就写了。那个别斯潘金得知以后便威胁说：‘我要敲碎这个米捷卡[6]的全身骨头，再不然就让他脑袋搬家……’瞧着吧，看他怎样来搬我的脑袋：到现在我这脑袋还是好好的呢。”

“哼，别吹牛，你的脑袋迟早保不住，”老头说，“你完全是个疯子！”

“怎么啦，叔，不是您自己对我说过……”

“我知道，知道你要对我说什么，”奥夫夏尼科夫打断了他的话，“的确，做人应该正直公道，应该乐于助人。有时候还应该豁得出去……可你难道全是这样做的吗？不是常常有人请你上酒馆吗？不是请你喝酒，向你鞠躬作揖，说：‘德米特里·阿列克塞伊奇，好老爷，帮帮忙吧，我们必当酬谢。’说着把一个银卢布或一张五卢布钞票偷偷地塞给你，是不是？啊？有没有这样事？说呀，有没有？”

“这事我的确有错，”米佳低下头回答说，“可我没有拿穷人的钱，我没有昧着良心。”

“现在你没有拿，一旦自己穷急了，就会拿的。没有昧着良心……哼，你呀！好像你维护的全是大好人呢！……那博里卡·彼列霍多夫你忘啦？……是谁替他奔走的？是谁庇护他的？啊？”

“彼列霍多夫他是自作自受，的确……”

“他挪用公款……这是闹着玩呀！”

“可是，叔，您想想看，他很穷，又养着一大家子……”

“穷，穷……他是个酒鬼，是个赌徒，问题就在这儿！”

“开头他是借酒浇愁。”米佳放低声音说。

“借酒浇愁！如果你有一副热心肠，你应该帮帮他，可你自己不该同那酒鬼一道上酒馆去。他能说会道，那有什么新鲜！”

“他人顶善良的……”

“在你眼里全是好人……怎么样，”奥夫夏尼科夫转身对妻子说，“给他送去了吗……就在那边，你知道的……”

塔季雅娜·伊利尼奇娜点点头。

“这些天你去哪儿啦？”老头子又说起来。

“在城里。”

“大概整天在那边玩台球，喝茶，弹吉他，跑衙门，跟商人子弟胡混，躲在后屋里写状子，是这样吗？……说呀！”

“就算是这样吧，”米佳微笑说……“嗐，我差点儿忘了：安东·帕尔费内奇·丰季科夫请您星期天上他家去吃饭。”

“我不去这个大肚皮家。吃老贵的鱼，放的油却是带哈喇味的。别去理他了！”

“我碰见了费多西娅·米海洛夫娜。”

“哪个费多西娅？”

“就是买下米库利诺那块地的地主加尔片琴科家里的那一个。费多西娅是米库利诺村的人。她在莫斯科做裁缝，承担代役租，能按时交纳租金，每年交一百八十二个半卢布……她手艺很好，在莫斯科很多人请她定做衣服。日前加尔片琴科去信召她回来，把她留在这儿，又不派她干什么活。她很想赎身，也向东家说过了，可是他不做任何决定。叔，您跟加尔片琴科相识，能不能去对他说一说？……费多西娅愿出高价赎身。”

“是不是花你的钱呀？是不？嗯，那好吧，我去跟他说说。不过我不知道，”老头带着不满的神色继续说，“这个加尔片琴科呀，上帝宽恕，可是个贪心鬼：他收购期票、放高利贷、抢购地产……是谁把他带到我们这地方来的？唉，我真看不惯这些外地人！跟他打交道不会很快有结果的；不过，试试看吧。”

“您就帮个忙吧，叔。”

“好吧，我帮忙。不过你得小心，得留神！好啦，好啦，别再说七说八了……行了，行了……不过往后你得小心为好，否则呀，米佳，你会吃苦头的，真的，会倒霉的。我不能老是替你担责任……我也不是有权有势的人。好啦，现在你去吧。”

米佳出去了。塔季雅娜·伊利尼奇娜也跟了出去。

“让他喝点茶吧，娇宠孩子的女人，”奥夫夏尼科夫朝她背后喊道……“这小子人不笨，”他继续说，“心眼也好，只是我很替他担心……唉，真对不起，尽顾聊这些小事，耽搁您这么久。”

通前室的门开了，进来了一个矮个子，头发花白，身穿丝绒外衣。

“啊，弗兰茨·伊万内奇！”奥夫夏尼科夫喊了起来，“您好！近来一切都好吗？”

亲爱的读者，让我来介绍一下这位先生。

弗兰茨·伊万内奇·列戎（Lejeune）是我的一位邻里，也是奥廖尔的一位地主，他通过不大寻常的手段取得了俄国贵族的荣誉称号。他出生于奥尔良，父母都是法国人，他跟着拿破仑前来侵略俄国，充当一名鼓手。起初一切都顺顺当当，这位法国佬也雄赳赳气昂昂地走进莫斯科。可是在回去的路上，这个可怜的列戎先生便冻得半死，鼓也丢了，还落到了斯摩棱斯克庄稼人的手里。那些庄稼人把他押到一个空荡荡的缩绒厂里关了一夜，第二天早晨便把他带到堤坝旁边一个冰窟窿前，就请这位“de la grande armée”[7]鼓手赏个面子，也就是说，让他钻到冰底下去。列戎先生没法接受这些庄稼人的盛情，只得用法语恳求这些庄稼人放他回奥尔良去。他说：“Messieurs[8]，那边有我的母亲，une tendre mère[9]。”可是这些庄稼人大概不清楚奥尔良城的地理位置，依然请他沿着这条弯弯曲曲的格尼洛捷尔卡河顺流而下，做一次水下旅游，而且已经轻轻推着他的颈椎和脊椎勉励他钻下去，蓦然传来了一阵铃声，这让列戎有说不出的高兴，一辆大雪橇向堤坝驶来，雪橇的后座又宽又高，铺着一条色彩斑斓的毯子，在前边拉套的是三匹黄褐色的维亚特卡马，雪橇上坐着的是一位身穿狼皮大衣，身材肥胖，满面红光的地主。

“你们在那儿干什么呀？”他问庄稼人。

“我们要把一个法国佬沉到河里去，老爷。”

“啊！”地主坦然地应了一声，就转过头去。

“Monsieur! Monsieur！[10]”那可怜的人呼喊起来。

“啊，啊！”那穿狼皮大衣的人带着斥责的口吻说话了，“该死的家伙，跟着拿破仑的侵略军闯到俄国来，烧毁了莫斯科，偷走了伊万大帝钟楼上的十字架，可现在却喊‘穆西，穆西！（先生，先生！）’现在夹起尾巴了吧！恶有恶报……走吧，菲利卡！”

马儿又跑动了。

“啊，等一下！”地主添说了一句……“喂，你这穆西懂音乐吗？”

“Sauvez-moi, sauver-moi, mon bon monsieur!”[11]列戎哀求说。

“瞧，这种小民族！竟没有人懂俄语！缪济克，缪济克，萨韦……缪济克……武？萨韦？（音乐，音乐，你懂音乐吗？懂吗？）喂，你说呀！科姆普列内？萨韦……缪济克……武？（听得懂吗？你懂音乐吗？）福尔托皮亚诺……茹埃……萨韦？（钢琴，你会弹吗？）”

列戎终于听懂了这地主所说的意思，便肯定地点点头。

“Oui, monsieur, oui, oui, je suis musicien; je jone tous les instruments possibles! Oui, monsieui…Sauvez-moi, monsieur!"[12]

“嘿，算你走运。”地主回答说……“伙计们，放了他吧；赏给你们二十戈比打点酒喝喝。”

“谢谢，老爷，谢谢，您就带他走吧。”

让列戎坐上了雪橇。他高兴得喘不过气来，哭着，哆嗦着，向地主、车夫、庄稼人鞠躬致谢。他身上只穿着一件带玫瑰色带子的绿色绒衣，而天气又冷得够呛。那地主默默地瞧了瞧他那冻僵了的发青的四肢，就把这倒霉蛋裹进自己的皮大衣里，带着他回家去。仆人们跑了过来。急忙给这法国人生火暖身，让他饱餐一顿，给他衣服穿。地主把他领到自己的几个女儿那里去。

“瞧，孩子们，”他对女儿们说，“给你们找到一位老师了。你们老是缠着我说：教我们音乐和法国话吧。现在给你们找来了法国人，他会弹钢琴……喂，穆西，”他指了指五年前从一个卖香水的犹太人那里买来的那架破钢琴，继续说，“露一手你的技艺给我们瞧瞧吧，茹埃！（弹吧！）”

列戎坐到椅上，心都吓愣了，因为他生来还没有摸过钢琴呀。

“茹埃吧，茹埃吧！”地主又重说了一次。

这可怜的人像击鼓似的拼命敲打着琴键，乱弹一气……“我当时心里想，”他后来对别人说，“我的救命恩人会抓住我的衣领，把我摔到门外去的。”令这个不得已的即兴演奏者大感吃惊的是，这地主听了一会儿，赞许地拍了拍他的肩膀。“好，好，”他说，“我看得出，你很有一手；现在你歇歇去吧。”

过了两个来星期，列戎从这个地主家转到了另一个地主家，此人既有钱也有学识，他挺喜欢列戎的愉快而温顺的性格，就把自己的养女许配给了他。后来列戎谋到了差使，变成了贵族，并把自己的闺女嫁给了奥廖尔的一个地主。这地主叫洛贝扎尼耶夫，是一个退伍的龙骑兵，会写诗，列戎自己后来也搬到奥廖尔来住了。

正是这个列戎，或者像现在称呼的弗兰茨·伊万内奇，在我还在座时，走进奥夫夏尼科夫的房里来，他同这位主人颇有交情……

也许读者跟着我在独院地主奥夫夏尼科夫家里已坐厌烦了，因此我就不再叨叨个没完了。

[1]指俄国的一种小地主，通常仅拥有一个院子和少量土地，他们大都是十六七世纪边防军下级军官的后裔。

[2]指俄国著名寓言作家克雷洛夫。

[3]是一种特种马，繁殖于沃龙涅日省著名的“赫列诺夫”养马场（即奥尔洛娃伯爵夫人的养马场）一带。——作者原注

[4]指法语C'est bon，意为“这很好”。——原注

[5]即弗拉季米罗维奇的别称。

[6]米佳的鄙称。

[7]法语：大军的。——原注

[8]法语：先生们。——原注

[9]法语：慈爱的母亲。——原注

[10]法语：先生！先生！

[11]法语：“救救找，救救我，仁慈的先生！”——原注

[12]法语：“是的，先生，是的，是的，我是音乐家；各种乐器我都会！是的，先生……救救我，先生！”——原注

利戈夫村

“咱们去利戈夫村吧，”那个已为读者所熟悉的叶尔莫莱有一次对我说，“那边的鸭子可多了，够咱们打的。”

对于一个懂门道的猎人来说，虽然野鸭算不上是什么特别诱人的野味，可是眼下一时没有其他野味可打（这时候是九月初，山鹬尚未到来，在野外追猎山鹑我已厌烦了），所以我便听从我的搭档的建议，前往利戈夫村去了。

利戈夫村是个地处乡野的大村庄，村里有一座年头不少的石建的单圆顶教堂，还有两个磨坊建在那条沼泽似的罗索塔小河上。这条小河在离利戈夫村约五俄里外的地方变成了一个宽阔的水塘，水塘的周围以及中央的一些地方长着密匝匝的芦苇，奥廖尔人称之为“芦苇荡”。就在这片水塘里，在那些水湾或芦苇之间的幽僻处，生息着无数的各类野鸭子，如绿头鸭、半绿头鸭、针尾鸭、小水鸭、潜鸭，等等。它们常常一小群一小群地在水面上飞来飞去，一听枪响，便腾空而起，像一片乌云，使猎人情不自禁地一手抓住帽子，拖长声地说：“哎——呀！”我和叶尔莫莱顺着塘边往前去，可是首先，这种野禽颇为小心谨慎，不待在塘边近处，其次，即便有掉队的、缺乏经验的小水鸭被我们击中而丧命，我们的狗也没法进到那密密麻麻的芦苇荡里去叼它回来。尽管这些狗崇高无比，富有自我牺牲精神，然而它们既不会游泳，也不能潜入水底，只能枉然地让那些锋利的芦苇叶子割伤自己的宝贝鼻子。

“不行呀，”叶尔莫莱终于喃喃地说，“这样可不成，得弄一只小船来……咱们回利戈夫村去吧。”

我们便往回走。还没有走上几步，就瞧见一只癞不叽叽的猎狗从茂密的爆竹柳后面蹿了出来，在它后面又出来一个中等身材的人，穿一件破破烂烂的蓝色外衣、一件浅黄色坎肩，一条深灰色裤子，裤腿随随便便地掖在破旧的长筒靴里，脖子上缠着一条红围巾，肩上扛着一支单筒猎枪。我们的狗按习惯的，以狗类所特有的中国式礼节[1]，同它们的新朋友互嗅几下，那个新朋友显然有些胆怯，夹着尾巴，竖起耳朵，直着腿，龇着牙，全身迅速地打着转。就在这时候那陌生人来到我们跟前，彬彬有礼地向我们鞠了个躬。看他模样约有二十五六岁；他那搽了大量格瓦斯[2]的淡褐色长发一绺绺地竖在头上，一双褐色小眼睛和蔼地眨巴着，脸上扎着黑头巾，仿佛是由于牙疼，满脸泛出甜滋滋的微笑。

“请允许我做一下自我介绍，”他以柔和的略具奉承的语调开始说，“我叫弗拉季米尔，是本地的猎人……听说您来了，并知道您来到我们的水塘边上，如果您不嫌弃，我定当为您效劳。”

这个叫弗拉季米尔的猎人说起话来，酷像扮演初恋情侣的地方青年演员。我同意了他的提议，还没有到达利戈夫村之前，就摸清了他的身世阅历。他是个已赎了身的家仆；少年时代学过音乐，后来当过侍仆，认得字；可以看得出，他读过一些杂七杂八的书，就像俄国的众多百姓一样，至今仍然身无分文，又无固定职业，几乎连吃饭也成问题。他的谈吐非常文雅，显然有些自我卖弄。他可能还是个极善于向女人献殷勤的汉子，在这方面他定会成功的，因为俄国的姑娘们很喜欢能说会道的男人。还有，从他话里我听出来，他时常上邻近地主家拜访，有时进城做客，玩普列费兰斯牌，同京城里的一些人也有交往。他对笑很拿手，能笑出千姿百态来；当他倾听别人谈话时，他嘴角露出的谦恭而含蓄的微笑，对于他则特别合适。他很留神倾听你的谈话，会完全赞同你的高见，可又不失自尊，似乎要让你明白，如有机会，他会向你表明自己的一家之见的。叶尔莫莱是个没多大教养的老粗，根本不懂什么“礼貌”，就随便对他称起“你”来了。不妨看一看，弗拉季米尔对他称“您”的时候，带的是什么样的嘲笑神情。

“您为什么包着一块头巾？”我问他，“是牙疼吗？”

“不是的，”他回答说，“这是因不慎而造成的不幸后果。我有一位朋友，是个好人，但对打猎一窍不通，这倒是常有的事。有一天他对我说：‘亲爱的朋友，带我去打猎吧，我挺想体会一下打猎的乐趣。’我当然不愿拒绝这位朋友。我给他搞来一支枪，就带他去了。我们打猎打了好一阵子以后，就想歇一会儿。我在树下坐下来；他没有坐下歇歇，就练习起操枪动作，并且把枪对着我瞄准。我请他停下来，可是由于缺乏经验，没有听我的。他一放枪，我的下巴颏和右手的食指就被报销了。”

我们来到了利戈夫村。弗拉季米尔和叶尔莫莱俩都认为，在这里没有只小船是打不了猎的。

“苏乔克有一只小平底船[3]，”弗拉季米尔说，“可我不知道他把它藏到哪儿啦。得跑去找他。”

“去找谁？”我问。

“这儿有一个人，绰号叫苏乔克[4]的。”

弗拉季米尔同叶尔莫莱一起前去找苏乔克。我对他们说，我在教堂附近等他们。我在墓地上参观一座座坟墓，偶然发现一个变黑了的四方形墓饰，其上刻有如下的文字，一面是法文：“Ci-gît Theophile Henri, vicomte de Blangy”[5]；另一面是：“此墓石下安葬的是法国臣民勃朗奇子爵的遗体，生于一七三七年，死于一七九九年，享年六十二岁”；第三面是：“愿逝者安息”；后第四面题着的是：

一位法国侨民长眠于此；
他出身高贵，才华出众。
他痛悼妻室家小的惨死，
离开受强暴践踏的故土，
远来到俄罗斯这个国度，
晚年备受热情接待和庇护；
教育子女，侍奉父母……
苍天让他在此永享冥福。

叶尔莫莱、弗拉季米尔同那个有怪绰号“苏乔克”的人来了，打断了我的沉思。

苏乔克光着脚丫，衣衫褴褛，蓬头乱发，外表像个丢了饭碗的家仆，年纪六十左右。

“你有船吗？”我问。

“船倒有一只，”他用疲惫而微弱的声音回答说，“只是太破了。”

“怎么回事？”

“船缝脱胶了；木楔子也从窟窿眼里掉出来了。”

“有什么大不了！”叶尔莫莱接着说，“可以塞些麻屑嘛。”

“那当然可以。”苏乔克表示同意说。

“你是干什么的？”

“替老爷家打鱼的。”

“你这打鱼的怎么搞的，你的船怎么这样破呢？”

“这条河里没有鱼好打啦。”

“鱼不喜欢沼泽上的褐色水皮。”我的猎伴严肃地说。

“那好，”我对叶尔莫莱说，“你就去搞些麻屑来，把船缝塞一塞，快一点。”

叶尔莫莱去了。

“照这样，咱们可能会沉到水底去？”我对弗拉季米尔说。

“不会吧，”他回答说，“不管怎样，可以断定水塘不很深。”

“是呀，水塘不深，”苏乔克说，他说话有点怪，像没有睡醒似的，“塘底是水藻和草，整个水塘都长着草呢。不过，也有深坑[6]。”

“可是，如果草长得太多的话。”弗拉季米尔说，“船也没法划动了。”

“这种平底船哪里是划的呢？要用篙子撑。我跟你们一块去吧，我那儿有篙子，不然用锹也行。”

“锹不好使，在有些地方可能还够不到底。”弗拉季米尔说。

“那倒真的，不大好使。”

我坐在一个墓石上等候叶尔莫莱。弗拉季米尔为了礼貌，向旁边走了几步，也坐下了。苏乔克仍然在原地站着，低着头，照老习惯把两手反剪在背后。

“请说说，”我开口说，“你在这儿当渔夫已很久了吗？”

“六年多了。”他身子颤了一下，回答说。

“早先你是干什么的呢？”

“早先当马车夫。”

“是谁没有让你继续当马车夫的？”

“新的女东家。”

“哪一个女东家？”

“就是买我们来的那一个。您不认得的，她叫阿列娜·季莫费夫娜，胖乎乎的……不很年轻了。”

“她为什么要让你去打鱼呢？”

“天知道她。她从自己的领地唐波夫来到我们这里，吩咐把所有的家仆都召集到一起，然后出来和我们见面。我们先是去吻她的手，她没什么表示，没有生气……后来就开始挨个地查问我们：干什么的，分担什么差使？轮到我了，她问：‘你是干什么的？’我说：‘马车夫。’‘马车夫？你算什么马车夫，瞧瞧你自己吧，你算什么马车夫呀？你不配当马车夫，给我去打鱼吧，把胡子剃了。我每次到这边来，你得给我供鱼吃，听见没有？……’——打那以后，我就算是渔夫了。她还说：‘要细心，要把我的鱼塘搞得好好的……’可是怎么把鱼塘搞得好好的呢？”

“你们以前是谁家的呢？”

“是谢尔盖·谢尔盖伊奇·彼赫捷列夫家的。我们是被当作遗产由他接管过来的。不过他掌管我们的时间不很长，总共六年。我是在他手下当马车夫的……但不是在城里——在城里他另有马车夫，我是在乡下的。”

“你从年轻时候起就一直当马车夫？”

“哪里是一直当马车夫呀！我是到了谢尔盖·谢尔盖伊奇手下才当的马车夫，更早的时候是当厨子，但也不是在城里当厨子，是在乡下干的。”

“那你是在谁家当的厨子？”

“是在以前的东家阿法纳西·涅费德奇家，也就是谢尔盖·谢尔盖伊奇的伯父家。利戈夫村就是阿法纳西·涅费德奇他买下的，谢尔盖·谢尔盖伊奇继承了这个田庄。”

“是从谁手里买下的？”

“从塔季雅娜·瓦西利耶夫娜手里。”

“哪一个塔季雅娜·瓦西利耶夫娜？”

“就是前年去世的那一个，在波尔霍夫附近……不对，是在卡拉切夫附近，她是个老处女……没有嫁过人。您不认识吧？我们是从她爹瓦西利·谢梅内奇手里转到她手下的。她掌管我们可久啦……有二十来年。”

“怎么，你在她家也是当厨子？”

“起先就是当厨子，后来又当咖啡工。”

“当什么？”

“当咖啡工。”

“这是哪门子差使呀？”

“我也不清楚，老爷。我在餐室里干活，管我叫安东，而不叫库兹马。这是女东家吩咐的。”

“你原来的名字叫库兹马吗？”

“叫库兹马。”

“那你一直只当咖啡工吗？”

“不是的，不是单干一样……也当戏子呢。”

“真的？”

“当然真的……我演过戏。我们女东家在家里办了个戏园子。”

“那你演过什么角色呢？”

“您指的什么呀？”

“你在戏台上干的什么呀？”

“您不知道吗？他们拉了我去，把我打扮一番；我被打扮好后就登台，或是站，或是坐，都得听安排。他们教我说啥，我就说啥。有一次我扮演个瞎子……他们在我两边眼皮下各搁一粒豌豆……可不是！”

“那你后来又干什么了呢？”

“后来我又去当厨子。”

“为什么把你降为厨子呢？”

“因为我的兄弟逃跑了。”

“哦，那你在第一位女主人的父亲那里干什么呢？”

“各种各样差使都干过：开头当小厮，当马车夫，当花匠，后来又让我管猎狗。”

“管猎狗？……你骑着马管带猎狗？”

“是骑着马管带猎狗，曾经摔个半死：人仰马翻，马也受伤了。我们那老东家可严厉啦；下令揍了我一顿，就打发我到莫斯科一个鞋匠那里学手艺。”

“怎么还去学手艺？难道你管猎犬那时候还是个孩子？”

“论岁数嘛，当时我已经二十出头了。”

“怎么二十多了还去当学徒呢？”

“大概没什么吧，既然是东家吩咐，也就可以嘛。幸好，他很快就死了，他们又让我回乡下来。”

“那么你的煮饭烧菜手艺是什么时候学的呢？”

苏乔克稍稍抬起那又瘦又黄的脸，笑了笑。

“这还用得着学吗？……连老娘儿们都会煮饭烧菜嘛！”

“哦，”我说，“你这辈子，库兹马，见识真不少呀！既然你们这儿没什么鱼，那你现在当渔夫干些什么呢？”

“我嘛，老爷，没什么可怨的，让我当个渔夫，就得感谢上帝了。这里还有一个像我这样的老家伙，叫安德烈·普佩里，女东家派他在造纸厂的汲水房干活。她说，白吃饭是罪过。……普佩里还指望她发慈悲呢：他有个堂侄在女东家的事务所里当办事员；那堂侄答应替他向女东家求个情。求啥情呀……我还亲眼看见普佩里向他堂侄下跪叩头呢。”

“你有家眷吗？结过婚吗？”

“没有，老爷，没有。已去世的塔季雅娜·瓦西利耶夫娜——祝她进天堂！——是不许任何下人结婚的。说啥也不许！她常说：‘我不就是这样单身过的嘛，干吗要结婚呢？瞎胡闹！’”

“那你现在靠什么过日子呀？拿工钱吗？”

“啥工钱呀，老爷……有口饭吃，就谢天谢地了！我很知足。愿上帝保佑我们女东家长命百岁！”

叶尔莫莱回来了。

“船修好了，”他严肃地说，“拿篙子去吧——你！……”

苏乔克就跑去拿篙子了。在我跟这个可怜的老头交谈的时候，猎人弗拉季米尔不时地带着鄙夷的微笑瞧瞧他。

“这人是个傻瓜蛋，”当苏乔克走开之后，他说，“是一个没半点教养的人，一个泥腿子，如此而已。他连家仆也称不上……尽是瞎吹……他哪里当得了戏子，您想想看！您跟他聊天白劳神！”

过了一刻钟，我们已经坐在苏乔克的平底船上了。（我们把狗留在一个小屋里交马车夫叶古季尔照看。）我们感到不大对劲，可我们这些猎人是不好挑剔的。苏乔克站在平头的船尾用篙子“撑”船；我和弗拉季米尔坐在船的横档上；叶尔莫莱坐在前边船头上。尽管船缝已用麻屑塞好，水依然很快在我们脚下渗上来了。还好，没有一丝风，水塘仿佛睡着一般。

我们的船走得相当之慢。老头费劲地从黏黏的水底烂泥里拔出长篙来，篙子上缠满了一条条绿色的水藻；睡莲的密丛丛的圆叶子也阻碍着我们船的前进。我们终于到了芦苇荡边，这一下可不得了。野鸭由于我们突然光临它们的领地而大为惊慌，叫着喊着地从水塘里腾空而起，枪声也追着它们砰砰地响起，瞧着这些短尾巴的飞禽在空中翻着筋斗，扑通扑通地重重掉到水里，那真教人开心。我们当然无法把射下的鸭子全都弄到手，因为伤轻的已钻到水里去了；有些已被打死的掉进密匝匝的芦苇荡里，即使叶尔莫莱那双山猫般的眼睛也找不到它们；虽然如此，快到中午时候我们的小船已经装满野鸭了。

让叶尔莫莱大为称心的是，弗拉季米尔的枪法极不高明，他每次射击落空之后，就装出一副惊讶的样子，检查检查枪，吹一吹，表示枪不好使，最后向我们解释他之所以没射中的原因。叶尔莫莱像往常一样，身手不凡，弹无虚发；我嘛，枪法依旧没长进。苏乔克以从年轻时就侍候老爷的人的那种眼光瞧着我们，不时地喊道：“那边，那边还有一只鸭子！”他常常在背上搔痒痒——不是用手，而是靠晃动肩胛骨去搔。天气棒极了：我们的头上高高地、徐徐地移动着一团团白云，明晰地倒映在水中；周围响着芦苇的沙沙声；太阳照耀下的水塘处处像钢铁似的闪着亮。我们已准备返回村子，霎时间发生了一件大煞风景的事。

我们早就发现河水一直慢慢地渗进我们的船里。我们让弗拉季米尔负责用水瓢往外舀水，那水瓢还是我有先见之明的猎伴从一个在打瞌睡的村妇那里偷来以备不时之需的。当弗拉季米尔没有忘记自己的职责时，情况还算不错。可是到了打猎快结束时，那些野鸭仿佛是向我们表示告别似的一群群地飞了起来，使我们几乎来不及上弹药。我们正在紧张地射击的时候，没有顾得小船渗水的情况——突然间，由于叶尔莫莱猛的一扑（他竭力想抓住一只被打死的鸭子，全身压向船的一侧），我们的这只破船便随之倾侧，灌进了很多的水，于是也堂而皇之地向塘底下沉，幸亏船不是处在深水的地方。我们惊喊了起来，可是为时已晚：我们已经处在齐脖子的水里了，满船的死鸭子漂浮在我们的周围。如今我一想起我的这几位猎伴当时吓得发白的脸色（当时我大概也不会是容光焕发的），不能不感到好笑；不过在那个时刻，说实话，我是想不到发笑的。我们每个人都把枪举在头上，苏乔克大概因模仿主人惯了，也把篙子高高举起。叶尔莫莱第一个打破了沉默。

“呸，糟透了！”他往水里唾了一口，嘟哝着说，“真想不到有这样事！都是你的错，老鬼！”他朝苏乔克气愤愤地说，“你这只是什么船呀？”

“全怪我。”老头喃喃地说。

“你倒好，”我的猎伴掉过头向弗拉季米尔说，“你管什么来着？为什么不舀水？你，你，你……”

弗拉季米尔已顾不上回驳了：他冷得像树叶似的颤抖着，上下牙直磕碰着，毫无意义地微笑着，他的伶牙俐齿，他的文雅的礼貌和自尊感不知哪儿去了！

那该死的小船在我们脚下微微晃动着……在小船下沉的那一小会儿，我们感到河水异常之冷，但很快就习惯了。最初的恐惧过去之后，我环顾了一下，离我们十来步远的周围全是芦苇；远处，从芦苇上方，可看到塘岸。“坏啦！”我心想。

“咱们怎么办？”我问叶尔莫莱。

“看一看再说：总不能在这儿过夜吧。”他回答说。“喏，你把这只枪拿着。”他对弗拉季米尔说。

弗拉季米尔没有说三道四地服从了。

“我去探一探浅水的地方。”叶尔莫莱颇有信心地说，仿佛每个水塘里必有可以蹚水过去的浅处——他拿过苏乔克的篙子，小心地探着塘底，向岸边进发。

“你会游泳吗？”我问他。

“不，不会。”他的声音从芦苇的后边传来。

“哦，那会淹死的。”苏乔克淡然地说，他开先不是怕危险，而是怕我们怨怒，这会儿已全然定下心来了，只是有时大声喘气，似乎不觉得有任何必要去改变自己的处境。

“定会白白地去送死。”弗拉季米尔抱怨似的说。

过去一个小时多了，叶尔莫莱还没有回来。这一个小时我们觉得长极了；开头我们跟他频频地相互呼应；后来他对我们的呼喊回应得渐渐少了，最后声息全无了。村子里响起晚祷的钟声。我们也不相互交谈，甚至尽量互不相视。野鸭在我们上空来回飞翔；有一些想停歇在我们的近处，可又猛地腾飞起来，叫叫嚷嚷地飞走了。我们的身体开始发僵了。苏乔克眨巴着眼睛，似乎想要睡觉。

叶尔莫莱终于回来了，我们高兴得无法形容。

“喂，怎么样呀？”

“我到了岸上了；路探到了……咱们动身吧。”

我们本想立即就动身，然而他却先从没在水中的口袋里掏出绳子，把一些死鸭子的腿一一系上，用牙齿咬住绳子的两端，然后才缓缓地向前走去；弗拉季米尔跟在他后面，我跟在弗拉季米尔后面，苏乔克走在最后面。离岸边约两百来步了，叶尔莫莱大胆地、不停地走着（他已摸熟了这条道），只是有时喊一声：“靠左边点，右边有坑！”或者喊：“靠右边点，靠左会掉下去的……”有时水深没脖，可怜的苏乔克比我们三人个矮，有两次呛了水，直吐水沫。叶尔莫莱朝他严厉地喊：“喏，喏，喏！”苏乔克竭力往上蹿，乱迈双脚，一蹦一跳地终于踩到较浅的地方，但即使在最危急的关头他也不敢抓住我外衣的衣襟。我们终于爬上岸了，可是已筋疲力尽，一身污泥，里外湿透。

大约过了两小时，我们已尽可能把衣服晾干，并一起坐在一间宽敞的干草棚里，准备用晚餐。马车夫叶古季尔是一个动作特别慢而笨的人，是个既审慎而又迷糊的人，他站在大门边，诚心诚意地请苏乔克吸烟。（我发现俄国的马车夫能很快交成朋友。）苏乔克猛吸一阵，以至感到恶心：他又吐痰又咳嗽，看样子相当满足。弗拉季米尔显得懒洋洋的，歪着小脑袋，不大言语。叶尔莫莱擦着我们的枪。那些狗将尾巴摇得更快了，急等着麦粥喝；马在棚檐下又跺脚又嘶鸣……太阳就要下山了；它的余晖射向四处，形成一条条深红色的带子；金黄色的云彩越来越细地在天空上扩散开来，宛如梳洗过的羊毛……村子里响起了阵阵的歌声。

[1]当时的俄国人认为中国人的礼节复杂而奇特，故有此比喻。

[2]本是一种清凉饮料，但俄国的农人和仆人常用它做发油。

[3]指由一些用旧船板钉成的平底船。——作者原注

[4]意为小树枝。

[5]法文：勃朗奇子爵泰奥菲尔·安里安葬于此。——原注

[6]指塘底或河底的深陷处。——作者原注

美丽的梅恰河畔的卡西扬

在一个多云的夏日里我坐着一辆颠簸的小马车打猎归来，那种闷热天气（大家知道，这样的日头有时热得比大晴天更够人受，尤其在没有风的时候）使我沮丧极了。我打着盹，身下颠得东摇西晃，郁闷地耐着性子，听任那燥裂得嘎嘎直响的车轮下被辗得坎坎坷坷的大路上不断扬起的细白灰尘来侵蚀我的全身——蓦地里我的车夫神色变得异常不安，动作慌张，这引起了我的注意，片刻之前，他本来比我还困得厉害呢。他拽了拽缰绳，在驾驶座上手忙脚乱起来，并吆喝起马儿，不时地朝旁边某处瞧望。我四面环顾了一下。我们这车子正走在宽阔的耕作过的平川上，一些也耕作过的不大高的山冈呈现着平缓的慢坡，波浪形地伸延到这儿；从这儿放眼望去，周围四五俄里的旷野可尽收眼底。远处有一片片不大的桦树林，唯有它们圆圆的锯齿状树梢打破了几乎笔直的地平线。一条条小路在田野上向四处延伸，有的伸到低洼处就不见了，有的绕到小丘上，其中的一条在我们前边约五百步远的地方和我们所走的大路相交，我看见有一队列正走在那条小路上。我的车夫所瞧的就是那个队列。

这是出殡的行列。一辆套着一匹马的马车在缓缓前进，车上坐着一位神甫；一个教堂执事坐在他身旁驾着车，跟在车子后面的是四个没戴帽子的汉子，抬着一具罩着白布的棺材；有两个婆娘跟在棺材后边。其中一个婆娘的尖细的悲哭声突然飞进我的耳朵；我细细倾听：她在一边哭一边诉苦。在空荡荡的田野上到处响着这忽高忽低、单调而悲痛的声音。车夫催赶着马儿，他想赶在那个送葬行列的前头。在半道上遇到死人可是个不祥之兆呀。他果然在死人还没有到达大路之前就在大路上飞奔前去了；可是我们还没有走出百来步，我们的马车却猛然一震，车身倾斜了，差点翻了车。车夫勒住了正跑得起劲的马，挥了下手，啐了一口。

“怎么回事？”我问。

我的车夫没有吭声，慢悠悠地爬下了车。

“到底怎么啦？”

“车轴断了……干裂了。”他沉着脸回答说，突然气急败坏地整了整拉梢马身上的皮套子，致使那马歪斜了几下，可是那马挺住了，打了声响鼻，抖了抖身子，若无其事地用牙齿搔起前脚的小腿来。

我走下车，在路上站了一会儿，茫茫然感到很不愉快，不知如何是好。右边的车轮几乎全歪倒在车子底下了，似乎怀着说不出的绝望，那车毂朝上仰着。

“这一下怎么办？”我终于问。

“就怪那些人！”我的车夫说，用鞭子指了指送葬的行列，它已拐上大路，正向我们走近，“我一向就忌讳这个，”他继续说，“这兆头准着呢——遇到死人会倒霉……准定。”

他又去找那匹拉梢马的麻烦。那匹马看到他情绪不佳，态度严厉，就决心站着不动，只是偶尔谦卑地甩甩尾巴。我前前后后来回踱了一会儿，又在车轮边站住了。

这时候死人已经赶上了我们。这个悲哀的行列缓缓地从大路拐到草地上，从我们旁边绕了过去。我和车夫脱下帽，向神甫鞠个躬，跟抬棺材的人对望了一眼。他们费劲地走着；他们宽阔的胸膛高高地鼓起。跟在棺材后边的两个婆娘中有一个已经相当老了，脸色苍白；她那发呆的因悲痛而扭曲了的脸仍保持着严肃庄重的神情。她默默地走着。偶尔抬起一只干瘦的手去擦擦那薄薄的瘪进去的嘴唇。另一个婆娘是一个二十五六岁的年轻女人，两眼发红，流着泪水，整张脸都哭肿了。她从我们旁边经过时，停止了哭诉，用袖子掩着面……当死人从我们旁边过去，再回到大路上时，又响起了她那悲悲切切的、令人肠断的哀号。我的车夫默默地目送那有节奏地晃动着的棺材过去后，向我转过头来。

“这是为木匠马尔滕出殡，”他说，“就是里亚博沃的那个。”

“你怎么知道的呢？”

“我一看到那两个婆娘就知道了。那个老的是他娘，年轻的是他老婆。”

“他是病死的吗？”

“是的……得了热病……前天管家派人去请大夫，可是大夫不在家……这木匠是个好人哪；他有点好喝酒，可他是个挺棒的木匠。瞧那婆娘哭得多么伤心……话说回来，大家都知道婆娘的眼泪不值钱。婆娘的眼泪就像水……可不。”

他弯下身，从拉梢马的缰绳下面钻过去，双手抓住马轭。

“可是，”我说，“咱们怎么办？”

我的车夫先是以膝盖顶住辕马的肩部，晃了两下马轭，整了整辕鞍，然后又从拉梢马的缰绳下面钻出来，顺手推一下马嘴，走到车轮旁。他站在那里，一边细细瞧着车轮，一边慢吞吞地从怀里掏出扁形的鼻烟盒，慢吞吞地揪开小系带，打开鼻烟盒，慢吞吞地把两根粗大的手指探进鼻烟盒（两根手指勉强伸得进去），把烟丝揉了又揉，先歪起鼻子，便一下一下地闻起鼻烟来，每闻一下，都咝咝了一会儿，还难受地眯缝着、眨巴着噙泪的眼睛，陷入深深的沉思。

“喂，怎么样呀？”我终于问。

车夫把鼻烟盒小心地塞进口袋，他没有用手，而只是动了动脑袋，让帽子扣到眉毛上，心事重重地爬上驾驶座。

“你去哪儿呀？”我不无惊讶地问他。

“请上来坐好吧。”他平静地回答，并拿起缰绳。

“咱们这车还能走吗？”

“还能走。”

“那车轴……”

“请上来坐好吧。”

“可是车轴断了呀……”

“车轴断是断了；可还凑合到得了移民村……也就是得慢慢地走。走过前面的林子，再往右拐，那边有个移民村，叫尤金村。”

“你看，咱们这车子到得了吗？”

我的车夫不再回答我的问话了。

“我还是下来走好。”我说。

“那随您……”

他挥了一下鞭子。几匹马就跑动了。

我们的车子居然勉强走到了移民村，虽然右边前轮差点儿掉下来，并且转动得非常之怪。在一个小山丘上它几乎要脱开了；可是我的车夫恶声恶气地吆喝起来，车子终于顺当地跑下了小山丘。

尤金移民村不过有六座矮小的茅屋而已。这些茅屋已经歪歪斜斜了，虽然盖起来大概没多久，因为有几家院子还没有圈上篱笆。我们进了村后，竟没有遇上一个人；甚至连鸡犬也难得见到；仅有一条短尾巴的黑狗一看见我们便急忙地从一个干透了的洗衣槽里跳了出来（它也许是因为太口渴了，才跑到槽里去的），没叫一声便慌慌张张地从大门底下溜进去了。我走进第一座茅屋，推开穿堂的门，呼唤一声主人——没有人答应。我又唤了一声，便听到另一扇门里有一只猫在饿得直叫。我用脚踢开门：一只瘦猫在黑暗中闪着绿色的眼睛，从我身旁蹿了过去。我向房间里探头一看：半边黑洞洞的、烟气腾腾，又空空荡荡。我来到院子里，也不见人影……一只小牛犊在栏里哞哞地叫；一只跛足的灰鹅瘸着腿向一旁稍稍走开。我又走到第二家，这一家也没有人。我到了院子里……

在阳光照耀的院子正中，即阳光晒得最热的地方，躺着一个人，脸朝着地，头上蒙着衣服，我以为那是一个孩子。在离他几步远的草棚下停着一辆破旧的小马车，车旁站着一匹套有破烂马具的瘦马。阳光穿过破草檐上的条条窄缝射下来，给马的蓬松的枣红色鬃毛染上一个个明亮的斑点。在高高的椋鸟巢那里，椋鸟们一面在叽叽喳喳地聊天，一面从它们的空中楼阁里瞧着下边。我走到那个在睡觉的人身旁，唤醒他来……

他抬起头，一看到我便立即蹦了起来……“什么事，要干什么？怎么回事？”他半睡半醒地嘟哝说。

我没有马上回答他，因为他那副模样令我大为吃惊。此人原来是个五十来岁的矮子，一张又小又黑又满是皱纹的脸，尖尖的鼻子，一双褐色的小得几乎看不到的眼睛，他那小脑袋上长着浓密的黑鬈发，宛如蘑菇的伞帽。他的整个身体异常瘦弱，他那眼神是那样的古里古怪，实在难以用言语去形容。

“要干什么？”他又一次问我。

我便把事情对他说了说；他听着，那双慢慢眨巴着的眼睛始终盯着我看。

“能不能给我们搞到一根新的车轴？”最后我说，“我会乐意给钱的。”

“你们是什么人呀？是打猎的不是？”他将我从头到脚打量一番之后问道。

“是打猎的。”

“你们大概是打天上的鸟……打林子里的野兽？……你们残杀上帝的鸟，流无辜的血，不是造孽吗？”

这个奇怪的小老头说起话来慢声慢气，他那嗓音也令我惊异。从他的嗓音里非但听不出半点衰老气，而且它显得惊人的甜美，带有青春气息，近乎女性的温柔。

“我没有车轴，”他稍稍沉默之后又说，“这个车轴又不合适（他指了指他那辆小马车），你们那辆大概是大马车吧？”

“在村子里能找得到吗？”

“这里算什么村子呀！这里谁也没有车轴……再说各家都没有人在，全去干活了。请走吧。”他忽然说，又躺到了地上。

我怎么也没料到会是这样。

“听我说，老大爷，”我拍拍他的肩膀说，“劳驾，帮帮忙吧。”

“请快走吧！我累了：我刚进了趟城才回来。”他对我说了这句话后，就把衣服拉到头上。

“劳驾啦，”我继续说，“我……我给钱嘛。”

“我不要你的钱。”

“请帮帮忙嘛，老大爷……”

他抬起上半身，盘起他的两条小细腿坐着。

“那我就领你到迹地[1]去吧，商人在那边买下了我们的一片林子——真造孽，他们砍掉了林子，盖了一个办事处，真造孽。你可以在那里定做一个车轴，或者买个现成的。”

“那太好了！”我高兴地喊道，“太好了！……咱们走吧。”

“橡木做的车轴是很好的。”他继续说，还没有站起身来。

“到那迹地远吗？”

“三俄里。”

“这没什么！咱们可以坐你的车子去。”

“不行呀……”

“那咱们就走去，”我说，“走吧，老大爷！车夫在外边等着咱们呢。”

这老头不很乐意地站了起来，跟着我走到院子外边。我的车夫正在生大气：他想要饮马，可是井里的水太少了，而且水的味道不佳，可是依车夫们所说，饮水是头等大事……然而他一见到这老头，便咧嘴笑了笑，点点头，招呼道：

“嘿，卡西亚努什卡[2]！你好！”

“你好，叶罗费伊，公正的人！”卡西扬闷声闷气地回答说。

我立即把他的建议告诉了车夫；叶罗费伊表示同意，便把车子赶进院子里。在他有条不紊地忙着卸马具的时候，那老头肩靠着大门站着，不高兴地时而瞧瞧他，时而瞧瞧我。他似乎有些困惑：依我看，他不大欢迎我们的突然到来。

“连你也给迁过来啦？”叶罗费伊在卸马轭时突然问他。

“我也被迁过来了。”

“唉！”我的车夫透过牙缝说，“你知道，那木匠马尔滕……你不是认识里亚博沃的马尔滕吗？”

“认识。”

“唉，他死啦。我们刚才遇到他的棺材。”

卡西扬打了一下战。

“死啦？”他说，低下头去。

“是呀，死啦。你为什么不给他治好病呢，啊？人家都说你会治病，你是医生嘛。”

我的车夫显然是拿这老头寻开心，嘲笑他。

“怎么，这是你的车呀？”他肩膀朝马车耸了耸，接着说。

“是我的。”

“哼，车……车！”他重复了两次，抓住车的辕杆，差点把车翻个底朝天……“车！……您坐什么到迹地去呀？……我们的马套不进这个辕杆：我们的马都高高大大的，而这算个什么呀？”

“我真不知道，”卡西扬回答说，“你们坐什么去；要不就用这一匹牲口。”他叹口气补充说。

“用这一匹？”叶罗费伊接过话说，一边走到卡西扬的这匹驽马跟前，轻蔑地用右手中指戳了戳马的脖子。“瞧，”他带着指责的口吻补了一句，“它睡着了，这懒蛋！”

我要叶罗费伊快些把马套好。我很想亲自同卡西扬一起到迹地去，因为那边常常有松鸡。等到车子全套好了，我同我的狗一起凑凑合合地坐到翘得高低不平的树皮车底上，卡西扬缩成一团，也坐到前边的车杆上，脸上仍是先前那副抑郁的神情。叶罗费伊走到我跟前，带着神秘的样子低声说：

“您同他一道去，老爷，要当心。他可怪着呢，他的绰号叫跳蚤。我不清楚您怎么会了解他的……”

我本想对叶罗费伊说，直到这一会儿，我都觉得卡西扬是个顶懂道理的人，可是我的车夫立即用同样的语调接着说：

“您可得留点心眼，看他是不是带你到那里去。车轴嘛您得自个儿挑选：挑坚实一些的……喂，跳蚤，”他又大声地说，“在你们这儿能搞到点面包吃吗？”

“去找一找，会找到的。”卡西扬答道，扯了扯缰绳，我们的车子就起动了。

令我确实惊异的是，他的马跑得相当不赖。一路上卡西扬不吭一声，问他什么，他都不大乐意回答，或者断断续续地回答。我们很快就到达迹地，又找到了那里的办事处。那是一座高高的木房子，孤零零地耸立在一个不大的山沟上，那山沟被马马虎虎地围了一道堤坝，从而变成了一口池塘。我在办事处里见到两个年轻的伙计，他们的牙齿雪白雪白，眼睛甜蜜蜜的，说话也甜蜜蜜的，又很伶俐，脸上浮着甜蜜蜜的狡猾的微笑。我向他们买了一根车轴后，就回到迹地上，我以为卡西扬会留在马旁边等着我，可是他突然向我走来。

“怎么，去打鸟吗？”他说，“啊？”

“是的，如果找得着的话。”

“我跟你一道去……行吗？”

“行，行。”

我们便前去了。伐去树木的地方约有一俄里。说真的，我打量卡西扬的时间比注视自己的狗的时间要多，给他起“跳蚤”这外号是不无道理的。他那黑黑的没有遮盖的小脑瓜（不过他的头发可顶任何帽子）在灌木丛里一闪一闪。他走起路来格外敏捷，似乎老在蹦蹦跳跳，时不时地弯腰，扯些草塞在怀里，嘴里在嘟嘟哝哝，老是用他好奇而古怪的眼光打量着我和我的狗。在低矮的灌木丛里，在一些“小旮旯”里，在砍过树木的地方，常常有些灰色小鸟从一棵树到另一棵树地飞着，啁啾着，又飞上飞下。卡西扬滑稽地学着小鸟叫，和小鸟们相互呼应。一只小鹌鹑从他的脚边飞起，啾啾地叫着，他也跟着它啾啾地叫；一只云雀飞下来，在他头顶上鼓动翅膀，嘹亮地歌唱着，卡西扬也跟着它一道唱起来。跟我他一直没有说话……

天气晴好，比先前更晴好；但炎热依然如故。明朗的天空上稍稍飘动着高高的稀疏的云朵，白中带点黄，宛如晚来的春雪，有时又像卸下的白帆，平平的，长长的。它们像棉花似的蓬松柔软的花边每一会儿都在慢慢地然而很明显地变化着：这些云朵都在渐渐消融，没有投下阴影来。我和卡西扬在这迹地上逛了很久。不及一俄尺[3]高的嫩枝以光滑的细枝围着那些发黑的矮树墩；这些树墩上长满了带灰边的圆圆的海绵状木瘤，这种木瘤可以熬制成火绒；草莓向它们伸来粉红色的小须；木瘤上还长出密匝匝的蘑菇。讨厌烈日暴晒的长草不断缠绊我的双脚；树上微微发红的嫩叶闪着金属般的强烈的光，使人眼花缭乱；到处有一串串淡蓝色的野豌豆、一朵朵金黄色的毛茛花、半紫半黄的蝴蝶花，异彩纷呈；一些荒无人迹的小径上长满一丛丛红色小草，那是原来的车辙，小径旁边堆着几俄丈[4]见方的一垛垛木柴；由于风吹雨打都变黑了；它们投下了斜方形的淡淡的阴影，其他地方就没什么阴影了。轻风时吹时停，有时一下直接扑面而来，仿佛吹得起劲了，周围的一切都欢快地喧闹起来，摇晃起来，动了起来，蕨类植物柔软的顶端也在翩翩起舞——你正在为风的来临而欢喜……可是它又停下来了，一切又都不动了。唯有螽斯仿佛恼怒了，放声齐鸣着——这种不断的郁闷而枯燥的叫声真令人厌倦死了。这种叫声同正午的固执的酷热倒很匹配；这种叫声仿佛是酷热所生，仿佛是酷热把它从炽热的地里召唤出来的。

我们连一群鸟儿也没有碰上，后来就去到另外的迹地上。这儿一些新伐倒的白杨树可悲地躺在地上，压住了一些青草和小灌木；其中有些树上的叶子还是绿绿的，可它们已经死了，从一动不动的树枝上萎靡地耷拉上来，其他树的叶子已经干枯了，蜷缩了。一堆堆新鲜的黄白色木片躺在潮湿发亮的树墩旁，散发着特别的沁人心脾的带苦味的气息。在远处靠近树林的地方，斧子发出沉闷的响声，每隔一会儿，就有一棵青葱的树木好像鞠着躬、伸开两臂似的庄重而缓慢地倒下来……

老半天都没有找到任何野禽；最后，从那长满苦艾的橡树丛里飞出一只秧鸡。我放了一枪；秧鸡在空中翻了个身便栽下来了。一听到枪声，卡西扬便赶紧用手遮住眼，一动不动，直到我装好枪，捡起那只秧鸡。等我向前走了，他便到那死秧鸡落下的地方，弯下身去，瞧着那溅上几滴血的草地，摇了摇头，惶恐地瞧了我一眼……后来我听见他嘟哝说：“造孽！……唉，真造孽呀！”

炎热终于迫使我们躲进树林。我急忙跑到一个高高的榛树树丛下，树丛上边优美地舒展着一棵槭树的轻盈的树枝，那是一棵年轻而挺拔的槭树。卡西扬在一棵砍倒的白桦树粗的一端坐下来。我端详着他。树叶在高处轻轻摇曳，叶子的淡绿色阴影在他那随便用黑色上衣裹着的孱弱的身体上和他那小脸上缓缓地前后滑动。他没有抬头。他老是不吭声，使我感到挺没趣，我便仰面躺下来，欣赏起那些乱纷纷的树叶在明亮的高高的空中平静地嬉戏。在树林里席地仰卧，向上眺望，真是其乐无比呀！你会觉得，你是在观赏深不可测的海洋，觉得它辽阔地伸展在你的“下边”，树木不像是从地上耸起，倒像是大树的根往下伸，垂直地落在明净如镜的波浪中；树叶时而像绿宝石似的透亮，时而浓得成为黄绿色和墨绿色。在远一些的地方，细枝末梢上有一单片叶子纹丝不动地停在透明的蓝空里，旁边的另一片叶子在晃动着，好像池中的鱼儿在戏耍，似乎是自己在动，而不是风吹动的。一团团白云像一座座水下仙岛，悄悄地浮来，又悄悄地离去。忽然，这整片海洋，这光辉的天空，这些洒满阳光的树枝和树叶，全都流动起来，闪烁着流动的光，响起清新的、颤悠悠的沙沙声，宛如突然而来的波浪的无休止的细微拍溅声。你静静待着，瞧着，心中变得多么欢畅、宁静、甜美，这是笔墨所无法形容的。你瞧，那深邃清澈的蓝空会使你的嘴唇泛上跟它一样纯洁无瑕的微笑，一些幸福的回忆，就像天空中的云，也好像与那些云一道，缓缓地飘过你的心头。你老觉得你的目光越投越远，它带着你奔向那平静的、明亮的无底的深处，使你无法脱开这种高处，这种深处……

“老爷，老爷呀！”卡西扬冷不防地用他那洪亮的嗓音说话了。

我惊异地抬起点身来；在这之前，他对我的问话往往爱答不理，可这一下他却自动开口了。

“你有什么事？”我问。

“你为什么射死鸟儿呢？”他直盯着我的脸说。

“什么为什么呀？……秧鸡是种野味，可以吃嘛。”

“你可不是为了吃而打死它的，老爷，你才不去吃它呢！你打死它为的是取乐。”

“你自己可能也吃鹅、吃鸡什么的吧？”

“那些禽类是上帝规定给人吃的，而秧鸡是树林里的自由的鸟儿。也不光光是秧鸡，还有许许多多的生物：所有树林里的、田野里和河里的、沼地里和草地上的、高处的和低处的——打死它们都是罪孽，要让它们在世上活到自己的寿限才是……人有自己的食物；人另有吃的和喝的东西：粮食——上帝的恩赐，和天赐的水，还有老祖宗传下来的家禽家畜。”

我惊奇地瞧了瞧卡西扬。他说起话来可流畅着呢；他没有字斟句酌，说得既平静又兴奋，既温和又严肃，有时还闭起眼睛。

“那么依你看来，捕鱼也是罪过的啰？”

“鱼的血是冷的，”他挺自信地回答说，“鱼是不会作声的生物。鱼没有恐惧，没有快乐；鱼是不会说话的东西。鱼没有感觉，鱼的血也不是活的……”他沉默一下，又接下说，“血是神圣的东西！血不能见天上的太阳，血是避光的……让血见光是大罪过，是大罪过和可怕的事……唉，是大罪过呀！”

他叹了口气，低下头来。我瞧着这位奇怪的老头，说真的，心里感到十分的惊讶。他的话不像是庄稼人说的话，普通的老百姓说不了这样的话，嘴巧的人也说不了这样的话。这种话是经过思索的，是严肃而奇怪的……我没有听说过这类的话。

“请问，卡西扬，”我直盯着他那微微泛红的脸问道，“你是干什么行业的？”

他没有立即回答我的提问。他的目光不安地转了片刻。

“我是依上帝的吩咐过日子，”他终于回答说，“说行业嘛，我没有，我什么行业也不干。我打小起就非常无知；只干一点能干的事，我干活不大行……我哪儿行呀？身体差，手也笨。不过，春天的时候我就去逮夜莺。”

“逮夜莺？……你不是说，树林里的、田野里的，其他任何地方的生物都不应该碰吗？”

“是这样，杀死它们是不应该的，死应该是自然到来的。就拿木匠马尔滕来说吧，木匠马尔滕本是活着的，可是活得不长便死了；现在他的老婆既为丈夫悲伤，也为不大点儿的孩子发愁……没有一个人，也没有一种生物能混得过死。死不会随便来，可是你也逃脱不了它；不过帮助死是不应该的。我是不会打死夜莺的，决不会的！我逮夜莺不是为了折磨它们，不是害它们的命，而是为了让人高兴，让人开心快乐。”

“你是去库尔斯克[5]逮夜莺吗？”

“库尔斯克我也去，有机会时还去得更远。在泥沼地里或树林旁过夜，独自一人在田野里，在荒僻地方过夜：那里有山鹬啾啾地啼鸣，有兔子吱吱地呼喊，有野鸭子嘎嘎地叫唤……晚上我留神地观察，早上我细细地倾听，天有点亮时就在灌木丛上撒网……有的夜莺唱得可甜美啦，也很悲伤……真的很悲伤。”

“你卖夜莺吗？”

“卖给善良的人。”

“那你还做些什么？”

“怎么做什么？”

“你干什么活呀？”

老头沉默了一会儿。

“我什么活也不干……我干活很差劲。可是我会识字。”

“你识字？”

“我会识字。这多亏上帝和一些好心人。”

“那么，你有家小吗？”

“没有，没有家小。”

“怎么的呢？……都死了吗？”

“不，就是没有：我这一辈子不走运。这全是上帝的安排，我们都是在上帝的安排下过日子的；做人应当正直——这最要紧！就是说，得让上帝中意。”

“你没有亲戚吗？”

“有……不过……就是……”

老头不大愿意说。

“请说说，”我又说起来，“我听到我的车夫问你为什么不把马尔滕的病治好，这么说你会治病？”

“你的车夫是个正直人，”卡西扬有所考虑地回答说，“可也不是没有罪过。管我叫医生……我算什么医生呢！……谁又会治病呢？一切全得听上帝的。是有一些……有一些草呀、花呀确实有些效用。比如说鬼针草吧，对人就有益处；车前草也是；说说这些草并不丢脸，这都是一些纯洁的草——是上帝赐给的。可是另外有些草就不是这样了：它们是有点用，可也是罪过，连说说它们都有罪过。要不，还得一边做祈祷……当然啰，也有这方面的祷词……谁信谁就得救。”他放低声音补充了一句。

“你没有给马尔滕什么药吗？”我问。

“我知道得晚了，”老头回答说，“有什么说的呢！人的寿命生来就有定数。木匠马尔滕是个短命的人，他在世上活不长久，就是这么回事。可不，凡是注定在世上活不长久的人，太阳就不像对旁人那样给他温暖，粮食对于他也没什么用——好像有什么在召他去……是这样的；愿他的灵魂安息吧！”

“你们被迁到这儿很久了吗？”稍沉默了一会儿之后，我问。

卡西扬震颤了一下。

“不，不很久，大概有四年吧。老东家在世那会儿，我们都是住在自己原来的地方，后来监护局要我们搬迁。我们那老东家心肠软，脾气温和，愿他进天国！当然，监护局做得也对；看来，也只好这样。”

“你们原先住在什么地方？”

“我们本住在美丽的梅恰河边。”

“那地方离这儿远吗？”

“一百来俄里吧。”

“那边好一些，是吗？”

“好一些……好一些。那边地方宽阔，河流多，那是我们的老家；这儿不开阔，又缺水……我们在这儿很孤单。在我们美丽的梅恰河边，你登上山冈，登上去一看，我的上帝呀，那是什么景致呀，啊？……有河，有草地，有森林；那儿有教堂，再过去又有草地。能看得远远的，远远的。看得多远啊……你瞧呀，瞧呀，实在美极了！而这边的土质确实好一些，是砂质黏土，庄稼人都说，这是上好的砂质黏土；我那些庄稼满处都长得好着呢。”

“喂，老大爷，你说实话，你大概很想回老家走走吧？”

“是呀，很想回去看一看。不过到处都不错。我是个没有拖家带口的人，不愿意老待在一个地方。可不是！老待在家里有什么劲？很想出去走走，出去走走，”他提高嗓门接着说，“那的确会轻松愉快些。太阳照耀着你，上帝更看清你，唱起歌也更带劲。看见有什么好的草，你看出来了，就采一些。那儿有流水，比如说，是泉水，是圣洁的水；你发现了，就喝个够。天上的鸟儿在歌唱……库尔斯克再过去就有草原，那是多好的草原啊，真让人惊奇，让人喜欢！那是多么的宽广，真是上帝的恩赐呀！人家都说，那些草原直通温暖的大海，那儿住着一只叫‘加马云’[6]的鸟儿，它的声音可甜美啦。树上的叶子无论冬天秋天都不掉落，银树上长着金苹果，人人都活得很满意，很公正……我很想到那边去走走……要说，我到过的地方也不算少了！我到过罗姆内，到过辛比尔斯克那座挺有名气的城市，也到过有不少金子做的教堂圆顶的莫斯科；到过‘乳娘奥卡河’，到过‘亲爱的茨娜河’，到过‘母亲伏尔加河’，我见过许许多多的人，许许多多善良的庄稼人，也到过一些体面的城市……所以我很想到那边去……而且……很想……也不光是我这个有罪的人……别的许多庄稼人也都穿着树皮鞋，一路乞讨着，去寻求真理……是呀！……待在家里干什么呢，啊？人间没有公道，就是这么一回事……”

后面这几句话卡西扬说得很快，几乎听不清；后来他又说了些什么，我连听也听不见，他那脸上露出古怪的表情，使我不由得想起了“疯子”这个称号。他低下头，咳嗽了一声，似乎清醒过来了。

“多好的太阳呀！”他放低声音说，“多好的恩赐呀，上帝！林子里多温暖呀！”

他耸了耸肩膀，沉默了一会儿，不在意地瞧了瞧，轻声地哼唱起来。我没法听清他曼声唱的歌曲的全部歌词，我只听清下面这两句：

我的名字叫卡西扬，
外号是“跳蚤”……

“哎！”我想，“这是他自个儿编的吧……”他突然战颤了一下，不出声了，凝望着树林的深处。我掉过头，看见了一个农家的小妞，年纪八岁左右，穿着一件无袖的蓝色外衣，头上裹着带格子的头巾，黝黑的光胳膊上挎着一只篮子。她大概怎么也没有料到会遇见我们，真所谓是撞上了我们，她一动不动地站在苍翠的榛树丛的阴凉的草地上，那双乌黑的眼睛惊慌地瞅着我们。我刚看清她，她一下就躲到树后面去了。

“安努什卡！安努什卡！过来，别怕。”老头亲切地唤她。

“我怕。”传来她尖细的声音。

“别怕，别怕，上我这儿来。”

安努什卡不声不响地离开她躲藏的地方，悄悄地绕了个圈——她那稚嫩的小脚走在浓密的草地上几乎没有一点声响——从老头近旁的树丛里走了出来。她不是八岁左右，像我起初看到她那矮小的个子所估计的那样，她已有十三四岁了。她的整个身体又小又瘦，但很匀称，很灵巧，那张漂亮的小脸酷像卡西扬的脸，虽然卡西扬的长相并不好看。同样尖尖的脸形，同样奇特的眼神，既狡猾又诚挚，带点沉思，又很敏锐，举止也相似……卡西扬扫了她一眼，她站到了他的身旁。

“怎么，采蘑菇呀？”他问。

“是的，采蘑菇。”她带着羞涩的微笑回答说。

“采到多吗？”

“挺多的。”（她迅速瞥了他一眼，又微微一笑。）

“有白的吗？”

“白的也有。”

“让我瞧瞧，让我瞧瞧……（她从胳膊上放下篮子，把遮着蘑菇的宽宽的牛蒡叶子掀开一半。）嘿！”卡西扬朝篮子弯下身，说，“多棒的蘑菇呀！安努什卡真行呀！”

“这是你女儿吗，卡西扬，是吗？”我问。（安努什卡的脸有点红了。）

“不是，是亲戚，”卡西扬装作不在意的样子说，“喂，安努什卡，你走吧，”他马上又添说一句，“好好走。小心点……”

“干吗让她走着回去呀！”我打断他的话说，“让她坐我们的车走吧……”

安努什卡的脸红得像罂粟花，她两手抓住篮子上的绳子，惶惑不安地瞧了瞧老头。

“不，她能走得了，”他仍然用满不在乎的懒洋洋的声调回答说，“这对于她没什么……她能走回去……走吧。”

安努什卡很快就走进树林去了。卡西扬目送着她，然后低下头，微微笑了笑。在这长长的微笑里，在他对安努什卡所说的几句话里，在他同她说话时的那种声调里，有一种难以言表的热烈的疼爱和亲切之情。他朝着她离去的那个方向瞧了瞧，又微微一笑，摸摸自己的脸，点几下头。

“你为什么这样急着打发她走了呢？”我问他，“我本想向她买些蘑菇呢……”

“要是您想买，您到我家里一样可以买嘛。”他回答说，这是他第一次使用“您”这称呼。

“你的这小丫头挺可爱嘛。”

“不……哪儿话……这……”他好像不大愿意地回答说，从这一会儿起他又回到先前的那种沉默中去。

我想了种种法子，试图让他重新打开话匣子，可是我明白我是白费劲的，因此我便往迹地走去了。此时炎热已稍稍消退了些；然而打猎仍不得手，或者如我们常说的，我还是不走运，只好带着一只秧鸡和一根新车轴回到村子里去。车子快进院子了，卡西扬突然向我转过身来。

“老爷，老爷呀，”他开口说，“我对不起你；是我让所有的野禽躲开了你。”

“怎么这样说呢？”

“我懂这种法术。你的狗挺聪明，是只好狗，可是它毫无办法。你以为人很了不起，不是吗？可是就说野物吧，人能拿它们怎么样呢？”

如果我对卡西扬解释，用“咒语”让野禽躲开是不可能的，那是没有用的，所以我就什么都不说了，这时候我们的车子已拐进大门里了。

安努什卡不在屋里；她已经先到家了，把一篮子蘑菇搁在屋里。叶罗费伊先是对这个新车轴横挑鼻子竖挑眼地做了一番不公道的评价之后，就把它安上了。过了一小时我们就要动身，我拿些钱给卡西扬，起先他不肯收，后来想了想，在手心里攥了一会儿，便揣进怀里了。在这一小时里，他几乎不说一句话；他仍然倚着大门站着，也不搭理我的车夫的责备，跟我告别时也极为冷淡。

我刚一回来，便发现我的叶罗费伊心情抑郁……可也是，他在村子里什么吃的也没有找到，给马饮的水又很差劲。我们出发了。他坐在驾驶座上，连后脑勺都表现出不满，他极想跟我絮叨絮叨，可是他在等我先开口发问，这时候他只是低声地发发牢骚，对马儿教训几句，有时说得挺刻薄。“村子！”他咕哝说，“还算是个村子呢！想要点格瓦斯——连格瓦斯他妈的也没有……哼，真见鬼！那水呀，简直叫人恶心！（他大声啐了一口。）黄瓜没有，格瓦斯没有——屁都没有。哼，你呀，”他朝着右边的拉梢马大声地说，“我可知道你，大滑头一个！你喜欢偷懒不是……（他抽了它一鞭。）这马现在全变狡猾了，早先这畜生多听话呀……哼，哼，你敢回头瞧！……”

“告诉我，叶罗费伊，”我开口说，“这个卡西扬是个什么样的人？”

叶罗费伊没有立即回答我，他向来是个喜欢思考和从容不迫的人；我一下就猜到了，我的问话使他非常高兴，甚为得意。

“跳蚤吗？”他拽了拽缰绳，终于说开了，“是一个怪人，简直就是个疯子，这样怪的家伙，可不是一时半会儿能找到第二个的。比如说吧，就跟咱们这匹黄褐马一样德行，很不听话……就是说，不爱干活。不用说，他哪是干活的人呀，那身干骨是很差——不过，总得……他打小就是这副德行。最初他跟着他的叔叔们拉脚——他们都是赶车的——后来他大概干腻了，就甩手不干了。他就在家里窝着，可是连家里也待不住，他就是这样不安分的人——就像个跳蚤。幸亏他遇上了好心肠的东家，没有强求他干这干那。打那时候起，他就像只没人看管的山羊，到处溜达晃游。他真是怪得出奇，鬼知道怎么这样：有时候一声不吭，像个树墩，有时候一下说起话来——天知道他会说些什么。有这样的人吗？真没有这样的。他这人真不成体统。可是唱歌倒唱得不错。唱得满像回事，很不赖，很不赖。”

“他真的会治病吗？”

“治什么病呀！……哼，他哪儿会呀！他就是这样好吹。话说回来，我的瘰疬倒是他给治好的……”他沉默了一下，又说，“他哪里会治病呀！是笨蛋一个。”

“你早认识他啦？”

“早认识了。我跟他在瑟乔夫卡村时是邻居，在美丽的梅恰河那边。”

“那么，我们在树林里遇上的那个叫安努什卡的丫头是他家里的人吗？”

叶罗费伊回头瞧了瞧我，龇出整口牙齿笑了笑。

“嘿！……是的，是他家的。她是个孤儿，没有娘，不知道谁是她的娘。咳，可能是他的亲人吧，太像他了……她就住在他家里。是个机灵的丫头，没得说；是一个好丫头，老头可心疼她啦，这丫头确实不错。说来您不一定信，他还想教自己的安努什卡识字呢。他当真会这样做的，他就是这么一种怪人嘛。他这个人可没个准儿，没个分寸的……吁——吁——吁！”我的车夫突然打住了话，勒住了马，向一旁弯过身，闻起气味来。“好像有股煳味？确实！我不喜欢这些新车轴……最好上点油……我就去弄点水吧，正好这儿有个小池塘。”

叶罗费伊从驾驶座上慢慢地爬下来，解下水桶，就去池塘里打水，回来后，他听到轮毂突然吸足了水而发出一阵吱吱声，有些高兴起来……在十来俄里的路程上，他不得不给发烫的车轴浇了六七回水。我们到家的时候，天色已经完全黑下来了。

[1]林中砍伐了树木的地方。——作者原注

[2]卡西扬的小称或昵称。

[3]相当于0.71米。

[4]一俄丈相当于2.134米。

[5]那边有优良品种的夜莺，歌喉甜美，很珍贵。

[6]传说中天堂上的鸟。

办事处

那是秋天里遇上的事。我扛着猎枪在野外已逛了好几个小时，若不是下着凄冷的蒙蒙细雨，我也许在傍晚之前也不会回到库尔斯克大路旁有我的马车等着我的那家旅店去的。那细雨从一大早就下开了，像老处女似的叨叨没完、毫不怜惜地纠缠着我，终于逼得我只好就近找一个哪怕可暂时避避雨的地方。我正在思量朝哪个方向走，我的视野里突然出现一个搭在豌豆田旁边的低矮的窝棚。我就向那窝棚走去，往棚檐下一瞧，看到了一个衰弱不堪的老头，他那模样使我一下想起了鲁滨孙在荒岛的一个洞穴里所看到的那只垂死的山羊。那老头蹲在地上，眯着昏沉沉的小眼睛，像兔子似的慌忙而又小心地（这可怜的老头牙齿全掉光了）咀嚼着又干又硬的豌豆粒，不断地让它在嘴里翻来倒去。他全神贯注地咀嚼着，以至没有发觉我的到来。

“老大爷，喂，老大爷！”我招呼说。

他停止了咀嚼，高高地扬起眉头，使劲睁开眼睛。

“什么事？”他口齿不清地说，声音沙哑。

“这一带哪儿有村子？”我问。

老头又咀嚼起来。他听不清我说的话。我更大声地又问了一遍。

“村子？……你有什么事？”

“想去避避雨。”

“什么？”

“避避雨。”

“哦！（他搔了搔自己的后脑勺。）那你呀，就这样走，”他一下说起话来，胡乱地摆动着手，“这样吧……你就顺着林子边走，走过去以后，那边就有一条路；你别走那条路，要一直往右走，一直往右，一直往右……那边有个阿纳涅沃村。要不然就到西托夫卡村。”

我好不容易才听明白老头的话。他那胡子妨碍他说话，他那舌头也不大听使唤。

“你是哪儿的人？”我问他。

“什么？”

“是哪儿人呀，你？”

“阿纳涅沃村的。”

“你在这儿干什么呀？”

“什么？”

“你干什么呀，在这儿？”

“在这儿看守。”

“你看守什么呀？”

“豌豆。”

我忍不住哈哈笑了。

“得了吧，你多少岁数啦？”

“天知道呢。”

“你眼力大概不好吧？”

“不好。常常什么也听不见。”

“请问，那怎么让你当看守呢？”

“这上头的人才知道。”

“上头的人！”我一边想着，不无怜悯地瞧了瞧可怜的老头。他摸了摸，从怀里掏出一块硬邦邦的干面包，像小孩似的啃了起来，使劲缩起那本来已塌陷的腮帮子。

我便朝着林子那方向走去，以后向右拐，照那老头的指点，一直走，一直走，终于来到了一个大村子。村里有一座新式的，也就是带圆柱的石结构教堂，还有一座宽敞的地主住宅，也带有圆柱。透过密麻麻的雨丝，大老远便可看到一所盖着木板屋顶、耸着两个烟囱的房子，它比旁的房子高，想必是村长的住屋，我就向那个房子走去，希望他家里有茶炊、茶、糖和不很酸的鲜奶油。我的狗哆嗦了一下，陪我登上了台阶，进入穿堂，推开门一看，里面不是摆着一般农家的陈设，而是摆有几张堆着文书的桌子、两个红色柜子、溅满墨水的墨水瓶、笨重的锡制吸水沙盒、长长的羽毛笔，等等。其中一张桌子旁坐着一个二十来岁的小伙子，他长着一张浮肿的病态的脸，一双小眼睛，额门肥胖，鬓毛浓密。他整齐地穿着一件灰色土布外套，衣领和衣襟上油光光的。

“您有什么事？”他一下翘起头问我，那样子就像一匹马被人突然抓起头来似的。

“这儿是管家的住处……或是……”

“这儿是主人的总办事处，”他打断我的话说，“我是在这儿值班……难道您没有看见牌子吗？挂着牌子呢。”

“这儿有可烘衣服的地方吗？村子里哪家有茶炊？”

“怎么会没有茶炊呢，”穿灰外套的小伙子神气地回答说，“您到季莫费神甫那儿去，或者到下房那边去，要不去找纳扎尔·塔拉瑟奇，找看家禽的阿杉拉费娜也行。”

“你这是在跟谁说话呢，你这笨蛋？你不让人睡怎么的，笨蛋！”有人在隔壁房间里说话了。

“进来了一位先生，问哪儿可以烘烘衣服？”

“什么样的先生？”

“我不认识。他带着狗和猎枪。”

隔壁房间里床咯吱地响了。门开了，进来一个五十来岁的人，矮矮胖胖的，脖子粗得像公牛，眼睛鼓鼓的，腮帮滚圆，满脸油光。

“您有何贵干？”他问我。

“想烘一下衣服。”

“这儿不是烘衣服的地方。”

“我不知道这儿是办事处；不过，我会付钱的……”

“兴许这儿也可以吧，”这胖子回答说，“那么请上这边来。（他带我去到另一房间，但不是他刚才从那儿出来的那一间。）您就在这儿，好不好？”

“好的……给点茶和奶油行吗？”

“行，马上给送来。您先把衣服脱了，休息一下，茶过一会儿就得。”

“这是谁的田庄呀？”

“女主人叶列娜·尼古拉耶夫娜·洛斯尼亚科娃的。”

他出去了。我打量了一下四周：我在的这房间与办事室之间隔有一道板壁，挨板壁摆着一张很大的皮面沙发；还有两张也是皮面的椅子，椅子背高高的，摆在朝马路的唯一的窗子两旁。在糊有带粉红花纹的绿壁纸的墙上挂着三大幅油画。其中一幅画的是一条戴蓝脖套的猎狗，并题有几个字——“这是我的欢乐”；在狗的脚边画有一条河，河的对岸有一棵松树，树下蹲着一只大得过分的兔子，竖着一只耳朵。另一幅画上画着两个老头在吃西瓜；西瓜后面远处显出一个希腊式柱廊，上题“娱乐宫”几个字。第三幅画上画有一个躺着的半裸体女人，呈透视缩狭形，有一对红红的膝盖和肥肥的脚后跟。我的狗赶紧拼死劲钻到沙发底下，显然在那里吸了不少灰尘，所以接连大打喷嚏。我走到窗前。看见从地主住宅到办事处的路上斜铺着木板：这种预防措施是顶管用的，因为我们这一带地方都是黑土壤，加上雨水连绵，到处泥泞不堪。这座背向马路的地主宅院附近的情况，也和一般地主宅院周围的情况差不多：穿着褪色花布衫的丫头们在跑前跑后；仆人们在泥泞地里费劲地行走，有时停下步，心思重重地搔搔脊背；甲长的一匹拴着的马懒洋洋地摇着尾巴，高高地抬头去啃栅栏；母鸡咕咕地叫着；患痨病似的火鸡不停地相互呼喊着。有一座大概像澡堂的黑乎乎的破房子，台阶上坐着一个体格坚实的小伙子，手里拿着吉他，颇有激情地唱着一首有名的情歌：

唉，我就要离开这美丽的地方，
前往荒僻的遥远他乡……

胖子走进我在的这间屋子。

“给您送茶来了。”他带着愉快的微笑对我说。

穿灰外套的小伙子，即那个办事室值班员，把茶炊、茶壶、垫着破茶碟的茶杯、一小罐鲜奶油和一串硬如石头的波尔霍夫面包圈摆在一张旧的牌桌上。胖子便走出去了。

“这是什么人，”我问值班的小伙子，“是管家吗？”

“不是，他原先是主任出纳，现在升为办事处主任。”

“难道你们没有管家吗？”

“没有。有总管，米海拉·维库洛夫，可没有管家。”

“那么有主管人吗？”

“当然有的：一个德国人，卡洛·卡雷奇·林达曼多尔；不过他不做主。”

“那你们这里谁做主呢？”

“女主人自己。”

“原来是这样！……那么你们办事处里的人多吗？”

小伙子想了一下。

“有六个人。”

“有些什么人呀？”

“有这样一些人：首先是瓦西里·尼古拉耶维奇，主任出纳；还有彼得是办事员，彼得的兄弟伊万也是办事员，另外一个伊万也是办事员；科斯肯金·纳尔基佐夫也是办事员，还有我——还没有全都算上。”

“你们女主人家里仆人大概很多吧？”

“不，不算很多……”

“到底有多少呢？”

“总共大约一百五十来个吧。”

我们两人都沉默了一会儿。

“你的字写得很好，是吗？”我又开口问。

小伙子咧开嘴笑了笑，点点头，到办事室里拿来一张写满了字的纸。

“这就是我写的。”他低声说，不停地微笑着。

我看到一张淡灰色的四开纸上用漂亮而粗大的笔迹写着如下的一些字：

命　令

阿纳尼耶夫地主庄园总办事处
命令总管米海拉·维库洛夫（第209号）

接到此令后务必从速查明，何人于昨夜醉酒并唱下流小曲，闯入英国式花园惊扰法籍家庭教师恩热尼夫人？守夜人职责何在？守夜者系何人，竟让出现如此不规之事？命你对上述情况详加侦查，并尽快呈报本处。

办事处主任尼古拉·赫沃斯托夫

命令上盖着一个大印章，印上写的是：“阿纳尼耶夫村地主庄园总办事处印”。下方还有一个批示：“切实执行。叶列娜·洛斯尼亚科娃。”

“这是女主人亲笔批的吗？”我问。

“当然是的，她总是亲笔批的。否则命令不能生效。”

“怎么，这命令是由你们交给总管吗？”

“不，他自己会来念的，就是说，由旁人念给他听，因为他不识字。（值班的小伙子又沉默了一会儿。）您认为怎么样，”他微笑着又说，“写得不错吗？”

“挺好。”

“不过不是我起的稿。科斯肯金对这个很拿手。”

“怎么？……你们写命令都要先起稿？”

“怎么能不起稿呢？直接写是写不整洁的。”

“你拿多少钱薪水？”我问。

“三十五卢布，外加五卢布鞋补。”

“你满意吗？”

“当然满意，我们这个办事处不是任何人都进得了的。说实话，我是有路子的，我的叔叔是当领班的。”

“你过得好吗？”

“挺好的。不过说句实话，”他叹了口气继续说，“我们这种人，比如说，要是在商人那里做事，那会过得更好。我们这种人在商人那里会过得更自在。昨天晚上有个从韦尼奥夫来的商人到了我们这儿，他们一名伙计就跟我这么说的……好着呢，没得说，好得很。”

“商人给的薪水多些，是吗？”

“那才不呢！要是你向他讨薪水，他就会拽住你的脖子赶你走。不，在商人那里你得诚实可靠，敢担责任。他供你吃，供你喝，供你穿，供你一切。要是你称他的意，他会给得更多……拿薪水干什么呀！完全用不着……再说啦，商人生活简单，是俄罗斯式的，跟我们的一样：你跟他外出，他喝茶，你也喝茶；他吃什么，你也吃什么。商人……怎么能比呢：商人可不像地主老爷。商人不胡来；比如他生气了，揍你几下就完事了。他不刁难人，不侮辱人……跟着地主老爷可就遭罪了！什么都不称他的心：这样不好，那样不对。你给他一杯水或者一些吃的，他会说：‘哟，水有臭味，哟，吃的东西有臭味！’你拿出去，在门外站一会儿，再送进去，他会说：‘哦，现在好了，哦，现在没有臭味了。’要是侍候女主人呀，对您说吧，女主人就更难对付了！……小姐就更不用提了！……”

“费久什卡！”办事室里传来那胖子的喊声。

值班的小伙子敏捷地走了出去。我喝了一杯茶，躺在沙发上睡着了。我大约睡了两小时。

醒来后，我本想坐起来，然而身子懒得动；我闭上眼睛，可是没有再睡。隔壁的办事室里有人在低声谈话。我不由得倾听起来。

“是呀，是呀，尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇，”有一个声音说，“是这样。这不能不考虑；的确不能不……咳！”（说话的人咳了一声。）

“相信我吧，加夫里拉·安托内奇，”是胖子的声音在说，“我还不知道这里的规矩吗，您想想看。”

“您不知道还有谁知道呀，尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇：您在这儿可以说是头号人物了。可这怎么办才好呢？”我不熟悉的声音继续说，“咱们怎么个决定呢，尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇？想听听您的。”

“拿什么决定呀，加夫里拉·安托内奇？可以说，这件事全在于您呀。看来，您不乐意。”

“得了吧，尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇，您说的什么呀？我们就是做生意、做买卖的呀；我们就是来买货的嘛。可以说，尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇，我们就是靠这个的嘛。”

“八卢布。”胖子一字一字地说。

传来了叹息声。

“尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇，您要价太高了。”

“加夫里拉·安托内奇，不能再让了，苍天在上，不能再让了。”

一阵沉默。

我悄悄地抬起身子，通过壁缝看了看。胖子背朝我坐着。他的对面坐着一个四十来岁的商人。此人有点干瘦，脸色苍白，仿佛抹了一层素油。他不断地摸着胡子，眼睛非常灵活地眨巴着，嘴唇不时地发颤。

“可以说，今年的幼苗长势棒极了，”他又说起来，“我一路都在观赏。打沃龙涅日那边起全长得棒极了，可说是头等的。”

“的确，幼苗长得不赖，”办事处主任回答说，“可是您要知道，加夫里拉·安托内奇，秋天长势好，春天收成未必高。[1]”

“这倒是，尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇：一切都得听上帝的；您说得完全对……你们那位客人或许醒了吧。”

胖子转过身来……听了一下……

“没醒，还在睡。不过，也可能……”

他走到门口来。

“没醒，还在睡。”他重说了一遍，又回到原来的位置上。

“喂，怎么样呀，尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇？”商人又开始说，“这个事总得有个了结吧……那就这样吧，”他继续说，不停地眨着眼睛，“这两张灰的和一张白的[2]奉献大人，那边呢（他用头指一下主人的宅院）六个半卢布。击手为定，怎么样？”

“四张灰的。”胖子回答说。

“唉，三张吧！”

“四张灰的，不要白的。”

“三张，尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇。”

“三张半，一个子儿也不能少了。”

“三张，尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇。”

“别再说了，加夫里拉·安托内奇。”

“您可真不好说话，”商人喃喃地说，“这样我还不如跟女主人去谈呢。”

“那就请便吧，”胖子回答，“早该如此。的确，您干吗找麻烦呢？……那样好得多！”

“唉，得啦，得啦，尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇。怎么一下就火呢！我只是说说嘛。”

“不，实际上……”

“得了吧，我说……说着玩的嘛。好吧，就给三张半，拿你真没办法。”

“本该要四张的，我犯了傻，性太急了。”胖子埋怨地说。

“那么那边，女主人那边，给六个半卢布，尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇，粮食给六个半卢布行吧？”

“已说定了，六个半。”

“好吧，击手为定，尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇（商人张开手指拍一下这位主任的手掌）。上帝保佑您！（商人站起身来。）尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇老爷，我这就去见女主人，我就说，尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇已同我谈定六个半卢布这个价了。”

“您就这样说吧，加夫里拉·安托内奇。”

“那就请您收下。”

商人把一小沓票据交给了这位主任，鞠了个躬，摇了摇头，用两个手指夹起帽子，耸了耸肩膀，波浪式地扭动一下腰，颇有礼貌地踩着咯吱作响的靴子走出去了。尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇走到墙边，我看到，他是在点商人交给他的票据。门口探进一个长着棕黄头发和浓密的络腮胡子的脑袋。

“怎么样啊？”那个人问，“全谈妥了吗？”

“全谈妥了。”

“多少？”

胖子生气地摆了摆手，指了指我这房间。

“啊，那好！”那个人说，随即就不见了。

胖子走到桌旁坐下来，摊开账本，取过算盘，拨动起算珠，他不是用右手的食指而是用中指去拨的，这样更显得体。

值班的小伙子进来了。

“你有什么事？”

“西多尔从戈洛普尔卡来了。”

“啊！叫他进来。等一等，等一等……先去看一下，那位先生怎么样了，还在睡或是醒了。”

值班的小伙子走进我这房间。我把头靠在当枕头的猎袋上，闭着眼睛。

“睡着呢。”值班的小伙子回到办事室，低声地说。

胖子从牙缝里嘀咕了几句。

“好，叫西多尔进来吧。”他终于说。

我又欠起身子。进来的是个大块头的庄稼汉，三十岁上下，身体壮健，红红的脸颊，淡褐色的头发，短短的鬈胡子。他向圣像祷告了一下，向办事处主任鞠了个躬，两手拿着帽子，挺直身子。

“你好，西多尔。”胖子说，一边拨着算盘。

“您好，尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇。”

“路上情况怎么样啊？”

“还好，尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇。有一点泥泞。”（庄稼汉说得很慢、很轻。）

“你老婆身体好吗？”

“她会怎么样啊！”

庄稼汉叹了口气，一条腿向前挪一下。尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇把笔搁在耳朵上，擤了擤鼻涕。

“这回你来干什么呀？”他继续问，一边把方格手巾塞进口袋里。

“听说，尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇向我们要木匠。”

“怎么，你们没有木匠还是怎么的？”

“我们哪会没有呢，尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇，我们那儿是林场嘛，谁都知道。眼下是大忙时节，尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇。”

“大忙时节！你们都喜欢替别人干活，不爱给自己的女主人干……全是一样嘛！”

“活嘛的确都是一样，尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇……可是……”

“怎么说？”

“工钱太……那个……”

“那有什么，瞧，你们都惯坏了。你算啦！”

“话得这么说，尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇，总共一个礼拜的活，要拖上一个月。一会儿木料不够，一会儿又派我们上花园里去扫路。”

“那有什么呢！女主人亲自吩咐的，你我有什么好说的呀。”

西多尔不吭声了，两腿倒来倒去。

尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇一边歪着头，一边专心地拨起算珠来。

“我们那边的……庄稼人……尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇，”西多尔终于又开口了，每个字都说得结结巴巴，“要我给大人您表表心意……这儿……一点小意思……”（他把他那只大手伸到上衣怀里，掏出一个红花纹手巾包。）

“你干什么，你干什么，你疯了，还怎么的？”胖子急忙打断他的话，“去吧，上我家去，”他继续说，几乎把这个吃惊的庄稼人往外推去，“去问问我老婆……她会请你喝茶的，我马上就来，去吧。别怕，去就是了。”

西多尔走出去了。

“这个……笨熊！”办事处主任朝他背后嘟哝了一句，摇摇头，又打起算盘来。

突然从外边，从台阶上响起一片喊声：“库普里亚！库普里亚！库普里亚不好惹啦！”过不了一多会儿，一个身材矮小的人走进了办事处，他那样子像有肺病，鼻子特别长，眼睛大而呆滞，神情甚为傲慢。他穿着一件破旧的上衣，领子是棉绒的，纽扣很小。他肩上扛着一捆柴火。有五六个仆人围着他，他们一个劲地喊着：“库普里亚！库普里亚不好惹啦！库普里亚当火头军啦，当火头军啦！”可是这个穿棉绒领上衣的人根本不去理会同伴们的起哄，而且面不改色。他步子均匀地走到炉子旁边，卸下肩上的柴火，抬起身子，从后边口袋里掏出鼻烟盒，瞪起眼睛，把掺着灰的草木犀末塞进鼻子。

这一伙吵吵嚷嚷的人进来时，胖子皱起了眉头，站起身来；但看到是怎么回事后，便微笑了，只是叫他们别嚷嚷，说隔壁房间里有个打猎的人在睡觉。

“什么样的猎人？”有两个人同声问。

“是位地主。”

“啊！”

“让他们闹腾好了，”穿棉绒领外衣的人摊开双手说，“关我什么事！只要不来碰我。我是当火头军了……”

“当火头军了！当火头军了！”那伙人欢欣地跟着喊说。

“是女主人下的令嘛，”他耸耸肩膀继续说，“你们等着吧……还要让你们当猪倌呢。我是个裁缝，还是个好裁缝，是从莫斯科一流师傅那里学的手艺，替一些将军缝过衣服……我的这套本事谁也夺不走。你们有什么好神气的呢？……有什么呢？怎么呢，你们脱开老爷的权势了吗？你们只不过是吃白饭的，是懒虫。要是让我自由，我不会饿死的，我不会完蛋的；要是给了我身份证，我会好好付代役租，会让老爷们满意的。可你们会怎么样？会完蛋，会像苍蝇一样完蛋，一下就得完蛋！”

“你胡扯，”一个头发淡黄的麻脸的小伙子打断了他的话，这小伙子系着红领带，衣服的肘部已破了，“你曾经带着身份证出去闯过，可老爷就没见你交过一个子儿的代役租，你也没有替自己捞回半个子儿：勉勉强强拖着双腿回家来，从那以后只能穿一件破衣衫过日子。”

“那有什么法子呢，孔斯塔京·纳尔基济奇！”库普里扬[3]回答说，“人一旦恋爱上了，这个人也就完了，毁了，待你先活到我这把年纪，再来对我评头论足吧。”

“你爱上的是什么人呀！瞧她那副丑模样！”

“不，你可别这样说，孔斯塔京·纳尔基济奇。”

“谁能相信你呢？我是见过她的；去年我在莫斯科亲眼见过的。”

“去年她确实差了点。”库普里扬说。

“听我说，先生们，”一个人用轻蔑而随便的语调说，他是一瘦高个，满脸的粉刺，鬈曲头发抹得油光光的，大概是个侍仆，“让库普里扬·阿法纳西奇给咱们唱唱他那支小曲吧。喂，唱起来吧，库普里扬·阿法纳西奇！”

“对呀，对呀！”其他的人都附和说，“亚历山德拉真行呀！他把库普里亚给抓住了，没得说……唱吧，库普里亚！……好样的，亚历山德拉！（仆人们为了表示更大的亲昵，称呼男人时常常用阴性词尾。）[4]唱呀！”

“这儿不是唱歌的地方，”库普里扬强硬地回答说，“这儿是主人的办事处。”

“这关你什么事？兴许你自个儿想当办事员吧！”孔斯塔京带着粗野的笑声回答说，“准是这样！”

“一切都得听女主人的。”这可怜的人说。

“瞧，瞧，想得多美呀？瞧，多有趣呀！哈！哈！哈！”

大家都哈哈大笑了，有的人还蹦跳起来。笑得最大声的是一个十四五岁的孩子，他大概是一个生活在仆人中的贵族的儿子：穿着一件带青铜扣的坎肩，系着雪青色领带，那肚子已经长得圆鼓鼓的了。

“听我说，库普里亚，你得承认，”尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇显然也变得高兴了，和气了，扬扬得意地说，“当伙夫不怎么样吧？可能挺没有意思的吧？”

“那有什么，尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇，”库普里扬说，“的确，你如今当上了我们这里的办事处主任，不错，这的确没有什么好说的；但是你曾经也倒运过，也住过庄稼人的小茅屋呀。”

“你给我当心点，别不识相，”胖子气急地打断他的话，“人家是同你这傻瓜开玩笑；你这傻瓜，人家肯理睬你，你得感谢才是。”

“我是随便说说，尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇，对不起……”

“我也随便说说。”

门一下开了，跑进一个小厮来。

“尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇，女主人要你去一下。”

“谁在女主人那里？”他问这小厮。

“阿克西尼娅·尼基季什娜和一个从韦尼奥夫来的商人。”

“我马上就去。你们，伙计们，”他用诚恳的语调接着说，“你们最好同这位新任伙夫一起离开这儿吧，说不定那德国佬跑来了，正好去告状呢。”

胖子整了整自己的头发，用那只几乎被衣袖全遮住的手捂住嘴咳嗽了一声，扣好衣扣，迈着大步上女主人那边去了。过不多会儿，这伙人和库普里亚跟着出去了。留下来的只有我那个老相识，即那个值班的小伙子。他本来要削羽毛笔，可是坐在那里睡着了。几只苍蝇立刻利用这个大好时机围住他的嘴巴。一只蚊子停在他的脑门上，端端正正地摆开几只小腿，把自己的整个嘴慢慢地扎进他那柔软的肉里。先前那个长着棕黄头发和络腮胡子的脑袋又在门口出现了，它张望了一下，便同自己的十分丑陋的身躯一起走进办事室里来了。

“费久什卡！费久什卡！老睡大觉！”那个人说。

值班的小伙子睁开了眼睛，从椅子上站立起来。

“尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇上女主人那儿去啦？”

“上女主人那儿去了，瓦西利·尼古拉伊奇。”

“啊哈！”我心想，“原来他就是主任出纳。”

主任出纳开始在房里来来去去地走着。然而，与其说他在来回地走，不如说他在来回溜，那样子真像只猫。他穿一件后襟很窄的黑色的旧燕尾服，衣服肩部直晃荡；他的一只手搁在胸前，可另一只手不断地去抓那根马毛做的又高又窄的领带，紧张地把头转来转去。他脚上穿的是一双羊皮靴子，走起路来很轻柔，没有咯吱咯吱地发响。

“今天雅古什金的一位地主来找过您。”值班的小伙子补说了一句。

“哦，找过我？他说了些什么？”

“他说，他晚上去秋秋列夫家等您。他说：‘我有件事要跟瓦西利·尼古拉伊奇谈一谈。’到底什么事，他没有说，他说：‘瓦西利·尼古拉伊奇知道的。’”

“哦！”主任出纳应了一声，走到窗口旁。

“喂，尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇在办事处吗？”穿堂里传来一个响亮的声音。一个身材高高的人跨进门来，他看起来怒气冲冲，那张脸不大端正，但表情丰富，显得很大胆，衣着十分整洁。

“他不在这儿？”他迅速地环视一下四周，问道。

“尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇到女主人那里去了，”主任出纳回答说，“您有什么事，跟我说吧，帕韦尔·安德列伊奇，您可以跟我说……您要什么？”

“我要什么？您想知道我要什么吗？（主任出纳很不自然地点点头。）我要教训教训他这个大肚皮的坏蛋，这个挑拨是非的卑鄙家伙……我让他挑拨挑拨看！”

帕韦尔猛地坐到椅子上。

“您怎么啦，您怎么啦，帕韦尔·安德列伊奇？消消气……您怎么不难为情呀？您别忘了您是在说谁呢，帕韦尔·安德列伊奇！”主任出纳喃喃地说。

“在说谁呢？他当上了办事处主任，关我什么事！真是的，怎么选用这种人！简直可以说是把一头羊放进菜园子！”

“得啦，得啦，帕韦尔·安德列伊奇，得啦！别提了……这些小事说它干什么呀？”

“哼，这只狡猾的狐狸，摇尾巴去了！……我要等他回来。”帕韦尔气愤愤地说，拍了一下桌子。“瞧，他的大驾光临了，”他向窗外一瞧，接着说，“说到谁，谁就到。我们恭候着呢！”（他站起身来。）

尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇走进办事处。他喜形于色，但一瞧见帕韦尔，便有点发窘。

“您好，尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇，”帕韦尔向他慢慢地迎上前去，别具用意地说，“您好。”

办事处主任什么也没有回答。门口出现了一个商人的脸。

“你为什么不搭理我呢？”帕韦尔继续说，“不过，不……不，”他又说，“这样不是事儿；吵呀骂呀都没有用处。是呀，你最好对我说说，尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇，你为什么老跟我过不去？为什么老要毁了我？你说说看，说呀。”

“这儿不是跟您说个明白的地方，”办事处主任有些不安地回答说，“而且也不是时候。不过，说实话，有一点我觉得很奇怪：您凭什么说我要毁了您或者老跟您过不去呢？再说啦，我怎么能够让您过不去呢？您又不是这办事处的人。”

“那还用说，”帕韦尔回答说，“要是那样就更糟了。可是您为什么装蒜呢，尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇？……反正您明白我的意思。”

“不，我不明白。”

“不，您明白。”

“不，对上帝发誓，我不明白。”

“还对上帝发誓呢！既然是这样，那您说说，您怕不怕上帝！您为什么不让那位可怜的姑娘有条活路呢？您想让她怎么样？”

“您说的是谁呢，帕韦尔·安德列伊奇？”胖子故作惊讶地问。

“怪啦！不知道，真的吗？我说的是塔季雅娜。您怕上帝吧——为什么要报复呢？您得顾点脸面：您是个有家室的人，您的孩子都长得有我这般高了，我也是个人嘛……我要结婚，我的行为堂堂正正。”

“这事凭什么怪我呢，帕韦尔·安德列伊奇？是女主人不准你们结婚：这是女主人的意思！关我什么事呢？”

“跟您不相关？您不是跟那个老妖精，那个女管家勾搭在一起吗？您没有去搬弄是非吗？嗯？您说说，你们没有无中生有地去诬陷那个无依无靠的姑娘吗？她不是由于你们的慈悲才从洗衣的变成刷盘子的吗？不是由于你们的慈悲她才挨打，才穿粗布衣服的吗？……讲点脸面吧，讲点脸面吧，您这老家伙！没准您会得中风死的……您总得向上帝做交代吧。”

“您骂吧，帕韦尔·安德列伊奇，您骂好了……看您还能骂多久！”

帕韦尔一下火了。

“怎么？想威胁我？”他愤怒地说，“你以为我怕你？不，伙计，你看错人了！我有什么好怕的？……我上哪儿都找得到饭吃。而你呢，可就是另一码事啦！你只能在这儿瞎混混，挑拨是非，偷偷摸摸……”

“瞧你倒神气起来了，”办事处主任也按捺不住了，打断了他的话，“一个庸医，不过是一个庸医，有什么屁本事！听你说话的口气，好像多么了不起！屁！”

“哼，庸医，要是没有这个庸医，您这位大人早在坟墓里烂掉了……我真不该把你这样的人给治好了。”他透过牙缝低声说。

“是你把我治好的？……不，你是想毒死我；你让我吃了芦荟。”办事处主任接过说。

“要是除了芦荟，没有旁的药能治你的病，那怎么办呢？”

“芦荟是医药管理部门禁用的药，”尼古拉继续说，“我还要去控告你呢。你是想害死我——就是这么回事！只是上帝不答应罢了。”

“算了，算了，你们两位……”主任出纳开口说。

“你别管！”办事处主任喊道，“他就是想毒死我！你对这个不明白？”

“我何必呢……听我说，尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇，”帕韦尔绝望地说，“我最后一次请求你……你这样逼我，我没法忍了。你就让我们安生吧，明白吗？要不然，我对你说吧，咱们两人中会有一个人没有好结果。”

胖子勃然大怒。

“我不怕你，”他嚷了起来，“听见没有，你这乳臭小子！我跟你老子就斗过，我制服过他——这可做你的前车之鉴，当心吧！”

“别提我父亲的事，尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇，别提！”

“滚你的吧！你凭什么给我定规矩？”

“你听着，不准提！”

“你也听着，别太放肆……你以为女主人那么需要你，如果她必须从我们两人里挑一个——那你是保不住的，伙计！谁都不许胡闹，小心点吧！（帕韦尔狂怒得直打哆嗦。）那个塔季雅娜丫头是自己活该……等着吧，还有她受的呢！”

帕韦尔举起双手，扑了上来，办事处主任被重重地摔在地上。

“把他铐起来，铐起来。”尼古拉·叶列梅伊奇哼哼起来……

这出戏的终场我就不去描述了；就这样我还担心，我是否已让读者感到难受。

当天我就回家去了。过了一星期左右，我听说女主人洛斯尼亚科娃仍留下帕韦尔和尼古拉两人供自己差使，而把那个塔季雅娜丫头打发走了，显然是不需要她了。

[1]这里是指秋播春收的作物。

[2]这里是指钞票的颜色。灰色钞票为五十卢布，白色钞票为五卢布。

[3]即库普里亚的正式称呼。

[4]例如这里把亚历山大称为亚历山德拉，又如把库普里扬称为库普里亚。

孤　狼

傍晚我打完猎，独自驾着一辆赛跑马车回去。距家还有七八俄里路；我的马儿是匹脚力矫健的好母马，它在飞尘滚滚的大路上欢腾地奔驰着，时不时地打着响鼻，晃着耳朵；那只疲累了的狗在车轱辘后边步步紧跟，仿佛有绳子牵住似的。大雷雨就要来了。前面有一大片淡紫色的云从树林后边徐徐地升起；在我的头顶上空，有一条条长长的灰云朝我飞掠过来；爆竹柳惊惶地摇晃着，簌簌作响。闷人的炎热骤然变得又潮又冷；阴影迅速地变浓了。我拿缰绳抽一下马，让车子奔下溪谷，越过一条长满柳丛的干枯的小溪，上了坡，进入了一片树林。在我前面那片已经昏暗下来的密密的榛树丛里有一条曲曲弯弯的路；我的马车费劲地前进着。百年的老橡树和椴树向四处伸出坚硬的老根，横在深深的旧车辙上；我的马车在这些树根上颠颠蹦蹦，我的马也走得跌跌绊绊的。狂风猛地在上空怒号起来，随之树木也开始大肆喧哗，大颗大颗的雨点凶猛地敲打着树叶，电光一闪，雷声响开了。下起了倾盆大雨。车子缓缓而行，没多久便不得不停了下来：我的马陷在泥泞里了，四下黑得什么也看不见。我随便地躲到一个宽宽的树丛下。我蜷缩起身子，遮着脸，耐着性子等待雨停，突然在电光中瞥见大路上有一个高高的人影。我便朝着那个地方细细凝视——那人影仿佛是从我车旁的地里冒出来的。

“什么人？”一个响亮的声音问。

“你是什么人呀？”

“我是这里的护林人。”

我报了自己的姓名。

“哦，我知道的！您是回家去的吧？”

“是回家。可你瞧，多大的雷雨呀……”

“是呀，大雷雨。”那声音回答说。

一道白晃晃的电光把这个护林人从头到脚照得通亮，紧接着响起急促而暴烈的雷声。雨下得倍加起劲了。

“不会很快就过去的。”护林人又说了一句。

“怎么办呢？”

“要不，我带你到我家去吧。”他若断若续地说。

“那就麻烦你了。”

“请坐上车吧。”

他走到马头旁，抓住马笼头，把马从泥泞里拉了出来。马车起动了。我的车子宛如“大海中一叶扁舟”，摇摇晃晃，我抓住车子的坐垫，一边吆喝着狗。我那可怜的母马费劲地走在烂泥地里，四腿时而打滑，时而磕绊；护林人在车辕前边东摇西晃，像个鬼影。我们走了一大阵子；我的带路人终于停下脚步。“我们到家了，老爷。”他语调平和地说道。篱笆门嘎的一声推开了，几只小狗齐声叫喊起来。我抬起头，借着闪电的亮光，看到围着篱笆的宽敞院落中间有一座小房子。从一扇小窗里透出暗淡的灯光。护林人把马牵到台阶旁，便敲起门来。“马上来，马上来！”响起一个尖细的童声，又听到光脚丫的踩步声，门闩砰一声拨开了，一个穿着小衬衫，腰间束着布带子的十一二岁的小姑娘举着提灯，出现在门口。

“给老爷照路。”他对她说，“我把您的车子推到棚子里。”

小姑娘瞥了我一眼，便往屋里走去。我跟着她走了进去。

护林人住的只有一间屋子，熏得黑黑的，而且很低矮，屋里空荡荡的，没有高板床，也没有隔墙。墙上挂着一件破皮袄。长凳上搁着一支单管猎枪，屋角里放着一堆破烂；炉子旁摆着两只大瓦罐。桌上燃着松明，悲愁地爆燃一阵，又慢慢地暗下来。房子的正中有一根长竿，一端挂着一个摇篮。小姑娘熄灭了提灯，坐到小板凳上，用右手摇起摇篮，用左手整了整松明。我瞧了瞧周围，心里感到很不好受：夜晚走进农家的屋子真是很不愉快的事。摇篮里的婴儿不安而急促地呼吸着。

“你是一个人在家吗？”我问小姑娘。

“一个人。”她说得几乎听不清楚。

“你是护林人的闺女？”

“是护林人的。”她低声地回答。

门咯吱一声响了，护林人低着头，跨进门来。他从地上拿起提灯，走到桌子旁，把提灯点上了。

“点松明您兴许不习惯吧？”他说，抖了抖鬈发。

我瞅了瞅他。我很少看到有这样帅气的汉子。他身材魁梧，宽肩膀，体形健美。从那淋湿的麻布衬衫里突露出结实的肌肉。黑黑的鬈曲的大胡子把他那严肃而刚毅的脸盘遮住了一半；两道相挨着的阔眉毛下闪动着一对无畏的不很大的褐色眼睛。他的两手轻轻地叉着腰，站在我的面前。

我向他道了谢，并问了他的名字。

“我叫福马，”他回答说，“而外号叫孤狼[1]。”

“你就是孤狼呀？”

我倍感好奇地打量了他。我常常听到我的叶尔莫莱和其他人谈论护林人孤狼的事，附近的庄稼人都像怕火似的怕他。听他们说，世上还不曾有过像他那样尽心尽责的护林人：“连一捆枯枝都不让人拿走；要是你拿走林中的东西，无论在什么时候，哪怕在深更半夜，他会像雪一样从天而降，突然出现在你的面前，你休想抗拒，因为他力大无比，又像魔鬼那样灵活……没有任何东西能收买他，无论金钱美酒都不管用；他不受任何诱惑。有些人多次想干掉他，都干不成。”

附近的庄稼人就是这样评说孤狼的。

“原来你就是孤狼呀，”我重复了一句，“伙计，我听人说起过你。人家说你是什么人都不放过的。”

“我是尽自己的职责，”他阴郁地回答说，“总不能白吃主人家的饭呀。”

他从腰后取出斧子，蹲在地上削起松明来。

“怎么，你没有内当家的吗？”我问他。

“没有。”他回答说，使劲地挥一下斧子。

“是不是去世了？”

“不……是的……去世了。”他说着，一边转开脸去。

我不作声了；他抬起眼睛看了看我。

“跟一个过路的城里人私奔啦。”他带着苦笑说。小姑娘低下了头；婴孩醒来了，哭喊起来；小姑娘走到摇篮旁。“拿着，给他吃吧。”孤狼说，一边把一个脏兮兮的奶瓶塞到小姑娘手里。“把他给丢下啦。”他指指婴孩又低声地说。他走到门口停下步，转过身来。

“老爷，您兴许，”他说，“不要吃我家的这种面包吧，可是我这儿除了面包……”

“我不饿。”

“哦，那算了。我本应给您烧上茶炊，可是我没有茶叶……我去看看您的马怎么样了。”

他走出去，砰一声带上门。我再次打量了四周。我感到这屋里比原先更显凄凉了。冷却的烟气散发着一股不好闻的苦味，使我呼吸得很难受。小姑娘坐在原地一动不动，也不抬一下眼睛；她有时晃几下摇篮，羞涩地把滑下的衬衫往肩上拉一拉；她那光着的两腿一动不动地垂着。

“你叫什么名字？”我问。

“乌莉塔。”她轻声回答，把愁苦的小脸垂得更低了。

护林人进来了，坐在板凳上。

“雷雨快过去了，”沉默了一会儿之后，他说，“要是您想回去，我送您出林子。”

我站起身来。孤狼取过枪，检查了一下火药池。

“拿这枪干什么呀？”我问。

“林子里有人捣乱……在母马山沟那边有人在砍树。”他补充了一句，作为对我的疑问眼光的回答。

“从这儿能听得见？”

“在院子里听得见。”

我们一起走出来。雨已经停了。远处还聚集着一大团一大团的浓云，有时还闪着长长的电光，但在我们的上边有些地方已露出深蓝的天空，星星透过疾飞着的薄云闪烁着。从黑暗中开始呈现出那些沾满雨水、被风刮得东摇西晃的树木的轮廓。我们倾听起来。护林人摘下帽，低下头。“喏……喏，”他突然说，伸手指了指，“瞧，就拣这样的夜晚来偷。”除了树叶的喧哗声外，我什么也听不出来。孤狼把马从棚子下牵了出来。“我这样前去，”他低声说，“也许会让他溜掉的。”“我跟你一起走着去……可以吗？”“好吧，”他回答，把马牵了回去，“咱们把他一下抓住，然后我送你回去。咱们走吧。”

我们走着：孤狼在前面走，我跟着他。天知道他是怎么认得出路的，他只是偶尔停下脚步，那是为了听一听斧子的砍树声。“瞧，”他低声地说，“听见吗？听见吗？”“哪儿呀？”孤狼耸了耸肩膀。我们下到山沟里，风稍静了片刻，斧子的均匀响声清晰地传入了我的耳朵。孤狼瞧了我一眼，摇摇头。我们踩着湿淋淋的野草和荨麻继续向前。传来一阵低沉的持续的轰响声……

“砍倒了……”孤狼喃喃地说。

这时候天空越来越明净了；林子里也有点亮了。我们终于走出了山沟。“请在这儿等一下，”护林人轻声地对我说，他弯下腰，举起枪，消失在丛林中。我专注地去听。透过喧闹不已的风声，我隐约听到从不远处传来的轻微声响：斧子小心地砍树枝声、车轱辘的轧轧声，马儿的响鼻声……“往哪儿跑？站住！”骤然响起孤狼铁一般的喊声。另外还响起了一种像兔子般的哀叫声……出现了一阵打斗声。“瞎说，瞎说，”孤狼气喘吁吁地嚷着，“你跑不了……”我朝那吵闹的方向奔去，一步一绊地跑到那打斗的地方。护林人在砍倒的树旁地上动来动去；他按住那个偷树的人，用腰带反绑那个人的双手。我走上前去。孤狼站起来，把那个人也拉了起来。我看到的是一个庄稼人，他浑身都湿透了，衣服破破烂烂的，长长的大胡子乱蓬蓬的。那里站着一匹瘦弱的马，一张凹凸不平的草席遮着它的半身，马的旁边还停有一辆小货车。护林人不吱一声，那庄稼人也默默无言，只是摇动着脑袋。

“放了他吧，”我对着孤狼的耳朵轻声地说，“这棵树我来赔。”

孤狼不声不响地用左手抓住马鬃，用右手抓住偷树贼的腰带。“喂，快点，狡猾的家伙！”他厉声说。“斧子在那里，您拿上吧。”庄稼人喃喃地说。“干吗把斧子丢掉呢？”护林人说，一边捡起那把斧子。我们便往回走。我走在最后边……又开始稀稀拉拉地掉起小雨点，不多一会儿便变成瓢泼大雨。我们好不容易才回到那座小屋。孤狼把抓来的那匹马赶进院子中间，把那庄稼人带进屋里，把绑他的腰带结子松开一些，让他坐在屋角里。那小姑娘本来已经在炉边睡着了，此时猛地跳了起来，带着惊惶的神色默默地打量着我们。我在板凳上坐下来。

“咳，好凶的雨呀，”护林人说，“只好再等等了。您要不要躺一会儿？”

“谢谢。”

“因为您在这儿，我本来想把他关到贮藏室里去，”他指了指庄稼人继续说，“可是那门闩……”

“让他待在这儿吧，别折腾他了。”我打断孤狼的话说。

那庄稼人蹙着眉头看了看我。我在心里发誓，无论怎么得想法子放走这个可怜的人。我在板凳上坐着不动。在灯光下我可以看清他那干枯的皱巴巴的脸，倒挂的黄眉毛，惶惶不安的眼睛，瘦骨嶙嶙的肢体……小姑娘躺在他脚边的地板上又睡着了。孤狼在桌子旁坐着，两手托着脑袋。蝈蝈在屋角里叫着……雨还在敲打着房顶，顺着窗子直往下流；我们都没有吭声。

“福马·库济米奇，”庄稼人猝然用低沉而衰弱的声音说，“哎，福马·库济米奇。”

“你要干什么？”

“放了我吧。”

孤狼不回答。

“放了我吧……是饿得没法呀……放我走吧。”

“我可知道你们这种人，”护林人沉着脸回答说，“你们整个村子就是贼窝——尽是贼。”

“放了我吧，”庄稼人一再哀求说，“管家……我家给毁了，行行好……放了我吧！”

“毁了！……不管谁都不该去偷嘛。”

“放了我吧，福马·库济米奇……别毁了我。你知道，你那东家会要我的命的。”

孤狼转过脸去。庄稼人打起战来，仿佛患了热病。他的头摇晃起来，呼吸也快慢不均了。

“放了我吧，”他又沮丧又绝望地一再哀求说，“放了我吧，求求你，放了我吧！我会赔钱的，真的。实在是饿得没法……你知道，孩子们哭着要吃。真的没法子。”

“那你还是不该去偷嘛。”

“就让那匹马，”庄稼人继续说，“就让那匹马留下作抵押吧……我只剩下这头牲口了……放了我吧！”

“我说了，不行。我也是做不了主的，东家会追究我的。再说也不该放纵你们。”

“放了我吧！是穷得没法呀，福马·库济米奇，实在是穷得没法……放了我吧！”

“我可知道你们这种人！”

“就放了我吧！”

“哼，跟你有什么可讲的，老实地待着吧，要不我就……知道吗？你没看见有位老爷在这儿吗？”

这个可怜的人垂下了头……孤狼打了一个呵欠，把头靠在桌子上。雨仍然下个不停。我等着看事情如何了结。

庄稼人猛然挺起身子。他那双眼睛冒出怒火，脸都涨红了。“那你就吃了我吧，你就掐死我吧，”他眯上眼睛，挂下嘴角，说了起来，“你这该死的凶手，你就喝基督徒的血吧，喝吧……”

护林人转过身去。

“我对你说话呢，你这野蛮的家伙，你这吸血鬼，我说你呢！”

“你喝醉了，还怎么的？怎么骂人呢？”护林人惊诧地说，“你疯了，是吗？”

“喝醉了！……那是花了你的钱吗，你这该死的凶手，野兽，野兽，野兽！”

“你这家伙……我要治治你！……”

“我有什么好怕的呀？反正都得死；没有了马，我还有什么活路？你打死我，是死，饿死，也是死，反正一样。一切全得完蛋：老婆、孩子，让他们全去死……可你呢，等着吧，会有受报应的时候！”

孤狼站了起来。

“打吧，打吧，”庄稼人以狂怒的声音说，“打吧，来，来，打呀……（小姑娘急忙从地上蹦了起来，盯着他看）打呀！打呀！”

“闭嘴！”护林人大喊一声，跨前两步。

“算了，算了，福马，”我喊了起来，“放开他……由他说吧。”

“我偏不闭嘴，”这个不幸的人继续说，“反正一样得完蛋。你这凶手，野兽，你怎么不死呀……等着吧，你作威作福长久不了！有人会掐死你，等着吧！”

孤狼抓住他的肩膀……我扑过去救助那庄稼人……

“您别动，老爷！”护林人朝我喊了一声。

我并不怕他威吓，已经伸过手去；然而令我极为惊诧的是，孤狼一下子把绑着庄稼人胳膊肘的腰带扯掉了，抓住他的衣领，把他的帽子扣到他眼睛上，打开门，把他推了出去。

“带着你的马滚蛋吧！”他朝庄稼人的背后喊道，“你当心点，下一次我可……”

他回到屋里，在屋角里翻寻起什么。

“咳，孤狼，”我终于说，“你真让我惊奇呀，我看你是个好人哪。”

“唉，得了，老爷，”他苦恼地打断我的话说，“只求您别说出去。现在最好还是由我送您走吧，”他接着说，“您一时等不到雨停的……”

院子里响起那庄稼人的马车轱辘的声音。

“听，他走了！”他咕哝说，“下回我就不饶他！……”

半个小时之后，他便与我在林边上告了别。

[1]奥廖尔省的人常把孤单而忧郁的人称为孤狼。——作者原注

两地主

知音的读者们，我曾荣幸地向你们介绍过我的几位地主乡邻；现在请让我顺便（对于我们这些当作家的人来说，什么都是顺便说的）再向你们介绍两位地主，我常在他们那边行猎，与他们相识，他们都是极可敬、极善良的人，在附近几个县里深受普遍的尊敬。

我先来为你们描述一下退伍陆军少将维亚切斯拉夫·伊拉里奥诺维奇·赫瓦伦斯基吧。论外表嘛，他是个高个子，早年时身材非常挺拔，如今皮肤略有些松弛了，但绝没有老态，甚至不能说是年岁已老，还处于成熟的年龄呢，也可以说，正值大好年华呢。的确，从前端庄的，至今依然悦目的脸形已有了些变化，脸皮有点下垂，眼角密布亮闪闪的皱纹，一部分牙齿，正如普希金援引萨迪的话[1]所说的那样，已经不在了；淡褐色的头发，至少那些还保全下来的头发，由于用了一种护发剂而变成淡紫色的了，那种护发剂是在罗姆内马市上从一个装成亚美尼亚人的犹太佬那儿买来的。话说回来，维亚切斯拉夫·伊拉里奥诺维奇步履矫健，笑声洪亮，走起路来踢马刺碰得丁儿当啷直响；他常捻着小胡子，还自称为老骑士，可大家都清楚，真正的老年人是决不以老头子自称的。平日里他老穿一件双排扣上衣，纽扣直扣到顶，领带结得老高，衣领浆得挺挺的，下穿带花点的军式灰裤子；帽子直扣到额头，却让后脑勺整个暴露在外。他是个很善良的人，可是有着怪得出奇的见解和习惯。比如说吧，对于贵族中一些既没钱也没有权势的人，他决不肯平等相待。跟他们说话时，总是把脸紧贴在浆硬的白衣领上，斜眼瞪着他们，或者猛然用明亮而呆板的目光扫他们一眼，不言不语，动一动头发下面的整个头皮。连话语的发音也变了，比如，他不说“多谢啦，帕韦尔·瓦西利伊奇”，或者“请到这儿来，米海洛·伊万内奇”，而是说成“谢，帕尔·阿西利奇”，或者“请这来，米哈尔·瓦内奇”。对待社会地位卑微的人，他那副态度就更怪了：对他们不瞧一眼，在说明自己的意愿或吩咐之前，便带着忧心和思索的神情，接二连三地反复问：“你叫什么呀？……你叫什么呀？”他把“什么”这个词说得特别重，而其他几个词说得溜快，这样一来，他那话音就变得像公鹌鹑的叫唤声了。他整天里忙这忙那，而且吝啬得可怕，但又不是一个好当家：竟起用一个退伍的骑兵司务长，一个愚不可及的小俄罗斯人当管家。不过，在管理家业方面，我们这里还没有什么人能比得上彼得堡的一位达官贵人，他从自己的管家的报告里得知，他庄园里的烤禾房时常失火，粮食损失严重，于是他便下了一道极严厉的禁令：从今以后，在火没有彻底熄灭之前，不准把禾捆搬进烤禾房。那位官老爷还想要让自己的所有田地都种植罂粟，显然，这是出于极简单的算计：说是罂粟比黑麦贵，所以种罂粟上算。他还给自己的农奴婆娘们下了令，命她们戴的头饰要根据彼得堡寄来的样式。果然，他庄园里的婆娘们至今还戴这种头饰……不过已是戴在帽子上边了……现在我再回头说说维亚切斯拉夫·伊拉里奥诺维奇吧。维亚切斯拉夫·伊拉里奥诺维奇是个顶顶出格的好色鬼，他在自己县城的林荫道上一瞧见秀色可餐的女人，便连忙前去跟踪，此时他的步态马上变得一瘸一拐，那光景真是妙极了。他很喜欢玩牌，不过只同一些身份低下的人玩；他们尊称他为“大人”，他可以随意呵斥他们。当他同省长或其他什么当官的玩牌时，他的态度便起翻天覆地的变化：他会面带笑容，连连点头，察看他们的眼色——显出一副甜蜜蜜的样子……即便输了钱，也不埋怨。维亚切斯拉夫·伊拉里奥诺维奇不大读书，一读书，胡子眉毛便会不住地颤动，脸上好像自下而上地滚着波浪。当他偶尔浏览（自然是当着客人的面）Journal des Dèbats[2]各栏目时，他脸上的这种波浪式动作便特别显眼。他在选举中常扮演相当重要的角色，可是由于舍不得花钱，他不愿接受贵族长这一荣誉称号。“诸位，”他常常对那些捧他的贵族们说，而且是以充满爱护下属和自有主张的口气说，“多谢诸位的美意；可我意已决，我愿安闲自在，享享清福。”说过之后，把头向左右转了几下，随后庄重地把下巴和脸颊紧贴在领带上。他年轻时候曾当过某位要人的副官，他对那位要人只称名字和父名，甚为尊敬。有人说，他似乎不光是担任副官职位，比如说，他似乎曾穿着全套制服，甚至扣好领扣，在澡堂里拿浴帚帮上司洗澡——不过，并非每种传闻都是可信的呀。可是，连赫瓦伦斯基将军本人也不喜欢去谈自己的军人生涯，这的确奇怪得很；他似乎也没有打过仗。赫瓦伦斯基将军住在一座不很大的房子里，单身一人；他平生还没有体验过琴瑟相谐之乐，因此至今仍是个未婚男子，甚至可以说是个顶有出息的择婿对象。不过，他有一位女管家，三十五六岁，黑黑的眼睛，黑黑的眉毛，体态丰盈，皮肤鲜嫩，长有一点髭须，平日里穿着浆得挺挺的衣服，逢礼拜天便戴上薄纱套袖。在地主们招待省长或其他权贵们的盛大酒宴上，维亚切斯拉夫·伊拉里奥诺维奇往往表现非凡，在这样场合他真可谓如鱼得水。在这种宴会上，他若不是坐在省长的右侧，那也是坐得离省长不远；在宴会开始的时候，他显得较为自尊自重，身体后仰一点，但不转头，侧目向下打量着客人们圆滚滚的后脑勺和坚挺的衣领；可到了宴会快散的时候，他便乐开了，开始朝四方投出微笑（朝省长方面从宴会一开始他就微笑了），有时甚至提议为女士们，用他的话说，为“我们星球的装饰”干杯。赫瓦伦斯基将军在各种隆重的和公众的庆典仪式、会考场所、宗教仪式、集会和展览会上也显得相当出色，受祝福时也很得体。这位将军手下的仆人们在岔道口、渡口以及类似的地方都不喧闹、不叫嚷；相反，在请行人让开或请车辆让行的时候，都用悦耳的带喉声的男中音说：“劳驾，劳驾，请让赫瓦伦斯基将军过去。”或者说：“赫瓦伦斯基将军的马车……”赫瓦伦斯基的马车样式确实陈旧得很；仆人们穿的号衣也相当破旧（不必说，都是些带红镶边的灰色号衣）；几匹马也都垂垂老矣，辛苦一辈子了；而这位将军一向不求奢华，甚至认为追求奢华有辱他的名声。他说话没有什么特殊口才，也许是没有机会表现自己的口才，因为他不仅讨厌争论，而且根本容不得辩论，总是避免做各种冗长的谈话，特别是同年轻人的谈话。这样做确实有其道理，要不然怎么对付得了当今的这些人呢：他们会对他不听从，会对他失敬。在地位高的人面前，赫瓦伦斯基大都是缄口不语，可是对那些地位低，显然被他瞧不起而仅有点交往的人，他说话便显得既短促又尖刻，老是使用如下的词语：“可是，您说的，尽是废话”，或者“阁下，我终于，不得不，警告您”，或者“可是，您终究应该明白，您是在跟谁打交道”，等等。邮政局长、常任陪审员、驿站长们对他怕得要命。他府上从来不招待任何人，正如传闻所说的，他是个吝啬鬼。即便有这种种缺点，他仍算是个出色的地主。邻里们都说他是一个“老军人、无私的人、规矩人、vieux grognad[3]”。在人们谈起赫瓦伦斯基将军的优秀而实在的品质时，只有一位省检察官在一边冷笑——嫉妒使人什么做不出来呢！……

现在还是让我们来谈谈另一位地主吧。

马尔达里·阿波洛内奇·斯捷古诺夫跟赫瓦伦斯基一无相似之处：他大概不曾在什么地方供过职，也从来没有被看作一个美男子。马尔达里·阿波洛内奇是个矮矮胖胖的小老头，谢顶，双下巴，有一双柔软的手，大腹便便。他很好客，性格诙谐；可以说，日子过得挺滋润；不管寒去暑来，老穿着一件条纹棉长衣。仅有一点他是跟赫瓦伦斯基将军一样的：他也是光棍一条。他有五百个农奴。马尔达里·阿波洛内奇经营自己的田庄很重门面；为了不落伍于时代，他早在十来年前便从莫斯科的布捷诺普公司购来一架脱粒机，把它锁在库房里，心里也就感到踏实了。只有在晴朗的夏日里，他才吩咐套好那赛跑马车到田野里看看庄稼，采集些矢车菊。马尔达里·阿波洛内奇完全是按老方式过日子的。他的住宅也是老式的建筑：在前室里照旧散发着格瓦斯、脂油蜡烛和皮革的气味；这里右边有一个餐具柜，里面搁着烟斗和毛巾；餐室里有家族成员的肖像、苍蝇、一大盆天竺葵和一架寒酸的钢琴；客厅里有三张长沙发、三张桌子、两面镜子和一个声音沙哑的自鸣钟，钟上的珐琅已变黑了，钟面上有镂花的青铜指针；书房里有一张堆着纸张的书桌；有一个浅蓝色屏风，上面贴着从上一世纪各种图书中裁下的图画；有几个书柜，里面堆着发霉发臭的书籍，还有蜘蛛和黑黑的尘埃；有一把臃肿的安乐椅；还有一扇意大利式窗子和一扇朝花园的钉死了的门……总之，应有尽有。马尔达里·阿波洛内奇家奴仆成群，一律穿着老式服装：高领的蓝色长外套、深暗色的裤子和浅黄色的短坎肩。他们称客人为“老爷”。他家的产业是由一个庄稼人出身的总管替他经营，他的大胡子有整个皮袄那样长；家务事是由一个裹着深棕色头巾的老太婆料理，她一脸皱纹，为人吝啬。马尔达里·阿波洛内奇家的马厩里养着三十匹大大小小的马；他外出时常乘坐一辆重达一百五十普特的自制四轮马车。他待客非常热情，饭菜十分丰盛，也就是说，凭着俄式的厚酒肥肉熏人昏醉的特点，使客人直到晚上除了玩牌外什么也干不了。他自己从来都是无所事事，连一本《释梦》书也没有读下去。像这样的地主在我们俄国还大有人在。有人问我怎么要谈起他，为了什么？……那么，我就来讲一讲自己对马尔达里·阿波洛内奇的一次访问，权作回答吧。

我是在夏天的一个晚上来到他家的，当时大约七点钟。他刚做过晚祷，客厅门口一张椅子的边上坐着一位神甫，年纪轻轻的，样子十分腼腆，可能是新出宗教学校校门不久的。马尔达里·阿波洛内奇照例非常亲切地接待我：他对每个来客都是真诚欢迎的，他一般说来是个顶和善的人。神甫站起身，拿起帽子。

“等一下，等一下，神甫，”马尔达里·阿波洛内奇一边还握着我的手一边就朝他说，“别走……我已让人给你拿酒了。”

“谢谢，我不会喝酒。”神甫局促地嘟哝说，脸红到了耳根。

“瞎说什么呀！你们这样的人哪能不会喝酒呢！”马尔达里·阿波洛内奇回答说，“尤什卡！尤什卡！给神甫拿酒来！”

尤什卡是个又高又瘦、年约八十的老头，他端着一个沾满肉色斑点的托盘进来，盘上放着一杯伏特加酒。

神甫推三阻四地婉谢。

“喝吧，神甫，别扭扭捏捏啦，这不大好。”地主带点责备口气说。

可怜的年轻人只好从命。

“好，神甫，现在你可以走了。”

神甫鞠躬告辞。

“好的，好的，走吧……一个多好的人哪，”马尔达里·阿波洛内奇目送着他说，“我对他挺满意的；只是有一点：还很嫩。老是守着教规，连酒都不沾。您怎么样啊，我的老弟？……您怎么样，好吗？我们到凉台上去吧——瞧，多美的夜晚。”

我们去到凉台上，坐下来海聊起来。马尔达里·阿波洛内奇朝下边瞧了瞧，顿时陷于极度的不安。

“这是谁家的鸡？这是谁家的鸡？”他大喊起来，“是谁家的鸡在花园里乱窜？……尤什卡！尤什卡！快点跑去看看，是谁家的鸡跑到花园里乱窜？……这是哪一家的鸡呀？我禁止过多少遍啦，说过多少回啦！”

尤什卡跑去了。

“简直乱了套！”马尔达里·阿波洛内奇说，“太不像话！”

我现在仍记得，那几只不走运的母鸡，两只花斑鸡和一只白凤头鸡还在苹果树下悠然信步，有时用持续的咯咯声来抒发自己的情怀，骤然间，不戴帽子、手持棍子的尤什卡和另外三个成年仆人协同一致地向它们急奔过来。这一下真热闹开了。三只母鸡叫喊着，拍着翅膀，跳蹦着，咕达咕达地吵翻天；仆人们跑着，磕磕碰碰，摔倒在地；主人发狂了似的从凉台上大喊：“抓住，抓住！抓住，抓住！抓住，抓住，抓住！……这是谁家的鸡，这是谁家的鸡？”一个仆人终于抓住了那只凤头鸡，把它按住在地。正在这时候，一个十一二岁的、蓬头散发的小丫头拿着一根长棍，越过篱笆从外边跳进花园里。

“啊，原来是她家的鸡呀！”地主高兴地喊了起来，“是马车夫叶尔米尔家的鸡！他让他的娜塔尔卡来赶鸡了……怎么不叫帕拉莎来呢。”地主低声地加了一句，一面意味深长地一笑。“喂，尤什卡！别去抓鸡了；把娜塔尔卡给我抓来。”

在气喘吁吁的尤什卡还没有跑近那个吓破胆的小丫头身边之前，不知从哪儿冒出了女管家，她抓住小丫头的胳膊，在她背上啪啪地揍了好几下……

“就得这样，就得这样，”地主接着说，“揍揍揍！揍揍揍！……把鸡扣下来，阿夫多季娅，”他又大声地添了一句，并喜形于色地朝着我说，“老弟，这回打猎打得怎么样呀？您瞧，我都出汗了。”

马尔达里·阿波洛内奇哈哈大笑起来。

我们仍然待在凉台上。这晚间确实非常好。

仆人给我们上了茶。

“请问，”我开口说，“马尔达里·阿波洛内奇，迁到山谷那边大路旁的那几家是您的佃户吗？”

“是我的……怎么？”

“您这是怎么啦，马尔达里·阿波洛内奇？这可不应当呀。拨给那些庄稼人的房子太差，太小了；周围连棵树也见不到；甚至连个小鱼塘也没有；井只有一口，而且还是不顶用的。难道您就不能找个别的地方吗？……还听说，您把他们以前的大麻田也收走了？”

“地界是这么划的，拿它有什么办法呢？”马尔达里·阿波洛内奇回答我说，“这样划地界我也觉得有些不合适。（他指指自己的后脑勺。）我看不出这种划法有什么好处。至于我收回他们的大麻田，没有在他们那边挖养鱼塘什么的——关于这些事嘛，自有我的道理。我是个老实人，按老规矩行事。依我看，老爷终究是老爷，庄稼人终究是庄稼人……就是这么回事。”

对于这样明白的不容置疑的理由，自然是没法与他再说了。

“而且，”他接着说，“那些庄稼人不是东西着呢，很令人头痛。尤其是那边的两家；先父——祝他升天堂——在世时就讨厌他们，挺讨厌他们。对您说吧，我有这样的体会：如果老子是贼，儿子必定也是贼；有什么法子呢……唉，遗传呀遗传，这可是个严重的问题！坦白地对您说吧，我把那两户中没有轮到的人都送去当兵了，把他们东一个西一个地拆散开来；可也根除不了，有什么办法？他们能繁殖着呢，这些可恶的家伙。”

此时周围全然寂静下来了。只是有时吹来一阵阵晚风，每当一阵风停息在房子近处时，从马厩那边频频响起的有节奏的鞭打声传到了我们的耳朵。马尔达里·阿波洛内奇刚刚把斟满茶的碟子[4]端到嘴边，而且已经张开了鼻孔——大家都知道，地道的俄罗斯人都是先张开鼻孔才喝茶的——可是他停住没喝，侧耳倾听，点了点头，然后才呷了一口，就把碟子放到桌子上，露出最慈祥的微笑，似乎不由自主地应和起那些鞭打声，喊着：“啪啪啪！啪啪！啪啪！”

“这是怎么回事？”我惊讶地问。

“这是按我的吩咐，在那边惩罚一个调皮鬼……就是那个在餐室里干活的瓦夏，您知道吗？”

“哪个瓦夏？”

“就是头些时候侍候我们用餐的那个，长一脸大胡子的。”

无论怎么愤慨，也抵抗不住马尔达里·阿波洛内奇那明亮而柔和的目光。

“您怎么啦，年轻人，您怎么啦？”他摇着头说，“您干吗这样盯着我看，难道我是个坏蛋吗？惩罚是出于爱护嘛，您是懂得的。”

过了一刻钟，我便向马尔达里·阿波洛内奇告辞了。我乘车经过村子时，瞧见了那个餐室听差瓦夏。他在马路上走着，一边咬着核桃。我让车夫勒住马，唤他过来。

“喂，伙计，你今天挨打了？”我问他。

“您怎么知道？”瓦夏反问说。

“是你家老爷对我说的。”

“是老爷亲口说的？”

“他为什么让人打你呢？”

“我是该挨打的，先生，该挨打的。我们这儿不会平白无故惩罚人的；我们这儿不会这样做的——确实不会。我们的老爷不是那号人；我们的老爷……全省都找不出他这样的好老爷。”

“走吧！”我对车夫说。“这就是旧俄罗斯呀！”在回家的路上我这样琢磨着。

[1]萨迪系十三世纪波斯诗人。普希金在《叶甫盖尼·奥涅金》（第八章第五十一节）中引用他的诗句说：“有的远在天涯，有的已不在人间。”原意是指友人的离去，此处借指牙齿的脱落。

[2]法语：《评论报》。

[3]法语：好唠叨的人。——原注

[4]旧时俄国人的喝茶方式是，先把杯里的茶倒入碟子里，然后从碟子里喝茶。

列别江

亲爱的读者们，打猎的主要一种好处，就在于它让你时常坐着马车一处又一处地东奔西跑，这对于一个清闲无事的人说来，确是一种莫大的乐趣。当然，有的时候（特别是在雨天）就不那么愉快了，比如在乡间土路上彷徨，或者在荒野里完全迷了路，这种时候随便遇到一个庄稼人，就只好叫住他问：“喂，老乡！去莫尔多夫卡怎么走呀？”而到了莫尔多夫卡后，又得向一个笨头笨脑的婆娘（庄稼汉们都下地干活去了）打听：离大路旁的客店还远不？怎么个走法？车子跑了十来俄里，不见有客店，却来到了一个地主住的破败穷酸的霍多布勃诺夫小村，把一群躺在路中央齐耳朵深的黑褐色烂泥里的猪吓得半死，它们万万没有想到竟有人前来打扰。每当驶过那些摇摇欲坠的小桥，奔下山谷，越过满是烂泥的小溪，也不是什么愉快的事；令你不愉快的还有，几天几夜奔波在绿色原野中的大路上，或者——老天保佑，切莫遇上——在一面写着数字二十二，另一面写着数字二十三的五颜六色的里程标前的烂泥地里陷上几个小时；一连几个星期吃的尽是鸡蛋、牛奶和人人夸奖的黑麦面包，也够你受的……然而，所有这些不便和不顺心会换来另一类的好处和满足。不过，现在就来谈谈正题吧。

由于以上已谈了很多，就毋需向读者详述我在四五年前是怎样来到列别江，来到那里最杂乱的集市的经过了。我们这号猎人常常在某个早晨乘车离开或多或少属于祖传的领地，打算在第二天傍晚便回家来的，可是这儿停停，那儿停停，没完没了地射猎鹬鸟，结果便来到了伯绍拉河风光秀丽的河畔；再说，凡是爱好猎枪和猎狗的人，也都狂热爱慕世上最高贵的动物——马。所以，我一到列别江，住进一家旅店之后，换套衣服，便前往集市去了。（旅店里有一名年轻伙计，二十来岁，瘦高个，带有甜美的鼻音，他已告诉我，说某某公爵大人，即某某团队的马匹采购员，就住在他们这旅店里；另外还来了许多士绅，天天晚上有茨冈人唱歌，剧院里在演出《特瓦尔多夫斯基老爷》；他还说，马的价码很高，可是都是些好马。）

在集市的广场上停着一排排大车，多不胜数，大车后边站着各种各类的马：跑大步的马、养马场的马、比秋格马、拉货车的马、驿马和普通的农家马。还有一些膘肥毛滑的马，按毛色分类，披着各种颜色的马衣，紧紧拴在高高的架木上，胆怯地向后斜视着马贩子主人手中的为它们所十分熟悉的鞭子；草原贵族们从一二百俄里外送来的家养的马，由一个年老体衰的车夫和两个头脑迟钝的马夫照看着，它们摇晃着长长的脖子，跺着蹄子，百无聊赖地啃着木桩；一些黄褐色的维亚特卡马相互紧靠在一起；一些长有波浪形尾巴、毛茸茸蹄肘、大屁股的跑大步马像狮子似的威严地站立不动，它们中有灰色带圆斑点的，有乌黑色的，也有枣红色的。行家们毕恭毕敬地站在它们的面前。在一排排大车分隔成的走道上，聚集着各种身份、各种年龄和各种模样的人。那些穿蓝外套、戴高帽子的马贩子狡猾地窥视和等待着买主；突眼鬈发的茨冈人不住地奔前跑后，查看马的牙齿，扳看马腿，掀起马尾巴，叫叫嚷嚷、骂骂咧咧，充当掮客，抽签抓阄，或者死乞白赖地缠住一个戴军帽、穿海狸领军大衣的马匹采购员。一个体格壮实的哥萨克挺着身子骑在一匹长着鹿脖子的瘦骟马上，打算把这匹马连同马鞍和笼头“整套”出售。有些庄稼人，穿着胳肢窝处破了的皮袄，拼死劲地挤过人群，一伙一伙地挤到那辆套着“试用”马的大车旁边；或者，在狡猾的茨冈人的协助下，在一旁的某处费尽气力地讨价还价，互相一连击了上百次掌，结果还是各要各的价；这期间，那匹作为他们争吵对象的披着破席子的劣等马，只管在一边眨眼睛，一副事不关己的神气……说来也是，由谁来揍它，对于它不都一样！有几个高额门、染了胡子的地主老爷，脸上带着尊严的神情，头戴波兰式四角帽，身穿厚呢大衣，只套上一只袖子，傲慢地在同几个戴羽绒毛帽子和绿手套的大肚皮商人说着话。各种团队的军官们也在这里挤来挤去凑热闹；一名个子特高的德裔胸甲骑兵神情冷漠地问一个瘸腿的马贩子：“这匹棕黄马要卖什么价？”一个十八九岁的淡黄发的骠骑兵正在为一匹瘦健的溜蹄马物色一匹拉梢马；有一个驿站车夫，戴着有孔雀毛的矮帽子，穿着褐色上衣，一副皮手套塞在窄窄的绿腰带里，他正在寻求一匹辕马。马车夫们有的在替自己的马梳编尾巴，有的在把马鬃弄湿，有的在向老爷们恭敬地提些忠告。做完买卖的人视各自的情况，有的奔大酒店，有的去小酒馆……奔忙、叫嚷、动脑筋、争吵、和解、骂、笑——这一切都是在齐膝深的泥污中进行的。我想替自己的马车选购三匹脚力好的马，因为我原来的几匹马有些不大中用了。我已找到了两匹，而第三匹还没有选好。在吃过我在这里不愿描述的一顿饭之后，（埃涅阿斯[1]早已懂得，回想过去的痛苦是何等的不愉快），我就到那个所谓的咖啡厅去，那儿天天晚上都云集着马匹采购员、养马场场主以及其他的过路人。在烟草的浓烟腾腾的台球室里，已聚有二十来个人。其中有一些放荡不羁的年轻地主，穿着轻骑兵的短上衣和灰裤子，留着长长的鬓发，搽了油的小胡子，带着高傲而放肆的神情环顾着周围；另外有几个穿哥萨克服装、脖子特短、眼睛浮肿的贵族在那儿难受地呼哧呼哧着；商人们在一旁聚坐，即所谓处于“另席”。军官们在无拘无束地交谈。有一位公爵在打台球，他是个二十二三岁的年轻人，脸上带着愉快的但又有点瞧不起人的神情，穿着常礼服，敞着衣襟，里边是红绸衬衫，下面穿的是肥大的丝绒灯笼裤；他正在同退伍的陆军中尉维克托·赫洛帕科夫比试台球。

退伍的陆军中尉维克托·赫洛帕科夫是个三十来岁的小个子，黑黑的皮肤，瘦瘦的身材，乌黑的头发，深棕色的眼睛，塌扁的鼻子。凡有选举和集市，他都热心地参观。他走起路来一蹦一跳，神气活现地甩开滚圆的胳膊，歪戴着帽子，卷着他那灰蓝色棉布衬里的军服袖子。赫洛帕科夫先生很会讨好彼得堡的一些富有的纨绔子弟，跟他们一块儿抽烟、喝酒、玩牌，跟他们称兄道弟。他们为何垂青于他，那很难搞个明白。他并不聪明，甚至也不算滑稽；也不适合于做供人逗乐取笑的小丑。其实，他们只不过是像对待一个善良而空虚的人那样，随便同他交往一阵；与他来往三两个星期之后，就不同他来往了，他也不去招呼他们了。赫洛帕科夫中尉有一个特点，他在一年有时两年的时间里经常反复说同一句话，不管恰当不恰当；这句话一点也不风趣，可天知道为什么能让大家发笑。七八年以前，他不管到哪儿都说着这样一句话：“向您致敬，感谢之至。”那时候庇护他的人每次都笑得死去活来，并让他一再重复“向您致敬”；后来他开始使用一句相当复杂的话：“不，这您就那个了，克斯克塞[2]——结果就是这样嘛。”这句话同样也大获成功；过了两三年，他又想出了一句新的俏皮话：“您别急嘛，上帝的人，裹着羊皮。”等等。有什么不好呢！您瞧，就是这些毫无意思的话使他有吃、有喝、有衣穿。（他自己的家产早已挥霍殆尽，如今就专靠朋友们过日子了。）要知道，他没有任何旁的能耐。的确，他每天能抽百来烟斗的茹可夫烟，一打起台球，右脚能跷得比脑袋还高，瞄准的时候，发狂地转着手上的台球杆——可是这种种花招也不是人人都赞赏的。他饮酒也很海量……不过，在俄国凭酒量是难以出风头的……总之，他混得这么成功，对于我完全是个不解之谜……可有一点是清楚的：他很谨慎，不外扬家丑，不揭任何人的短……

“嘿，”我一见到赫洛帕科夫时心里就想，“当前他的口头语是什么呢？”

公爵打中了白球。

“三十比零。”那个长着黑脸，眼皮下有青疤的患肺病的记分员大喊一声。

公爵把一个黄球啪的一声击进边上的球囊里。

“好！”坐在角落一张单条腿摇摇晃晃的小桌旁的一个胖乎乎的商人，用整肚子的气发出赞扬的喊声，他喊了之后觉得有些难为情。幸亏没有人注意他，他喘了一口气，捋了捋胡子。

“三十六比零！”记分员用鼻音喊道。

“怎么样呀，伙计？”公爵问赫洛帕科夫。

“怎么样？当然是勒勒勒拉卡利奥奥翁[3]，的确是勒勒勒拉卡利奥奥翁！”

公爵扑哧一笑。

“怎么，怎么？再说一遍！”

“勒勒勒拉卡利奥奥翁！”退伍的陆军中尉得意地重复了一遍。

“这就是他目前的口头语！”我心想。

公爵把一个红球击进了球囊。

“咳！不能这样，公爵，不能这样，”一个眼睛发红、鼻子细小、头发淡黄、脸上显出婴儿般睡相的小军官突然喃喃地说起来，“不要这样打……应该是……不是这样！”

“该怎样呢？”公爵回头问他。

“应该……那样……用双回球的打法。”

“是吗？”公爵透过牙缝低声地说。

“怎么样，公爵，今天晚上到茨冈人那儿去吗？”发窘的年轻人急忙接着说，“斯捷什卡要唱歌呢……还有伊留什卡……”

公爵没有搭理他。

“勒勒勒拉卡利奥奥翁，老弟。”赫洛帕科夫狡猾地眯起左眼说。

公爵哈哈大笑。

“三十九比零。”记分员报告说。

“零就零……瞧我怎样打这个黄球……”

赫洛帕科夫转了几下手里的台球杆，瞄准了一会儿，可滑了球杆。

“唉，勒拉卡利奥翁。”他气恼地喊了起来。

公爵又大笑起来。

“怎么，怎么，怎么？”

然而赫洛帕科夫不愿再重复他那句口头语了，也要撒点娇嘛。

“您的杆子打滑了，”记分员说，“让我来擦上点白粉……四十比零！”

“对啦，诸位，”公爵没有专朝着某个人，而是朝着所有在场的人说，“你们听着，今天晚上在剧院里得把韦尔任姆比茨卡娅喊出来。”

“当然啰，当然啰。那一定，”好几位士绅争着喊，他们把附和公爵的话视为莫大的荣幸，“一定把韦尔任姆比茨卡娅喊出来……”

“韦尔任姆比茨卡娅是位出色的演员，比索普尼亚科娃强多了。”一个留小胡子、戴眼镜、可怜巴巴的人在角落里尖声尖气地说。好可怜的人呀！他心里本来是非常欣赏索普尼亚科娃的，他这样奉承也没用，公爵也没有赏他一眼。

“茶房，拿烟斗来！”一个容貌端正、气度轩昂的高个子士绅朝着自己的领带喊了一声。从各种特征看来，他像个赌棍。

茶房忙着去取烟斗，回来时向公爵大人报告说，驿站车夫巴克拉加要见他。

“啊！好，叫他等一下，再拿点酒给他。”

“是，大人。”

正如后来人家告诉我的，这个叫巴克拉加的人是个年轻、漂亮、深受宠幸的驿站车夫；公爵很喜欢他，送过他几匹马，有时还同他赛马，同他一起整夜整夜地去玩乐……这位公爵从前是个放荡鬼，挥霍着呢，如今您可能认不出他来了……瞧他现在身上香水味多浓、衣服多挺括，又多傲气啊！他公务繁忙，而主要的是，他多么明白事理呀！

然而烟草的烟雾熏得我眼睛有些难受了。最末一次听过赫洛帕科夫的喊声和公爵的笑声之后，我便回到自己的房间。房间里有一张带高高的弯靠背的长沙发，它很窄，有些塌陷，垫子是鬃制的，茶房已为我在沙发上铺好了被褥。

第二天我到各家院子去相马，打有名的马贩子西特尼科夫家开始。我走进栅栏门，来到铺着沙子的院落里。在敞开的马厩门前站着的正是老板本人，他已不年轻了，又高又胖，穿着高翻领的兔皮皮袄。一见到我，他便慢慢地迎上来，两手把帽子举在头顶上，拖着长声说：

“啊！您好。大概是来看马的吧？”

“是的，来看看马。”

“请问，要什么样的？”

“请让我看看，您有些什么马？”

“好的。”

我们走进马厩。有几只白色巴儿狗从干草堆上爬起来，摇着尾巴向我们跑来；一只长胡子的老山羊带着不满的神情退到一边去；三个穿着油腻腻的厚实皮袄的马夫默默地向我们鞠躬。左右两边是一些地面垫得高高的马栏，里面站着近三十匹护养良好，皮毛洁净的马。有一些鸽子在横梁上飞来飞去，咕咕地啼叫。

“您要做什么用的马，是做坐骑的，或是繁殖用的？”西特尼科夫问我。

“既做坐骑，也为繁殖。”

“明白了，明白了，明白了。”马贩子抑扬顿挫地说，“彼佳，给这位先生看看那匹银鼠。”

我们来到院子里。

“要不要从屋里搬出个凳子坐坐？……不要？……那随您便。”

马蹄在木板上嗒嗒地响着，一声鞭子，那个四十岁左右、麻脸而黝黑的伙计彼佳牵着一匹体态匀称的灰色公马从马厩里跳了出来，让马用后腿直立了一会儿，又带着它在院子里跑了两圈，然后灵活地让马停下来供客人细看。银鼠舒展一下身子，打了一声响鼻，翘起尾巴，转过头，瞟了我们一下。

“这家伙训练得真不错！”我心想。

“让它随便动动，让它随便动动。”西特尼科夫说，一边凝视着我。

“您看怎么样？”他终于问道。

“马不赖，可两只前腿靠不大住。”

“腿都棒着呢！”西特尼科夫很有把握地回答说，“还有那屁股……您瞧瞧……宽得像炕似的，简直可以睡人。”

“蹄腕骨长了些。”

“长什么呀，瞧您说的！让它跑跑，彼佳，让它跑跑，让大步跑，大步跑，大步跑……不要让跳。”

彼佳又带着银鼠在院中跑起来。我们都没有说什么。

“好了，牵它进去吧，”西特尼科夫说，“把那匹鹰给我们牵来。”

鹰是匹像甲虫似的乌黑色的荷兰种公马，臀部下垂，躯体瘦而壮，看起来比银鼠强一点。它属于猎人们所说的“可劈、可砍、可控”那一类的马，也就是说，它们跑动起来，前边两腿向左右扭动，前进的步子不大。中年商人们很欣赏这样的马，因为它们跑起来活像机灵的茶房的潇洒步态；饭后出去溜达，让这种马单独拉车倒是很不错的：它们拉起做工粗糙的轻便马车，载着饱得动不了的马车夫，胃里烧得难受的气喘吁吁的商人，穿着淡蓝绸衣、披着紫头巾的虚胖的商人老婆，一路转动着脖子，晃晃悠悠，挺卖力气。我也不要这匹鹰。西特尼科夫又让我看了几匹马……最后我看上一匹伏叶科夫种的带圆斑点的灰马。我忍不住了，高兴地拍了拍它的脖子。西特尼科夫立刻装出不在乎的样子。

“怎么样，它拉车行吗？”我问。（谈到大走马，都不说它跑得怎样。）

“行呀。”马贩子泰然地回答。

“可不可以试一试？……”

“当然可以。喂，库济亚，把追风马套上车。”

驯马人库济亚是个行家，他驾着车在马路上跑了三四回，每次都经过我们眼前。这马跑得不错，步子不乱，屁股不往上蹶，运脚自如，尾巴翘开，跑起来很稳当。

“这马您要什么价？”

西特尼科夫漫天要价。我们就在马路上讨价还价起来，冷不防有一辆套着搭配得当的三匹马的驿车从拐弯处朝我们辚辚地奔驰过来，挺气派地停在西特尼科夫家大门口。坐在这辆狩猎用的豪华马车上的就是那位公爵，立在他旁边的是赫洛帕科夫。驾车的人就是那个巴克拉加……驾得多帅呀！真像是他驾车连耳环也通得过，好小子！两匹拉梢马小巧灵活，长着乌黑的眼睛、乌黑的腿，跑得那么带劲，那么矫健；只要一声吆喝，就会跑得见不到影！那匹深褐色辕马像天鹅似的仰着脖子，挺着胸膛，四腿像箭一般直，不时地晃晃脑袋，高傲地眯着眼睛……多帅气呀！即使是伊万·瓦西里耶维奇[4]在复活节出游乘坐的马车也不过如此呀。

“大驾光临，欢迎欢迎！”西特尼科夫喊了起来。

公爵跳下马车。赫洛帕科夫从另一边慢悠悠地走下车来。

“你好，伙计……有马吗？”

“大人您要马，怎能没有呢！请进来……彼佳，把孔雀牵出来！让他们把那匹大伙夸也准备好。先生，您的事嘛，”他转身又朝我说，“咱们另找时间再商定……福姆卡，给公爵大人拿一张凳子来。”

那匹孔雀是从一个特设的马厩里牵出来的，那马厩我先头没有注意到。这匹强壮的深枣红色马竟能这样四腿腾空。西特尼科夫竟转过头去，眯起了眼睛。

“嘿，勒拉卡利翁！”赫洛帕科夫欢呼起来，“热姆萨（我喜欢它）。”

公爵笑了起来。

费了好大劲才使孔雀停下来；它一直拖着马夫在院子里跑；最后才把它逼到墙边。它打着响鼻，身子抖嗦着，有些畏缩了，而西特尼科夫还逗弄它，朝它挥鞭子。

“朝哪儿瞧？看我整治你！哦！”马贩子亲切地吓唬它说，一面情不自禁地欣赏起自己的马。

“多少钱？”公爵问。

“大人要，就五千吧。”

“三千。”

“不行呀，大人，请原谅……”

“对你说，三千，勒拉卡利翁。”赫洛帕科夫插嘴说。

我没有等谈完交易就走了。在马路一头的拐角处，我看到一座浅灰色小房子的大门上贴着一大张纸。纸的上方有钢笔画的马，尾巴像烟囱似的竖着，脖子老长老长，马蹄下边有甲古体写的几行字：

此处有各种毛色之马匹出售。此处马匹均是从唐波夫地主阿纳斯塔塞·伊万内奇·车尔诺巴依之著名草原养马场运到列别江集市来的。皆属体格优良之马，训练完善，脾性温顺。请买主先生同阿纳斯塔塞·伊万内奇本人商洽；如阿纳斯塔塞·伊万内奇不在，可同马夫纳扎尔·库贝什金商洽。买主先生，请对老汉多多关照！

我停下脚步。心里想，那就去看一看著名的草原养马场场主车尔诺巴依先生的马吧。

我想从边门进去，可是与平常不一样，这边门是闩着的。我敲了敲门。

“是哪位呀？……是买主吗？”一个女人尖声地问。

“是的。”

“马上来，先生，马上来。”

边门开了。我看见的是一个五十来岁的婆娘，没有披头巾，脚穿靴子，皮袄敞开着。

“请进吧，主顾，我马上就去告诉阿纳斯塔塞·伊万内奇……纳扎尔，喂，纳扎尔！”

“什么事？”一个七十岁老头的含糊声音从马厩里传来。

“把马匹准备好；买主上门了。”

那老妇人向屋里跑去了。

“买主，买主，”纳扎尔埋怨地回答她说，“我洗马尾巴还没有全洗完呢。”

“嘿，好一个清静所在呀！”我心想。

“你好，先生，欢迎光临。”我背后慢慢传来一个响亮而悦耳的声音。我转身一瞧，我跟前站着一个穿蓝色长襟大衣的中等身材的老头，满头白发，脸带亲切的微笑，有一双漂亮的蓝眼睛。

“你要买马？请吧，先生，请吧……要不要先到我屋里喝杯茶？”

我谢绝了。

“好，悉听尊便。请原谅，先生，我是按老规矩办事。（车尔诺巴依先生说话不慌不忙，突出ó音[5]。）你知道，我这儿一切都很简单随便……纳扎尔，喂，纳扎尔。”他又用长声喊了一句，没有提高嗓门。

纳扎尔是个满脸皱纹的老头，长着鹰钩鼻和楔形大胡子，他在马厩门口出现了。

“先生，你要什么样的马呢？”车尔诺巴依接着问。

“不要太贵的，拉车用。”

“好的，有这种用的马，好的……纳扎尔，纳扎尔，把那匹灰骟马牵来给老爷看看，知道吗，就是站在最边上的那一匹，还有那匹额头有白斑的枣红马，要不，牵美娘所生的那匹枣红马，知道吗？”

纳扎尔转身回到马厩里。

“你就拉着笼头把它们牵出来吧，”车尔诺巴依朝着他喊，“先生，我这儿，”他用明亮而温和的目光望着我的脸，一边继续说，“可不像旁的马贩子一样，他们尽是骗人！那些人给马喂各种各样的姜，喂酒糟和盐[6]，简直胡来！……在我这儿，你一切都看得明明白白，我们不会骗人。”

牵出了两匹马。我都不喜欢。

“咳，那就把它们牵回去吧。”阿纳斯塔塞·伊万内奇说，“牵别的马来给我们看看。”

给我看了另外几匹马。我终于选定一匹便宜一些的马。我们开始谈价钱。车尔诺巴依先生不急不躁，说话在理，还一本正经地指天发誓，所以我就不能不对这位老头“多多关照”了：我付了定金。

“好了，现在，”阿纳斯塔塞·伊万内奇说，“让我按老规矩把马缰绳从我的衣裾里交到你的衣裾里……你会为得到这匹马而感谢我的……多神气的马呀！结实得像胡桃……没受过半点伤……道地的草原马！配什么马具都行。”

他画了个十字，把自己的大衣襟衬在手上，抓住马笼头，把马交给我。

“现在马就是你的了……要喝杯茶吗？”

“不，多谢您了，我该回去了。”

“那请便……现在就让我的马夫跟着你把马送去吗？”

“是的，如果行的话，现在就走吧。”

“好的，先生，好的……瓦西利，喂，瓦西利，跟老爷一道去；把马送去，把钱收来。再见吧，先生，上帝保佑你。”

“再见，阿纳斯塔塞·伊万内奇。”

给我把马送到了住处。第二天一瞧，这马原来是有气肿病的，而且腿又瘸。我本想把它套上车，可是这匹马一个劲儿往后退；用鞭子抽它，它却发起倔来，又踢又踹，而且躺倒不干了。我只好立刻去找车尔诺巴依先生。我问：

“在家吗？”

“在家。”

“您这是搞的什么呀，”我说，“把一匹患气肿病的马卖给我。”

“患气肿病？……哪会呢！”

“它还瘸腿呢，而且倔得很。”

“瘸腿？我不知道，显然是你的车夫不知怎么把它弄伤了……苍天在上，我不瞎说……”

“按道理，阿纳斯塔塞·伊万内奇，您应该把这匹马收回。”

“不，先生，您别生气：马一出这家门，买卖就算了结啦。事先你该看清楚嘛。”

我明白是怎么回事了，只好自认倒霉，笑了笑，就回来了。幸亏我为这次教训付的代价不算太大。

两三天后我就离开了。过了一星期，我在回家路上又顺便来到列别江。我在咖啡厅里见到的几乎还是那一伙人，又看到那位公爵在打台球。可是赫洛帕科夫先生的命运已发生了如往常一样的变化。那位淡黄发的小军官已取代他享受公爵的恩宠了。可怜的退职陆军中尉当着我的面又把自己的口头语试了试，以为可能如以前那样招人喜欢，可是公爵非但没有笑，反而皱起眉头，耸了耸肩膀。赫洛帕科夫耷拉下脑袋，缩起身子，躲到屋角里，不声不响地替自己装起烟斗……

[1]希腊神话中的人物。

[2]这是法语的译音。意为：这是什么。

[3]原文是ррраяалиооoн，是раĸалия（坏蛋、无赖）的讹音。

[4]即伊万雷帝。

[5]此处指他的方言发音，即把非重音的o都念成重读的o。

[6]喂酒糟和盐，马会迅速上膘。——作者原注

塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜和她的侄儿

亲爱的读者，让我们携着手，一块儿乘车去游玩吧。天气好极了；五月的天空蓝盈盈的；爆竹柳光滑的嫩叶仿佛冲洗过似的，亮亮闪闪；宽阔平坦的大路上长满了带红茎的小草，那是绵羊最可心的食物；在左右两边山冈的长长的缓坡上，轻轻地荡漾着绿葱葱的黑麦；一小片一小片的云影在黑麦上晃动着稀稀落落的斑点。放眼远眺，可看见一片片黑乎乎的树林、一个个闪烁的池塘，一座座黄灿灿的村庄。大群大群的云雀腾空而起，歌唱着，又拼死劲地冲下来，伸长脖子，昂立在一个个小土块上；一只只白嘴鸦停歇在大路上，瞅着我们，身子紧贴着地面，让我们的车子驶过去，然后蹦了几下，不大甘心地飞到一边去；在峡谷对面的山上，有一个庄稼人在耕田；一匹短尾巴、鬃毛蓬松的花斑马驹腿脚不稳地跟在它母亲后边跑，可以听得见它的细声细气的嘶喊。我们的车子驶进一片白桦林；浓烈的清新气息沁人心脾。车子已来到一个村口的栅栏处了。车夫跳下车，马儿们喷着响鼻，拉梢马东张西望，辕马甩着尾巴，把头靠在轭上……栅栏门轧轧地打开了。车夫又坐上车……走吧！前面便是村庄了。跑过了五六户人家，我们便往右拐，下到一处洼地，又跑上一个堤坝。在一个不很大的池塘的另一边，在苹果树和丁香树的圆圆的树梢后边，可看到一座木屋的先前曾是红色的木板屋顶，还有两个烟囱；车夫让车子沿着围墙往左跑，在三只老朽的长毛狗沙哑的尖叫声中，把车子驶进了那敞开着的大门，在宽敞的院落里威风地兜了个圈，经过马厩和库房时，他向一个侧身迈过一道高门槛走进贮藏室敞着的门里去的老管家婆文雅地鞠一下躬，终于把车子停在一个带有明亮的窗子可外表黑乎乎的小屋的台阶前……我们已来到塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜家了。瞧，她亲自打开了通风窗，朝我们点头招呼了……您好呀，大娘！

塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜是位五十岁上下的女人，有一对又大又突的大眼睛，鼻子有点扁，脸颊红润，双重下巴。脸上露着慈爱可亲的神情。她从前嫁过人，可不久便守寡了。塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜是个极不平凡的女人。她住在自家的小田庄上，深居简出，很少和邻里交往，然而挺喜欢一些青年后生。她出生于一个相当贫寒的地主之家，没有受过什么教育，换句话说，她不会讲法语；甚至连莫斯科也没有去过——话说回来，尽管有这种种不足之处，可她为人质朴、善良，思想感情方面也很开放，甚少染有小地主婆们习见的通病，这着实令人惊异不已……一个妇道人家长年蜗居于穷乡僻壤之地，却不搬弄是非，不叽叽喳喳，不低三下四，不冲动，不压抑，不因好奇而急得打哆嗦……真可说是一种奇迹！她平日穿一身塔夫绸连衣裙，戴一顶淡紫色飘带的白色便帽；她很好吃，但不食之过饱；蜜饯、干果、腌菜之类都交托给女管家去制作。那么您会问，她成天做些什么呢？……看书吗？不，她不看书；说真的，书籍不是为她而出版的……如果没有客人来访，我这位塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜冬天就坐在窗下织袜子；夏天则到花园里，种种花、浇浇水，一连几小时逗着小猫玩，喂喂鸽子……她家务干得很少。但如果有客人来，有她所喜欢的邻近的年轻人来，那塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜的精神头也就来了；招呼客人落座，请他喝茶，听他谈天说地，冲他笑，有时还拍拍他的脸颊，可是她自个儿不大说话；人家有了不幸和痛心的事，她就给以安慰，给以善意的忠告。有多少人向她倾吐自家的隐私、内心的秘密，伏在她手上哭泣！她常常跟客人面对面地坐着，轻轻地支着胳膊，那么关切地瞅着客人的眼睛，那么友爱地微笑着，使客人不由得想：“您是个何等真诚的女人啊，塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜！让我把心里的话掏出来对你说说吧。”在她的几个小巧而安适的房间里，人们都感到又温馨又舒坦；她家里的天气总是晴朗的，如果可以这样形容的话。塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜是个好得令人惊异的女人，可是没有谁对她感到惊异。她的清醒的头脑，她的坚强和豁达，她对旁人的悲欢的热情关怀，总之，她的种种美德似乎是与生俱来的，她没有花费什么气力和辛苦就获得的……不可能把她想象成为另外的样子，所以，也用不到去感谢她。她特别喜欢瞧年轻人在那里嬉戏和玩闹；她把双手交叉在胸前，仰着头，眯着眼睛，坐在那里微笑着，有时忽然叹息一声说：“唉，你们呀，我的孩子们，孩子们！……”所以，人们往往很想走到她跟前，拉住她的手说：“请听我说，塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜，您不知道自己的可贵，虽然您非常单纯，没念过什么书，可您是个很不寻常的人哪！”光是她的名字便带有某种熟悉、亲切的味道，人们都乐于听到她的名字，她的名字会引起人们友善的微笑。比如，我有好几次在途中向遇到的庄稼人问路：“老乡，到格拉乔夫卡怎么走呀？”他就会说：“先生，您先到维亚佐沃耶，再从那边到塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜那儿，塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜那边的任何人都会指给您路的。”庄稼人在提到塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜这名字的时候，都带点特别意味地点点头。她的家业不大，用的仆人不多。住屋、洗衣房、贮藏室和厨房都交给女管家阿加菲娅去料理。这位女管家曾当过她的保姆，是个非常善良的、爱哭鼻子的、没了牙齿的老婆子。归她调遣的有两个身健力壮的丫头，她们的脸宛如安东诺夫苹果，坚坚实实，又红得发紫。已年届古稀的老仆波利卡尔普担任侍仆、管事，并兼管餐室的事务。这老头古怪得很，挺有学识，是一个退职的小提琴手，很崇拜维奥第[1]，可对拿破仑很仇恨（称他为波拿巴季什卡[2]），另外对夜莺十分着迷。他在自己的屋里常养着五六只夜莺；早春时节，他会在鸟笼旁坐上好几天，等候夜莺的第一声“啼啭”，一等到后，便双手掩面，呻吟地说：“唉，可怜呀，可怜呀！”继而放声大哭，泪流如注。波利卡尔普身边有一个帮手，那就是他的孙子瓦夏，这是个十一二岁的孩子，一头鬈发，眼睛水灵灵的；波利卡尔普对这孙子疼爱至极，从早到晚跟他叨咕个没完。他还要管孙子的教育。“瓦夏，”他说，“你说，波拿巴季什卡是强盗。”“那你给我什么呀，爷爷？”“给你什么？……什么也不给……要知道你是什么人？你是不是俄国人？”“我是阿姆琴人，爷爷，是在阿姆琴斯克[3]生的。”“哦，笨蛋！阿姆琴斯克又是在哪儿呢？”“那我怎么知道呀？”“阿姆琴斯克是在俄国嘛，笨蛋。”“在俄国又怎么样呀？”“怎么样？已经故世的斯摩棱斯克公爵大人米海洛·伊拉里奥诺维奇·戈列尼谢夫－库图佐夫在上帝的帮助下，把波拿巴季什卡从俄国国土上赶了出去。关于这件事还编了一首歌呢：‘波拿巴跳不了舞了，他把吊袜带走丢了……’你要懂得，是公爵解救了你的祖国。”“这关我什么事呢？”“唉，你这笨孩子，真笨！假如不是米海洛·伊拉里奥诺维奇公爵把波拿巴季什卡赶了出去，如今就会有法国佬拿着棍子来敲你的脑瓜了。他会走到你跟前说：‘科曼……武……波尔捷……武？[4]’接着就会啪啪地揍你一顿。”“那我用拳头揍他的肚子。”“他会对你说：‘彭茹，彭茹，维涅……伊西[5]’——就会揪住你的头发，揪得紧紧的。”“那我就踢他的腿，狠狠地踢，踢他那疙里疙瘩的腿。”“这说对了，他们的腿都是疙里疙瘩的……可是他要把你的手捆起来，那怎么办呢？”“我才不让他捆呢，我会叫马车夫米海依来帮我。”“可是要知道，瓦夏，你和米海依对付不了法国佬，那怎么办？”“哪会对付不了？米海依力气大着呢！”“那你们要拿法国佬怎么样呢？”“我们就敲他的脊梁，狠狠地敲。”“那他就要喊：‘帕东，帕东，塞武普莱[6]！’”“那我们就对他说：‘就不对你塞武普莱，你这个法国佬！……”“好样的，瓦夏！……那你就喊：‘波拿巴季什卡是强盗！’”“那你就给我糖吧！”“瞧这小子！……”

塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜同女地主们很少往来；她们不高兴上她家做客，她也不善于与她们应酬，听着她们叽叽喳喳地瞎聊，她就要打瞌睡，振作一下，使劲睁开眼睛，可又打起瞌睡来。一般说来，塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜不喜欢女人。她有一位朋友，是个很老实很不错的年轻人，他有一位姐姐是个三十八岁半的老姑娘，心眼非常好，可是有点心理变态，有些矫揉造作，容易冲动。她弟弟常向她谈起这位女乡亲的事。有一天早晨，这位老姑娘半句话也没说，便叫人给她备马，骑上马就奔塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜家来了。她穿一身长长的连衣裙，戴着帽子，蒙着绿色面纱，披散着鬈发，进入前室，经过把她当作人鱼而吓蒙了的瓦夏身旁，直入客厅。塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜吓得够呛，本想站起身来，可两腿已发软了。“塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜，”这位女客用恳求的声调说起来，“请恕我冒昧；我是您的朋友阿列克塞·尼古拉耶维奇·克×××的姐姐，我从他那里听说了许多关于您的事，所以决定前来拜识您。”“非常欢迎。”受惊的女主人喃喃地说。客人摘下帽子，甩了甩鬈发，便挨着塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜坐下来，握住她的手……“看来，这就是她，”她用深思的、感动的声音说了起来，“这就是那个善良、开朗、高尚、神圣的人！这就是那个单纯而又深沉的女人！我多么高兴，我多么高兴啊！我们以后会互相敬爱的！我终于放下心了……我想象中的她正是这样，”她盯看着塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜的眼睛，低声地补充说，“您真的不生我的气吗，我的善心人，我的好人？”“哪儿的话呀，我很高兴……您要不要喝点茶？”客人谦逊地微微一笑。“Wie wahr, wie unreflectirt[7]，”她轻声地说，仿佛是自言自语，“请允许我拥抱您，我亲爱的朋友！”

这位老姑娘在塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜家坐了三个小时，嘴巴半刻不停地叨叨着。她竭力向这位新相识讲解她本人的价值。这位不速之客走后，晦气的女主人立即去洗了澡，喝了不少椴树花茶，便上床躺着了。到了第二天，这位老姑娘又来了，一坐就是四个小时，临走时还说，以后天天都要前来拜访塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜。要知道，她是想让这个如她所说的具有丰富天性的女人得到充分的发展，想弥补其教育上的不足。倘若真的这样下去，那非把这位女主人折磨死不可，幸亏情况起了变化：首先，过了两三个星期，这位老姑娘对自己弟弟的女朋友“完全”失望了；第二，她爱上了一个过路的年轻大学生，立即跟他殷勤而热烈地通起信来；她在信中一般都祝愿他过神圣而美好的生活，表示要牺牲“整个自己”，只要求他称她为姐姐；她很投入地去描写大自然，并大谈歌德、席勒、培堤那和德国哲学——终于使这个可怜的年轻人陷于悲观失望之中。可是青春的力量还是胜利了：一天晨，他怀着对这个“姐姐和好朋友”的极大气愤和憎恨醒来了，由于心里有火，他差一点儿把自己的侍仆痛揍一顿；后来在很长的时间里，只要听到人家稍稍谈到崇高而无私的爱情，他便气得几乎要把那人吃了……打那以后，塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜就比以前更加不愿意跟自己的女邻里们交往了。

唉！世上哪有永恒不变的事呀。我对诸位所讲的这位善良女地主的日常生活情况都是过去的事了；她家中过去的那一派宁静气氛已永远被打破了。如今她家里住着一个侄儿，是从彼得堡来的一个美术家，他在这里已住了一年多了，事情是这样的。

七八年以前，塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜家里寄养着一个失去了双亲的十一二岁的孤儿，这是她亡兄的儿子，名叫安德留沙。安德留沙长有一双明亮的水灵的大眼睛、小小的嘴巴、端正的鼻子、漂亮的高高的额门。他说话的嗓音轻柔而甜美，外表整洁，举止得体，待客亲切而殷勤，常怀着孤儿的敏感去吻姑母的手。常常是客人刚刚进门，他已把椅子给客人端过来了。他从不调皮捣蛋，总是文文静静；他坐在角落里读书写字，显得那么谦恭、安分，甚至不把身子靠在椅背上。有客人进来，安德留沙就站起身来，有礼貌地笑笑，脸泛红晕；客人离去了，他又坐下来，从衣兜里掏出带小镜子的刷子，梳梳自己的头发。他打小便爱画画。他只要得到一小片纸，便立即向女管家阿格菲娅要来剪刀，把纸细心地剪成正四方形，给四周画上边，就画起画来：画一只带大瞳孔的眼睛，或画一个又高又直的鼻子，或画一座有烟囱的、还冒出缕缕炊烟的房子，或画一只像长凳似的“en face”[8]的狗，画一棵停着两只鸽子的小树，在下边题上字：“安德列[9]·别洛夫佐罗夫画，某年某月某日，于小布雷基村。”在塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜的命名日到来之前，他特别用心地画了两三个星期的画。到了那一天，他第一个前去祝贺，并呈上一束扎着玫瑰色带子的小画卷。塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜亲了侄儿的前额，解开了带子：小画卷展开了，呈现在姑母的好奇目光前的是一座圆形的、笔墨生动的殿堂，带有一排廊柱，中央是祭坛，祭坛上燃烧着一颗心，还有一个花冠；在上边，在弯弯曲曲的封带上，用工整的字体写着：“献给姑妈和恩人塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜·鲍格达诺娃，以表最深切的挚爱之情。尊敬和热爱您的侄儿赠。”塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜又吻了吻他，并赠他一个银卢布。然而她对这个侄儿并没有多大的挚爱：她不很喜欢安德留沙的这种阿谀奉承的表现。这时候安德留沙渐渐长大了；塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜开始为他的前程操心了。一个意外的机会使她摆脱了困境……

情况是这样的：大约七八年前，她家有一天来了一位贵客，他就是六品文官和勋章获得者彼得·米海雷奇·别涅沃连斯基先生。别涅沃连斯基先生从前曾在附近的县城里任职，那时他常来看望塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜；后来他迁往彼得堡，并入了内阁，谋得了要职。他常常因公出差，有一回在出差途中他想起了这位旧相识，就顺便前来她家，想在“乡村幽静生活的怀抱”里休息两天，消除一下公务的烦心。塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜以她平素的好客热情招待了他，于是别涅沃连斯基先生……不过，在继续讲这故事之前，亲爱的读者，让我先向诸位介绍一下这位新的人物吧。

别涅沃连斯基先生是个胖胖的中等身材的人，面相温和，两腿短短的，两手肥肥的；他穿一件非常整洁的宽松的燕尾服，高高地系着一条宽领带，衬衫雪白，绸坎肩上挂着一根金链，食指上戴着一个宝石戒指，头上罩着浅黄色假发；言谈恳切而温和，走路没有声响，开心地微笑，开心地转动眼睛，开心地把下巴垂到领带上，总之，是个很开心的人。上天也给了他一副极慈善的心肠：他易于掉泪，也易于狂喜；此外，他对艺术也燃烧着一腔无私的热情，确实是无私的热情，因为，如果照实说，别涅沃连斯基先生对于艺术恰恰是一窍不通的。令人惊奇的是，他的这种热情是从哪儿来的呢？是哪些神秘莫解的法则所使然吗？看起来他也是个讲实际的，甚至很普通的人……话说回来，在我们俄国，这样的人多着呢。

对美术和美术家的喜爱使这些人带有一种说不出的甜腻劲；同他们往来，同他们交谈，那可够人受的：他们简直是一种涂了蜜的木棍。比如说吧，他们从来不把拉斐尔叫拉斐尔，不把科累佐叫科累佐[10]，他们总是说“神圣的桑齐奥，无与伦比的德·阿莱格里斯”，而且必定把所有的o都发成ó音。那些不很高明、自命不凡、滑头滑脑、平平庸庸的画家往往被他们捧为天才，或者更确切说，被捧为“铁（天）才”；他们的嘴老离不开什么“意大利的蓝天”“南国的柠檬”“布伦塔河畔的芳香”，等等。“唉，瓦尼亚，瓦尼亚，”或“唉，萨沙，萨沙，”他们常相互深情地说，“咱们应该到南国去，到南国去……咱们在心灵上都是希腊人，古希腊人！”可以看一看他们在展览会上，在某些俄国画家的某些作品前面的那副神情。（应该指出，这些先生大都是热烈的爱国者。）有时他们退后一两步，仰着头，有时又走近画面；他们的眼睛老显得油亮亮、湿乎乎的……“啊，我的天哪，”他们终于用激动得发颤的声音说，“有灵魂，有灵魂呀！啊，心灵呀，心灵呀！充满灵气！多么有灵气呀！……多好的构思！构思真巧呀！”而且他们自家的客厅里挂的又是些什么样的画呀！每天晚上去他们家里喝茶，听他们海聊的又是些什么样的美术家呀！而他们拿给这些美术家看的自己房间的透视图景又是什么呀：右边是一个刷子，锃亮的地板上有一堆垃圾，窗边桌子上摆着一个黄色的茶炊，还有主人自己，他穿着便服，头戴小帽，脸颊上还映出明亮的光点！那些来拜访他们的头发长长、面带轻狂笑容的缪斯后裔们又是些什么人啊！在他们的钢琴旁边尖声怪叫的脸色苍白铁青的小姐们又是些什么人呀！由于在我们俄国已经形成这样的风气：一个人不能只沉迷于一种艺术，什么都得享受。所以毫不奇怪这些痴迷艺术的先生们对于俄国文学，尤其对于戏剧都给予大力支持……《贾科贝·萨纳扎尔》一类的作品就是为这些先生们而写的：得不到认可的天才跟世人和整个世俗的那种被描写过千百次的斗争深深触动他们的灵魂……

别涅沃连斯基先生到来的第二天，在饮茶的时候，塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜叫侄儿拿他的画来给客人看看。“他在您这儿画画？”别涅沃连斯基先生不免惊讶地问道，并带着关切的神情朝安德留沙转过身。“可不是，他在画画，”塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜说，“他可喜欢画画啦！他自己画，没有老师教。”“啊，给我看看，给我看看。”别涅沃连斯基先生接着说。安德留沙脸红了，微笑着，把自己的小画册递给客人。别涅沃连斯基装作很内行的样子翻看着画册。“很好嘛，年轻人，”最后他说，“很好，非常之好。”他抚摸了一下安德留沙的头。安德留沙赶紧吻了吻他的手。“您瞧，多有才气呀！……恭喜您，塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜，恭喜您。”“可是，彼得·米海雷奇，这儿给他请不到老师。到城里请又太贵。邻近的阿尔塔莫夫家倒是有一位画家，听说挺棒的，可是那家女主人不准他给别人教课。说是会败坏自己的趣味。”“哦，”别涅沃连斯基先生应了一声，沉思起来，皱起眉头瞧了瞧安德留沙，“好，这事咱们等会儿商量商量。”他忽然补充了一句，并搓了搓手。就在当天，他请塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜跟他单独谈一谈。他们关起门来。半小时之后，他们招呼安德留沙前来。安德留沙进来了。别涅沃连斯基先生站在窗前，脸上微微泛红，眼睛闪亮。塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜坐在角落里，抹着眼泪。“啊，安德留沙，”她终于开口说话，“你要谢谢彼得·米海雷奇：他要培养你，带你去彼得堡。”安德留沙站在原地发愣了。“您对我坦率地说说，”别涅沃连斯基先生开始以充满尊严和垂怜的口吻说，“你想不想当艺术家，年轻人，你有没有感到对艺术负有神圣的使命？”“我很想成为艺术家，彼得·米海雷奇。”安德留沙胆怯地回答说。“你这样想我很高兴。当然啰，”别涅沃连斯基先生继续说，“你离开你尊敬的姑妈是会很难过的；你一定对她怀有深切的感激之情。“我十分热爱我的姑妈。”安德留沙打断他的话说，并眨巴起眼睛。“那当然，那当然，这是很可理解的嘛，对你也应大加称赞；不过，将来你有了成就……那将会多么高兴……”“拥抱我吧，安德留沙。”这位慈善的女地主喃喃地说。安德留沙扑过去搂住她的脖子。“好啦，现在去谢谢你的恩人吧……”安德留沙搂住别涅沃连斯基先生的肚子，踮起脚尖，才勉强够着他的手，恩人确实把手缩回去，可没有过急地缩回……总该让孩子高兴点，让他满意点，也可以让自己开心。过了两三天，别涅沃连斯基先生便带着自己新收养的孩子离去了。

在别离后的头三年里，安德留沙频频地写信回来，有时还在信里附一些画。别涅沃连斯基先生偶尔也在信上附上几句话，大都是赞扬性的话；后来信写得少了，越来越少了，最后干脆就没有了。整整一年里侄儿的音信杳然；塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜已经放不下心，突然她收到一封短简，内容如下：

亲爱的姑妈！

我的保护人彼得·米海洛维奇[11]已于三天前病故了。残酷的中风使我失去了这位最后的靠山。当然，我今年已快二十岁了；在过去的七年里我做出了一些出色的成绩；我深信自己具有才华，并可借此为生；我没有灰心，不过，如果可能的话，请您尽快汇给我二百五十卢布。吻您的手，其他待以后再叙。

塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜就给侄儿汇去了二百五十卢布。过了两个月，他又来信要钱；她把手头仅有的钱凑足数，又给他汇去了。第二次汇出款之后，还不到六个星期，他又第三次来信要钱，说是要买颜料，替捷尔捷列舍涅娃公爵夫人画一幅预定的肖像画。塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜这次没有给钱。“要是这样的话，”他又给她来信说，“我想到您的村子里养一养身子。”就在这一年的五月，安德留沙真的回到了小布雷基村。

塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜起初认不出他来了。从他的来信推想，她以为他是个瘦弱有病的人，但看到的却是一个肩宽体胖的小伙子，长着一张红润的宽脸庞，一头油亮亮的鬈发。瘦小苍白的安德留沙已变成了一个壮健的安德列·伊万诺夫[12]·别洛夫佐罗夫。他不光是外表上变了。从前那种本分、腼腆、谨慎、整洁不见了，换成了马虎、蛮横和令人受不了的邋遢；他走起路来大摇大摆，往安乐椅里一靠，往桌子上一趴，伸开四肢懒洋洋地躺着，大声地打呵欠；对姑妈、对仆人都很粗鲁。他说，我是艺术家，是自由的哥萨克！要知道我们是与众不同的！常常一连几天不动一笔；一旦所谓灵感来了，便装腔作势，像是喝醉了酒似的，又难过，又笨拙，又吵闹；两颊烧得红彤彤，两眼蒙蒙眬眬；大吹自己的才华、自己的成就，吹自己如何发展，如何前进……其实，论能力，他只配勉强画画一般的肖像画。他十分的无知，什么书也不去读，艺术家还读书干吗呀？大自然、自由、诗歌——就是他的灵感之源。只要晃晃鬈发，学学夜莺叫，吸吸茹可夫烟就行了！俄罗斯人的豪放固然是好，但它只适合于很少的人；而二把刀的缺乏才气的波列扎耶夫[13]之流是叫人受不了的。这位安德列·伊万诺维奇就赖在姑妈家了，白吃的面包显然很对他的胃口。他往往使客人感到无聊得要命。他常常坐在钢琴前（塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜家里也有钢琴），用一根指头摸索着弹起《勇敢的三套马车》；敲着琴键，配奏和音；一连几小时痛苦地哼唱瓦尔拉莫夫的情歌《孤独的松树》或《不，医生，你不要来》，眼睛下边肥得流油，脸颊如鼓一般油光光的……或者，猛的一声狂喊“平息吧，激情的浪涛”……塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜听了直发抖。

“事情真怪啦，”她有一次对我说，“当今编的歌怎么都是丧里丧气的，我们那个时候编的歌就不一样，悲伤的歌也有，可听起来总是很舒服的……比如：

来呀，到草地上找我来，
我在这儿把你徒然盼待；
来呀，到草地上找我来，
我整天在这儿流泪……
唉，待你真到草地上找我来，
我的朋友，恐怕我人已不在！

塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜调皮地微笑了一下。

“我痛——苦，我痛——苦呀。”侄儿在隔壁房间大喊起来。

“你得啦，安德留沙。”

“别离之时心悲怆。”不肯安静的歌手继续唱道。

塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜摇摇头。

“唉，这种艺术家真够我受的！……”

打那时候起已过去一年了。别洛夫佐罗夫至今还住在姑妈家里，并一直打算上彼得堡去。他在乡下更加发胖了。谁能想到呢，姑妈对他疼爱极了，邻近一带的丫头们都对他着了迷……

昔日的许多朋友已不再来登塔季雅娜·鲍里索夫娜家的门了。

[1]维奥第（一七五三——一八二四），意大利小提琴家。

[2]拿破仑的名字叫波拿巴，波拿巴季什卡是其卑称。

[3]当地称姆岑斯克为阿姆琴斯克，称当地居民为阿姆琴人。阿姆琴人生性勇猛，所以我们那里的人常警告仇人说“阿姆琴人要登门了”。——作者原注

[4]法语的俄译音：你好吗？

[5]法语的俄译音：你好，你好，到这儿来。

[6]法语的俄译音：请您饶了我，饶了我吧！

[7]德语：多么真诚，多么直爽。

[8]法语：正面的。

[9]安德列是他的正式名字，安德留沙是安德列的小称或爱称。

[10]拉斐尔·桑齐奥（一四八三——一五二〇），科累佐·德·阿莱格里斯（一四九四——一五三四），都是意大利文艺复兴时期的画家。

[11]即米海雷奇的正式称呼。

[12]原文如此，可能是笔误，应该是伊万诺维奇。

[13]波列扎耶夫（一八〇四——一八三八），俄国诗人。

死

我有一个邻里，是一个年轻的地主，也是一个喜好打猎的年轻人。在七月里的一个晴朗的早晨，我骑着马去找他，约他一同去猎松鸡。他答应了。“不过，”他说，“咱们就顺着我家那片小树林去到祖沙；我要顺便去瞧一瞧恰普雷吉诺；您知道我的那个橡树林吧？我正让人在那边伐树呢。”“那就去吧。”他便吩咐备马。他穿上一件带野猪头像的铜纽扣的绿外衣，带上一个粗毛线猎袋和一个银水壶，扛上一只崭新的法国猎枪，得意地照了一通镜子，唤了一声自己的猎狗埃斯佩兰斯，这只狗是他的表姐、一个有好心肠而没有头发的老姑娘赠给他的。我们一起动身了。我这位邻里还带上两个跟班的，一个是甲长阿尔希普，是个矮矮胖胖的庄稼人，长着一张四方脸，颧骨特高；另一个是前不久从波罗的海沿岸省份雇来的管家戈特利勃·丰－德尔－科克先生，他是个近二十岁的青年人，身材瘦削，浅黄头发，高度近视眼，溜肩，长脖。这位邻里是新近才掌管这块领地的。这是他的一位伯母留给他的遗产。那伯母就是五品文官夫人卡尔东·卡塔耶娃，是个胖得出奇的女人，即使躺在床上，也难受得哎哟哎哟个没完。我们骑着马进入了小树林。“你们在这里空地上等我一会儿。”我的邻里阿尔达利翁·米海雷奇对自己的两个同伴说。那德国人鞠下躬，就下了马，从衣袋里掏出一本小书，似乎是约翰·叔本华的小说，在一丛灌木旁坐了下来；阿尔希普仍待在太阳光下，木然不动地待了一个小时。我们在灌木丛里转来转去，连一窝野禽也没有找到。阿尔达利翁·米海雷奇表示想到大树林去。那一天我自己都不相信会有什么好收获，也就勉强跟着他去了。我们回到了那块空地上。德国人标了一下书页，站起身来，把书放回衣袋，费劲地骑上了他那匹淘汰下来的短尾巴母马，这匹马只要稍稍一碰就要乱叫乱踢的；阿尔希普振了振精神，一下拽动两根缰绳，夹了夹两腿，终于使他那匹受惊的、被压得够呛的小马跑动起来。我们又动身了。

阿尔达利翁·米海雷奇的这片林子我从小便很熟悉。那时候我和我的那位极为善良的法国家庭教师德齐雷·弗勒利先生（可他每天晚上老让我喝列鲁阿药水，差点儿永远毁了我的健康）经常到恰普雷吉诺树林里游玩。这整片林子大约有两三百棵粗大的橡树和梣树。它们挺拔而粗壮的树干在榛树和花楸树的金灿灿、亮晶晶的绿叶中黑乎乎地屹立着，非常之美；树干高高地耸起，齐整地呈现在明朗的蓝空中，展开如帐篷般的宽阔而多节的枝丫；鹞鹰、青鹰、红隼在静止不动的树梢下飞来飞去，鸣声不绝，五颜六色的啄木鸟使劲地啄着厚实的树皮；随着黄鹂婉转的鸣声，突然在茂密的枝叶中响起了黑鸫的嘹亮鸣声；在下面的灌木丛里，知更鸟、黄雀和柳莺啾啾地啼唱着；燕雀在小径上敏捷地跑来跑去；雪兔小心地“一拐一拐地走着”，顺着林边悄悄前进；红褐色的松鼠淘气地从一棵树跳到另一棵上，突然坐了下来，把尾巴翘到头顶上。在草丛里，在高高的蚁蛭旁，在蕨类植物美丽如雕的叶子的淡影下，紫罗兰和铃兰在竞芳争妍，还长着红菇、乳菇、卷边乳菇、橡菇和红色蛤蟆菇；在草地里，在宽阔的灌木丛里，长着红艳艳的草莓……在林子里阴凉处何等舒坦呀！在最热的时候，在大中午，这儿就像夜间一般：寂静、芳香、清爽……我曾在恰普雷吉诺度过一段快乐的时光，所以，说真的，如今进到这片十分熟悉的树林，不免有些伤感。一八四〇年那个毁灭性的无雪的冬天，竟没有饶过我的老朋友——橡树和梣树；它们干枯了、光秃了，只有几处披着病弱的绿叶，它们悲哀地耸立在小树木的上空，那些小树木是来“接替它们的，可还接替不了”[1]……还有一些下边长满叶子的树木，似乎带着责备和绝望的神情向上挺起自己缺乏生气的、折断了的树枝；另有一些树的叶子虽然不及昔日那么繁茂，却还相当浓密，从这些树叶中伸出一根根粗大、干枯的死枝；还有一些树的树皮已经脱落了；还有一些树完全倒下了，像死尸似的在地上腐烂着。谁能料到呢，在恰普雷吉诺树林里竟找不到一处阴凉的地方！我望着那些即将死去的树，心里想，你们也许感到羞愧和痛心吧？……我想起了柯尔卓夫[2]的诗：

何处去了呀，
那高雅的谈吐，
那傲慢的劲头，
那皇家的气度？
如今安在呢，
那绿色的势头？……

“怎么搞的呀，阿尔达利翁·米海雷奇，”我开口问，“为什么在去年不把这些树砍掉呢？如今它们已卖不了以前十分之一的价钱了。”

他只是耸了耸肩膀。

“这得问我那位伯母了；一些商人揣着钱，找上门来，缠着要买呢。”

“Mein Gott！Mein Gott！”[3]丰－德尔－科克－步－叹，“多么淘气[4]！多么淘气！”

“怎么淘气？”我这位邻里笑着问。

“我是想梭（说），多么可希（惜）。”（我们知道，德国人在学会我们的字母“Л”的发音后，就把这字母读得特别重[5]。）

特别使他感到可惜的是那些倒在地上的一棵棵橡树——确实如此，要不然磨坊主就会出大价钱买它们的。可是甲长阿尔希普却无动于衷，毫不痛心；相反，他甚至在这些倒地的树木上挺开心地跳过来蹦过去的，还用鞭子抽打着玩。

我们向那伐树的地方慢慢走去，冷不防轰的一声倒下一棵树来，随着响起了呼喊声和说话声，过不多会儿，一个脸色苍白、头发蓬乱的年轻庄稼人从树林深处向我们跑来。

“怎么啦？你往哪儿跑？”阿尔达利翁·米海雷奇问他。

他立即停下脚步。

“哎呀，阿尔达利翁·米海雷奇老爷，大事不好了！”

“怎么回事？”

“老爷，马克西姆被树砸坏了。”

“怎么砸的？……是那个承包人马克西姆吗？”

“就是他，老爷。我们在砍一棵梣树，他站在一旁看……站着，站着，就到井边打水去，大概是想喝水。突然间梣树轧轧地响起来，直对着他倒下来。我们朝他大声喊：快躲开、快躲开、快躲开……要是他从旁边一闪就好了，可是他直着往前跑……准是吓慌了。

梣树树梢就压住了他。天知道为什么这棵树倒得这么急……兴许是树心已烂透了。”

“你是说把马克西姆砸坏了？”

“砸坏了，老爷。”

“死了吗？”

“没有，老爷，还活着呢——可是他的腿和胳膊都砸断了呀。我就是跑去请谢利韦斯特奇大夫的。”

阿尔达利翁·米海雷奇吩咐甲长骑马到村里请谢利韦斯特奇，自己则快马加鞭地奔向伐木地点……我也跟着他去。

我们看见可怜的马克西姆躺在地上。十来个庄稼人围在他的身旁。我们下了马。他几乎没有痛苦地哼哼，偶尔还把眼睛睁得老大，好像很惊异地瞧瞧周围，咬咬铁青的嘴唇……他的下巴在颤抖，头发黏在额头上，胸部忽快忽慢地起伏着：他快要死了。一棵年轻椴树的淡影在他的脸上轻轻地晃动着。

我们弯下腰看他。他认出了阿尔达利翁·米海雷奇。

“老爷，”他以听不大清的声音说起话来，“您派人……去请……牧师吧……上帝……惩罚我……腿、胳膊都砸断了……今天……是礼拜天……可是我……可是我……却没有让弟兄们歇着。”

他沉默了一会儿。他憋得喘不上气。

“请把我的钱……交给我老婆……我老婆……扣掉欠的……奥尼西姆清楚……我欠了……谁的钱……”

“我们已派人去请大夫了，马克西姆，”我那邻里说，“也许你还不会死的。”

他想要睁开眼睛，使劲地扬了扬眉毛和眼睑。

“不，我就会死的。瞧……死神来了，她来了，瞧……弟兄们，如有对不住的地方，请大伙原谅吧……”

“上帝会原谅你的，马克西姆·安德列伊奇，”在场的庄稼人以低沉的声音一起说，并脱下帽子，“请你原谅我们。”

他猛然绝望地摇了摇头，愁苦地鼓起了胸，又瘪了下去。

“总不能让他死在这儿吧，”阿尔达利翁·米海雷奇大声地说，“弟兄们，把那边大车上的席子拿过来，咱们把他抬到医院去。”

有两三个人向大车跑过去。

“昨天……我在瑟乔夫村的……叶菲姆那里……”这个就要死去的人口齿不清地说，“买下一匹马……已付了定钱……那马算是我的了……也把它……交给我老婆……”

几个庄稼人把他抬放到席子上……他全身痉挛起来，像一只中了弹的鸟儿，随之便僵直了……

“死了。”庄稼人们低沉地说。

我们默默地上了马，就离去了。

可怜的马克西姆的死使我陷入了沉思。俄罗斯庄稼人死得好奇怪呀！他们临死前的心情既不能说是坦然的，也不能说是无动于衷；他们的死像是执行一种仪式：又冷静又简单。

几年前，我的另一个邻近村子里，有一个庄稼人在烘禾房里被火严重烧伤了。（他本来就会死在烘禾房里了，恰好有个城里人路过，把这个烧得半死的人拖了出来：是那个人先让自己在一桶水里浸一身水，然后跑去打开那烧着的屋檐下的门。）我到他家里去看他。屋子里又黑又闷，烟气腾腾。我问，烧伤病人在哪儿？“那边，老爷，在炕上。”一个极悲伤的婆娘拖着腔回答我。我走过去，看见那庄稼人躺着，盖着一件皮袄，费劲地喘着气。“你感觉怎么样？”烧伤病人在炕上挣扎着想起来，可遍体是伤，命在旦夕。“你躺着，躺着，躺着……怎么样？好些不？”“当然不妙呀。”他说。“很疼吗？”他没有作声。“不需要什么吗？”又没有回答。“要不要喝点茶？”“不要。”我走开一点，坐在凳子上。我坐了一刻钟，坐了半小时——屋子里死一般沉寂。在屋角里，在神像下边的桌子旁，躲着一个五六岁的小丫头，她在啃面包。母亲有时朝她吓唬一下。过道里有人走动。发出响声，还有人在说话；弟媳妇在切白菜。“啊，阿克西尼娅！”病人终于说话了。“要什么？”“给点格瓦斯。”阿克西尼娅端来格瓦斯给他。又是一阵沉默。我低声问：“给他进过圣餐了吗？”“进过了。”看来是，一切都安排妥了：只是在等他咽气。我受不住了，便出来了……

我又想起了一件事，有一次我顺便到红山村医院去看望一位熟人，他是那里的医士，名叫卡皮东，也是个猎迷。

这所医院原先是地主家厢房；它是女地主亲自创办的，或者说，是她叫人在门上方钉了块蓝色牌子，牌上写着“红山医院”几个白色的字，又亲手交给卡皮东一个精美的本子，让他作为登记病人的名字之用。在这本子的头一页上，这位慈善女地主手下一个谄媚者和仆从题上了以下的诗句：

Dans ces beaux lieux, où règne l'allégresse,
Ce temple fut ourert par la Beauté;
De vos seigneurs admirez la tendresse,
Bons habitants de Krasnogorié!—[6]

另有一位士绅又在下边附上一句：

Et moi aussi j'aime la nature!

Jean Kobyliatnikoff[7]

医士自掏腰包买了六张床铺，举行过祝福仪式之后，便着手替上帝的子民们治病了。除他之外，医院里还有两个人：患有疯病的雕刻匠帕韦尔和当过厨娘的一只手麻痹的梅利基特里莎。他们两人从事药剂的配制，烘晒或浸泡草药；他们还负责一些患热病的人。患疯病的雕刻匠神情忧郁，寡言少语；天天夜里都要唱《美丽的维纳斯》那首歌，一见到过路的人，便前去请求人家许他跟一个早已死去的姑娘马拉尼娅缔结良缘。一只手麻痹的女人常常揍他，还让他去照看火鸡。有一次我在卡皮东医士那儿闲坐。我们刚刚聊起我们新近一次打猎的事，突然有一辆大车驶进院子里来，拉车的是一匹异常肥壮的浅紫灰色马，像这样的马一般只有磨坊主才会有。车上坐着一个身穿新外套、长着花斑大胡子的壮实的汉子。“嗨，瓦西里·德米特里奇，”卡皮东朝窗外喊道，“欢迎光临……”他朝我低声说：“这是雷博夫希诺的磨坊主。”那汉子呼哧着下了车，走进医士的房间，用眼睛找一下神像，并画了十字。“怎么样呀，瓦西里·德米特里奇，有何新闻？……您也许有点病吧，看您的气色不佳呀。”“是呀，卡皮东·季莫费伊奇，有点不对劲。”“您感觉怎么啦？”“是这样的，卡皮东·季莫费伊奇。前些日子我在城里买了几个磨盘，运回了家，我从车上卸磨盘的时候，也许用力过猛了，肚子里咯噔地响了一下，像是有什么东西断了似的……从那一会儿起就老是感到不舒服。今天特别的不对劲。”“唉，”卡皮东嘟哝一声，嗅了嗅鼻烟，“大概是疝气吧。您得这病多久啦？”“已经是第十天了。”“第十天了？（医士从牙缝里吸了口气，并摇了摇头。）我给您检查一下……唉，瓦西里·德米特里奇，”他最后说道，“你的情况不对头呀；你的病可不是闹着玩的；留在我这儿吧；从我这方面说，我会尽心尽力的，可是我没法打包票。”“真的这样糟吗？”磨坊主吃惊了，便低声地问。“是的，瓦西里·德米特里奇，很糟；若是您早两三天来我这儿，那就会没事，一下就可以治好；可是现在您体内已经发炎了，这就不好办，眼看就要变成坏疽了。”“不会吧，卡皮东·季莫费伊奇。”“我已对您说了嘛。”“这怎么会呢！（医士耸了耸肩膀。）因为这一点小病，我就会死吗？”“我没有说会死……只不过请您留在这儿。”这位汉子琢磨来琢磨去，瞧了瞧地板，然后又瞧了我们一眼，摸了摸后脑勺，便拿起帽子。“您去哪儿呀，瓦西里·德米特里奇？”“去哪儿？还会去哪儿呀，回家呗，既然病得这么糟，既然这样，就得去好好安排了。”“那您就是糟蹋自己身体了，瓦西里·德米特里奇，得了吧；就现在这样我都奇怪，您怎么到得了这儿的？请留下吧。”“不，卡皮东·季莫费伊奇兄弟，要死，就死在家里吧；我在这儿死算什么呢——我家里天知道会出什么事呢。”“病情会怎么发展，瓦西里·德米特里奇，还不清楚……当然，病是危险的，很危险，这毫无疑问……所以您应该留下来。”（那汉子摇摇头。）“不，卡皮东·季莫费伊奇，我不留下……您给开一点药倒行。”“光有药还不行呀。”“我说了，不留下。”“那就听便吧……以后可别怨我！”

医士从本子上撕下一小页纸，开了药方，并告诉他还该做些什么。那汉子拿了药方，给了卡皮东半个卢布，便离开房间，坐上车子。“再见了，卡皮东·季莫费伊奇，有对不起您的地方，请多原谅。万一有了什么，请关照我的孩子们！”“唉，留下吧，瓦西里！”那汉子只是摇摇头，用缰绳抽了一下马，就驾车出了院子。我走到外边大路上，瞧一会儿他的背影。道路泥泞，而且坑坑洼洼；磨坊主很自如地驾驭着马，小心翼翼地、从容不迫地赶着车，跟相遇的人点头招呼……到第四天他就呜呼哀哉了。

俄罗斯人往往都死得莫名其妙呀。此时此刻我回想起许许多多死去的人。我也想起了你呀，我的老友，没有读完大学的阿韦尼尔·索罗科乌莫夫，卓越的、极为高尚的人！我又看到你那患肺病的发青的脸，你那稀疏的淡褐色头发，你那和蔼可亲的微笑，你那热烈兴奋的目光，你那修长的四肢；又听到你那细弱而亲切的声音。那时候你住在一个大俄罗斯地主古尔·克鲁皮亚尼科夫家里，教他的两个孩子福法和焦济亚学俄文、地理和历史，耐着性子去忍受主人古尔那些令人难堪的玩笑、管家粗鲁的恭维、恶劣的男孩子们的恶作剧；你带着苦笑并不怨不怒地去满足无聊女主人的刁钻无理的要求；不过，每天晚饭过后，你终于忙完了各种各样的事，完成了各种各样的职责，坐到了窗前，抽起烟斗而沉思了起来，或者饶有兴味地翻阅起那个如你一样无家可归、命运不济的土地测量员从城里带来的残缺油污的厚本杂志，那时候你便会休息过来，感到轻松舒坦！当时你多么喜欢形形色色的诗、形形色色的小说啊，你的眼睛多么易于流泪，你笑得多么的开心，你那孩子般纯洁的心灵对人们充满多么真挚的爱，对一切善和美充满多么高尚的同情！应该说句实话，你不是一个非常聪明机灵的人；你既没有天生的好脑力，又不生性勤勉，在大学里你被认为是学习最差的学生之一；上课时你睡觉，考试时你目瞪口呆，可是，看到同学成绩好、进步快，是谁的眼睛会高兴得闪光，是谁会激动得喘不过气？——是阿韦尼尔……是谁盲目地相信自己朋友们的高禀赋，是谁为他们骄傲、吹捧，并极力加以袒护？是谁没有嫉妒，不讲虚荣，是谁无私牺牲自己，是谁乐意去服从那些不配替他解鞋带的人？……都是你，都是你，我们善良的阿韦尼尔！我记得：你为了“应聘”，怀着多么悲伤的心情和同学们告别；不祥的预感使你深受折磨……果然，你在乡下过得很不舒心，在乡下，没有你可向之恭敬请教的人，没有你可惊叹的人，没有你可爱慕的人……乡下人和一些受过教育的地主都把你当作教书匠来对待：有的对你粗鲁，有的对你不恭。再说，你的长相不大出色，胆子又小，容易脸红、冒汗，口齿又不麻利……连乡间的空气也未能使你恢复健康：你却像蜡烛似的熔化着，可怜的人呀！不错，你的房间朝向花园；稠李树、苹果树、椴树常把自己轻盈的花瓣撒在你的书桌上、墨水瓶上、书本上；墙壁上挂着蓝绸的时钟垫子，它是那位善良多情的德国女郎——一个金发碧眼的家庭女教师——临别时赠给你的；有时有些老朋友从莫斯科来探望你，朗读别人的甚至自己的诗引得你欣喜若狂；然而孤独、难以忍受的奴仆般的教书匠身份、不能获得的自由，还有无穷尽的秋天和冬天、缠人的病患……多么可怜的阿韦尼尔呀！

我在阿韦尼尔死去之前不久曾看望过他。他那时几乎已走不动路了。地主古尔·克鲁皮亚尼科夫没有把他撵出家门，但停发了他的薪金，给焦济亚另聘了一位教师……让福法进了武备中学。阿韦尼尔坐在窗边一张旧的伏尔泰式安乐椅里。天气出奇的好。明朗的秋日天空在一排掉了叶子的深褐色椴树上方欢快地泛蓝；树上还有最后一批金灿灿的叶子在微微颤动，簌簌作响。冷冻的大地在阳光下冒着水汽，渐渐化冻；太阳红红的斜光照着枯衰的草地；空中仿佛有轻微的响声；从花园里传来园丁们清晰可闻的话声。阿韦尼尔穿着一件破旧的布哈拉长袍；绿色的围巾在他那瘦得可怕的脸上投下死沉沉的色调。他见到我高兴极了，伸出手来，打开话匣子，接着咳嗽起来。我让他缓缓气，并挨着他坐下来……阿韦尼尔的膝上放着一本抄得工工整整的柯尔卓夫诗集；他微笑着用手拍拍这本诗集。“这才叫诗人呢。”他使劲压下咳嗽，嘟哝着说，继而用难以听清的声音吟诵起来：

鹰的翅膀
难道被捆住了？
它的道路
难道全被堵了？

我不让他往下念了，因为大夫不准他多说话。我知道什么合他的心意。可以说，索罗科乌莫夫从来没有去“追求”科学，但是，他对当今伟大思想家们已取得些什么成就这样的问题则是很感兴趣的。他常在某个角落里抓住一位同学，向他细细询问起来，他倾听着，惊异着，别人说的他都相信，然后便人云亦云地去说。他对德国哲学特别感兴趣。我给他讲起黑格尔（要知道，这是陈年旧事了）。阿韦尼尔便信以为是地点着头，扬起眉，微笑着，轻声地说：“我懂，我懂……啊，真好，真好……”这个死之将至的、无依无靠、被人抛弃的穷苦青年那种孩子般的求知欲使我感动得掉泪。应当指出，跟一切肺病患者大为不同的是，阿韦尼尔对自己的病情心中很有数，他不去骗自己……可是又怎样呢？——他不悲不叹，对自己的境况竟一次也不提……

他鼓起气力，开始谈莫斯科、谈同窗学友、谈普希金、谈戏剧、谈俄国文学；他还回忆起我们的宴饮、我们小组里的热烈辩论，痛惜地提到两三位亡友的名字……

“你记得达莎吗？”最后他又说，“那是颗金子一般的灵魂呀！多真挚的心呀！她多么的爱我……她现在怎么样啦？也许消瘦了？憔悴了？这可怜的姑娘呀！”

我不忍让病人失望——又何必让他知道，实际上他的达莎如今胖得滚圆，正跟商人孔达奇科夫兄弟打得火热呢，她涂脂抹粉，说话嗲声嗲气，还会骂街。

然而，我瞅着他那张憔悴不堪的脸，心想，能不能让他搬出这儿呢？也许还有可能让他治好病……可是阿韦尼尔没有让我把话说完。

“不，老同学，谢谢啦，”他说，“在哪儿死都是一样。反正我是活不到冬天了……干吗白白打扰别人呢？我在这一家已经习惯了。说真的，这儿的主人们……”

“很差劲，是吗？”我插嘴问。

“不，不是差劲！像是些木头疙瘩。可是我不能怨他们。这儿有些邻居：地主卡萨特金有一个闺女，蛮有教养的，是个很可爱的，极善良的姑娘……不骄傲……”

索罗科乌莫夫又咳嗽起来。

“一切都无所谓了，”他歇了歇，又接着说，“要是谁许我抽烟就好了……我不能就这样死去，我要把烟抽够！”他狡猾地眨眨眼睛，添上一句：“感谢上帝，我活够了，认识了一些好人……”

“你起码该给亲戚们写封信嘛。”我插话说。

“给亲戚写信干什么呢？求帮助吗，他们是不会帮助我的；我死了，他们自会知道的。唉，谈这个干什么呀……你最好给我说说，你在国外见到些什么？”

我谈了起来。他聚精会神地听着我说。傍晚时我离去了，过了十来天，我收到了克鲁皮亚尼科夫先生如下的来信：

阁下，请允许我告知您一个不幸的消息，您的友人阿韦尼尔·索罗科乌莫夫先生，即住在我家的大学生，已于三日前午后二时病故，今日我出资将他安葬于本区一教堂内。他嘱我转交一些书籍和本子，今随函寄奉。他遗下二十二个半卢布，还有其他一些物件，均已交其有关亲戚。您的友人临终时神志清明，心绪可谓泰然，我全家与之诀别时，他亦无任何遗憾之表示。内人克列奥帕特拉·亚历山大罗夫娜向您致意。您的友人之死，使她深为感伤；至于我，托上帝的福，身体尚佳。

顺致敬意。

古尔·克鲁皮亚尼科夫

我还想起了许多其他的例子，这里无法一一细述。只再说一件吧。

一位年老的女地主就要死了，当时我正在她身边。神甫已为她念起送终祈祷。他忽然发现病人真的要咽气了，赶紧把十字架给她。女地主不满地挪开一点身子。“你急什么呀，神甫，”她用僵硬的舌头说，“你来得及的……”她吻了吻十字架，正要把手伸进枕头底下，气便断了。那枕头下放着一块银卢布：这是她为给自己做送终祈祷的神甫准备的劳务费……

唉，俄罗斯人死得好奇怪呀！

[1]一八四〇年严寒凛冽，到十二月底却没有下过雪；树苗全冻死了，许多美丽的橡树林都毁于这个无情的冬天。很难恢复起来，因为土地的生产能力显然减退了；在“禁伐区”（曾举着圣像绕行过的）空地上，已没有了先前那样的高大树木，只是自然地长出白桦和白杨；换句话说，我们还不会造林。——作者原注

[2]柯尔卓夫（一八〇九——一八四二），俄国诗人。

[3]德语：我的天哪！我的天哪！

[4]这德国人把жалость（可惜）误说成щалость（淘气），使人听来可笑。

[5]在上面这句话中，那德国人就有这样发音上的毛病，如把хотел，读成хотели，等等。

[6]法语：

在欢喜无比的美好之乡，
美人亲自创建了这座殿堂；
赞叹你们主人的慷慨好施吧，
我们善良的红山村人！——

[7]法语：我同样热爱大自然！

伊万·科贝利亚特尼科夫

歌　手

科洛托夫卡是一个不大点儿的村庄，早先属于一个女地主（她由于性子又凶又泼而被邻近的老乡取了外号叫“刁婆”，她的真名倒无人知晓了），而如今已归彼得堡的一个德国人所有了。这个小村庄坐落在一个寸草不长的小山坡上，那小山被一道可怕的山沟从上到下割开了，这道山沟是急流猛冲猛刷而成的，它像深渊似的张着口子，蜿蜒在马路当中，它比河流更狠地——河流上至少可以架桥——把这个穷山村一劈为二。几棵瘦巴巴的爆竹柳怯生生地顺着两侧的沙土坡往下排列；在干枯的黄铜色的沟底上躺着一些黏土质大石板。没有说的，这景观确令人不愉快，可是附近各处的老乡却都熟悉到科洛托夫卡的路：他们经常乐于奔这儿来。

在山沟的顶头，离它的像狭缝似的开头处几步远的地方，有一座四方形的小木屋，它独处一方，同其他的房子不相接邻。屋顶是麦秸铺的，并有一个烟囱；一扇窗子宛如敏锐的眼睛，盯着山沟，冬日夜晚，屋里亮着灯，老远就能在朦胧的雾色中看见它，它闪烁着，似乎成了每个过路的农人的指路明星。小房子的门上方钉着一块蓝色牌子；这小木屋就是一家小酒馆，号称“颐和居”[1]。这家酒馆里的酒价不见得比规定的价格便宜，可是上门的顾客却比附近其他各个同类店铺的顾客多得多，其原因就同这酒馆的掌柜尼古拉·伊万内奇有关了。

尼古拉·伊万内奇早年曾是一个身材挺拔、脸色红润、一头鬈发的帅小伙，可是如今已变成一个过于发福的人了，头发也白了，一脸的肥肉，眼睛显得狡猾而和善，油光光的脑门上布满了一道道的皱纹——他在这科洛托夫卡已待了二十余载了。正像大多数酒馆的掌柜一样，尼古拉·伊万内奇也是个挺有心计的机灵人。他并不特别奉迎人，也不那么能说会道，但自有一套吸引顾客、留住顾客的招数。在这位恬淡的店主的虽然有点锐利但很安详亲切的目光下，顾客们在他的柜台前一坐便感到愉快舒心。他有很多明智的见解；他对地主、农民和市商的生活都熟悉得很。在别人遇到难处的时候，他能给人出点好主意，不过，他为人谨慎，私字当头，宁肯置身于事外，至多是略微地，似乎毫无用意地做点暗示，以此帮助他的顾客——而且是他所喜欢的顾客——明辨事理，好自为之。凡是俄国人所看重的或感兴趣的事情，比如对牛马和牲畜，对森林，对砖瓦，对器皿，对毛布皮革，对歌曲舞蹈，等等，他都样样在行。在没有顾客的时候，他常常盘起两只细腿，像麻袋似的坐在自家门前的地上，跟一切过往行人打招呼，亲切寒暄。他一生见多识广，目睹过几十个常来他这儿买酒的小贵族的相继去世，他对方圆一百俄里内发生的事都一清二楚，可是他从来不乱说，不显摆自己，从来不自炫；连眼光极锐利的警察局长都未加怀疑的事他都知底细。他总是寡言少语，爱笑笑，动动酒杯。乡亲们都很敬重他：县里身份最高的地主、高级文官谢列彼坚科每次路过他家门口，都要谦逊地向他点头致意。尼古拉·伊万内奇是个很有影响的人物：一个有名的盗马贼偷了他一个朋友家的马，他能让那个贼把马还回来；邻近一个村子的庄稼人不愿接纳新的主管人，他也能说服他们，还有不少诸如此类的事。不过，不要以为他做这些善事是出于正义感，出于对朋友邻里的古道热肠，非也！他只不过是尽力防止出什么乱子，免得破坏他的宁静。尼古拉·伊万内奇已经成家，并有了娃娃。他的妻子是个鼻尖眼快做事麻利小市民出身的女子，近一个时期来，也像她丈夫一样有些发福了。他把一切都托付给妻子，钱也交她保管。那些爱发酒疯的人都很怕她；她不喜欢这种人，因为从他们那里赚不到多少钱，却吵得要命；比较合她心意的倒是那些沉默寡言、郁郁不乐的人。尼古拉·伊万内奇的娃娃们都还小；先头生的几个都夭折了，而活下来的几个长得都很像爹娘：看着这几个健康的孩子的小脸，是很令人愉快的。

那是一个酷热不堪的七月天，我慢慢地挪着脚步，带着我的狗，顺着科罗托夫卡山沟往上走，朝着“颐和居”酒馆走去。赤日当空，像发了狂似的，不住地蒸着、烤着；空气中弥漫着令人窒息的尘土。羽毛亮泽的白嘴鸦和乌鸦张着嘴，苦相地瞅着过路的行人，似乎在求人们的同情。唯有麻雀们不觉愁苦，张开羽毛，叽叽喳喳地叫得比先前更凶，忽而在篱笆上打架，忽而从尘土飞扬的大路上一齐起飞，如阴云一般在绿油油的大麻地上空飞来飞去。我渴得难受极了。近处无水可饮：在科洛托夫卡，就像在许多其他僻远村庄一样，由于没有泉水和井水，庄稼人们喝的都是池塘里的浑水……可是谁能把这种令人恶心的池水称作饮水呢？我就想到尼古拉·伊万内奇那儿要一杯啤酒或格瓦斯喝喝。

老实说，一年四季里，科洛托夫卡都没有令人赏心悦目的风光；这里特别令人感到郁闷的是热不可耐的七月耀眼阳光烘烤下的景象：破旧的褐色屋顶，这个深深的山谷，焦枯的、尘土滚滚的牧场，在牧场上失望地游荡着的长腿瘦母鸡；原先地主住宅剩下的灰色白杨木屋架和变成一个个洞穴的窗子；周围长满荨麻、苦艾和杂草、飘满鹅毛、晒得滚烫的黑乎乎的池塘；池塘边半干的污泥和坍向一边的堤坝；堤坝旁被踩成灰末状的土地上那些热得难以喘气、直打嚏喷的绵羊；还有它们悲愁地互相拥挤，尽量把头低低垂下，似乎觉得这场难堪的酷热不知何时才会最后过去的那种沮丧的忍耐神情。我拖着疲惫的脚步走到尼古拉·伊万内奇的酒馆门前，照旧引起了孩子们的惊奇，惊得他们睁大眼睛无所用意地观望着；我的到来也引起狗的狂叫，它们以此来表示愤怒，它们叫得那样声嘶力竭、气势汹汹，仿佛内脏都要喊破了似的，以至于后来它们自己都咳了起来，喘了起来——这时候，酒馆门口出现一个个子高高的汉子，没有戴帽，穿着一件厚呢大衣，低低地束着一条浅蓝色腰带。从样子看他像一个仆役；浓密的灰发竖在他那张又干又皱的脸孔上边。他在唤一个什么人，急忙忙地挥动着双手，他那双手挥动得明显超过他自己所希望的程度。看得出来，他已经喝醉了。

“来呀，来呀！”他使劲扬起眉毛，嘟哝地说起话来，“来呀，眨巴眼，来呀！瞧你那个样，老弟，老磨磨蹭蹭，真是的。这可不好，老弟。人家都在那儿等你呢，可你这么磨蹭……来呀。”

“哦，来了，来了。”响起一个发颤的声音，从房子的右边出来一个矮矮胖胖的瘸子。他穿着一件相当整洁的呢外衣，只套上一个衣袖；高高的尖顶帽直扣到眉毛上，使他那圆圆的胖脸平添了调皮和嘲笑的表情。他那双小小的黄眼睛滴溜溜地直转，那薄薄的嘴唇上老是浮着拘谨的不自然的微笑，那又尖又长的鼻子难看地突向前面，像个船舵。“来了，伙计，”他接着说，一瘸一拐地向酒馆走去，“你喊我干什么呀？……谁在等我？”

“我喊你干什么？”穿厚呢大衣的人带点责备的口吻说，“你这个人哪，眨巴眼，真是怪呀，老弟，喊你到酒馆里去，你还要问干什么！大伙都好心地等着你呢：土耳其人雅什卡，还有怪老爷，还有从日兹德拉来的包工头。雅什卡跟包工头打赌：赌一大瓶啤酒——看看谁胜过谁，也就是说，看谁唱得更好……明白吗？”

“雅什卡要唱歌？”外号眨巴眼的人兴致勃勃地说，“你没瞎说吧，笨瓜？”

“我不瞎说，”笨瓜郑重地回答，“你才爱胡扯呢。既然打了赌，当然就要唱，你这笨牛，你这滑头，眨巴眼！”

“那好，咱们走吧，糊涂蛋。”眨巴眼说。

“嘿，至少你来吻一下我嘛，我的心肝。”笨瓜张开双臂，嘟哝说。

“瞧你这个娇里娇气的伊索[2]。”眨巴眼轻蔑地说，一边用胳膊肘推开他，接着两人都躬点身，走进那扇低矮的门里。

听到他们的这番对话，强烈地勾起了我的好奇心。我曾不止一次听说，土耳其人雅什卡是附近一带最出色的歌手，这一次我偶然遇到机会可以听一听他跟另一名歌手的比赛。于是我便加快脚步走进酒馆。

在我的读者中，有机会光顾乡村酒馆的人恐怕不会很多；可是我们这些打猎的人哪儿不去呢。乡村酒馆的建筑都是非常简单的。一般都是由一间幽暗的前室和带烟囱的正屋组成。正屋由一道板壁隔成里外间，里间是任何顾客都不可以进的。在板壁上，在一张宽宽的橡木桌子上方，开有一个长方形的大壁洞。这种桌子，或者说柜台，就是用来卖酒的。正对着这大壁洞有一排货架，货架上并排摆着大大小小封着口的酒瓶。正屋的前半部分是接待顾客用的，放着几条长板凳，两三个空酒桶，拐角处摆着一张桌子。大部分乡村酒馆里光线都很差，在它们的圆木结构的墙壁上，几乎看不到那些为一般农舍所不可缺的花花绿绿的通俗版画。

当我踏进这个名为颐和居的酒馆时，里面已经聚集了很多人。

柜台的后边照例站着尼古拉·伊万内奇，他那身躯几乎与壁洞一般宽。他穿着一件印花布衬衫，肉嘟嘟的脸颊上泛着慵懒的微笑，正在用白白胖胖的手给刚刚进来的朋友眨巴眼和笨瓜倒两杯酒。在他后边靠窗的屋角处，可看到他那位眼睛很尖的妻子。房中央站着土耳其人雅什卡，二十三四岁，身材瘦削而挺拔，穿一件长襟土布蓝外衫。他看起来像是个豪爽的工厂工人，可那身体似乎很难说是多么壮健。他的两颊有些瘪，有一双显得不安的灰色大眼睛，一个端正的鼻子，那小鼻孔老是在动，白皙的额门稍有点斜，淡黄色鬈发梳向后面，嘴唇很大，可很漂亮，富于表情——这脸上的一切都显示他是个敏感而有激情的人。他很激动：眨巴着眼睛，呼吸时粗时细，两手发颤，像患热病似的——他的确在发一种热病，一种突如其来的惶惶不安的热病，凡是要面对众人讲话或唱歌的人，常常都会这样。他的身旁站着一个四十来岁的汉子，宽肩膀、宽颧骨、低额门，有一双鞑靼人式的小眼睛，鼻子短而扁平，下巴方方的，头发乌黑亮泽，硬如鬃毛。他那黑不溜秋的带铅色的脸，特别是他那苍白嘴唇的表情，如果不是在这样平静沉思的话，几乎可以说是凶狠的。他几乎待着不动，不过在慢慢地打量着四周，活像套在轭下的公牛。他穿一件带有光滑铜纽扣的旧外衣；粗大的脖子上围着一条旧的黑色绸围巾。人称怪老爷。在他正对面，在圣像下边长凳上坐着的是雅什卡的比赛对手——从日兹德拉来的包工头。他是一个三十岁上下的汉子，个头不高，可很坚实，麻脸、鬈发、扁扁的狮子鼻，滴溜溜的褐眼睛，稀稀的下巴胡。他神气地打量着周围，把双手掖在屁股下，穿着滚边的漂亮靴子的双脚悠然自得地摇晃着，发出啪啪的响声。他穿一件带棉绒领的崭新的灰呢薄上衣，在这个领子的映衬下，那件紧包住喉头的红衬衫便显得格外的醒目。在对面的角落里，在门的右边的一张桌子旁边坐着一个庄稼人，穿着一件又窄又旧的长袍，肩部有一处大洞。阳光滚着稀稀的黄色光波，透过两扇小窗的沾着灰尘的玻璃射了进来，似乎也战胜不了房间里常驻的昏暗：各种用具什物上只亮出淡淡的光斑。然而屋子内相当凉爽，我刚一进入屋里，闷热之感便一下消去了，真是如释重负。

我的到来，我看得出来，起初使尼古拉·伊万内奇的顾客们略感不安；但他们看到他像对一位熟人那样跟我招呼问候，便安心下来，不再把注意力集中在我身上了。我要了啤酒，坐到房角里那个穿破长袍的庄稼汉旁边。

“嘿，怎么啦！”笨瓜一口气喝干了一杯酒，忽然大喊起来，并且怪模怪样地挥动双手，用以配合自己的叫喊，显然，不带这种动作他是说不出话来的，“还等什么呀？开始就开始嘛。对吗？雅沙[3]？……”

“开始吧，开始吧。”尼古拉·伊万内奇表示赞成地说。

“那咱们就开始吧，”包工头带着自信的微笑冷静地说，“我准备好了。”

“我也准备好了。”雅科夫激动地说。

“喂，开始吧，伙计们，开始吧。”眨巴眼尖声尖气地喊道。

可是，尽管都一致表示要开始，却没有人起头开唱；包工头甚至没有从凳上站起来——大家似乎在等待着什么。

“开始！”怪老爷阴沉而断然地说了一声。

雅科夫战颤了一下。包工头站了出来，把腰带紧了紧，清清嗓子。

“那由谁先来呢？”他用略为改变的声音问怪老爷。怪老爷仍然一动不动地站在房间正中，宽宽地叉开两条肥腿，把两只强劲的手插在灯笼裤的裤兜里，几乎直插到胳膊肘。

“你，你先来，包工头，”笨瓜嘟哝说，“你先来，伙计。”

怪老爷皱皱眉头扫了他一眼。笨瓜无力地吱了一声，发起窘来，望望天花板，耸耸肩膀，不吭声了。

“抓阄吧，”怪老爷一字一顿地说，“把酒放在柜台上。”

尼古拉·伊万内奇弯下腰，气喘吁吁地从地板上拿起一瓶酒，放在柜台上。

怪老爷瞧了瞧雅科夫，说了声：“来！”

雅科夫把手伸进衣袋里掏，掏出一个铜子，用牙咬出一个印记。包工头从怀里掏出一个新的皮钱包，不慌不忙地解开带子，把许多小硬币倒在手心里，选出一个崭新的铜子。笨瓜脱下他那顶破掉了帽檐的旧帽子拿上来，雅科夫把他那铜子扔进帽里，包工头也把铜子丢了进去。

“你抓一个吧。”怪老爷朝眨巴眼说。

眨巴眼得意地笑了笑，两手捧着帽子，摇晃起来。

室内顿时变得鸦雀无声，两个铜币相互碰撞，发出轻轻的叮当声。我留意地朝周围扫了一眼：每张脸上都显出紧张等待的神情；怪老爷本人也眯起眼睛；坐在我旁边的那个穿破长袍的庄稼人也好奇地伸长脖子。眨巴眼把手伸进帽子，掏出的是包工头的铜子：大家都松了一口气。雅科夫的脸红了一下，包工头用手绺了绺头发。

“我说过的嘛，你先唱，”笨瓜叫起来，“我说过的嘛。”

“行了，行了，别嚷嚷了。”怪老爷轻蔑地说。“开始吧。”他向包工头点点头说。

“那我唱什么歌呢？”包工头兴奋地问。

“随你唱什么，”眨巴眼回答说，“想唱什么就唱什么呗。”

“当然，唱什么要随你便，”尼古拉·伊万内奇把手缓缓地叉在胸前，附和着说，“这事不好给你指定。唱你想唱的吧；不过得好好地唱；然后我们会公正地评判的。”

“不用说，会公正的。”笨瓜接过话说，并舔了舔空酒杯的边。

“伙计们，让我稍稍清一下嗓子。”包工头说，用手指摸摸上衣领子。

“好啦，好啦，别拖了，开始吧！”怪老爷断然说，并低下头去。

包工头略微思索一下，晃了晃头，站了出来。雅科夫盯着他看……

不过，在描述这场比赛之前，先来把这故事中的每个出场人物略做几句介绍，我想，这不是多余的吧。他们之中有几个人的生平，我在这颐和居酒馆里遇到他们的时候就已经有所闻了；另外几个人的情况是我后来才打听到的。

先来说说笨瓜吧。此人的真名是叶夫格拉夫·伊万诺夫，可是周围一带谁都管他叫笨瓜，他本人也常用这个外号来称呼自己，所以这个外号就叫开了。的确，对于他那很不起眼的、老是焦急不安的相貌，这外号是最适当不过了。他本来就是一个吊儿郎当放荡惯了的独身家仆，原先的几个主人早就不要他了，由于没有了任何差使可干，也就拿不到一个铜子的薪水，但他有办法每天慷他人之慨去吃吃喝喝。他有一批愿供他喝酒饮茶的相识，那些人自己也搞不清图的是什么，因为他不仅不会替大家逗闷助兴，相反，他那无聊的贫嘴、令人讨厌的赖皮、热狂的举动、不断发出的不自然的笑声，都令大家厌烦。他既不会唱歌，又不会跳舞，平生从来没有说过一句聪明的话，没有说过一句有用的话，老是瞎说八道，胡诌一气——是个十足的笨瓜。可是在方圆四十俄里之内，没有一次酒会上没有他那瘦长的身影在客人们中间晃来晃去，大家都对他习惯了，把他作为势所难免的坏现象而加以容忍。说实话，大家都瞧不起他，但唯一能使他老实下来，不敢胡作非为的人，就是那位怪老爷。

眨巴眼跟这个笨瓜可截然不同。眨巴眼这外号对于他也很合适，虽然他那双眼睛眨得并不比别人的多；大家都知道，俄罗斯人对于起外号都很拿手。尽管我曾费了大力去打听此人的更详细的经历，可是对于我，或许也对于别的许多人来说，他一生经历中还留下一些模糊不清之点，用读书人的话说，被不可知的漆黑所掩盖了。我只听说，他早先曾在一个无儿无女的老太太家里当马车夫，他带着交他照管的三匹马溜之夭夭，失踪了整整一年，后来他大概遭了不少苦难，深知过流浪生活是没有好处的，所以便自动跑回来了，这时他已经成了瘸子，他跪在女主人脚下求饶，在后来的几年里他卖力地干活，将功补过，渐渐博得了女主人的喜欢，终于得到她的完全信任，当上了管家；女主人过世后，他不知怎么地获得了自由，变成了小商人，开头向乡亲们租些地种瓜，后来就发了，如今日子过得挺滋润。这个人阅历深，有脑子，为人既不恶也不善，比较会打算；他深懂人情世故，善于拉关系。他小心谨慎，同时又如狐狸一般机灵；他像老太婆似的爱叨叨，却从来不会说漏嘴，倒是能让别人掏出心里话；不过，他不会像其他一些狡猾家伙那样装糊涂，他是很难装傻的：我从来没有见过比他那双狡黠的小眼睛更锐利更聪明的眼睛。这双眼睛从来不是简单地在看，总是在细细观察或悄悄窥视。眨巴眼有时会一连几个星期去思量一件似乎很简单的事，可有时会突然下决心去干一件铤而走险的事，看样子他这一下非倒霉不行了……可你瞧，他全办成了，一切顺利。他是很走运的，他相信自己的运气，相信征兆。总的说来他很迷信。大家都不喜欢他，因为他对人漠不关心，可是他很受大家尊敬。他的家里只有一根独苗，他对这儿子可疼爱极了。这孩子有这样的父亲来培养，想必会鹏程万里呢。“这小眨巴眼长得真像他老子。”现在有些老头子在夏日晚间聚坐在墙根土台上聊天的时候，已经悄悄地这样议论他了，大家心里都明白这话里的意思，也就不多说什么了。

关于土耳其人雅科夫和包工头，没法加以细叙。雅科夫的外号叫土耳其人，因为他确实是一个被俘的土耳其女人所生。就心灵而论，他是个道道地地的艺术家，可按身份他则是一个商人办的造纸厂里的汲水工。至于包工头嘛，说实话，他的经历我仍不得而知，我只觉得他是一个很有心眼很机灵的城市小市民。但是关于怪老爷，倒值得较详细地表一表。

此人的外表给人的最初印象就是觉得他有些粗鲁、沉闷，可又具有不可抗拒的魅力。他长得很粗笨，像我们所常说的，是个“铁汉子”，他身上带着坚不可摧的壮健劲。而且说来也怪，他那狗熊般的形体也不乏某种特有的风雅，它可能来自对自身强壮的十分冷静的自信。初次见到他的风采，很难断定这位赫拉克勒斯[4]是属于哪一阶层的人；他不像家仆，不像小市民，不像退职的穷文书，也不像家道败落、地产不多的贵族——那都是些好养狗、爱打架的家伙，而他的确是别具一格的人。无人知晓他是打何处流落到我们县里的。有人说，他出身于独院地主，从前似乎在某处供过职，但有关这方面的确切情况大家都不知道，也没有人可以打听——从他本人嘴里更是探听不出来的，因为没有比他更嘴严、更阴沉的人了。也没有人确切知道他是何以为生的。他不干任何手艺活，也不去谁家走走，几乎不跟任何人交往，然而他有钱花；的确，钱虽然不多，但是有得花的。他为人并不谦虚——他压根没什么可谦虚的——但他很平和；他自在地活着，似乎毫不关注周围的人，也绝对用不着某个人的帮助。怪老爷（这是他的外号，他的真名是彼列夫列索夫）在附近一带是挺有威望的；虽然他不光无权对任何人发号施令，而且连他本人也丝毫没有让那些与之偶然打交道的人听从于他的意图，可是许多人都立刻乐意服从于他。他一说话，别人都服，他的影响力总是起作用的。他几乎滴酒不沾，也不跟女人拉拉扯扯，他所酷爱的是唱歌。这个人身上有许多不解之谜；似乎他那身上可怕地潜藏着某种巨大的力量，这种力量仿佛知道自己一旦升起，一旦爆发，就会毁掉自己，毁掉所碰到的一切；如果这个人一生中不曾有过这一类的爆发，如果他不是因有了经验而幸免于毁灭，时刻严格地管束自己，那样想就大错特错了。特别令我惊讶的是，他身上有着某种天生的狂暴气质和同样天生的高雅气质的混合——这样的混合我在其他人身上从未见到过。

现在言归正传，包工头站了起来，半闭起眼睛，以极高亢的假嗓唱了起来。他那嗓音相当甜润动听，虽然略显沙哑。他的声音像陀螺似的旋转着，变化着，不断地由高转低，又不断地回到他所保持的高音，特别使劲地拉长一会儿，再慢慢停息下来，随后又猛一下以雄壮豪迈的气势接续前面的曲调。他的声调变化有时大胆得很，有时又很可笑，这种变化会让行家听得过瘾，若是让德国人听了，大概就会大为生气的[5]。这是俄罗斯的tenore di grazia, ténor léger[6]。他唱的是一首欢快的舞曲。我透过那没完没了的装饰音、附加的和声和扬声，只听清下面几句歌词：

我这年轻轻的小伙，
要把这小块地耕作，
我这年轻轻的小伙，
让它开满红花朵朵。

他唱着，大家聚精会神地倾听着。他显然感到这是唱给行家们听的，所以如俗话说的，使出了浑身解数。的确，我们这一带的人对于唱歌都很懂行，难怪这奥廖尔大道上的谢尔盖耶夫村以其十分和谐悦耳的歌声而闻名于全俄国。包工头唱了很久，可是没有引起听众的强烈共鸣；他缺乏合唱的协助；末了，唱到一个特别成功的转折处，连怪老爷也笑了，笨瓜憋不住了，高兴得大声喝彩。大家都精神一振。笨瓜和眨巴眼低声地和唱起来，并大声地喊：“棒极了……加油，好小子……加油，加把劲，鬼家伙！再加把劲！再鼓鼓气，你这狗东西，狗崽子……鬼勾你的魂！”等等。尼古拉·伊万内奇在柜台后边赞赏地来去晃着脑袋。笨瓜终于跺起脚，踏起小步，扭起肩膀，而雅科夫的眼睛如炭火似的燃烧起来，全身像树叶一般颤动着，胡乱地微笑着。唯有那怪老爷神色不变，依然在原地不动；不过他那凝视包工头的目光有些柔和了，虽然嘴边仍留着轻蔑的表情。包工头看到大家都表现出满意的样子，更来劲了，完全飘飘然起来，猛加装饰音，舌头如鸟儿般啼啭，如鼓似的敲响，猛烈地扯着嗓门，他终于累坏了，脸色发白，热汗淋淋，让全身朝后一仰，吐出最后的渐趋微弱的高音，这时候听众向他报以一片狂烈的喝彩声。笨瓜扑上去搂住他的脖子，他那骨瘦如柴的长胳膊搂得包工头喘不过气来；尼古拉·伊万内奇肥肥的脸上泛出一片红晕，他似乎变年轻了；雅科夫疯了似的喊道：“棒极了，棒极了！”——连坐在我旁边的那个穿破长袍的庄稼人也按捺不住了，用拳捶一下桌子，喊了起来：“啊哈！真好呀，他妈的真好呀！”并使劲往旁边啐了一口唾沫。

“哎呀，伙计，真让人过瘾呀！”笨瓜喊道，一边搂着疲惫不堪的包工头不放，“真让人过瘾呀！没说的！你赢了，伙计，你赢了！恭喜你——酒归你啦！雅什卡比你差远啦……我对你说，他差远啦……你相信我的话吧！”（他又把包工头往怀里搂。）

“快放开他，放开吧，别老缠着……”眨巴眼生气地说，“让他坐在凳子上吧，瞧，他很累了……你这笨蛋，伙计，真是笨蛋！干吗缠个没完？”

“好吧，就让他坐下，我来为他的健康干一杯。”笨瓜说着，就去到柜台前，“记你的账上，伙计。”他朝包工头添说一句。

包工头点点头，便在板凳上坐下来，从帽子里掏出毛巾，擦起脸来；笨瓜又急又贪地喝干了一杯酒，照酒鬼的习惯，喉咙里咯咯地响着，一面装出一副忧心忡忡的样子。

“唱得好呀，伙计，唱得好，”尼古拉·伊万内奇亲切地说，“现在该是你唱了，雅沙[7]：要小心，别怯场。我们瞧一瞧谁胜过谁，我们瞧瞧……包工头唱得很好，真的很好。”

“非常好。”尼古拉·伊万内奇的妻子说，一边微笑着，瞧了瞧雅科夫。

“好得很呀！”坐在我旁边的庄稼人低声重复了一次。

“啊，迟疑鬼波列哈[8]！”笨瓜冷不防地喊了起来，走到衣服肩部有破洞的庄稼人跟前，用手指戳戳他，蹦跳起来，并笑得直打战。“波列哈！波列哈！格，巴杰[9]，滚出去，迟疑鬼！你来干什么呀，迟疑鬼？”他边笑边喊。

这可怜的庄稼人发窘了，本已打算站起来，赶忙离开，蓦然响起怪老爷铜钟般的声音：

“这讨厌的畜生要闹腾什么呀？”他咬牙切齿地说。

“我没什么，”笨瓜嘟嘟哝哝说，“我没什么……我只是……”

“那好，闭上你的嘴吧！”怪老爷说，“雅科夫，开始吧！”

雅科夫用手摸摸喉咙。

“怎么回事，伙计，有点那个……唉……不知道怎么回事，真的，有点那个……”

“嘿，得啦，别怯场呀。多羞人呀！……干吗扭扭捏捏的？……唱吧，好好地唱。”

怪老爷低下头，等待着。

雅科夫静默了一下，朝周围瞧了瞧，一只手捂着脸。大家都把眼睛盯着他，尤其是那个包工头，在他的脸上，透过平常的自信和受到喝彩后的得意神情，露出了不由自主的轻微不安。他靠在墙壁上，又把双手掖在屁股下，可两腿已不再晃悠了。雅科夫终于露出自己的脸——它像死人的脸一样苍白，眼睛透过垂下的睫毛微微闪亮。他深深地吐了一口气，就唱了起来……他最初的声音很轻，也不平稳，仿佛不是出自他的胸腔，而是从某个远处飘来，似乎是偶然飞进这房子里来。这颤悠的，如金属般的音响对我们每个人都产生了奇妙的作用。我们互相地你看我，我看你，尼古拉·伊万内奇的妻子把身子挺得笔直。继这第一声之后是一个较为坚定的悠长的声音，但它显然还是发颤的，好像一根弦被手指用劲一拨而猛地发响之后，仍会颤动几下，才最后迅速停下来。在第二声之后是第三声，之后那郁闷的歌声才渐渐激昂起来，向四处荡漾开来。他唱道：“田野上的小路一条又一条。”我们都感到甜美而可怕。说实话，我很少听到这样的声音：它稍稍带点碎裂声，也有点发颤；开头甚至还带点苦痛的韵味，但其中却蕴有真挚深沉的激情、青春的气息、力量、甘甜味，还有一种淡淡的迷人的哀愁。这歌声里鸣响着、喘息着一颗俄罗斯的正义的炽热灵魂，它紧紧抓住你的心，直接扣动俄罗斯人的心弦。歌声激荡着，飘扬着。显然，雅科夫也陶醉了：他已不显胆怯了，他全然沉浸于幸福之中；他的声音已不再战栗了——它在颤动，但这是激情的隐约的内在颤动，这样的激情正像箭似的刺穿着听众的灵魂。他的歌声越发坚强有力，越发嘹亮了。记得有一天傍晚，那正是海水退潮的时候，大海在远处汹涌澎湃，我看到平坦的沙滩上停着一只大白鸥，它一动不动地歇着，那丝绸似的胸脯染着晚霞的红光，只是偶尔朝着熟悉的大海、朝着低沉的通红的夕阳慢慢地舒展着它那长长的翅膀。我听着雅科夫的歌声，就想起了那只大白鸥。他唱着，全然忘记了自己的竞赛对手，忘记了我们所有的人，但他显然受到我们无声的、热情的关切的鼓舞，犹如游泳者受到水浪的激荡而大感兴奋一样。他唱着，那一声声都给人以亲切的和无比舒展的感觉，仿佛是熟悉的草原无边无际地展现在你的眼前。我感到，我的泪水在心中沸腾，涌上眼睛。蓦然间一阵低沉的、压抑的哭声使我吃了一惊……我向周围瞧了瞧——看见掌柜的妻子趴在窗台上哭泣。雅科夫向她迅速瞅了一眼，唱得比先前更嘹亮，更甜美了。尼古拉·伊万内奇垂下了头；眨巴眼转过身去；笨瓜也深深动情了，笨相地张着嘴巴，呆站着；那个穿灰长袍的庄稼人在角落里低声抽泣，一面摇着脑袋，嘴里嘟嘟哝哝；怪老爷的紧锁的眉毛下也涌出大颗的泪珠，沿着他那钢铁般的脸慢慢地滚动着；包工头把握起的拳头按在额头，木然不动……若不是雅科夫在一个很高的异常尖细的音上戛然而止，仿佛他的声音是断了一样，真不知大家的这种悲凄的感受将如何收场呀。没有人叫喊，甚至没有人动一动；大家似乎都在等待，看他是否还要再唱；可他睁大了眼睛，似乎对我们的沉默感到惊异，以疑问的目光环顾了一下大家，他才明白，他获胜了……

“雅沙。”怪老爷喊了一声，把一只手搭在他的肩上，就不说话了。

我们全都愣站着。包工头缓缓地站起来，走到雅科夫跟前。“你……是你……你赢了。”他好不容易终于说了这样一句，便从屋子里跑出去了……

他这一迅速而决然的动作似乎打破了眼前的痴迷状态，大家猛的一下兴高采烈地谈论起来。笨瓜往上一蹦，叽里咕噜地说起来，两手如风车车翼一般地挥动着；眨巴眼拐着腿走近雅科夫，跟他亲吻起来；尼古拉·伊万内奇欠起身来，郑重地宣布，他个人添赠一瓶啤酒；怪老爷笑得那样慈祥可亲，我怎样也想不到在他的脸上会看到这般的笑容；穿灰长袍的庄稼人两手抹着眼睛、脸颊、鼻子和胡子，在屋角里叨咕着：“好呀，好极了，即使我是狗娘养的，我也说好呀！”尼古拉·伊万内奇的妻子满脸通红，赶紧站起来走了开去。雅科夫如孩子似的享受着自己胜利的喜悦；他的脸全变了样，尤其是他那眼睛闪耀着幸福的光彩。他被拥到柜台前；他把那个不住地哭泣的穿灰长袍的庄稼人也喊过来，又叫掌柜的儿子去找包工头，然而没有找到他，于是大家就喝起酒来。“你再给我们唱吧，你就给我们直唱到晚上吧。”笨瓜高举双手，反复地叨叨着。

我再次瞧了雅科夫一眼就出来了。我不愿留下来——我怕损坏了自己的印象。可是天气依然热不可当。它仿佛形成浓重的一层罩在大地之上；透过极细微的几乎发黑的灰尘，似乎可看到一些又小又亮的火花在深蓝色的天空中旋转回荡。一切都默默无声；在疲惫乏力大自然的深深沉默中藏着某种绝望的、备受压抑的东西。我慢慢地来到干草棚里，躺在刚刚割下但已几乎干透了的草上。我久久不能入睡；我耳朵里仍好一阵子响着雅科夫那迷人的歌声……然而，炎热和疲乏终于占了上风，我死死地睡了过去。当我醒来时，四处都已黑下来了；散堆在周围的草散发出强烈的香气，而且有点潮乎乎的了；透过破棚顶的细细木条，可看到苍白的星星在有气无力地闪烁着。我走出了棚子。晚霞早已消失了，它的余晖还在天边微微泛白；而在不久前还热烘烘的空气里，排开夜晚的清凉，仍扑来一阵阵的热气，胸中仍渴望着凉风的吹拂。没有风，也没有乌云；整个天空是那么的纯净、清澈而又昏暗，那里静悄悄地闪烁着无数的不很明亮的星星。村子里闪着点点灯火；从不远处亮光光的酒馆里传来乱哄哄的喧闹声，我似乎从中听出了雅科夫的声音。那里不时地爆发出哄堂大笑声。我走到窗前，把脸贴在玻璃上：我看到了一种虽很热闹活跃但令人很不愉快的场景：大家都喝得醉醺醺的——从雅科夫起，全喝醉了。雅科夫袒露着胸膛，坐在凳子上，用沙哑的嗓音唱着一首庸俗下流的舞曲，一边懒洋洋地弹拨着吉他的琴弦。一绺绺被汗水湿透的头发低垂在他那苍白得可怕的脸上。在酒馆的中央，变得肆无忌惮的笨瓜脱去了上衣，在那个穿灰长袍的庄稼人跟前跳跳蹦蹦，狂舞一气；庄稼人也用自己发软的双脚在那里费劲地跺着、蹭着，乱蓬蓬的胡子里露出毫无意义的微笑，偶尔挥一挥手，似乎想说：“真带劲！”他那脸显得可笑极了；尽管他使劲地扬起眉毛，可是那发沉的眼皮却不肯抬起来，老是遮着那双几乎看不见的、无精打采可又甜滋滋的眼睛。他正处于酩酊大醉的人的那种有趣的状态，任何一个过路人看到他那张脸，必定会说：“真逗，老兄，真逗！”眨巴眼整张脸红得像只虾，他张大鼻孔，在角落里带嘲弄地笑着；唯有尼古拉·伊万内奇真不愧是酒馆掌柜，仍然保持着一向的冷静。屋子里聚集了许多新来的顾客；可是我没有看见怪老爷在那里。

我转身离去，快步地走下科洛托夫卡所处的小山冈。这小山冈脚边伸展着广阔的平原；沉没在漫漫夜雾中的平原显得更加无边无际，似乎与暗下来的天空融为一体。我沿着山沟旁的路大步地往下走，蓦然从平原的远处传来一个男孩子的响亮声音。“安特罗普卡！安特罗普卡！……”他一个劲地用失望的哭声喊着，并把最后一个音拉得长长的。

他稍停了一会儿，又叫喊起来。他那声音在静止不动的、睡意蒙眬的空气中响亮地荡漾开来。他把安特罗普卡这名字至少喊了三十来遍，突然从平地的另一端，仿佛从另一世界传来隐约可闻的回音：

“什么事？……”

那男孩子立即以又喜又怒的声音喊道：

“上这儿，你这鬼家伙！……”

“干……什……么……呀？”过了好一会儿另一声音才回答。

“因为阿爸要……揍……你……呢。”第一个声音急忙地喊道。

第二个声音没有再回答了，那个男孩子又呼喊起安特罗普卡这名字来。当天色全黑了下来，我已经绕着离科洛托夫卡四俄里、围着我的村子的那片树林边走过来的时候，我还听得到他那越来越稀、越来越弱的喊声……

“安托罗普卡！”这声音似乎依然飘荡在夜色沉沉的空中。

[1]所谓“颐和居”，乃是人们乐于来聚集的地方，是指提供休息娱乐的地方。——作者原注

[2]伊索是古希腊寓言作家。在旧俄国常把这名字用作讽刺语，指的是言语费解的人。

[3]雅沙、雅什卡，都是下面所称的雅科夫的小称或昵称。

[4]古希腊神话中的大力士。

[5]德国人一般喜爱典雅的音乐，不欣赏这种花哨的唱法。

[6]意大利文和法文：抒情男高音。——原注

[7]也是雅科夫的一种昵称。

[8]波列谢南部，即起自博格霍夫县和日兹德拉县交界处的长形林带的居民称为波列哈。他们的生活方式、性格、语言方面具有许多特点。他们由于性格多疑和不爽快而被称为迟疑鬼。——作者原注

[9]波列哈说话时，几乎每句话都添上一种惊叹声：“格！”“巴杰”。——作者原注

彼得·彼得罗维奇·卡拉塔叶夫

大约是五年前的秋天，我在从莫斯科去图拉的途中，由于搞不到马，只得在驿站的房子里瞎待了几乎一整天。我是打猎回来的，我太粗心了，竟然事先就把自己的三匹马打发走了。驿站长是个有大把年纪的人，脸色阴沉沉的，头发耷拉到鼻子上，有一对昏昏欲睡的眼睛。我向他左诉苦右请求，而他只是断断续续地拿气话来回答，愤愤然地把门关得砰砰响，似乎在怨恨自己干的这份差使，并且还到台阶上去斥责手下的车夫，那些车夫有的手里端着笨重的马轭在烂泥地里慢慢地挪步，有的坐在板凳上打呵欠、搔痒痒，不大理睬自己顶头上司的愤怒叫嚷。我已喝过三四回茶，几次想睡都没有睡着。把窗子上和墙壁上的题字全念遍了：我无聊得要死。我怀着冷漠而绝望的心情瞧着自己马车翘起的车杆，蓦然响起了叮当的铃声，随即看到一辆套着三匹疲惫不堪的马的小马车到了台阶上停住了。来人跳下车开口就喊：“快给换马！”接着便进屋来。就在他听到驿站长回答说没有马而露出通常的惊异表情时，我已经怀着一个百无聊赖的人所具的贪婪的好奇心把这个新同伴从头到脚打量了一番。从外表看他年近三十。他的脸上有天花留下的消除不掉的麻斑，那张脸又干又黄，还带有很不悦目的铜色；黑里泛青的长发在脑后一圈圈地披在衣领上，前边的卷成洒脱的鬓发；一双发肿的小眼睛愣神地瞧着，上嘴唇上翘着几根小胡子。他穿得像个去赶马市的随随便便的地主：一件油污斑斑的花上衣，一条退了色的淡紫色绸领带，一件带铜扣子的马甲，一件带大喇叭口的灰裤子，裤脚下露出一点没擦净的皮靴的靴尖。他身上冒出冲鼻的烟味和酒气；他那几乎被上衣袖口遮住的红润肥胖的手指上戴着几枚银戒指和图拉戒指。这样的人物在俄国何止是几十个，可以遇到成百上千的。跟他们这种人结交，应该照实说，是没有任何乐趣可言的。可是，尽管我带着这种成见去观察这位来人，却不能不注意到他脸上那种由衷的和善和热忱的神情。

“您瞧，这位先生也在这儿等了一个多钟头了。”驿站长指着我说。

“一个多钟头！”我心想这坏老头真会拿我开玩笑。

“也许他不是那么急需吧。”来者回答说。

“这我们就不清楚了。”驿站长沉着脸说。

“难道就没有办法可想了？确实没有马吗？”

“没有办法。一匹马也没有。”

“好吧，那就叫人给我拿茶炊来。那就等吧，没法子。”

来者在凳子上坐下来，把帽子甩在桌子上，用手捋了捋头发。

“您用过茶吗？”他问我。

“用过了。”

“跟我一起再喝几杯好吗？”

我同意了。那把棕色大茶炊第四次出现在桌子上。我拿出一瓶罗姆酒。我把这位交谈者看作一个稍有地产的贵族，并没有看错。他的姓名是彼得·彼得罗维奇·卡拉塔叶夫。

我们聊了起来。他到来还不过半个钟头，已经推襟送抱地对我讲述自己的生平。

“如今我是要去莫斯科，”他在喝第四杯的时候对我说，“目前我在乡下已经没事可干了。”

“怎么会没事可干呢？”

“的确没事可干。家业都搞垮了，说实话，我害得庄稼人也破产了；这些年年景不佳，没有收成，再加上种种灾祸……”他垂头丧气地向一旁瞧了瞧，“再说，我算个什么当家的呀！”

“到底为什么呢？”

“不成器呀，”他打断我的话说，“天下哪有我这样的当家人呢！”他把头扭向一边，接连地抽着烟，又接着说：“您看着我，也许以为我是个……可是我，对您说实话，只受过中等教育呀；又没有多少家产。请原谅，我这个人心直口快，而到头来……”

他没有把话说完，便甩了一下手。我就劝他不要这样想，让他相信我很高兴与他相识，等等，后来我还说，管理家业似乎不需要受过分高深的教育。

“我同意，”他回答说，“我同意您的看法。不过总得要有一种特殊的办法……有的人把庄稼人掠夺一空，反倒没事！可是我……请问，您是从彼得堡来的或是从莫斯科来的？”

“我从彼得堡来。”

他从鼻孔里喷出一缕长长的烟气。

“我是去莫斯科谋点差事干干。”

“您打算谋什么差事呢？”

“还说不好，到那边再看吧。不瞒您说，我很怕当差：那是得负责任的。我一向住在乡下，您知道，我习惯了……可是没有法子……穷呀！唉，我可穷怕了！”

“可是今后您就要住在京城里了。”

“在京城里……唉，我不知道京城里有什么好的。瞧瞧看，也许那里不错……我觉得不可能比乡下好。”

“难道您就不可能再待在乡下了吗？”

他叹了一口气。

“不可能了。村子现在可以说不是我的了。”

“怎么回事？”

“那里有一个好人——一个乡亲在经管……一张票据……”

可怜的彼得·彼得罗维奇用手摸了摸脸，想了一下，摇摇头。

“唉，有什么法子……”他稍沉默了一会儿，接着说，“可是说实话，我怨不得谁，全怪自己。我喜欢瞎折腾……真见鬼，喜欢瞎折腾！”

“您在乡下过得愉快吗？”我问他。

“先生，”他直盯着我的眼睛，一字一顿地说，“我曾养了十二对猎狗，对您说吧，那样的猎狗是不可多得的呀。（后面的词他是拉长声说的。）逮野兔本事大着呢，猎起珍奇野兽来像蛇一样灵，简直厉害得不得了。那些猎狗是值得我夸赞的。现在事情都成为过去了，用不着瞎说。我常扛着枪去打猎。我有一头叫孔捷斯卡的狗，它捕猎时的姿势好看着呢，嗅觉灵敏极了。有时我走近沼泽地，喊一声：快找！要是它不去找，哪怕您带十几条狗前去，也是白搭，什么也不会找到！要是它去找——那就非找到不行……而且在家里它也很懂礼貌。用左手拿给它面包，并且说犹太佬吃的，它就不要，若是用右手给它，说小姐吃的，它立刻就抓过去吃。我还有一条它下的狗崽，也棒着呢，我本来想带到莫斯科去，可是有位朋友把那狗崽连同猎枪向我要去了；他说，老兄，你在莫斯科用不到这些玩意儿；老兄，那边完全是另一种天地。我就把这狗崽，还有枪都给了他；这样，全都留在那里了。”

“您在莫斯科也可以打猎嘛。”

“不打了，打什么呀？从前不会克制，如今就得忍着点。正想请教您，在莫斯科生活开销怎么样，很高吗？”

“不，不太高。”

“不太高？……请问，莫斯科有茨冈人吗？”

“什么样的茨冈人？”

“就是在集市上跑来跑去的那种人。”

“有的，在莫斯科……”

“啊，这就好。我喜欢茨冈人，他妈的，我就喜欢……”

彼得·彼得罗维奇闪现出豪爽快乐的眼神。可顷刻间他又在凳子上不安地转动起来，随之便陷入沉思，垂下头，并把空杯子举到我面前。

“给我一点儿您的罗姆酒。”他说。

“可是茶已喝光了。”

“无所谓，就这样喝，不用茶……唉！”

卡拉塔叶夫双手托着头，胳膊支在桌子上。我默默地瞅着他，已等着醉酒的人所特喜欢发出的那种感叹，甚至洒下的眼泪，可是待到他一抬起头，他脸上那种深沉的忧郁表情确实让我大为吃惊。

“您怎么啦？”

“没什么……想起点旧事。一件难忘的事……很想给您说说，不过我不大好意思打扰您……”

“别客气啦！”

“好吧，”他叹口气接着说，“常有一些巧事……比如说，我就遇上过。如果您要听，我就讲给您听听。不过，我不知道……”

“请您讲讲吧，亲爱的彼得·彼得罗维奇。”

“这事说来有点那个……是这样的，”他开始说了，“可是我真不知道……”

“得啦，就讲吧，亲爱的彼得·彼得罗维奇。”

“好，我来讲。这可以说是我的一次巧遇。我是在乡下住的……有一次我突然看到了一个姑娘，啊，一个多么出色的姑娘呀……她长得又漂亮又聪明，而且非常善良！她名叫马特廖娜。可她只是一个普通的丫头，您明白吗，就是一个农奴丫头，简单说就是一名女奴。而且她又不是我家里的，而是属于别人家的——糟就糟在这里。我真的是爱上了她——这样的事确是很有趣吧——而她也爱上了我。于是马特廖娜便一再请求我，要我把她从女主人那里赎出身来；我自己也考虑过这件事……而她的女主人是一个很富有又很可怕的老太婆，住在离我家十五六俄里的一个村子里。后来有一天，我吩咐给我备好一辆三套马车——由我的那头溜蹄马驾辕，这是一匹特种的亚细亚马，取名叫拉姆普尔多斯——我穿得漂漂亮亮的，就驱车前去拜访马特廖娜的女主人。到了那边一看：房子很大，有厢房，有花园……马特廖娜已在大路拐弯处等我，本想同我说几句话，可只是吻了吻我的手便走开了。后来我走进前室，问：‘在家吗？……’一个高个子听差问我：‘您贵姓，怎样通报？’我说：‘伙计，你去说地主卡拉塔叶夫前来有事商谈。’听差进去了；我等候着，心里老在想：会是怎么样呢？也许那老巫婆会漫天要价，别看她很有钱。没准会要五六百卢布。那听差终于转回来了，说声：‘有请。’我跟着他走进客厅。安乐椅上坐着一个身材瘦小、脸色发黄的老太婆，眨巴着眼睛。‘您有何贵干？’您知道，开头我认为需要客气几句，比如说，‘能拜识您，深感荣幸’。她说：‘您搞错了，我不是这儿的女主人，我是她的亲戚……您有何贵干？’我立即对她说，我需要同女主人谈件事。‘马丽娅·伊利尼奇娜今天不会客：她身体不舒服……您有何贵干？’我心想，没有办法，就对她说说我的事吧。老太婆听完了我的话，就问：‘马特廖娜？哪一个马特廖娜？’‘马特廖娜·费多罗娃，库利克的女儿。’‘费多尔·库利克的女儿……您怎么认识她的？’‘偶然认识的。’‘她知道您的意愿吗？’‘知道的。’老太婆沉默了一会儿，突然说：‘我要给她点厉害瞧瞧，这小贱人……’说实话，我听了大吃一惊。‘干吗这样呢，得了吧……我准备出钱替她赎身，您就说个数吧。’这老家伙低声地发狠起来。‘您想拿钱来哄人呀，我们才不稀罕您的钱呢……我要给她点厉害瞧瞧，我要把她……我要打掉她的蠢念头。’老太婆气得咳嗽起来。‘怎么，她嫌我们这儿不好？……哼，这个死丫头，上帝原谅我的罪过！’说实在的，我火了。‘您干吗要恐吓这个可怜的姑娘呢？她有什么错？’老太婆画了一下十字。‘哎呀，我的上帝，耶稣基督！难道我不能教训自己的奴仆吗？’‘她不是您的人呀！’‘哼，马丽娅·伊利尼奇娜会管这件事的；先生，这与您无关；我要让马特廖娜瞧明白，她是谁家的奴仆。’说实话，我差点儿向这可恶的老太婆扑过去，可一想到马特廖娜，手才放了下来。我胆怯起来，怕得不可言状；我一再央求这老太婆说：‘您要多少钱都行呀。’‘您要她干什么呀？’‘我喜欢她，好大娘；请设身处地替我想想吧……请让我吻吻你的手。’我真的吻了这恶婆娘的手！‘好吧，’这妖婆嘟嘟哝哝说，“我会对马丽娅·伊利尼奇娜说的；看她怎么吩咐，您过两三天再来。’我惶惶然地回了家。我开始意识到，这件事我办得不妥，本不该让她们知道我的心意，可等我想到了这一点已经晚了。过了两三天，我又去见那女地主。我被领到办事室里。室内摆了很多很多鲜花，陈设讲究，女主人坐在一把极精致的安乐椅里，头靠在一个枕垫上；上次见到的那个女亲戚也在座，还有一个长着淡黄头发、穿绿色连衣裙、歪嘴的小姐，大概是个女伴当吧。老太婆用鼻音说：‘请坐吧。’我坐了下来。她问起我多大年纪，在哪儿做事，来这里想干什么，她显得高高在上，神气活现。我一一做了回答。老太婆从桌子上拿起一块手绢，朝自己扇了又扇……她说：‘卡捷林娜·卡尔波夫娜已经把您的来意报告过我了，报告过了，可是我立有一条家规：不放奴仆出去侍候别人。这样的事不得体，这对于体面人家很不合适，这不成体统。我已经处理过了，您就不必再费心了。’‘得了吧，什么费心……也许是您很需要马特廖娜·费多罗娃吧？’‘不，’她说，‘不需要她。’‘那么您为什么不肯把她让给我呢？’‘因为我不愿意；不愿意就是不愿意。我已经做了处理：把她遣送到草原村庄去。’我似乎受到雷轰一般。老太婆用法语对那位穿绿衣服的小姐说了两三句话，那小姐便出去了。老太婆又说了：‘我是个严讲规矩的妇人，再说我的身体又不好，经不起打扰。您还是个年轻人，而我已经上了年纪，所以我有资格给您提点忠告。您去谋份差事干干，找个门当户对的女子结亲不是更好吗；有钱的未婚女子不多，但贫寒而品性好的姑娘是可以找得到的。’我瞧着这个老太婆，一点也不明白她在那里胡扯些什么，听倒是听见她说什么结亲，可我耳朵里老是回响着草原村庄这几个字。还结亲呢！……见鬼去吧……”

讲故事的人突然在这里停住了，瞧了瞧我。

“您还没有结婚吧？”

“没有。”

“当然，这事不说也明白了。我忍无可忍，就说：‘得了，大娘，你胡扯什么呀？结什么亲呀？我只是要您明白说句话，您肯不肯让出您的马特廖娜姑娘？’老太婆唉声叹气起来。‘哎呀，他烦死我了！哎呀，叫他走吧！哎呀……’那个女亲戚立刻跑到她身边，朝着我斥骂起来。老太婆还在哼哼着：‘我干吗受这份气？……难道我在自己家里做不了主吗？哎呀，哎呀！’我抓起帽子，疯了似的跑了出来。”

“也许，”讲故事的人接下说，“您会觉得我这样迷恋一个出身寒微的姑娘不怎么像话。我并不想为自己辩解……反正事情已经这样了……您信不信，我白天黑夜都坐立不安……痛苦死了！我老在想，为什么我害了这个不幸的姑娘！我一想到她穿着粗布衣服去放鹅，照主人的命令受着虐待，忍受那个穿柏油靴子的庄稼汉村长的百般辱骂——我便冷汗淋漓。我忍不下去了，打听到她被放逐的村子，便骑马前去。第二天傍晚才赶到那里。显然她们没有料到我会到那边去救她，所以没有下令如何防备我。我装作是邻村的人，直接去找村长。走进院子里一看：马特廖娜正在台阶上坐着，用手托着头。她本要叫喊，我急忙用手势让她别出声，并指了指后院，指了指田野。我走进屋里，跟村长聊了一阵，对他胡诌了一通，便找个机会出来找马特廖娜。这可怜的姑娘紧紧搂住我的脖子。我亲爱的人儿消瘦了，苍白了。我就对她说：‘没关系，马特廖娜，没关系，别哭。’可是我自己却潸潸泪下……我终于感到不好意思了，就对她说：‘马特廖娜，眼泪是消除不了痛苦的，要行动，就是说，要坚决行动，你必须跟我逃跑，必须这样做。’马特廖娜吓呆了……‘那怎么行呀！我会毁掉的，她们会把我整个吃掉！’‘傻瓜，谁找得到你？’‘找得到的，一定会被找到的。谢谢您了，彼得·彼得罗维奇，我一辈子忘不了您的情爱，可眼下您就别管我了；看来，我就是这样的命。’‘唉，马特廖娜，马特廖娜，我一直认为你是个坚强的姑娘呢。’的确，她的性格是很坚强的……还有一颗金子般的心！‘你干吗留在这儿呢！反正是一样，不会更糟的。你说说，你尝过村长的拳头了吗，啊？’马特廖娜的脸刷一下红了，嘴唇哆嗦起来。‘因为我，我一家的人会活不成的。’‘怎么，会把你家里的人……都流放吗？’‘会被流放的；我那哥哥准会被流放。’‘而父亲呢？’‘父亲倒不会被流放，他在我们那里是唯一的好裁缝。’‘那还算好；你哥哥即使这样也不会毁掉的。’您可知道，我横说竖说才说通了她；她还想起问我将来会不会为这事担责任……我说：‘这你就别管了……’我终于把她带走了……不是这一次，而是另一次：一天夜里我坐马车来把她带走了。”

“带走了？”

“带走了……就这样，她在我家里住了下来。我家的房子不大，仆人也少。说真的，我的仆人都很尊敬我；他们不会为任何好处而出卖我的。我开始过起快快活活的日子。马特列努什卡[1]经过一段时间休息，恢复了健康；我对她眷恋极了……她是个多么出色的姑娘呀！不知从哪儿学会的呀，她竟会唱歌、跳舞、弹吉他……我不让她给乡亲们看见，免得有人多嘴说出去！可我有一位朋友，是我的至交，叫戈尔诺斯塔叶夫·潘捷莱，您不认识吧？他对她简直倾慕极了；像对一位太太似的去吻她的手，真的。对您说吧，戈尔诺斯塔叶夫跟我可不一样：他是一个有学识的人，普希金的书他全读过；有时他跟马特廖娜和我聊天，我们听得可有味啦。他教会了她写字，多怪的人呀！我让她穿得简直比省长夫人还讲究；我给她缝了件毛皮镶边的深红色丝绒外套……这件外套她穿起来多气派呀！这件外套是一位莫斯科的时装店女老板按新潮款式缝制的，是带卡腰的。而且这个马特廖娜是多么的怪啊！有时候她沉思起来，一连几个钟头坐在那里，瞅着地板，眉毛一动不动；于是我也坐在那里瞅着她，怎么也瞅个没够，仿佛从来没有见过似的……她微微一笑，我的心就打战，如同有人呵我的痒痒。有时她会突然笑起来，开起玩笑，手舞足蹈起来；她那么火热地、紧紧地拥抱我，使我乐昏了头。我常常从早到晚只想着一件事：怎样能让她快快乐乐？您信不信，我送给她东西就是为了要瞧瞧她，我的心肝，是怎样的高兴，高兴得脸蛋通红，瞧瞧她怎样试穿我送她的新衣服，怎样换上新装前来亲吻我。不知道她父亲库利克是怎样打听到这事的；老爷子前来看望我们，并且一个劲地哭……这是出于高兴而哭的，您怎么想呢？我们给了他好多东西。她，我的小鸽子，最后亲自拿给他一张五卢布钞票——他竟扑通一声向她下跪——一个多么怪的老头呀！我们就这样过了五个来月，我真希望跟她这样过一辈子，可是我的命运太可悲了！”

彼得·彼得罗维奇把话停住了。

“出了什么事啦？”我关切地问他。

他摆了摆手。

“全都完蛋了。我把她也给毁了。我的马特列努什卡特别喜欢坐雪橇，而且常常由自己驾驶；她穿上自己的外套，戴上托尔若克式手套，一路只管叫呀喊呀。我们总是晚间出去，为的是不碰到什么人。有一回我们选了一个大好的天；天气寒冷、明朗、没有风……我们乘雪橇出去。马特廖娜握着马缰绳。我看着，看她把雪橇驾到哪儿去？难道要驾到库库叶夫卡去，驾到她那女主人的村子里去？可不，正是奔向库库叶夫卡去。我对她说：‘你疯了，你要上哪儿去呀？’她回头瞧了瞧我，笑了笑。她说：‘让我去闹一下。’我心想：‘唉，不管那么多啦……’从主人的宅院旁边驶过去是好玩的吗？您说说看，是好玩的吗？我们就这样前去了。我的溜蹄马平平稳稳地奔跑着，两匹拉梢的马简直如旋风般的飞奔——不多一会儿就看见库库叶夫卡村的教堂；再一看，有一辆旧的绿色雪地轿车在大路上缓缓地行驶，一个仆人站在车后脚镫上……是女主人，是女主人乘车来了！我本来就害怕的，可是马特廖娜用缰绳使劲地抽着马，向那轿车直冲过去！那轿车的车夫看到有辆雪橇迎面飞奔过来，便想避向一旁，可是车子转得太急了，便翻倒在雪堆上。车窗的玻璃碰碎了，女主人喊了起来：‘哎呀，哎呀，哎呀！哎呀，哎呀，哎呀！’女伴当也尖声叫喊：‘停下，停下！’而我们急忙从旁边溜过去了。我们的雪橇飞奔着，我心里在想：‘这下可糟了，我不该让她到库库叶夫卡来。’您猜怎么着？原来那女主人已认出了马特廖娜，也认出了我，过后这老太婆就去告我，说：‘我的逃亡女仆就住在贵族卡拉塔叶夫家。’她还花了大笔钱去贿赂有关当局。不出我所料，县警察局长找上我门来了；这位局长原是我的相识，叫斯捷潘·谢尔盖伊奇·库佐夫金，他表面上是个好人，可实质上是个坏人。他来了，如此这般说了一套，然后说：‘彼得·彼得罗维奇，您怎么干出这种事呢？……责任可严重呢，这方面法律有明文规定。’我对他说：‘当然，这事咱们要好好谈一谈，不过您路上辛苦了，要不要先吃点什么？’吃嘛他是同意的，不过他说：‘事情是要秉公处理的，彼得·彼得罗维奇，您自己想一想吧。’我说：‘那当然，事情要秉公处理，事情当然要……哦，我听说您有一匹黑毛马驹，要不要和我的那匹拉姆普尔多斯换一换？……至于那个马特廖娜·费多罗娃丫头嘛，我这里可没有。’他说：‘唉，彼得·彼得罗维奇，那丫头就在您这儿，要知道我们不是住在瑞士嘛……至于用我的马驹换您的拉姆普尔多斯倒是可以的；或者，就把这匹马带走也行。’这一次我好歹把他打发走了。可是那个老太婆比先头闹得更凶了；她说，花费万把块钱也不在乎。您知道不，当初她一见到我，便突然心血来潮，想让我娶她的那个穿绿衣服的女伴当——这是我后来才知道的，所以她才那样气恼。这种地主婆们什么鬼主意想不出来呀！……也许是由于无聊的关系吧。我得倒霉了：花些钱我倒不可惜，我把马特廖娜藏了起来——还是不行呀！她们老揪住我不放，可把我折腾死了。我负了债，身体也垮下来了……有一天夜里，我躺在床上，想来想去：‘我的天哪，我为什么受这番折磨？既然我不能抛弃她，那我该如何是好？……唉，我不能，绝对不能呀！’马特廖娜突然走进我的房间。那时候我已把她藏在离我家两三俄里的一个村子里。我吓坏了。‘怎么回事？你在那边被发现了？’‘不，彼得·彼得罗维奇，’她说，‘在布勃诺沃没有人来惊扰我，可是能长久这样下去吗？我的心都碎了，彼得·彼得罗维奇；我可怜您，我亲爱的；我一辈子忘不了您的情爱，彼得·彼得罗维奇，可是，现在我是来向您告别的。’‘你怎么啦，你怎么啦，疯啦？……怎么说告别？告什么别？’‘是这样……我要去自首。’‘你疯了，那我就把你锁在阁楼里……你是想把我毁了？要让我送命，是吗？’她没有吭声，眼瞧着地板。‘喂，你说话呀，说话呀！’‘我不愿再给您添麻烦了，彼得·彼得罗维奇。’唉，对她还能讲什么呢……‘可你知道吗，傻瓜，你知道吗，疯……疯丫头……’”

彼得·彼得罗维奇痛哭起来。

“您猜怎么着？”他在桌子上击了一拳，又继续说，一边紧蹙起眉头，然而眼泪仍是从他那火辣辣的两颊往下直淌，“这姑娘真的自首了，真的去自首了……”

“先生，马匹准备好了！”驿站长走进屋里，庄严地喊了一声。

我们两人都站了起来。

“后来马特廖娜怎么样了？”我问。

卡拉塔叶夫摆了摆手。

我跟卡拉塔叶夫那次萍水相逢之后，又过了一年，我因事到了莫斯科。有一回我在午饭前来到猎人市场后面的一家咖啡馆——那是莫斯科独具一格的咖啡馆。台球房里烟雾腾腾，烟雾中闪现着一些红彤彤的脸庞、小胡子、蓬松的头发、旧式的匈牙利外衣和最新潮的斯拉夫外衣。一伙穿着朴素常礼服的瘦老头在那里阅读俄罗斯报纸。那些跑堂的端着托盘，轻轻地踩着绿色的地毯，敏捷地东跑西跑。商人们面露苦恼紧张的神色在饮茶。蓦地里从台球房里走出一个头发有点散乱、步履不大稳健的人。他的两手插在口袋里，茫然地瞧了瞧周围。

“哎呀，哎呀，哎呀！彼得·彼得罗维奇！……别来无恙？”

彼得·彼得罗维奇差点扑上来搂我的脖子，他微微晃着身子，拉着我走进一个小单间去。

“就在这儿坐，”他说，热情地拉我到一张安乐椅上坐下，“这儿坐得舒服些。茶房，上啤酒！不，拿香槟！哎呀，说实话，真没料到，真没料到……来好久了？要待很久吗？真可谓是有缘分哪……

“是呀，记得吗……”

“怎么不记得呢，怎么不记得呢，”他急忙打断我的话说，“过去的事……过去的事呀……”

“那您在这儿现在干些什么呢，亲爱的彼得·彼得罗维奇？”

“您瞧，就这么活着。在这儿日子过得很好，这儿的人都很热情。我在这儿挺安心的。”

他叹了口气，抬眼望着天。

“在任职吗？”

“没有，还没有任职，可我想会很快有事干的。任职有什么呢？……人——是最重要的。我在这儿结识了一些很好的人呢……”

一名小厮用黑托盘端进来一瓶香槟酒。

“瞧，这就是个好人……是不是，瓦夏，你是个好人？为你的健康干杯！”

这小厮站了一会儿，礼貌地摇了摇头，笑了笑，就出去了。

“是的，这儿的人都很好，”彼得·彼得罗维奇接下说，“有感情，有灵魂……要不要我给您介绍介绍？都是些很体面的朋友……他们认识您会很高兴的。我告诉您……博布罗夫死了，真不幸。”

“哪一个博布罗夫？”

“谢尔盖·博布罗夫。是个很好的人；他照顾过我这个没知识的乡下人。戈尔诺斯塔叶夫·潘捷莱也死了。都死了，都死了！”

“您一直在莫斯科住？没有到乡下去？”

“到乡下去……我的村子被卖掉了。”

“被卖了？”

“是拍卖的……可惜您没有买！”

“那以后您靠什么过日子呢，彼得·彼得罗维奇？”

“我不会饿死的，老天爷会保佑！钱没有，而朋友会有。钱算得了什么？是堆尘土而已！黄金也是尘土！”

他眯起眼睛，把手伸进衣袋里摸了摸，掏出两个十五戈比和一个十戈比钱币放在手心上给我看。

“这是什么？这就是尘土！（钱币飞落在地上。）您还是告诉我吧，您读过波列扎耶夫[2]的诗没有？”

“读过。”

“看过莫恰洛夫[3]扮演哈姆莱特吗？”

“没有，没有看过。”

“没有看过，没有看过……（卡拉塔叶夫脸色发白了，眼珠不安地转来转去；他扭过脸去；嘴唇微微地痉挛着。）唉，莫恰洛夫，莫恰洛夫！‘把生命结束了——睡去了’。”他用低沉的嗓音说。

什么都完了；要是在这一种睡眠之中，
我们心头的创痛，以及其他无数血肉之躯
所不能避免的打击，都可以从此消失，
那正是我们求之不得的结局。死了，睡去了……[4]

“睡去了，睡去了！”他低声地重复了好几遍。

“请您说说看……”我正要问他，可他又满怀热情地接下念道：

谁愿意忍受人世的鞭挞和讥嘲，
压迫者的凌辱，傲慢者的冷眼，
被轻蔑的爱情的惨痛，法律的迁延，官吏的横暴，
和微贱者费尽辛勤所换来的卑视，
要是他只要用一柄小小的刀子，
就可以清算他自己的一生？……在你的祈祷之中，
不要忘记替我忏悔我的罪孽[5]。

他把头埋在桌子上。他结结巴巴地随便胡诌起来。

“又过了一个月！”他重新鼓起劲来念道：

短短的一个月以前
她哭得像个泪人儿似的，
送我那可怜的父亲下葬；
她在送葬时穿的那双鞋子还没有穿旧，
她就，她就……上帝啊！一头没有理性的畜生
也要悲伤得长久一些……[6]

他把一杯香槟酒端到嘴边，但没有去喝，而是继续念道：

为了赫卡柏！
赫卡柏对他有什么相干，他对赫卡柏又有什么相干，
他却要为她流泪？……
可是我，一个糊涂颟顸的家伙……
我是一个懦夫吗？谁骂我恶人？……
谁当面指斥我胡说？……
我应该忍受这样的侮辱，
因为我是一个没有心肝、
逆来顺受的怯汉……[7]

卡拉塔叶夫手上的酒杯掉下地了，他抓着自己的头。我似乎觉得我了解他了。

“唉，得了，”最后他说，“不要再去提旧事了……对吗？（他笑了起来。）为您的健康干杯！”

“您要在莫斯科待下去？”我问他。

“我要死在莫斯科！”

“卡拉塔叶夫！”隔壁房间里传来呼唤声，“卡拉塔叶夫，您在哪儿？到这儿来，亲爱的朋友！”

“他们喊我了，”他说着，笨重地从座位站了起来，“再见吧；如果有空，请上我那儿去聊聊，我住在×××。”

可到了第二天，由于一些意外情况，我得离开莫斯科，就没有再跟彼得·彼得罗维奇·卡拉塔叶夫见面了。

[1]即马特廖娜的昵称或爱称。

[2]阿·伊·波列扎耶夫（一八〇〇四——一八三八），俄罗斯诗人。

[3]帕·斯·莫恰洛夫（一八〇〇——一八四八），俄罗斯演员。

[4]请见《哈姆莱特》（朱生豪译，下同）第三幕第一场。

[5]请见《哈姆莱特》第三幕第一场。

[6]请见《哈姆莱特》第一幕第二场。

[7]请见《哈姆莱特》第二幕第二场。

幽　会

秋天，九月中光景，我在一个小白桦林里歇息。从一早便下起蒙蒙细雨，不时地交替出现暖烘烘的阳光；这是一种变幻莫测的天气。有时天空布满一层散淡的白云，有时几处豁然清朗，从散开的云层后面呈现出一片蓝空，明亮而亲切，宛如一只迷人的眼睛。我坐着，观赏着周围，倾听着。树叶在我头上低声喧闹；从它们的喧闹声里便可知道眼前属于什么季节。这不是春天欢快、战颤的笑语，不是夏天轻柔的沙沙声和绵绵絮语声，也不是深秋羞涩而冷峻的嘟哝声，这是一种难得听清的、催人欲睡的闲聊声。树梢上微风轻拂。被雨淋湿的林子里面在不断地变化着，时而阳光灿烂，时而云遮雾罩；有时整个通亮，仿佛万物都突露微笑：不很稠密的白桦细干顿时洒满白丝绸似的柔光，掉在地上的小树叶即刻变得色彩斑斓，闪烁着赤金般的光泽，高挑而蓬松的羊齿植物已染上像熟透的葡萄似的秋色，它们的优美茎秆在你眼前无尽头地、杂乱地相互交错在一起；有时四周蓦然微微泛蓝：艳丽的色彩顷刻间消失了，白桦树依然是白色的，可失去了亮泽，白得像未经冬天寒冷阳光照射过的新雪；那细雨又开始悄悄地、调皮地洒向树林，淅淅沥沥。白桦树上的叶子几乎还一片翠绿，虽然已显出几分苍白；独有一处长着一棵小白桦，全身是红色的或金色的，可以看到，当阳光五彩缤纷地滑翔着，突然穿过刚由亮晶晶的雨水冲洗过的茂密树枝，这棵小白桦在阳光中显得何等的光彩夺目啊。听不到鸟儿的啁啾：它们到各处歇息了，静默下来了；唯有偶尔响起山雀的嘲笑声，宛如铜铃。我在这片小白桦林歇息之前，曾带着我的狗穿过一片高高的白杨树林。说实话，我不大喜欢这种白杨树以及它淡紫色的树干和灰绿色的金属般的叶子，这种叶子被树高高地向上托起，像颤动的扇子一般在空中展开；我不喜欢它那些不适当地挂在长长茎秆上的零乱圆叶不停地摇晃的样子。这种树只有在某些夏日夜晚才显得可爱，那时候它独自耸立在低低的灌木丛中，染着夕阳的红光，闪闪烁烁，从根部到梢头染遍同样的红黄色；或者是在明朗有风的日子，它整个儿在蓝空中喧闹摇荡，或者窃窃私语，它的每片叶子似乎都要挣脱树枝，奔向远方，这种光景也很令人喜欢。不过总的说来我不喜欢这种树，所以我没有停留在白杨林里休息，而是跑到小白桦林里，找到一棵树枝低垂、可以避雨的树来藏身，我在欣赏一番周围的景色之后，便安稳地、舒坦地睡了一觉，这样的觉只有猎人才会领略得到。

我说不清自己睡了多大一会儿，当我睁开眼睛时，树林里到处洒满阳光，透过那欢腾喧闹的树叶，看得见浅蓝色的天空，它仿佛在闪闪发亮；云被风儿驱散了，消失了；天气格外清朗，你可感到空气中弥漫着一种特殊的干爽的新鲜气息，令你心旷神怡，精神焕发，它在向人们预告，在这整天的阴雨之后，将是一个平静清明的夜晚。我已准备起身，想再去碰碰运气，忽然我的眼睛看到一个呆然不动的人体。我细细一瞧，那是一个年轻轻的农家少女。她坐在离我二十步远的地方，正在埋头沉思，两只手搁在膝上；在一只半伸开的手掌上放着一束密匝匝的野花，随着她的一呼一吸，这束野花轻轻地滑落在方格裙上，那扣着领口和袖口的洁白衬衫，形成短短的柔和的皱褶，围在她的身躯上；大粒的黄色珠串盘成两行，从脖上挂到胸前。她颇有姿色。带点漂亮浅灰色的浓密金发在鲜红的狭发带下精心地梳成两个半圆形，那发带几乎移到白如象牙的额门上；她的脸庞的其他部分几乎被晒成古铜色，只有细嫩的肌肤才会有这样的颜色。我看不清她的眼睛，因为她没有抬起眼睛来；可是我清楚地看见她那副高高细细的眉毛和长长的睫毛，那睫毛是湿润的；在她的一边脸颊上还有干了的泪痕，它落在略微苍白的嘴唇上，在阳光下闪着亮。她的整个头部都显得挺可爱；虽然鼻子稍稍胖圆了一点，也无伤大雅。我特别喜欢她的脸部表情：它是那样的单纯而温柔，那样的忧伤，对于自己的忧伤又是那样充满稚气的疑惑。她显然是在等候一个人；林子里出现某种轻微的响动，她立即四下张望；在明净的阴影里，她那双像扁角鹿一样畏怯的明亮的大眼睛在我面前迅速地一闪。她倾听了片刻，睁大眼睛盯着发出轻微声响的地方，叹了口气，轻轻地扭过头，她的身子弯得更低了，开始慢慢地采摘花朵。她的眼睑红红的，嘴唇痛苦地颤动着，从那浓密的睫毛里又滚出了泪珠，沾在脸颊上，一闪一闪。就这样过了好一阵子；这可怜的姑娘木然不动，只是偶尔愁闷地动一动手，她在倾听，一直在倾听……林子里又有什么响了，她战颤了一下。响声没有停息下来，反而变得更清晰了，越来越近了，终于变成了坚定而急促的脚步声。她挺直了身子，似乎胆怯起来。她那凝视的目光颤抖起来，由于期待而闪亮。透过密密的树木，迅速地闪现出一个男子的身影。她细细一瞧，顿时满脸绯红，欢喜而幸福地微笑了，她本想站起身来，又立刻埋下头去，脸色泛白，有些腼腆，直到那个前来的人在她身旁停下步来，她才抬起颤抖的几近祈求的目光望着他。

我从自己的隐蔽处好奇地观望他。说实话，他没有带给我愉快的印象。从他的种种神情举止来看，他是一个富有的年轻地主所惯坏了的侍仆。从他那身打扮可看出他很讲时尚，炫示漂亮洒脱：他穿着一件古铜色短大衣，可能是主人穿旧了给他的，扣子直扣到领口，系着一条两端雪青色的粉红领带，头戴镶金边的黑丝绒便帽，直压到眉毛。他那白衬衫的圆领过分地撑着他的耳朵，硬顶着他的脸颊，浆硬的袖口遮住了他的整只手，直遮到红润而弯曲的手指，手指上戴着金银戒指，戒指上镶有毋忘侬花形的绿宝石。他脸色红润、鲜嫩，又有点无赖相，据我所知，这类脸孔几乎总是让男人们气恼，遗憾的是，女人们见了往往挺喜欢。他显然竭力让自己的有点粗鲁的相貌露出一副轻蔑而无聊的表情。他不断地眯起那双本来就过小的乳灰色眼睛，皱着眉头，撇下嘴唇的两角，不自然地打着呵欠，装出一种满不在乎，然而又不很巧妙的洒脱模样，时而用手整一整鬈曲得挺帅气的棕黄色鬓发，时而揪一揪竖起在肥厚上唇上的黄色小胡子——总之，他装腔作势得令人受不了。他一看见那位正在等候他的年轻的农家姑娘后，就开始装腔作势；他慢悠悠地、大摇大摆地走到她的跟前，站了一会儿，耸耸肩膀，把两手插在大衣口袋里，稍稍向这位可怜的姑娘投去匆匆而淡然的一瞥，便坐下来了。

“怎么，”他开始说，仍然向一旁瞧着别处，晃动一只腿，打着呵欠，“你在这儿等很久了吗？”

姑娘没能立即回答他。

“等很久啦，维克托·亚历山大雷奇。”她终于以很低的声音回答说。

“唉！（他摘下帽子，派头地用手捋捋那几乎从眉边长起的紧紧鬈曲着的浓发，威严地瞧瞧周围，又小心地把帽子盖在自己的宝贵脑袋上。）我把这件事全给忘了。再说，天又下雨！（他又打了一下呵欠。）事情太多了：哪能件件都顾得上，老爷还要骂人呢。我们明天就要动身了……”

“明天？”姑娘问，向他投去惊讶的目光。

“明天……行了，行了，别难过啦，”他看到她浑身哆嗦起来，慢慢垂下头去，他气恼地急忙说，“阿库利娜，请别哭啦。你知道我受不了这个。（他皱起自己的扁鼻子。）要不，我马上就走……哭哭啼啼，多蠢哪！”

“好吧，我不哭，我不哭。”阿库利娜赶紧说，一边尽力咽下眼泪。“这么说您明天就走？”她沉默了一会儿后说，“什么时候能和您再见面呢，维克托·亚历山大雷奇？”

“会见面的，会见面的。不是明年，就是以后。老爷看来想在彼得堡谋份差使干干，”他慢不经心地带点鼻音说，“说不定还要到外国去。”

“您会忘记我的，维克托·亚历山大雷奇。”阿库利娜悲伤地说。

“不，怎么会呢？我不会忘记你，不过你要变得聪明些，别犯傻，听你爹的话……我不会忘记你的，不会的。”（他坦然地伸了一下腰，又打一下呵欠。）

“别忘了我，维克托·亚历山大雷奇，”她用哀求的声音继续说，“我真的非常爱您，真是一切都为了您……您刚刚说，要我听我爹的话，维克托·亚历山大雷奇……可我怎能听我爹的话呢？……”

“怎么呢？”他仰躺着，把两手垫在脑袋下，他仿佛是从胃里掏出这句话。

“怎能听呢，维克托·亚历山大雷奇，您是知道的……”

她没有说下去。维克托玩弄着他的钢表链。

“你，阿库利娜，不是个笨丫头，”他终于说起话来，“所以就别说胡话了。我希望你好，你懂我的意思吗？当然，你不笨，可以说，不完全像个乡下姑娘；你娘也不一向是个乡下的婆娘。不过，你毕竟没受过教育，所以人家对你说话，你就该听。”

“多可怕呀，维克托·亚历山大雷奇。”

“胡说什么呀，亲爱的，有什么可怕的！你这是什么？”他向她挪近一些，继续说，“是花？”

“是花。”阿库利娜愁苦地回答。“这是我采的艾菊，”她稍显活跃地继续说，“牛犊挺爱吃的。这是能治瘰疬病的鬼针草。您瞧瞧，好奇怪的花呀；这么奇怪的花，我打小起一直没见过。这是毋忘侬，这是香堇菜……这是我为您采的，”她继续说，一边从黄艾菊下拿出一小束用细草扎好的浅蓝色矢车菊，“您要吗？”

维克托懒洋洋地伸手拿过花，不经意地嗅了嗅，把它放在手指里转来转去，带着沉思的庄严表情向天仰望着。阿库利娜瞧着他……在她忧郁目光里洋溢着温柔的忠诚、敬仰的顺从和爱心。她有些怕他，不敢哭泣，又要和他告别，又要最后一次欣赏他。他像土耳其皇帝似的伸开手脚躺在那里，带着大度的耐心和体谅忍受她的爱慕。说真的，我很气愤地打量着他红红的脸蛋：在这张脸蛋上，透过那种伪装轻蔑的冷淡，显出一种自满和讨厌的自负。在这片刻间阿库利娜显得可爱极了：她的整个心灵信任而热烈地显露在他的眼前，追求他，向他表示亲热，而他……他把矢车菊扔在草地上，从大衣的一侧口袋里掏出一个镶着铜镜框的圆镜片，把它按在一只眼睛上；可是不管他怎样使劲皱起眉头，抬起脸皮甚至鼻子来托住它，镜片仍然掉了下来，落在他的手上。

“这是什么？”惊讶的阿库利娜终于问道。

“单眼镜。”他神气地回答。

“做什么用的？”

“戴上它可以看得更清楚。”

“给我看看。”

维克托皱了皱眉头，但还是把镜片递给了她。

“小心，别打碎了。”

“别担心，不会打碎的。（她怯生生地把镜片按到一只眼睛上。）我什么也看不见呀。”她天真地说。

“你要把一只眼睛眯起来才是。”他以不满的指导者口气说。（她眯起了那只对着镜片的眼睛。）“不是这一只，不是这一只，笨蛋！眯另一只眼！”维克托喊道，不等她矫正自己的错误，便把单眼镜从她手里夺了回去。

阿库利娜脸红了，微微地笑着，转过脸去。

“看来我们用不了。”她说。

“当然啰！”

这位可怜的姑娘沉默了一会儿，深深地叹了口气。

“唉，维克托·亚历山大雷奇，您走了，我将怎么过呀！”她突然说。

维克托用衣襟擦了擦镜片，把它放回口袋里。

“那是，那是，”他终于说话了，“你起初的确会感到难过的。（他体谅地拍了拍她的肩膀；她轻轻地从肩上拉过他的手，羞涩地吻了吻它。）是啊，是啊，你的确是个好姑娘，”他得意地微笑一下，继续说，“可是有什么法子呢？你自己说说看！我和老爷是不可能留在这里的；现在冬天快到了，乡下的冬天——你是知道的——简直糟透了。在彼得堡可就大不一样了！在那里简直美妙得很，像你这样的笨丫头连做梦也梦不到的。多漂亮的房子、街道，还有社交、教育——简直令人吃惊……（阿库利娜像小孩似的微张着嘴，贪婪地、专注地听着他讲。）不过，”他在地上翻滚着身子，补充说道，“我把这一切说给你听干什么呢？反正你对这些也搞不明白。”

“为什么呢，维克托·亚历山大雷奇？我明白，我全明白。”

“瞧你什么样！”

阿库利娜低下了头。

“早先您不是这样同我说话的，维克托·亚历山大雷奇。”她说，没有抬起眼睛。

“早先？……早先！瞧你！……早先！”他似乎恼怒地说。

他俩都不吭声了。

“我该走了。”维克托说，已经用胳膊肘支起身子……

“再等一会儿吧。”阿库利娜用恳求的语气说。

“等什么呢？……我反正同你告别过了。”

“等一会儿吧。”阿库利娜重说了一遍。

维克托又躺下来，一边吹起口哨。阿库利娜一直盯着他看。我看得出，她渐渐地激动起来：她的双唇颤动着，她的苍白的脸颊微微地泛红……

“维克托·亚历山大雷奇，”她终于用断断续续的声音说起话来，“您好狠心哪……您好狠心哪，维克托·亚历山大雷奇，真的！”

“怎么狠心？”他皱起眉头问，稍稍抬起头，并转向她。

“好狠心呀，维克托·亚历山大雷奇。分别的时候哪怕对我说一句好话，哪怕说一句也好，对我这个孤苦不幸的人……”

“让我对你说什么呢？”

“我不知道；这您知道得更清楚，维克托·亚历山大雷奇。眼看您就要走了，哪怕说一句也好……凭什么我要受这样对待？”

“你这个人多怪呀！我能做什么呢？”

“哪怕说一句也好……”

“哼，说的老是这一套。”他气恼地说，一边站起身来。

“不要生气嘛，维克托·亚历山大雷奇。”她赶紧接着说，勉强忍住眼泪。

“我没有生气，只是你那笨样……你想要什么呢？我总不能跟你结婚吧？总不能吧？既然这样，你还想要什么呢？想要什么呢？（他伸过脸，似乎在等待回答，五指大大张开着。）

“我什么……什么也不要，”她结结巴巴地回答，勉强壮着胆子向他伸出发颤的双手，“在分别的时候，哪怕说一句话……”

她的眼泪如小溪似的流淌。

“哼，又哭啦，真是的。”维克托冷冰冰地说，把帽子从后面拉到眼睛上。

“我什么也不要，”她继续说，一边抽噎着，两手遮住脸，“可是我以后在家里怎么办呢？我怎么办呢？我会遭到什么呢，我这苦命人会怎么样呢？他们会把我这个孤苦无依的人嫁给我不喜欢的人……我太可怜了！”

“老是这样，老是这样。”维克托在原地倒换着两只脚，低声喃喃地说。

“你哪怕说一句，哪怕说一句……就说，阿库利娜，我……”

突如其来的撕肝裂肺的号哭没有让她把话说完——她扑倒在草地上，悲切地大哭起来……她全身抽搐地起伏着，后脑勺忽高忽低……长期压抑着的悲伤终于像洪流似的奔涌出来。维克托在她旁边站了一会儿，耸耸肩膀，转过身，大步地扬长而去。

过了不多一会儿……她平静下来，抬起头，跳起身来，向四周瞧了瞧，惊异地拍了拍手；她本想前去追他，可是她两腿发软，跪倒在地上……我忍不住了，急忙向她奔去；她刚一看见我，不知从哪儿得来一股气力——轻轻喊了一声，站起身来，消失在树林里，让散乱的花留在地上。

我站了一会儿，捡起那一小束矢车菊，走出林子，来到田野。太阳低悬在亮白的天空，它的光线似乎也变淡了，变冷了：它们没有辉耀，只是洒下平静的、几近无色的光。离黄昏不过半个来小时，而晚霞还刚刚出现。一阵阵的风穿过枯黄的麦茬向我飞扑而来；在这些麦茬前，蜷曲的小树叶急匆匆地飞腾起来，从旁边穿过道路，沿着林边空地飞卷而去；树林朝向田野的浓密一面都在颤动着，微微闪烁着，清晰而不耀眼；在稍稍发红的草上，在草茎上，在麦秆上，到处闪耀着、晃动着秋蜘蛛的无数丝线。我停下脚步……我忧伤起来：凋萎中的大自然露出虽还清新但不欢快的微笑，在这种微笑背后，不久将至的冬天的凄凉可怕景象似乎已在悄然逼近了。一只谨慎的乌鸦以双翼沉重而急剧地划着空气，高高地飞过我的上空，它回过头向我斜视一眼，又向上腾飞，时断时续地啼喊着，消失在林子的后面；一大群鸽子从打谷场急速地飞来，突然盘旋成柱形，接着匆忙地散降在田野上——这是秋天的标志！在寸草不长的小山冈后面有人在驾车赶路，传来一阵空马车的响声……

我回到了家；而那个可怜的阿库利娜的身影久久地没有离开我的脑海，她那束早已枯萎了的矢车菊，至今仍留在我的家里……

切尔托普哈诺夫的末路

一

我那次访问切尔托普哈诺夫之后约过了两年，这位仁兄便开始多灾多难了，确确实实地多灾多难了。在此之前他曾遇上过一些不称心、不顺遂，甚至倒霉的事，可是他对这些事全没在意，依然如“帝王”似的过他的日子。最先令他大为震惊又令他大为伤心的灾难乃是玛莎跟他分道扬镳。

玛莎在他家里似乎已过得非常习惯了，究竟是什么原因使她要离开这个家，那就很难道个明白了。切尔托普哈诺夫至死都认定，玛莎之所以背弃他，全要怪邻村的一个年轻人，此人是一个退伍的枪骑兵大尉，外号叫亚夫。按切尔托普哈诺夫的说法，这小子之所以能勾引女人，仅仅是因为他能不停地捻弄胡子，肯费大力气化妆打扮，并会用心良苦地哼哼哈哈；不过话说回来，应该认为这方面起主要作用的乃是玛莎血管里流着流浪的茨冈人的血液。且不管什么原因，反正在一个夏天的傍晚，玛莎把一些衣服什么的打了个包袱，就离开了切尔托普哈诺夫的家门。

在出走之前两三天里，她老待在角落里，缩着身子靠在墙壁上，宛如一只受了伤的狐狸，对谁都不吭一声，只是老在转悠着眼睛，在一边沉思默想，时而扬扬眉头，微微龇着牙，时而缓缓地移动两手，仿佛要把身子裹得严严的。以前她也闹过这样的“情绪”，不过从来没有持续多久。切尔托普哈诺夫知道这种情况，所以并不担心，也不去打扰她。有一天，他的管猎狗的仆人向他报告，说家里所剩的两只猎狗都完蛋了，他便前去查看一下，当他从狗舍回来的时候，碰上一个女仆，她用哆哆嗦嗦的声音报告说，玛丽娅·阿金菲叶夫娜[1]叫她向他问候，祝愿他万事如意，可是玛丽娅她再不回到他这个家了。切尔托普哈诺夫在原地转了两个圈，声嘶力竭地狂叫了一声，急忙就去追赶这个私奔的女人，顺手还捎上了手枪。

他在离家两俄里的一片白桦树林边上，在那条通往县城的大道上追上了她。太阳已低低地西垂了，周围的一切，树木、花草和大地顿时染得一片通红。

“要找亚夫去呀！要找亚夫去呀！”切尔托普哈诺夫一看见玛莎便痛心地哼哼说，“要找亚夫去呀！”他叨咕着，几乎一步一绊地向她跑过去。

玛莎停下步，转过脸朝着他。她背对阳光站着，所以全身黑乎乎的，如同用乌木雕成一样。唯有眼白像银色扁桃仁似的看得特清，而瞳仁却显得更黑了。

她把包袱扔到一边，交叉起双臂。

“您想到亚夫那里去，真不要脸！”切尔托普哈诺夫又说了一遍，本想抓住她的肩膀，可是一碰上她那目光，便慌了神，在原地犹豫起来。

“我不是上亚夫先生那儿去，潘捷莱·叶列梅伊奇，”玛莎坦然地低声回答，“可是我不能再同您一起过了。”

“怎么不能一起过啦？这是为什么？难道我有什么地方得罪了你？”

玛莎摇摇头。

“您没有任何得罪我的地方，潘捷莱·叶列梅伊奇，只是我在您家里待腻了……您过去对我好，我谢谢了，可是我不能再留下来——不能了！”

切尔托普哈诺夫大吃一惊；他甚至用两手在大腿上狠拍一下，蹦了起来。

“怎么能这样呢？你过得好好的，快快活活，平平安安，可突然觉得腻了！一说腻了就抛开他！包上头巾就走人。你受的各种尊敬不比一个当夫人的差呀……”

“这些对于我无所谓。”玛莎打断他的话说。

“怎么无所谓？从一个茨冈女骗子变成了一位夫人，能说无所谓吗？怎么个无所谓呀，你这天生的贱货！这种人能让人信得过吗？必定会背弃，背弃！”

他又低声地发狠。

“我没有想过什么背弃，也没有背弃过，”玛莎用她歌唱似的清晰声音说道，“我已经对你说过，我感到厌烦了。”

“玛莎！”切尔托普哈诺夫大喊一声，用拳捶一下胸，“别这样了，得了，你让我够难受的了！喂，算了！你只要想一想，季沙[2]会说什么；你至少要可怜可怜他嘛！”

“请您代我向季洪·伊万内奇问好，对他说……”

切尔托普哈诺夫两手一摆。

“不行，别胡扯了，你走不了！你的亚夫是等不到你的！”

“亚夫先生……”玛沙正要说下去……

“什么亚夫先生，”切尔托普哈诺夫滑稽地模仿她的口气说，“他是个十足的骗子、大滑头，他那副嘴脸就像个猴子！”

切尔托普哈诺夫同玛莎足足磨蹭了半个钟头。他时而靠近她，时而退开去，时而举手想揍她，时而向她低头哈腰，又哭，又骂……

“我受不了，”玛莎断然地说，“我苦闷极了……烦得要死。”她那脸上渐渐显出十分冷漠的几乎昏沉沉的神情，致使切尔托普哈诺夫问她，是否有人给她吃了麻醉药。

“是烦闷。”她说第十次了。

“那我就打死你，怎么样？”他猛然喊道，从口袋里掏出了手枪。

玛莎莞尔一笑；她的脸显出光彩。

“这有什么？打死我好了，潘捷莱·叶列梅伊奇，随您的便；回去我是不回去的。”

“不回去？”切尔托普哈诺夫扳起了扳机。

“不回去，亲爱的。永远不回去了。我的话说定了。”

切尔托普哈诺夫突然把枪塞到她手里，蹲在了地上。

“好，那你就打死我吧！没有你，我也不想活了。我让你厌烦——世上的一切也让我厌烦了。”

玛莎弯下腰，捡起自己的包袱，把手枪放在草地上，让枪口背向切尔托普哈诺夫，就挨着他坐下来。

“唉，亲爱的，你难过什么呢？难道你不了解我们茨冈女人吗？我们生性就是这样的嘛，习惯了。只要那个催人分手的‘厌烦’一出现，就会把魂召到老远老远的地方去，哪能留得下来呢？你就记住你的玛莎吧，这样的女友你是找不到第二个的；我也不会忘记你的，我的鹰；可是咱们的共同生活已经到头了！”

“我一向是爱你的呀，玛莎。”切尔托普哈诺夫用手蒙着脸，透过手指缝说……

“我也是爱过您的呀，我的朋友潘捷莱·叶列梅伊奇！”

“我过去爱你，现在还爱你，爱得发疯，爱得不知所以，现在我只要一想到，你过得好好的，却一下子无缘无故地抛开我，去四处流浪，我就会觉得，如果我不是一个倒霉的穷光蛋，那你就不会抛开我的！”

玛莎听了这番话只是笑了笑。

“你还曾经把我叫作不贪钱财的女人呢！”她说着，并抡起拳头在切尔托普哈诺夫的肩上打了一下。

他跳了起来。

“那么你至少拿我一点钱带上嘛——一个子儿没有怎么行呢？不过你最好还是打死我吧！我对你说真格的：你一枪打死我算了！”

玛莎又摇摇头。

“打死你？亲爱的，为什么要让人家把我流放到西伯利亚去呢？”

切尔托普哈诺夫颤抖了一下。

“原来你只是因为这个，因为怕服苦役……”

他又倒在草地上。

玛莎在他旁边默默地站了一会儿。“我为你遗憾，潘捷莱·叶尔梅伊奇，”她叹了口气说，“你是个好人……可是没有法子：再见吧！”

她转过身，走了几步。夜色已经降临，四处黑影幢幢。切尔托普哈诺夫腾一下站了起来，从后边抓住玛莎的两只胳膊。

“你就这样走了，毒蛇？想去找亚夫！”

“再见吧！”玛莎深情而又坚决地重说了一遍，便挣开手走了。

切尔托普哈诺夫望了望她的背影，便跑到放手枪的地方，拿起枪朝她瞄准，开了一枪……但是在扣动扳机之前把手向上一翘，让子弹从玛莎头上嗖地过去。她边走边回头瞧了瞧他，继续摇摇摆摆地向前走，似乎在逗弄他。

他掩着脸，急忙跑开……

可是他还没跑上五十来步，便猛然站住了，好像被拴住了似的。一个熟悉的、非常熟悉的声音向他飞来。是玛莎的歌声。她在唱“美好的青春年华”，句句歌声都在夜晚的空气里飘荡开来，哀怨而热情。切尔托普哈诺夫侧耳倾听。歌声渐渐地远去；一会儿低下去，一会儿又隐约可闻，可是仍像股热流……

“她这是有意刺激我呢。”切尔托普哈诺夫心里想，可他立刻又叹息说，“哦，不是的，这是她向我表示永别呢。”他泪如泉涌。

他于第二天便来到亚夫先生的家。亚夫先生是一个真正的社交界人物，不甘心于乡下的寂寞，而住到县城里去，正如他自己说的，为的是“离小姐们近些”。切尔托普哈诺夫没有遇上亚夫。据他的侍仆说，他头一天去了莫斯科。

“果然不出所料！”切尔托普哈诺夫怒气冲冲地喊道，“他们串通好了；她跟他私奔了……但等着瞧吧！”

他不顾侍仆的阻拦，冲进青年枪骑兵大尉的办事室。房间里的沙发上方挂着穿枪骑兵制服的油画肖像。“啊，你在这儿呀，你这没有尾巴的猴子！”切尔托普哈诺夫吼叫着，并跳上沙发，一拳打在紧绷着的画布上，打出了一个大洞。

“告诉你的混蛋主子，”他对那个侍仆说，“因为他自己的卑鄙嘴脸不在，所以贵族切尔托普哈诺夫就砸毁他的画像；如果他要我赔，他知道在哪儿可找得到贵族切尔托普哈诺夫！要不然我自己来找他！哪怕跑到海底，也要找到这个卑鄙下流的猴子！”

说了这几句话之后，切尔托普哈诺夫跳下沙发，便大摇大摆地离去了。

可那枪骑兵大尉亚夫却没有向他要求任何赔偿——他甚至没有在任何地方遇到过他——切尔托普哈诺夫也不想再去找这个情敌，他们两人之间也就没有任何故事好说了。关于玛莎的下落从那以后也音信杳然。切尔托普哈诺夫曾一度借酒浇愁，后来“醒悟”过来了。可这时候第二个灾难又找上他了。

二

那就是他的至交季洪·伊万内奇·涅多皮尤斯金的去世。在他去世前的约两年时间里，他那身体已经渐渐不行了：光是气喘，老是昏睡，醒来后，也不能立刻缓过神来。县城里的大夫说他患了“轻度中风”。在玛莎离去之前的三天里，也就是她感到“厌烦”的三天里，涅多皮尤斯金正躺在自己的别谢连杰夫卡村的家里，他得了重感冒。玛莎的出走更使他受到意外的打击。这件事对于他的打击也许比对切尔托普哈诺夫的更要严重。由于他生性柔弱和胆怯，因此除了对好友表示深切的同情，和自己的病态的困惑之外，就没有任何其他的表露……然而他的一切都垮了，一切皆空了。“她掏走了我的心。”他坐在自己喜爱的漆布沙发上摆弄着手指，低声地自言自语。甚至在切尔托普哈诺夫的情绪恢复正常之后，涅多皮尤斯金也还没有恢复正常，他仍然感到“心里全空了”。“就是这儿。”他指着胸中央高于胃的地方。他就这样直拖到冬天。严寒初临的时候，他的气喘病减轻些了，可是随之而来已不是轻度中风，而是真正的中风了。他不是一下子失去记忆的，他还能认出切尔托普哈诺夫，听到这位好友的绝望呼喊：“你这是怎么啦，季洪，你怎么不经我允许就要丢下我，像玛莎一样？”他还能用发僵的舌头回答：“我，潘……莱·叶……奇，我……总是……听您……的话……”然而，就在这一天，不等县城的大夫赶到，他就离开人世了。那大夫一看见他刚刚冷却的躯体，不免发出人生若梦的感叹，要一点“酒和鲟鱼干”消消愁。可以料得到，季洪·伊万内奇把自己的产业遗赠给了自己最尊敬的恩人和宽宏大量的保护人“潘捷莱·叶列梅伊奇·切尔托普哈诺夫”，然而这份产业并没有给最尊敬的恩人带来多大的好处，因为它很快就被拍卖了——其中一部分钱用来支付墓碑、雕像的费用。切尔托普哈诺夫想要给亡友的墓上立一座雕像，（在他身上显然表现出他父亲的秉性！）他是从莫斯科定制雕像的，它本该是一个在祈祷的天使；可人家介绍给他的那个经纪人认为外省对雕塑懂行的人很少，就没有给天使像，而是送来了一座福洛拉女神[3]像，它本是多年来装饰在莫斯科近郊一个荒芜了的叶卡捷琳娜时代的花园里的雕像，那经纪人没花钱就把它弄来了。不过这雕像倒很优美，具有罗可可风格：丰腴的手臂，蓬松的鬈发，袒露的胸前有一串玫瑰花，稍稍弯下点身子。这个神话中的女神至今仍风雅地抬着一只腿，屹立在季洪·伊万内奇的墓上，带着真正蓬帕杜[4]式的娇姿观赏着在她周围游玩的牛羊，它们是常来参观我们乡村墓地的游客。

三

切尔托普哈诺夫失去了自己的挚友之后，又是借酒浇愁，这一次的情况可比以前严重多了。他的家境已彻底走向衰败。没有钱去享受打猎的乐趣了，所剩无几的钱都花光了，最后几个仆人也被打发走了。潘捷莱·叶列梅伊奇已完全陷于孤独凄清了：连与之说句话的人都没有，哪还有什么人可与之谈谈心呢。唯独他身上的那股傲气仍不减当年。相反，他的境况越是不妙，他就变得越益傲慢，越益自负，越益难以接近。最终他变得十分粗野了。他只剩下一点安慰，一点乐趣，那就是他的那匹令人惊叹的坐骑了，它是一匹顿河种的灰毛马，被他取名为马列克－阿杰尔，确实是匹挺出色的牲口。

他得到这匹马的经历是这样的：

有一次切尔托普哈诺夫骑着马经过附近一个村子，听到一个酒馆旁边有一群庄稼人在吵吵嚷嚷。在那一群人中间，有几只强壮的手在同一处不停地上下起落。

“那边出了什么事？”他以自己特有的官腔问一个站在自家门口的老婆娘。

那婆娘倚在门框上，仿佛打盹似的朝着酒馆那边看热闹。一个浅色头发的小孩穿着印花布衬衫，袒露的胸前挂着一个柏木十字架，叉开两条小腿，捏着小拳头，坐在她的两只树皮鞋中间；一只小鸡就在近旁啄食一块硬如木头的黑麦面包皮。

“谁知道呢，老爷，”那老婆娘回答说，她向前弯下身子，把她的一只又皱又黑的手按在小孩的脑瓜上，“听说是我们这儿的一伙人在揍一个犹太佬呢。”

“怎么揍犹太佬？什么样的犹太佬？”

“谁知道呢，老爷。我们这儿来了个犹太佬；他是打哪儿来的——谁知道呢？瓦夏，宝贝，到娘这儿来；喔嘘，喔嘘，这只臭小鸡。”

那婆娘轰开了小鸡，瓦夏拉住了她的方格裙子。

“他们就是在揍他呀，我的老爷。”

“怎么揍他呢？为什么呀？”

“不清楚，老爷。总是有事呗。再说，怎么不揍呢？就是他，老爷，把耶稣钉在十字架上的呀。”

切尔托普哈诺夫吆喝一声，照马脖子抽了一鞭，就向人群直冲过去——闯进人群后，就用鞭子不分青红皂白地朝左右两边的庄稼人乱抽起来，一边以断断续续的声音说：“你们无法……无天！无法……无天！该由法律去管嘛，哪能私自……胡来！有法律！法律！！法……律！！！”

没过两分钟，这整群人纷纷四下散开了——在酒馆门前被打翻在地的原来是一个瘦小的黑不溜秋的人，身穿一件土布外衫，蓬头散发，伤痕累累……脸色惨白，翻着白眼，张着嘴……这是怎么回事？是吓晕了或是真的死了？

“你们为什么打死这个犹太人？”切尔托普哈诺夫威严地挥舞着鞭子，厉声喊道。

人群只答以低低的呜呜声。有的庄稼人捂着肩膀，有的捂着腰，有的捂着鼻子。

“揍得好凶呀！”后面有人说。

“用鞭子抽的呀！谁受得了！”另一个声音说。

“为什么打死这个犹太人呀？我问你们呢，你们这帮疯狂的野蛮人！”切尔托普哈诺夫又问一遍。

可是就在这时候，那个躺在地上的人腾的一下爬了起来，跑到切尔托普哈诺夫后边，哆哆嗦嗦地抓住他的马鞍边。

人群里爆出一阵哄笑。

“才打不死呢！”后面又有人说，“真像一只猫！”

“旦（大）[5]人，请替我说句好话，救救我！”这时候那不幸的犹太人把整个胸脯贴在切尔托普哈诺夫的腿上，“要不然他们会打死我的，打死我的，旦（大）人！”

“他们为什么打你？”切尔托普哈诺夫问。

“我系（实）在说不上来！他们有些牲畜死了……他们就怀疑……可系（是）我……”

“唔，这事我们以后会搞清楚的！”切尔托普哈诺夫打断他的话说，“现在你抓住马鞍跟我走吧。喂，你们呀！”他又转身向众人说，“你们认得我吗？我是地主潘捷莱·切尔托普哈诺夫，住在别索诺沃村。要是你们想告我，那就去告吧，也可以连带告这个犹太人！”

“为什么要告呀。”一个老成持重的白胡子庄稼人深深鞠躬说，他那模样酷像古代的族长。（可是刚才打犹太人时，他不比别人少使劲。）“潘捷莱·叶列梅伊奇老爷，我们对您很熟悉；您教训了我们，我们非常感谢！”

“为什么要告呀！”别的一些人也接话说，“那个反基督的家伙嘛，我们自有办法收拾他！他躲不过我们的！我们对付他，就像对付田野里的兔子一样……”

切尔托普哈诺夫耸了耸小胡子，哼了一声，就骑着马带上犹太人缓缓地向自己的村子走去，他就像从前解救季洪·涅多皮尤斯金那样，从迫害者手里救下了这个犹太人。

四

没过几天，切尔托普哈诺夫家留下的唯一小厮向他报告说，有个骑马的人来求见，想和他谈谈。切尔托普哈诺夫来到台阶上，看见那个他认识的犹太人骑着一匹非常漂亮的顿河良马，那匹马傲然地、一动不动地站在院落当中。那犹太人已脱下帽子掖在腋下，他的脚没有伸在马镫里，而是伸进马镫的皮带里；他那长外衫的破衣襟耷拉在马鞍的两边。一看见切尔托普哈诺夫，他的嘴唇便吧嗒起来，两肘抽搐着，双腿也晃动起来。可是切尔托普哈诺夫不仅没有答之以礼，反倒发怒了，一下全身冒火：一个讨厌的犹太人竟敢骑这样漂亮的马……太不像样了！

“喂，你这丑八怪！”他喊道，“立刻滚下来，要是你不想被摔在烂泥里！”

犹太人当即俯首听命，像个麻袋似的从马鞍上滚了下来，一手牵着缰绳，边微笑边鞠躬地走到切尔托普哈诺夫跟前。

“你有什么事？”潘捷莱·叶尔梅伊奇威严地问。

“旦（大）人，请您瞧瞧，这匹马怎么样？”犹太人不断鞠着躬说。

“嗯……确实……是匹好马。你是从哪儿搞来的？说不定是偷来的吧？”

“怎么会呢，旦（大）人！我系（是）个情（诚）实的犹太人，我系（是）为大人您搞到的，真的！我费了好大力气，好大力气！这确系（是）匹极难得的好马呀！这样的好马在整个顿河地区绝对找不出第二匹来！请瞧瞧，这马有多棒呀！请到这边来！（他对马吆呼：‘吁……吁……转过头，侧过身！’）咱们卸下马鞍吧。您看怎么样呀，旦（大）人？”

“马倒是好马。”切尔托普哈诺夫装作不在乎的样子重说了一遍，实际上胸内那颗心已兴奋得直跳。他是个狂热的马迷，对马非常懂行。

“旦（大）人，您摸摸它看！摸摸它的波（脖）子，嘿嘿嘿！对啦。”

切尔托普哈诺夫似乎不乐意地把手搁到马的脖子上，拍了两下，然后用手指从脖上隆起的部位起顺着脊背摸过去，直摸到肾脏上方的部位，像内行人那样在这个地方轻轻按了按。这马立刻拱起脊背，用一只傲慢的黑眼睛瞟了一下切尔托普哈诺夫，喷了口气，倒换了几下前腿。

犹太人笑了起来，轻轻地拍着手。

“它在认主人了，旦（大）人，认主人了！”

“嘿，别瞎说，”切尔托普哈诺夫懊恼地打断他的话说，“让我买你这匹马吗……我没有钱，要是说送给我，我不但没有接受过犹太人的赠物，就连上帝的赠物也没有接受过！”

“我怎么敢向您赠送东西呢，哪能呢！”犹太人大声说，“您就买下吧，旦（大）人……浅（钱）嘛我以后来拿。”

切尔托普哈诺夫沉思起来。

“你要多少钱？”他终于含糊地问。

犹太人耸耸肩膀。

“就按我买进的价吧。两百卢布。”

这匹马实际值这个数的两倍，也许值这个数的三倍。

切尔托普哈诺夫向一旁转过身，兴奋地打了个呵欠。

“那什么时候……付你钱呢？”他问，一边故意皱起眉头，不去瞧犹太人。

“那随旦（大）人的便好啦。”

切尔托普哈诺夫把头往后一仰，但没有抬起眼睛。

“这哪是回答呀。你得说准啰，希律[6]的后代！要我欠你的情还怎么的？”

“那就这样说定，”犹太人赶忙说，“过半年……行吗？”

切尔托普哈诺夫没有回答什么。

犹太人细瞅他的眼神。“行不行？能不能让我把马牵到马厩里去？”

“鞍子我不要，”切尔托普哈诺夫断断续续地说，“把鞍子拿走，听见吗？”

“好的，好的，我拿走，我拿走。”深感高兴的犹太人嘟哝说，就卸下马鞍，扛到肩上。

“至于钱嘛，”切尔托普哈诺夫继续说……“过半年后给你。不是两百，而是两百五十。你别说了！两百五十，说定了！到时候来找我。”

切尔托普哈诺夫仍不好意思抬起眼睛。他那自尊心从未受过如此严重的损伤。“这明明是赠送嘛，”他心里想，“他这是为了报恩，这鬼家伙！”他真想拥抱一下这犹太人，又想揍他一顿……

“旦（大）人，”犹太人鼓起勇气，咧着嘴笑道，“得按俄罗斯风俗办，把缰绳从我怀里递到您怀里……”

“你还想出什么花样？犹太人……竟讲起俄罗斯风俗！喂，谁在那儿？把马牵到马厩里去。给它喂些燕麦。过一会儿我就去看看。这样吧，给它起个名，叫马列克－阿杰尔！”

切尔托普哈诺夫刚迈上台阶，突然猛一转身，跑到犹太人身边，紧紧地握了握他的手。犹太人弯下身子，已经伸出嘴唇想吻他手，可是切尔托普哈诺夫往后一闪，小声地说了一句：“不要对任何人说！”就走进屋里去了。

五

从这一天起，马列克－阿杰尔便成了切尔托普哈诺夫生活中首要的大事，最为关心的对象，它也是他的主要欢乐所在。他爱这匹马胜过当初对玛莎的爱；他对这匹马的依恋甚于以前对涅多皮尤斯金的依恋。这匹马确实好极了！它像团火，真是一团火，简直是火药，可又有贵族的庄重派头！它能吃苦耐劳，要它奔哪儿，它就奔哪儿，听话得很；饲养起来又不费什么：如果没有什么饲料可喂，它便啃点脚下的泥巴吃就行。它慢步走的时候，就像用手抱着你，小跑的时候，仿佛让你坐摇篮，可一飞奔起来，连风也休想追得上！它从不气喘吁吁，因为它有的是通气的孔。它的四条腿坚如钢铁，跌跌绊绊的事，从未有过！跳沟、跳栏，对于它都不在话下；更不用说它多么聪明了！一听到你的声音，它会昂起头跑过来；你叫它站着，而自己离开，它会动都不动地待在那里；你只要一往回走，它便轻声嘶叫，像是要说：“我在这儿呢。”它什么也不怕：在漆黑的夜里，在迷漫的风雪中，它能认得出路；它决不让生人靠近：它会用牙齿咬生人！连狗也休想靠近它，只要一靠近，它立即用前蹄照狗的脑门一踢，那狗就别想活了。这匹马自尊心可强了：你拿鞭子只能装装样子在它头上晃几下，可不能真抽它！干吗要啰唆老半天呢，一句话：它是个宝物，而非寻常牲口！

切尔托普哈诺夫一谈起自己的马列克－阿杰尔，不知从哪儿来的这么多话！他对这匹马那真是关怀备至。这马的皮毛泛着银色，那银色不显旧，而显得很新，乌光亮泽；用手去摸摸，简直像天鹅绒一般！马鞍、鞍垫、笼头——整套马具配得那么适当、整齐、利索，真值得为之画画！切尔托普哈诺夫对它的照料真没得说，亲手给这匹爱马编额鬃，拿啤酒给它洗鬃毛和尾巴，甚至多次给马蹄抹油。

他常常骑着马列克－阿杰尔出去遛遛，但不是到乡邻家去（他跟乡邻们仍不相往来），而是到他们的土地，到他们的宅院附近溜达……意思是说：傻瓜们，欣赏欣赏我的马吧！有时他听说某处有人打猎——是有钱的老爷准备到远处的田野上去打猎——他立刻也奔到那里，在远远的一边纵横驰骋，大显雄风，让所有的观者都惊赏他的爱马的美姿和神速，可是不让任何人向他靠近。有一次有一个猎人竟带着所有手下的人马去追赶他；那个人看到切尔托普哈诺夫要避开他，便拼命向前紧追，一面使劲大喊：“喂，你听我说！把你的马卖给我，随你要多少钱！几千卢布我也舍得！把老婆、孩子给你也行！把我的家底全拿去吧！”

切尔托普哈诺夫突然勒住了马列克－阿杰尔。那猎人向他飞奔过来。

“先生！”那个人喊说，“你说吧，要什么？我的亲老子！”

“即使你是皇帝，”切尔托普哈诺夫不慌不忙地说（虽然他平生从来没有听说过莎士比亚[7]），“拿你的全部国土来换我的马，我也不换！”说罢便哈哈大笑，让马列克－阿杰尔竖起前腿，单用后腿像陀螺似的转了一圈，便一溜烟地飞奔开去。只见它在割过的庄稼地里一闪一闪的。那猎人（据说是个富甲一方的公爵）把帽子往地上一摔，猛地把脸扑到帽子里！他就这样在那儿躺了有半个钟头。

切尔托普哈诺夫怎么能不珍惜自己的这匹马呢？不正是仗着这匹马，他才得在所有乡邻面前重新显出明白无疑的优势、最后的优势吗？

六

可是时光一晃就过去，付款的日期说话就要到了。切尔托普哈诺夫不用说二百五十卢布，就连五十卢布也拿不出呀。怎么办呢，拿什么支付呢？“这有什么？”他终于打定主意，“如果那犹太人不讲情面，不愿延期，我就把房子和土地抵押给他，自己就骑上这匹马，随便去哪儿！宁可饿死，也不出让马列克－阿杰尔！”他焦急不安，甚至忧心忡忡。可这时候命运——第一次也是最后一次——怜悯他，对他露出微笑：有一位远房的姑妈——切尔托普哈诺夫连她的名字都不知道——在遗嘱中留给他一笔在他看来数目可观的款子，足足有两千卢布。这笔钱他得的可说正是时候，即犹太人要来拿钱的前一天。切尔托普哈诺夫几乎高兴得发疯，可是他并不想饮酒：自从得到马列克－阿杰尔的那一天起，他已滴酒不沾了。他跑到马厩里，吻了吻这位朋友鼻孔上方两边的脸，那是马的皮肤最柔软的地方。“这一下咱们不用分离了！”他拍拍马列克－阿杰尔那梳得整整齐齐的鬃毛下的脖子，大声地说。他回到房间里，数出两百五十卢布，封在一个纸包里。然后他仰身躺着，抽着烟，思量着该如何支配余下的钱——就是说，去买些什么样的狗：要真正科斯特罗姆种的，而且一定要红斑毛色的！他甚至还跟佩尔菲什卡聊了会儿，答应给他一件镶黄丝线的新上衣，然后他极为舒心惬意地睡去了。

他做了一个不祥的梦。他似乎觉得自己骑着马出去打猎，不过骑的不是马列克－阿杰尔，而是一头像骆驼似的古里古怪的牲口；一只雪白雪白的狐狸向他迎面跑来……他想挥动鞭子，想让狗去追捕，不料手里拿的不是鞭子，而是树皮，狐狸在他前面跑着，一边伸出舌头逗弄他。他从骑着的这骆驼上跳下来，绊了一跤，摔倒了……直摔在一个宪兵手里，那宪兵让他去见总督，他认出这总督就是亚夫……

切尔托普哈诺夫醒了。房间黑咕隆咚的；公鸡刚啼过二遍……

很远很远的地方传来马的嘶鸣声。

切尔托普哈诺夫抬起一点头……又听到一阵很弱很弱的马嘶声。

“这是马列克－阿杰尔在嘶喊！”他心里想……“这是它的嘶喊声！可是为什么这么远呢？我的天……这不可能……”

切尔托普哈诺夫顿时浑身发冷，猛一下跳下床，摸到靴子和衣服，忙着穿好，从枕头下抓起马厩的钥匙，急忙往外奔去。

七

马厩在院子的顶头；它有一面墙对着田野。切尔托普哈诺夫没有一下子把钥匙插进锁里，因为他的手在发抖，也没有立即转动钥匙……他屏着气一动不动地站了一会儿：门里边该有点动静才是呀！“马列什卡！马列茨[8]！”他低声地唤马：马厩里死一般的沉寂！切尔托普哈诺夫不由得猛扭了一下钥匙：门嘎的一声打开了……可能门没有上锁。他跨进门槛，又唤一声马，这一回是唤马的全名：“马列克－阿杰尔！”可是他那忠实的伙伴没有回应，只有一只老鼠在草堆里沙沙作响。这时候切尔托普哈诺夫冲进马厩的三个马栏中马列克－阿杰尔所处的那一栏里。虽然周围黑得伸手不见五指，他还是一下到了这一栏里……栏里空空如也！切尔托普哈诺夫的头天旋地转起来；他脑袋里仿佛有一只钟在当当地响。他想说些什么，可是只发出咝咝的声音。此时他喘起粗气，屈着两膝，用双手上下左右地摸，一栏一栏地摸过去……直摸到干草几乎堆到顶的第三个马栏，撞到一面墙上，又撞到另一面墙上，摔了一跤，翻了个筋斗，爬了起来，突然从半开着的门里慌张地奔到院子里……

“被人偷了！佩尔菲什卡！佩尔菲什卡！被人偷了！”他拼命大喊起来。

小厮佩尔菲什卡只穿一件衬衫，从他睡觉的那间储藏室里跌跌撞撞地跑了出来……

老爷和他唯一的仆人两个人都像醉汉似的在院子中心一下相撞了；他们像疯了似的相互绕起圈子。主人说不清是怎么回事，仆人也不明白要他前来干什么。“出事了！出事了！”切尔托普哈诺夫嘟哝说。“出事了！出事了！”那小厮也跟着他喊。“拿提灯来！赶快点上！火！火！”从切尔托普哈诺夫发僵的胸口终于迸出这句话。佩尔菲什卡赶紧奔回屋里拿提灯。

但取火点灯谈何容易：在当时的俄国黄磷火柴尚属稀罕之物。厨房里最后的余火早已熄灭了；火刀和火石找了好一阵才找到，而且不大好使。切尔托普哈诺夫咬着牙从惊慌失措的佩尔菲什卡手里夺过火刀火石，亲自打起火来：火星迸出不老少，可迸出更多的是骂声，以至哼哼声——然而火绒不是点不着就是很快熄灭，尽管四个鼓起的腮帮和四片嘴唇一齐使劲地吹都不管用。过了五六分钟，只多不少，才点着了那破提灯底上的蜡烛头。切尔托普哈诺夫在佩尔菲什卡陪同下冲到马厩里，把提灯举在头顶上，朝四处察看……

四处都是空无所有！

他急忙奔到院子里，把院内各处跑了个遍——哪儿都见不到马的影子！潘捷莱·叶列梅伊奇宅院四周的篱笆早已破破烂烂，许多处已经倾斜了，歪向地上……马厩旁的一俄尺宽的篱笆已经完全倒地了。佩尔菲什卡把这一处指给主人看了看。

“老爷！您来瞧一下这儿：白天还不是这样的。桩头都从地里露出来了，准是被人拔出来的。”

切尔托普哈诺夫提着提灯奔过去，在地上来回照了照……

“马蹄，马蹄，马掌印，马掌印，是新踩出的印子！”他急忙嘟哝说，“马是从这儿被牵出去的，从这儿，从这儿！”

他一下子跳过篱笆，大声呼喊：“马列克－阿杰尔！马列克－阿杰尔！”并直向田野奔去。

佩尔菲什卡困惑地待在篱笆旁。提灯的光圈很快在他眼前消失了，沉没在没有星月的黑沉沉的夜色里。

切尔托普哈诺夫绝望的喊声越来越微弱了……

八

他回到家的时候，已经出现一片朝霞。他变得没有人样了，浑身满是泥污，脸色粗野而吓人，眼睛阴沉得发呆。他以沙哑的嘟哝声赶走了佩尔菲什卡，关上自己的房间门。他疲惫得几乎站立不住，可是他没有上床躺着，而是坐到门边的一把椅子上，抱着脑袋。

“偷走了！……偷走了！……”

那个贼是用什么办法在深更半夜从上了锁的马厩里把这匹马巧妙地偷了出去的呢？马列克－阿杰尔连白天都不让任何生人靠近，怎么可能无声无息地把它偷走呢？连一只看家狗也没有叫喊，这怎么解释呢？的确，看家狗仅有两只，而且都是小狗，由于又冷又饿而紧趴在地上——可是也总该叫几声呀！

“现在失掉了马列克－阿杰尔，让我如何是好呢？”切尔托普哈诺夫心想，“如今我失去了最后的欢乐——我的死期到了，另外买一匹吧，好在手头还有点钱？可是到哪儿去找这样好的马呀？”

“潘捷莱·叶列梅伊奇！潘捷莱·叶列梅伊奇！”门外传来胆怯的呼唤声。

切尔托普哈诺夫跳了起来。

“是谁？”他用变了样的嗓音喊道。

“是我，你的仆人，佩尔菲什卡。”

“你有什么事？是找到了，还是跑回来了？”

“不是的，潘捷莱·叶列梅伊奇，是那个卖马的犹太人……”

“噢？”

“他来了。”

“呵呵呵呵呵！”切尔托普哈诺夫大喊起来，猛的一下开了门，“把他拉到这儿来！拉到这儿来！拉到这儿来！”

站在佩尔菲什卡背后的犹太人一见到自己的“恩人”蓬头散发、神情粗野地猛然闯出，就想抽身溜走；然而切尔托普哈诺夫两个箭步就抓住了他，像老虎似的掐住他的喉咙。

“啊，你来讨钱了！讨钱了！”他嘶哑地喊起来，似乎不是他在掐住别人，而是别人在掐住他，“夜里偷了去，白天来讨钱？是不是？”

“哪能呢，旦（大）……人。”犹太人哼哼起来。

“你说，我的马在哪儿？你把它搞到哪儿去了？卖给谁了？你说，你说，你说呀！”

犹太人已经连哼哼也哼不了啦；他那铁青的脸上惶恐的表情也消失了。两只手直挺挺地耷拉下来，他那被切尔托普哈诺夫猛烈摇晃的整个身子如芦苇似的前后摆动着。

“钱我会给你的，我会全数给你的，一文也不会少，”切尔托普哈诺夫喊道，“要是你现在不马上告诉我，我就要掐死你，像掐死一只小鸡那样……”

“您已经掐死他了，老爷。”小厮佩尔菲什卡平和地提醒说。

切尔托普哈诺夫此时才清醒过来。

他放开了犹太人的脖子；犹太人咕咚一声倒在了地上。切尔托普哈诺夫扶起他来，让他坐在凳子上，往他喉咙里灌了一杯酒，使他恢复知觉。待他恢复知觉后，就跟他谈起话来。

原来犹太人对马列克－阿杰尔被盗一事一无所知。再说，这马是他专为“最尊敬的潘捷莱·叶列梅伊奇”搞来的，为何又要把它偷走呢？

随后切尔托普哈诺夫领他到马厩里看看。

他俩察看了马栏、饲料槽、门锁、翻了翻干草、麦秸，然后又来到院子里；切尔托普哈诺夫指给犹太人看了篱笆旁的马蹄印——突然他猛拍了一下自己的大腿。

“等等！”他喊道，“这匹马你是在哪儿买的？”

“在小阿尔汉格尔县的韦尔霍先马市上买的。”犹太人回答说。

“向什么人买的？”

“向一个哥萨克买的。”

“等等，那个哥萨克是年轻的或是年老的？”

“中年岁数，算中年人。”

“那人怎么样？模样怎么样，没准是个狡猾的骗子吧？”

“没准系（是）个骗子，旦（大）人。”

“那骗子他对你是怎么说的，他早就有了这匹马？”

“记得他说过，他早就有了这匹马。”

“这就是了，别的人偷不了，只有他能偷！你想想看，喂，你上这儿来……你叫什么呀？”

犹太人抖擞一下，抬起那双乌黑的小眼睛瞧了瞧切尔托普哈诺夫。

“您问我叫什么名字？”

“嗯，是的，你叫什么？”

“莫舍尔·莱巴。”

“喂，莱巴，我的朋友，你是个聪明人，你想想看，除了旧主人，还有谁能把马列克－阿杰尔搞到手呢！只有他才能给它上鞍，套嚼环，脱下马衣——那马衣就扔在干草堆上呢！……简直就像在家里干的那样！若不是主人，任何别人不被马列克－阿杰尔踩死才怪呢！它会拼命叫喊，把全村都惊动的！你觉得我说得对吗？”

“说得对，说得对，旦（大）人……”

“这样看来，应该首先找到那个哥萨克！”

“可系（是）怎么找得到他呢，旦（大）人？我总共只见过他一回，怎么知道他现在人在哪儿？他姓甚名谁？哎呀呀，不好办呀！”犹太人说，苦恼地摇动他那长鬓发。

“莱巴！”切尔托普哈诺夫突然喊道，“莱巴，看看我！要知道我已失去理性，不能自控了……要是你不帮帮我，我就要自尽！”

“可系（是）我怎么能……”

“跟我一块儿去找那个贼！”

“可系（是）咱们上哪儿去找呀？”

“到集市上，到大路上小道上，到盗马贼出没的地方，到城里，到乡下，到村庄——哪怕找遍天涯海角！钱嘛你不用担心：老弟，我得到了一笔遗产！即使花尽最后一分钱，我也要找到我那朋友！那个哥萨克，那个坏蛋，是逃不脱咱们的手心！他跑到哪儿，咱们就追到哪儿！他入地，咱们也入地！他跑到魔鬼那儿，咱们就追到魔王那儿！”

“干吗到魔王那儿，”犹太人说，“不到魔王那儿也行嘛。”

“莱巴！”切尔托普哈诺夫接着说，“莱巴，你虽然是一个犹太人，你的信仰不好，可你的心灵比有的基督徒还好！你就可怜可怜我吧！我一个人去不行，我一个人会把事办砸了。我性子太急，而你有头脑，非常好使的头脑！你们那种族就是这样的：不用学，就什么都会！你也许会怀疑，心里想，他哪儿来的钱呢？那就到我房里去，我把所有的钱给你看一看。你把那些钱都拿去，连我脖子上的十字架也拿去——只要把马列克－阿杰尔给我找回来，找回来，找回来！”

切尔托普哈诺夫像打摆子似的哆哆嗦嗦，脸上大汗淋漓，与眼泪混到一起，消失在他的小胡子里。他紧握着莱巴的手，恳求他，差点儿去吻他……他真像发狂了。犹太人本来是不想答应的，想说明自己无论如何离不开，因为他还有事……那有什么用！切尔托普哈诺夫什么都不想听。无可奈何，倒霉的莱巴只好答应。

第二天，切尔托普哈诺夫和莱巴一起驾着一辆农用马车从别索诺沃村出发了。犹太人的样子有些尴尬，一只手扶着车栏，整个衰弱的身躯在摇摇晃晃的座位上颠簸着；另一只手揣在怀里，那儿搁着用报纸包好的一沓钞票；切尔托普哈诺夫像个木偶似的坐着，只是用眼睛向四处打量着，用整个胸膛呼吸着；腰里别着一把短剑。

“哼，那偷马的坏蛋，现在你可得当心！”车子驶上大道时，他这样嘟哝说。

他把家托付给小厮佩尔菲什卡和一个厨娘照管，那厨娘是一个耳聋的老婆子，他是出于怜悯才收留她的。

“我要骑着马列克－阿杰尔回来，”临别之际他向他们喊道，“否则就永远不回来！

“你干脆就嫁给我算了！”佩尔菲什卡用胳膊肘碰了碰厨娘，“反正咱们是等不到老爷回来的，不那样咱们会寂寞死的！”

九

过去了一年……整整的一年，潘捷莱·叶列梅伊奇音信杳然。那老厨娘死了；佩尔菲什卡准备抛下这个家，到城里去，他有一个堂兄弟在理发师那里当学徒，是那个堂兄弟一再叫他去的。突然传来消息，说主人要回来了。教区的执事收到了潘捷莱·叶列梅伊奇的亲笔信，他在信中告诉执事，说自己就要回别索诺沃村，请执事预先通知仆人做好应有的准备来迎接他。佩尔菲什卡对这句话的理解是，要他把灰尘稍稍打扫一下，并不很相信这消息是确实的；然而几天之后，潘捷莱·叶列梅伊奇本人骑着马列克－阿杰尔回到了自己的宅院，佩尔菲什卡才不得不相信执事的话是真的。

佩尔菲什卡向主人奔去，抓住马镫，想扶主人下马；可是主人自己已跳下了马，以胜利者的目光扫了一下周围，高声地说：“我说过，我会找到马列克－阿杰尔的，结果就找到了，让仇人和命运干瞪眼去吧！”佩尔菲什卡前去吻他的手，切尔托普哈诺夫却没有理会仆人的那份心意。他拉着缰绳，牵着马列克－阿杰尔大步朝马厩走去了。佩尔菲什卡仔细瞧了瞧主人，感到担心起来：“唉，这一年来他瘦多了，也老多了，脸色多么严厉可怕呀！”潘捷莱·叶列梅伊奇似乎是应该高兴的，因为他终于如愿以偿了；他的确是很高兴的……可是佩尔菲什卡仍然感到担心，甚至感到害怕。切尔托普哈诺夫把马安置在它原来的马栏里，轻轻地拍了拍它的后部，说：“好了，你又回家了！以后得当心呀……”当天他就从免除赋役的贫苦农人中雇来一名可靠的看守人；他在自己家里安顿下来，照原先那样过起日子来……

然而，不能完全像原先那样了……关于这一点后面再谈。

在归来后的第二天，潘捷莱·叶列梅伊奇把佩尔菲什卡叫来，由于没有别的人可谈，就只能找他来说说话。主人把如何找到马列克－阿杰尔的经过情形都讲给仆人听，当然，说得不失自己的尊严，而且是用低嗓音说的。切尔托普哈诺夫在讲的时候，一直脸朝窗坐着，用长烟筒吸着烟；而佩尔菲什卡站在门槛上，倒背着双手，毕恭毕敬地瞧着主人的后脑勺，听着他讲。他是这样讲的：他经过很多次徒劳的奔波和追寻之后，终于来到罗姆内集市上，那时候他已是一个人了，犹太人莱巴已不在了，因为莱巴生性软弱，吃不了苦，便丢下他走了；到了第五天，他已准备要离开了，最后一次在一排排马车旁边走过，突然在另外的三匹马中发现有一匹被拴在车辕下饲料袋旁的马，一看，正是马列克－阿杰尔！他立刻认出了它，马列克－阿杰尔也一下认出他，于是便嘶叫起来，挣扎着，用蹄子刨着地。

“它不是在哥萨克人那里，”切尔托普哈诺夫继续说着，仍然没有转过头来，并且还是用低沉的嗓音说，“而是在一个茨冈的马贩子手里；我当然立刻抓住自己的马，想把它强夺回来；可是那个狡猾的茨冈人像被开水烫了似的，朝着整个市场大喊大嚷，并一再发誓，说这匹马是从另一个茨冈人那里买来的，他要找人来做证……我才不理呢——我付了钱，就不管他怎么样了！对于我来说，最可贵的就是找回了自己的老朋友，精神上得到了安慰。可有一次我听信犹太人莱巴的话，抓住了一个哥萨克，以为他就是偷我的马的那个贼，打了他一顿嘴巴；可那哥萨克原来是一个牧师的儿子，结果硬要我赔偿名誉损失，敲走了我一百二十卢布。不过，损失一些钱没有什么，主要的是马列克－阿杰尔又回到我手里了！我如今运道好了，可以过过太平日子了。对你呢，波尔菲里[9]，我要吩咐一下：万一你在附近一带看见那个哥萨克，半句话也不用说，马上跑回来，把枪拿给我，我知道我该怎么办！”

潘捷莱·叶列梅伊奇对佩尔菲什卡就是这样说的；他嘴上虽然这样说，可心里并不是他所说的那么踏实。

唉，他在自己的心灵深处并不完全相信他所带回的这匹马真的就是马列克－阿杰尔。

十

让潘捷莱·叶列梅伊奇难堪的时候到来了。就是说，他极少有安心的时刻。的确，心情平静的日子也是有的：这时候他似乎感到心上的怀疑是瞎琢磨；他像赶走一只缠人的苍蝇一样赶开那种荒谬的念头，甚至还嘲笑起自己。可是也常遇到难堪的日子：那个纠缠不休的念头像从地下钻出的老鼠一样，又偷偷出来抓咬他的心，使他感到钻心般的深沉的痛苦。在找到马列克－阿杰尔的值得纪念的日子里，切尔托普哈诺夫只是感到得意和快乐……但是，他在找到的爱马旁边待了一整夜之后，到了第二天早晨，当他在旅店低矮的屋檐下给马备鞍的时候，有什么东西第一次在他心上刺了一下……他只是摇了摇头，可是种子已经播下了。在回家路上（约走了一星期），他心里很少发生怀疑。然而一回到自己的别索诺沃村，一来到以前真正无疑的马列克－阿杰尔所待的地方，心中的疑惑便变得更强烈、更明显了……在路上他骑着马大都缓缓而行，摇来晃去，东瞧瞧西看看，叼着烟斗抽抽烟，不大动脑子想这想那，只是偶尔暗暗想到：“像我切尔托普哈诺夫这样的人想干什么，就能干成！不说着玩！”一边得意地笑了；可是一回到家，就不是这样了。当然，这一切他都埋在自己的心里；单是那自尊心就不容他说出内心的惶惑。无论谁只要稍稍暗示一下这匹新的马列克－阿杰尔不像是原先的那一匹，他就要把这个人“撕成两半”。他有时碰见几个人，他们祝贺他“寻马成功”，但他不去寻求这种祝贺，而且比从前更加不愿与别人接触——这是多么不好的兆头呀！他几乎无时无刻对这匹马列克－阿杰尔进行考查，如果可以这样说的话；他常骑着这匹马到较远的田野上去测试它；或者悄悄地走进马厩里，关上门，站在马头前，盯着马的眼睛，低声地问：“你就是吗？就是吗？就是吗？”或者不声不响地细细察看它，一连几小时地凝视着它，有时高兴地嘟哝说：“没错！是它！当然是它！”有时又感到怀疑，甚至惶惑不安起来。

这匹马列克－阿杰尔与原先那一匹在形体上的差异倒不十分让切尔托普哈诺夫困惑……何况，它们之间的差异不算很大：原先那一匹的尾巴和鬃毛似乎稀疏一些，耳朵更尖些，蹄腕骨要短些，眼睛更明亮些——不过这仅是感觉而已；真正让切尔托普哈诺失感到困惑的则是那些所谓精神方面的差异。原先那一匹的习惯是另一样的，整个癖性也不一样。比如说，原先那一匹马列克－阿杰尔一看见切尔托普哈诺夫走进马厩，每次都回头瞧瞧他，并轻轻地嘶叫；而这一匹则若无其事地只顾自己吃草，或者低着头在那里打盹。当主人从鞍座上跳下来的时候，两匹马都是一样的站住不动；可是在主人呼唤的时候，原先那一匹立刻会迎声前来，而这一匹却像树桩似的仍然待着不动。原先那一匹跑得也是那么快，而且跳得更高更远；这一匹走起步来更显洒脱，可是跑起来便显得颠颠晃晃，有时马掌还会磕碰，就是说，后蹄磕碰前蹄，原先那一匹可从来没有这样的丑相，绝对没有！切尔托普哈诺夫觉得这一匹老耸耳朵，样子挺蠢，而原先那一匹正相反：一只耳朵总是往后贴，一直贴着，注视着主人！原先那一匹看到周围脏了，立刻就用后腿踢马栏的墙壁，而这一匹却满不在乎，哪怕粪便堆得齐它的肚子，它也无所谓。原先那一匹如果让它迎着风，立即会用整个肺部去呼吸，全身打战，而这一匹只是打打响鼻罢了；原先那一匹对于雨天的潮湿会感到不安，而这一匹对于潮湿则没什么反应……这一匹比较蠢，比较蠢！也缺乏原先那一匹的帅气。驾驭起来就更不用说了！原先那一匹是很可爱的，可是这一匹……

切尔托普哈诺夫有时就想到这一些，一想起这些事，便甚感痛苦。不过有的时候，他骑着这匹马在刚耕犁过的田野上奔腾驰骋，或者策马跃下山沟的沟底，再让它从最陡的坡下跳上来，这时候他便高兴得心都碎了，嘴里不住地大声叫喊，他感到，的确感到，他所骑的是真的、无可怀疑的马列克－阿杰尔，因为除了它能这样，还有哪匹马能有这样的本事呢？”

然而这时候也难免有倒霉和灾难的事。长时间去寻找马列克－阿杰尔，使切尔托普哈诺夫耗费了大量钱财；他已不再奢望去购置科斯特罗姆种猎狗了，而只是像从前那样独自骑着马在附近一带遛遛。有一天早晨，切尔托普哈诺夫在离别索诺沃村五俄里的地方又碰上那个公爵的猎队，即一年半以前他曾在他们面前显示过这马奔驰雄姿的那个猎队。这一回又出现了相似的情况：像那一天一样，也有一只灰兔从斜坡上的田埂下跳到了猎狗面前！“逮住它，逮住它！”整个猎队向前飞奔，切尔托普哈诺夫也纵马飞奔，不过不是与那猎队在一起，而是在离他们二百步左右的一边——情况正与那时候一个样。有一条大水沟曲里拐弯地从山坡上穿过，挡住了切尔托普哈诺夫的去路，水沟越往高去便越渐渐变窄了。就在他要纵马跳越过去的地方——一年半之前他的确在这里跳了过去的——还有八步宽，两俄丈深。在胜利的预感中，在那奇特地重现的胜利的预感中，切尔托普哈诺夫舞动鞭子，一边得意扬扬地大笑着。那一队猎人也在策马奔驰，同时又盯着这位勇猛的骑手。他的马像箭似的飞奔，水沟已近在鼻子尖下——快，快，一下跳过去，像上一回一样！……

然而这一匹马列克－阿杰尔猛然停住了，向左一转，便沿着沟边跑着，切尔托普哈诺夫不管怎样都没法使它扭过头朝向这大水沟。

显然，它畏惧了，失去自信了！

这时候切尔托普哈诺夫感到又羞愧又恼怒，差点儿哭了，放松缰绳，让马直朝前跑，奔到山里去，远远地避开那队猎人——但求不要听到他们嘲笑他的声音，尽快避开他们那些可恶的目光！

马列克－阿杰尔两肋带着鞭痕，浑身汗淋淋地跑回家来，切尔托普哈诺夫立即躲进房间里，锁上了门。

“不，这匹不是它，这匹不是我的那个朋友！那一匹即使扭断脖子，也不会让我出丑！”

十一

使切尔托普哈诺夫最后可以说走投无路的是下面的一件事。有一次他骑着马列克－阿杰尔从教士住区后边经过，那个住区位于别索诺沃村所属教区的教堂附近。他把皮帽子拉到眼睛上，弯着腰，双手搁到鞍桥上，缓缓地向前骑去；他心里很不愉快，思绪纷乱。冷不防地听到有人唤他。

他勒住马，抬起头，看见那个曾与他有过书信往来的教堂执事。这位神职人员那编成辫子的褐色头发上戴着一顶褐色风帽，身穿一件淡黄色土布外衣，比腰低很多的地方系着一条浅蓝色腰带。他是出来查看他的禾垛的。他一瞧见潘捷莱·叶列梅伊奇，觉得应该向他表示一下敬意，顺便向他打听点什么。大家都知道，教会人员要是没有这类用意，往往是不同世俗人士攀谈的。

然而切尔托普哈诺夫没有心思去理这位执事；他略微答个礼，嘴里含含糊糊说了句什么，便扬了扬鞭……

“您的马多么帅气呀！”教堂执事赶忙接着说，“的确可以值得称赞。说真的，您是个聪明异常的男子汉，简直像头雄狮！”这位教堂执事是以花言巧语闻名的，这使牧师十分气恼，因为那牧师缺乏口才，即使喝了酒也激不起他说话。“虽然坏人的诡计使你失去了一匹好牲口，”教堂执事继续说，“而您一点也没有灰心丧气，反而更加相信神意，给自己搞到了另外一匹，一点也不比先前那一匹差，甚至可以说更好……所以……”

“你瞎扯什么呀？”切尔托普哈诺夫沉下脸打断他的话，“这怎么是另一匹呢？这就是原来的那匹马；这就是马列克－阿杰尔嘛。我把它找回了。别瞎说……”

“哎！哎！哎！哎！”教堂执事一字一顿，慢条斯理地说，一边用手指捻弄着胡子，用他那明亮而专注的眼睛打量着切尔托普哈诺夫，“这是怎么回事呀，先生？我记得您的那匹马是在去年圣母节[10]之后约两星期被偷掉的，现在已是十一月底了。”

“啊，是的，这又怎么啦？”

教堂执事依然用手指捻弄着胡子。

“我的意思是，从那时候到现在已经过去一年多了，您的马当时是灰色带圆斑的，就像现在这样；甚至好像颜色更深了。这是怎么一回事呢？灰色马在一年里毛色会淡许多的呀。”

切尔托普哈诺夫颤抖了一下……仿佛是有人用长矛捅了一下他的心窝。可不是吗，灰色毛是会变淡的呀！这么简单的道理他怎么一直没有想到的呢？

“讨厌鬼！去你的吧！”他骤然大喊一声，疯狂地瞪了一眼，转眼间就跑得让那吃惊的教堂执事看不见了。

“唉！一切都完了！”

现在的确一切都完了，一切都破灭了，最后一张牌也输掉了！就因为“毛色会变淡”这句话，一下子全都垮了！

灰色马的毛色是要变淡的！

跑吧，跑吧，这该死的家伙！你跑不出这句话！

切尔托普哈诺夫骑马奔回家了，又把自己锁在屋子里。

十二

这匹无能的劣马不是马列克－阿杰尔，它与马列克－阿杰尔之间没有一丁点儿相似之处，任何稍有点头脑的人一眼就能看出这一点，而他，潘捷莱·切尔托普哈诺夫，却以最卑劣的方式来欺骗自己——不，他是有意地、成心哄骗自己，蒙混自己——如今这一切已经没有丝毫可怀疑的余地了！切尔托普哈诺夫在房间里踱来踱去，走到墙根就以同一姿势转过脚后跟，犹如笼子里的野兽。他的自尊心承受不了这种伤害；但不单单是自尊心受的伤痛令他寝食不安；他还陷入了绝望，愤恨得透不过气来，报复心便油然而起。可是去恨谁呢？向谁报复呢？向犹太人，向亚夫，向玛莎，向教堂执事，向偷马的哥萨克，向所有的乡邻，向社会，最后也向自己报复吗？他脑子里全乱了。最后一张牌打输了！（他很喜欢用这个比喻。）他又成了一个最没出息的、最被瞧不起的人，成了众人的笑柄、滑稽的小丑、十足的傻瓜，教堂执事的嘲笑对象！！……他想象着，他清楚地设想着，这个讨厌鬼会怎样对别人谈起这匹灰马，谈起这个愚蠢的马主人……真该死呀！……切尔托普哈诺夫极力想抑制心头涌上的怒火，可做不到；他想要说服自己，这匹马虽然不是马列克－阿杰尔，可毕竟是……一匹好马，可以为他服务好多年——这也不管用，而他立即生气地排斥了这种想法，好像这种想法里含有对原来那一匹马列克－阿杰尔的新的侮辱，因为他本来已经觉得自己很对不起它……还用说吗！他真是瞎了眼，真是蠢透了，竟把这匹又老又瘦的驽马跟它——原来的马列克－阿杰尔——等量齐观！至于说这匹驽马还能为他效力……难道他什么时候还愿意去骑它吗？决不会了！永远不会了！！……把它送给鞑靼人吧。把它喂狗吧——它不配派别的用场了……是呀！这样最好啦！

切尔托普哈诺夫在自己房间里踱了两个多小时。

“佩尔菲什卡！”他忽然下令，“马上到酒馆去；打半桶酒来！听见吗？半桶酒，要快！马上给我把酒搁在桌子上。”

没多一会儿酒就出现在潘捷莱·叶列梅伊奇的桌上了，他喝起酒来了。

十三

当时倘若有人看一看切尔托普哈诺夫，倘若有人亲眼看到他一杯接一杯喝酒时的那副阴沉沉恶狠狠的神情，这个人由不得准会吓得要命。夜已经降临了；桌上的蜡烛在灰溜溜地燃烧着。切尔托普哈诺夫已不再来来去去地踱步了；他坐在那里，满脸通红，眼睛显得模模糊糊，时而瞧瞧地上，时而凝望着黑洞洞的窗口；他有时站起来，倒一杯酒，喝干后又坐了下来，眼睛又凝视着一个点，身子一动不动，只是他的呼吸越来越急促了，脸越来越红了。看那样子，他正在心里酝酿着某种决定，这种决定使他自己也感到惶惶不安，不过也对它渐渐习惯了；这样的一种念头不停地进逼着，而且靠得越来越近了，同样的一种想象越来越清晰地呈现在眼前，浓浓的醉意激起狂热的冲动，他心中的愤恨已渐渐变为野蛮的情感，他那嘴唇上露出凶险的冷笑……

“哼，得立即动手！”他以一种认真的几乎苦闷的语调说，“不能等劲过去了！”

他喝干了最后一杯酒，从床头取来手枪——就是那支打玛莎的手枪，装好弹药，又把几个引火帽搁在衣袋里，以防万一，然后便来到马厩。

在他打开马厩门的时候，看守人向他跑了过来，而他朝看守人喊道：“是我！难道看不见？走开！”看守人稍稍退到一边。“睡觉去吧！”切尔托普哈诺夫又朝他喊道，“这儿你用不着看守了！有什么稀罕东西、有什么宝贝要看守呀！”他走进马厩。马列克－阿杰尔……这匹伪马列克－阿杰尔在草垫上躺着。切尔托普哈诺夫朝它踢了一脚，说：“起来，坏蛋！”然后把拴在饲料槽上的马笼头解下来，脱去马衣，扔在地上，粗暴地拉着这匹顺从听话的马在栏里转了个身，把它牵到院子里，又从院子里牵到田野上，这情形让那个看守人大为吃惊，他怎么也不明白，主人在三更半夜牵着这匹不戴笼头的马上哪儿去呢？他当然不敢问主人，只是目送着他，直到他在通向邻近树林的大路的拐弯处不见了为止。

十四

切尔托普哈诺夫迈着大步地走着，没有停歇，也没有回头瞧瞧；马列克－阿杰尔——我们就用这个名字称它称到底吧——百依百顺地跟着他走。这个晚上夜色相当明亮；切尔托普哈诺夫能够看出前面像一片黑点似的树林的齿形轮廓。夜晚的寒气从四面八方向他袭来，如果……如果不是另一种更强烈的醉意支配着他整个身心，他大概会被所喝的酒醉倒了。他的脑袋昏沉沉的，血液在喉咙和耳朵里嗡嗡作响，可是他的步伐是坚定的，并知道往何处去。

他下决心处死马列克－阿杰尔；他整天想的就是这件事……眼下他的决心已定！

他前去干这件事非但心中坦然，而且颇显自信，义无反顾，他像一个受责任感驱使的人那样去行动。他觉得这种“把戏”“简单”得很；只要消灭了这个冒充的家伙，他跟“一切”的账就一下算清了，并惩罚了自己的愚蠢，向自己的真正朋友做出了交代，又向全社会（切尔托普哈诺夫非常关注“全社会”）表明，跟他是不能开玩笑的……但主要的是：他要把自己跟这个冒充的家伙一起消灭，因为他还活下去干什么呢？这些想法在他脑子里是怎样形成的，为什么这在他看来是如此简单——那就很难解释了，虽然也不是完全不能解释：他很感委屈，又很孤独，身边没有知心的人，手头又一文不名，再加上喝了大量的酒、热血沸腾，已接近于疯狂状态，发疯的人的最荒唐行径，在他们本人看来，都自有其逻辑以至理由。切尔托普哈诺夫就总是完全相信自己的理由；他毫不动摇，他急于去对罪犯执行处决，可是他并没有使自己弄清楚：他所说的罪犯究竟是谁呢？……老实说，他对于自己要干的事很欠考虑。“必须结果它，必须，”他呆板而严厉地反复对自己说，“必须结果它！”

那个无辜的罪犯顺从地迈着小步跟在他的背后……而切尔托普哈诺夫心中却没有一丝的怜悯。

十五

他把这匹马牵到离树林边不远的地方，这儿有一条不大的山沟，沟里有一半面积长着小橡树。切尔托普哈诺夫走下山沟……马列克－阿杰尔绊了一下，几乎倒在他的身上。

“你想压死我吗，该死的家伙？”切尔托普哈诺夫喊了起来，似乎是为了自卫，他从衣袋里掏出手枪。他心中浮现的已不是残忍，而是一种特殊的麻木感，有人说，一个人在干犯罪的事之前，都陷于这种麻木感。但他自己的声音倒使他感到害怕：在黑森森的树枝的覆盖下，在树木繁生的山沟的腐臭而窒闷的潮气中，他的声音显得何等奇怪呀！此外，他上边的树顶上有一只大鸟蓦然拍拍翅膀，作为对他的喊声的回答……切尔托普哈诺夫哆嗦了一下。似乎他惊醒了他这件事的见证者——这是什么地方呀？在这样荒僻的地方，他是不该遇到任何一种有生命的东西的……

“去吧，鬼东西，你爱去哪儿就去哪儿吧！”他透过牙缝说，放开了马列克－阿杰尔的缰绳，用枪托在马肩上猛击了一下。马列克－阿杰尔立刻向后一转，爬出了山沟……就跑走了。它的蹄声不久便听不见了。刮起了一阵风，把各种声响都混合了，淹没了。

切尔托普哈诺夫自己也慢悠悠地爬出了山沟，到了树林边，沿着大路缓步向家里走去。他对自己很不满意；他脑子里和心灵里的沉重感扩散到他的四肢上；他一边走着，一边生着气，神色阴郁，心里不满，肚子又饿，似乎有人欺负了他，夺走了他的猎物和食物……

被人阻拦而自杀不成的人往往有类似的感觉。

突然有个东西从他背后朝他两肩之间碰了一下。他转身一瞧……马列克－阿杰尔就站在大路中间。它是跟着自己的主人来的，它用嘴碰了碰主人……报告自己来啦……

“啊！”切尔托普哈诺夫喊了起来，“是你呀，你自己要送死来啦！那就让你死吧！”

一眨眼间他拔出了手枪，扳起枪机，把枪口对准马列克－阿杰尔的额门，开了一枪……

这匹倒霉的马急忙往旁边一闪，用后脚站了起来，跳了十来步，猛一下重重地倒了下去，一边嘶哑地叫喊着，在地上痉挛地打滚……

切尔托普哈诺夫两手捂着耳朵跑了起来。他的两腿发软了。他那醉意、恶狠劲、愚蠢的自信一下子全消逝了。只剩下羞愧和丑恶的感觉——还有一种意识，一种明确无疑的意识：这一下他也让自己完蛋了。

十六

约过了六个来星期，小厮佩尔菲什卡认为有必要去拦住那个从别索诺沃田庄经过的区警察局长。

“你有什么事？”这位维护秩序的官老爷问。

“大人，劳您驾来我家一趟吧，”小厮深深地鞠躬说，“潘捷莱·叶列梅伊奇看起来要死了，所以我害怕得很。”

“怎么？要死？”警察局长问。

“确实是这样。起先他天天吃酒，如今他在床上躺着不起来，人已经瘦得厉害。我觉得眼下他什么也不明白了。完全不会说话了。”

警察局长下了马车。

“你怎么样，至少去请过神甫了吧？你的主人忏悔过了吗？行过圣餐礼了吗？”

“还没有。”

警察局长皱起了眉头。

“你这是怎么搞的呀，老弟？怎么可以这样呢，啊？或许你不清楚，这种事……责任很大呀，懂吗？”

“前天和昨天我都问过他，”着了慌的小厮接着说，“我说，‘潘捷莱·叶列梅伊奇，是不是让我去请神甫来？’他说，‘闭嘴，傻瓜，不是你的事你就别管。’而今天我去跟他说几句话，他只瞅了瞅我，动了动胡子。”

“他喝了很多酒吗？”警察局长问。

“可多了！大人，就劳您大驾，到他房间里去看看吧。”

“好吧，你带路！”警察局长嘟哝说，就跟着佩尔菲什卡前去。

等待他的是一种令人惊讶的场景。

在一间既潮湿又阴暗的后室里，切尔托普啥诺夫躺在一张铺着马衣的简陋的床上，枕着一个毛茸茸的毡斗篷。他的脸色已不是苍白，而是像死人一样蜡黄。一双眼睛深深陷在发亮的眼皮底下，那乱蓬蓬的胡子上边的尖鼻子还有点发红。他躺在那里，仍穿着那件从来不换的胸前缝有弹药袋的短上衣和吉尔吉斯式的蓝色灯笼裤，红顶的高皮帽遮住他的额门，直抵眉毛。切尔托普哈诺夫一手拿着猎鞭，另一只手里拿着一个绣花荷包，那是玛莎所赠的最后一件礼物。床边的桌子上搁着一个空酒瓶；床头的墙壁上钉着两张水彩画，其中一张画上，可看得出，画的是一个手拿吉他的胖子——大概是涅多皮尤斯金；另一张上画的是一个骑马奔驰的骑手……那马就像孩子们在墙壁上画的童话中的动物；然而认真画出的马毛上的圆斑、骑手胸前的弹药袋、骑手的尖头长筒靴和浓密的胡子可令人无疑地认出，画的必定是骑着马列克－阿杰尔的潘捷莱·叶列梅伊奇。

警察局长惊讶得不知所措。房间里死一般的寂静。“看样子他已经死了。”他心里想，于是提高嗓门喊道：“潘捷莱·叶列梅伊奇！喂，潘捷莱·叶列梅伊奇！”

这时候出现了一种非同寻常的场景。切尔托普哈诺夫的眼睛慢慢地睁开了，黯然失神的瞳孔先是从右边转到左边，后从左边又转到右边，最后停在来人的身上，看见了他……在两眼暗淡的眼白里有某种东西闪烁着，眼睛里似乎投出了视线；发青的嘴唇渐渐地张开，发出沙哑的、如已死去了的声音：

“世袭贵族潘捷莱·切尔托普哈诺夫就要死了；谁能拦住他呢？他不欠任何人的债，也一无所求……离开他吧，人们！走吧！”

拿着鞭子的手想要举起来……可举不动啦！嘴唇又合上了，眼睛也闭上了——切尔托普哈诺夫把身子挺得直直的，把脚后跟靠在一起，依旧躺在自己的硬绷绷的床上。

“等他死了，就来告诉我，”警察局长走出房间时，低声吩咐佩尔菲什卡说，“我看，现在就可以去请神甫了。要按规矩办，给他涂圣油。”

当天佩尔菲什卡就去请神甫来；第二天早晨他就去报告警察局长：潘捷莱·叶列梅伊奇已在昨天夜里去世了。

出殡的时候，护送他的棺材的有两个人：小厮佩尔菲什卡和犹太人莫舍尔·莱巴。切尔托普哈诺夫去世的消息不知怎的传到这个犹太人那里，他没有放过为自己的恩人尽最后一次义务。

[1]玛莎的正式名字和父名。

[2]季洪的昵称。

[3]罗马神话中的花神。

[4]法国路易十五的一位宠妃。

[5]这犹太人说俄语发音不正，常出现讹音。译文中我们也用一些别字来表示，并在括号中标出其正确读音。下同。

[6]公元前四十年至公元四年的犹太国王。

[7]莎士比亚的《理查三世》一剧中有一处这样写道：“马呀！马呀！我愿拿我的一半国土换这匹马！”

[8]马列什卡和马列茨都是马列克的昵称。

[9]佩尔菲什卡的正式称呼。

[10]旧俄历十月一日。

枯萎了的女人

长期忍受苦难的祖国——
你这俄罗斯人民的国度！

费·丘特切夫

法国有一句俗话说：“干渔夫、湿猎人，一副倒霉样。”对于捕鱼我历来不感兴趣，所以，渔夫在晴朗的好天气里会有什么感受，在阴雨天气里捕到大量鱼时的快乐能消除几分被雨淋湿的不快，我就无法评判。可是对于猎人而言，下雨确实是一种灾难。我同叶尔莫莱有一回到别廖夫县去打松鸡，恰好遇上这样的灾难。从大清早起雨便下个不停。为了避雨，我们什么招没有使过呀！我们把橡皮雨披差点披上了头，躲在树下，想少挨点雨浇……这种雨披妨碍射击就毋需说了，还恶作剧地让雨水漏了进来；而站在树下起初倒像是淋不到雨，可是后来树叶上的积水猛然一泻而下，根根树枝都朝我们身上浇水，仿佛从雨漏里下来似的；一股冰凉的水流灌进了领带，顺着脊背直往下淌……正如叶尔莫莱说的那样：没有比这更糟的了。

“不行呀，彼得·彼得罗维奇，”他终于喊道，“这样可不行！……今天是没法打猎了。一浇雨狗鼻子就不灵了；枪也打不着火了……他娘的！真不走运！”

“怎么办好呢？”我问。

“这样吧，我们到阿列克谢叶夫卡去。可能您不清楚，那边有一个属于您家老太太的田庄；离这儿七八俄里地。就在那边歇一夜，明天……”

“再回这儿来？”

“不，不回这儿……阿列克谢叶夫卡那边地方我熟……好些地方打松鸡比这儿强！”

我也不质问我的这位忠实的同伴为何起先不直接带我前去那些地方，就在这一天我们好歹到了我母亲的那个田庄，说真的，在这之前我没有想到有这样一个田庄。这田庄里有一间厢房，已经很破旧了，无人居住，因而很干净；我在这里过了挺安适的一夜。

第二天我一早就醒来了。太阳刚刚升起；天空中没有一丝浮云；周围闪耀着强烈的双重光辉：新鲜的朝阳和昨日大雨后呈现的光辉。人家在替我套车的时候，我就到那个从前一度是果园，如今已荒芜了的小花园里遛遛弯，这个小花园以它芬芳而滋润的草木丛从四面包围着那间厢房。在清新的空气里，在明朗的天空下是何等的惬意呀，云雀在那里飞翔啼唱，撒下了它们银珠般的嘹亮歌声！它们的翅膀想必沾满露珠，它们的歌声似乎也沾湿了雾水。我甚至脱下帽子，鼓起我的全胸膛欢快地呼吸着。在那不深的溪谷的斜坡上，在篱笆旁，有一个养蜂场；一条窄窄的小路通向那里，弯弯曲曲，宛如蛇爬，小路两旁长着密密麻麻的杂草和荨麻，在它们上边耸着不知来自何处的深绿色大麻的尖茎。

我顺着这条小路前去，来到了养蜂场。它的旁边有一间由篱壁隔成的棚子，人称冬季蜂房，是冬天里搁蜂箱用的。我往那半开半掩的门里一瞧，里面黑咕隆咚，可很幽静，也很干燥，透着薄荷和蜂蜜花的香气。棚角里搭有一副床板，上面躺着一个盖着被子的小不点儿的人体……我便想离开这里……

“老爷，老爷！彼得·彼得罗维奇！”我听到一个微弱、缓慢而嘶哑的声音，宛如沼地上苔草发出的簌簌声。

我停下步。

“彼得·彼得罗维奇！请过来呀！”这声音重复了一遍。我听到它是从棚子角落里，从那张我曾注意到的床板上传来的。

我走近一看——我惊呆了。我面前躺着一个活人的身躯，可是这像是什么呢？

脑袋全干瘪了，呈单一的青铜色，活像古书中画的圣像；鼻子窄得如刀刃一般；嘴唇几乎看不见了，不过牙齿倒很白，看得出那双眼睛，头巾下露出几绺头发，披在额门上。在下巴颏旁边，在被头褶子上，有两只也是青铜色的小手在那里挪来挪去，细柴棍似的手指在慢慢地摸索着。我更定神地瞧了瞧：那张脸孔非但不丑，还很漂亮——然而显得可怕，异乎寻常。我看到这张脸——金属般的两颊正在使劲……使劲浮出微笑，可又浮现不出，使我感到这张脸更加可怕了。

“您认不出我了吗，老爷？”这声音又轻轻地说；这声音像是从那微微颤动的嘴唇里蒸发出来似的。“哪里认得出来呢！我是卢克丽娅……记得吗，在斯帕斯科耶您家老太太那里的轮舞……记得吗，我还是领唱的呢？”

“卢克丽娅！”我喊了一声，“这是你呀？哪儿会呢？”

“是我，老爷，是我。我是卢克丽娅。”

我不知说什么才好，惊得发愣地瞧着这张黝黑的死板的脸和那双凝视我的明亮而没有生气的眼睛。真的是她吗？这个干尸般的女人竟然是卢克丽娅，竟然是我家全体仆人中第一号美人，那个苗条、丰满、红润、爱笑而又能歌善舞的姑娘！卢克丽娅，聪明可爱的卢克丽娅，我们那里所有的年轻小伙都追求过她；当时是个十六岁的孩子的我，也在偷偷地观赏她。

“哎呀呀，卢克丽娅，”我终于说道，“你怎么变成这副样子了呀？”

“遭了大灾大难了呀！您可别嫌我，老爷，别瞅着我的不幸而厌恶我——请坐在小桶上，坐近点，要不您听不清我的话……瞧，我的声音变得这么细了……我能见到您，真是高兴得很哪！您怎么上阿列克谢叶夫卡来了呢？”

卢克丽娅的话音非常微弱，然而没有停顿。

“是打猎的叶尔莫莱带我上这里来的。还是请你给我讲一讲……”

“讲一讲我遭的灾难？好吧，老爷。我出了这事已经很久了，有六七年了吧。那时候我刚刚嫁给了瓦西利·波利亚科夫——你记得吗，那个体格端正、头发鬈曲，替您家老太太管理餐室的年轻人？那时候你已经不在乡下，您到莫斯科上学去了。我同瓦西利非常恩爱，我一直忘不了他。事情发生在春天：有一天夜里……离天亮已经不远……我睡不着。一只夜莺在花园里唱得可甜啦……我忍不住了，便起了床，走到台阶上去听。夜莺在啼呀，唱呀……忽然我觉得有人在喊我，像是瓦西利的声音。喊声轻极了：‘卢莎[1]！……’我朝一旁瞧了瞧，可能由于我没全睡醒的关系，我踩了个空，从高高的台阶上直滚了下去，砰一声跌倒在地上！看起来我伤得不很重，因为我能很快爬了起来，回到自己的房间里。只是我的身体里边——内脏里边——像有什么断裂了似的……让我喘喘气……歇一会儿……老爷。”

卢克丽娅停下不说了，我惊讶地瞅着她。特别令我吃惊的是，她在讲她不幸的遭遇的时候几乎是愉快的，没有唉声叹气，一点没有怨言，也不指望别人的同情。

“从那时候起，”卢克丽娅接着说．“我开始消瘦，虚弱下来，我的皮肤变黑了，走路也困难了，后来两条腿全动不了啦，既不能站，也不能坐，只好老躺着。不想喝，也不想吃：身子骨越来越糟了。您家老太太发善心让我去看医生，送我进医院。可是我这个病怎么治也不见好。甚至没有一个医生能说得出我害的是什么病。他们对我什么方法没有用过呀，用烧红的铁铬我的背，把我放到冰块里冰，通通不管用。后来我这身子骨就僵硬了……这样一来，那些先生们便认定我的病是没法再治好了，而主人家里又不能收留我这个残废人……结果，把我送到这里来了，因为这里有我的几个亲戚。您看到了，我就这么活着。”

卢克丽娅又静默下来，又竭力装出微笑来。

“可是，你的情况真不得了呀！”我感叹了一声，我不记得还说了什么，随后问了一句：“那么，瓦西利·波利亚科夫怎么样了呢？”瞧我问得多蠢。

卢克丽娅的眼睛稍稍转向一旁。

“波利亚科夫怎么样吗？他很悲伤，难过了好一阵子，以后就同别的姑娘结婚了，那姑娘是格林诺耶村的人。您知道格林诺耶村吗？离我们这儿不远。她叫阿格拉费娜。他原先是非常爱我的，可是他究竟是年轻人嘛，总不能老是单身。我还哪能做他的伴侣呢？他找的这个媳妇人很好，很善良，他们已有了孩子。他在一个邻近的人家里当管家，是您家老太太允许他自由的，感谢上帝，他现在日子过得挺滋润。”

“你就这样老躺着吗？”我又问。

“我就这样躺着，老爷，已经躺了六七年了。夏天里我就躺在这儿，躺在这个小篱笆棚里；到天冷了，我就被搬到澡堂的更衣间去。我就去那儿躺着。”

“谁来服侍你、照料你呢？”

“这里也有好心的人。他们没有丢下我。我也不需要很多照顾。吃嘛我吃不了什么，水嘛，水就在这杯子里盛着：里面总是存着干净的泉水。我自己够得着这杯子。我的一只手还能动。这里有一个小丫头，是个孤儿；她常常来看我，真感谢她。刚才她还来过……“您没有碰见她吗？这小丫头长得挺俊的，皮肤又白。她给我送花来了；我可喜欢花啦。我们这儿没有种花——从前有过，后来就不见了。不过，野花也是挺好的，比家种的花还香呢。就拿铃兰说吧……可好啦！”

“你不寂寞、不难受吗，我可怜的卢克丽娅？”

“那有什么法子？我不想说假话，起先难受得很哪，后来习惯了，硬挺过来了，也就不在乎了；还有人比我更不幸呢。”

“这话怎么讲呢？”

“有的人还没有安身的窝呢！还有的人是瞎子，是聋子！而我，感谢上帝，眼力还挺好，耳朵也什么都听得见。田鼠在地底下打洞，我也听得见。各种气味我都能闻得出来，即使那气味多么细微！地里的荞麦开了花，或园子里的椴树开了花，不用对我说，我第一个先闻见。只要那边有点风吹过来就行。不，为什么要抱怨上帝呢？比我更不幸的人还多的是呢。就拿这种事来说吧：有的身体好的人很容易去造孽；而罪孽自己就不来找我了。前不久阿列克塞神甫来给我授圣餐，他就说：‘你用不到忏悔了，像你这种情况还能犯罪吗？’可我回答他说：‘脑子里想的罪呢，神甫？’‘哦，’他说着，自己也笑了，‘这种罪不大。’”

“大概我连脑子里想的罪也不大会犯。”卢克丽娅继续说，“因为我让自己养成习惯了：不去想事，特别是不去想以往的事。这样时间就过得快些。”

说实话，我听了深感惊讶。

“你老是一个人待着，卢克丽娅，你怎么能阻止你的脑子去想各种事呢？或者你老是睡着觉吧？”

“哦，不，老爷！我不是总能睡得着的。虽然说我没有大的病痛，可是我的内脏里常感到疼，骨头里也是，让我没法好好地睡。不……我就是这样躺着，躺着，也不去想什么；我只觉得我还活着，还会喘气——我整个就是这些了。我瞧着，听着。蜜蜂在蜂房里嗡嗡地响，鸽子停在屋脊上咕咕地叫，老母鸡带着小鸡来啄面包屑，或者飞来一只麻雀呀，一只蝴蝶呀，我都很高兴。前年竟有燕子在屋角里做起窝，在那里生儿育女。这多有意思呀！一只燕子飞回窝里，喂了孩子后又飞出去。再瞧，另一只燕子又飞回来接着喂孩子了。有时候没有飞进来，只是从开着的门边掠过，那些小燕子立刻就吱吱喳喳地叫唤，张开嘴巴等着……第二年我还等着它们再来，听说这里有一个猎人用枪把它们射死了。他为什么这样贪心？整只燕子不比甲虫大多少……你们这些打猎的先生们心真狠哪！”

“我是不射燕子的。”我急忙声明。

“有一回，”卢克丽娅又说起话来，“遇上一件蛮好笑的事！一只兔子跑了进来，真的！可能是狗在后面追它，它只得往门里直奔……就在我身旁坐了好半天，老是耸动鼻子，翘翘胡子——真像个军官！它望着我。它明白，我不会去伤害它。最后它站起来，一蹦一跳地到了门边，在门口回头瞧了瞧——就是那种样子！好笑着呢！”

卢克丽娅瞧了瞧我，似乎在说，不有趣吗？我为了让她高兴，就笑了笑。她咬了咬干燥的嘴唇。

“当然，冬天里我感到更差劲，因为太暗了；点蜡烛可惜，再说点了干什么呢？我虽然识字，常常喜欢读书，可是读什么呢？这里一本书也没有，即便有书，让我怎么拿着它，拿着书呢？阿列克塞神甫给我拿来过一本历书，想让我解解闷，可是他看到没有用，又拿回去了。话说回来啦，虽然很暗，还是听得到声音，比如蛐蛐叫，或者老鼠在一处搔抓。这种时候就很好：省得瞎想！”

“有时我也做做祷告，”卢克丽娅歇了一会儿，接着说，“不过这些祷告词我知道得不多。再说，我干吗去打扰上帝呢？我能向他祈求什么呢？我需要什么，上帝比我知道得更清楚。他让我扛十字架，说明他是疼我的。这一点我们该是懂得的。我念过《我们的主》《圣母颂》《受难者颂》，过后又不思不想地躺着了。这没有什么！”

大约过了两分钟。我没有去打破沉默，木然不动地坐在这个给我当凳子的狭窄小木桶上。在我面前的这个不幸的活人像石头似的僵化不动地躺着，她的这种悲惨情状也感染着我：我似乎也僵住不动了。

“你听我说，卢克丽娅，”我终于开口说了，“你听我说，我替你想个办法。我让人把你送到医院去，送到城里一家好医院去，你愿意吗？说不定你的病还能治好。至少你不会一个人……”

卢克丽娅微微地动了动眉毛。

“唉，用不着，老爷，”她忧虑地低声说道，“别送我进医院，别让我动了。我到那里只会更加痛苦。我的病哪里能治得好……有一回一个医生来，他要替我检查检查。我求他说：‘看在基督面上，别打扰我了。’他哪里听呀！就把我翻过来倒过去，对我的手和脚又揉又扭；他说：‘我这样做是为了科学；我是搞科学的人，是科学家！’他还说：‘你不听我的不行：我因为有功，脖子上挂了勋章，我是尽力替你们这类傻瓜治病的。’他把我折腾了半天，然后说了我的病名——那名字可古怪啦——过后就走了。后来整整一星期，我身上的每根骨头都发疼。您说，我只有一个人，老是一个人。不，不总是这样。常有人到这里来。我很安静，不会妨碍别人的。有时有些农家姑娘来这里聊天；有一个女香客也来过，她给我讲耶路撒冷，讲基辅，讲一些圣城的事。而我也不怕一个人待着。这样更好，真的……老爷，别让我动了，别送我去医院……谢谢您了，您是好心，只是别让我动了，好老爷。”

“那就随你的意吧，随你的意吧，卢克丽娅。我本来是为你好。”

“我知道，老爷，您是为我好。可是亲爱的老爷，谁能帮得了别人呢？谁能明白别人的心呢？人要自己帮自己！您不大信吧，有时候我独自这样躺着……好像整个世界除了我就没有别的人了。只有我一个人活着！我好像感觉，我突然想到……我被沉思抓住了——真是奇妙呀！”

“那时候你想些什么呢，卢克丽娅？”

“老爷，这怎么也不好说呀，是说不明白的。而且过后就忘了。那想法上来的时候，就像乌云散开了一样，好清新、好爽快呀，而究竟是什么呢——搞不明白！我只是想，要是我旁边有人，就出现不了这种想法，除了自己的不幸之外，我就什么也感觉不到。”

卢克丽娅用劲叹了一口气。她那胸膛就像其他肢体一样，不听她指挥了。

“老爷，我看您的样子，”她又开始说了，“您非常可怜我。您不要太可怜我了，真的！我举例对您说吧：现在我有时还……您定记得，从前那时候我是一个多么快乐的人？一个爱玩的丫头！……是这样吧？现在我还唱歌呢。”

“唱歌？……你？”

“是的，唱歌，唱些老歌、轮舞歌、占卜歌、圣歌，还有各种各样的歌！我以前会唱的很多，现在也没有忘记。只是现在不唱舞曲。我眼前这种情况，唱它不合适。”

“你怎么唱呢？……不出声地唱？”

“有时不出声，有时也出声地唱。大声唱是不行了，但还可以听得清。我对您说过，有一个小丫头常来我这儿。她是个挺聪明的孩子。我就教她唱歌，她已从我这里学会了四首歌。您不信吧？请等一下，我马上唱给您听……”

卢克丽娅吸了一口气……这个半死不活的人要唱歌，这念头在我心中不由得引起了恐惧。可是在我能说出话来之前，我的耳边已经颤动起悠长的、难得听清的，然而纯正的声音……随之是第二声、第三声。卢克丽娅唱的是《在草地上》。她唱的时候，她那张僵化了的脸上没有一点表情变化，连眼睛也死盯着不动。然而这可怜的、使劲发出的，像一缕轻烟在摇曳的微弱嗓音唱得多么动人啊，她想把全部心曲吐个痛快……我已没有恐惧的感觉，我的心被一种难以言表的怜惜之情钳住了。

“唉，唱不了啦！”她突然说，“没有气力了……我真高兴看到您。”

她闭起了眼睛。

我把一只手放在她的冰凉的小手指上……她看了看我，她那如同古雕像上镶着金睫毛的深色眼睑又闭上了。过了一会儿，这眼睑在昏暗中闪耀起来……是泪水把眼睑打湿了。

我依然一动不动。

“我真是的！”卢克丽娅突然带着出人意料的气力说道，眼睛张得老大，竭力想把泪水挤出眼睛，“不羞人吗？我怎么搞的？我很久不这个样了……从瓦夏[2]·波利亚科夫去年春天来看我那天之后，我就没有这样过。他坐着跟我说话的时候，我倒没有怎么的；待到他走了，我一个人就大哭了一场！不知打哪儿来的那么多眼泪……我们妇道人家的眼泪原是不值钱的。老爷，”卢克丽娅又接着说，“您大概带手绢了吧……请别嫌我，替我擦一擦眼泪。”

我急忙满足了她的要求，并把手绢留给她。她先是不肯要……说：“我要这礼物干什么呢？”这手绢是很普通的，但很洁白。后来她用自己瘦弱的手指抓住它，就不再松开了。我已经适应了我们两人待的地方的暗黑，能够清楚地辨认出她的面容，甚至能看到从她那青铜色脸上泛出的微微红晕，能在这张脸容上发现——至少我觉得如此——它昔日的秀美的痕迹。

“老爷，您问过我，”卢克丽娅又说起来了，“我是不是老睡觉？我睡得确实很少，可是每次睡着时都做梦，很好的梦！我从来没有梦见自己有病，梦里的我总是那么健康、年轻……有一点让我痛苦：我一醒来，想让身子舒展舒展，可是我全身好像被捆住了。有一回我做了一个好奇特的梦啊！要不要讲给您听听？好，请听吧。我梦见自己好像站在田野里，周围都是高高的熟了的黑麦，金灿灿的……好像有一只棕黄色的狗跟着我，样子凶着呢凶着呢，老是要咬我。我手上好像有一把镰刀，不是普通的镰刀，简直是个月亮，是像镰刀的时候的月亮。我必须用这个月亮割完这片黑麦。可是因为炎热使我疲倦得很，月亮照得我眼花，我犯懒了，周围长着矢车菊，多么大的矢车菊呀！它们都转过头朝着我。我心想，我要把这些矢车菊采下来；瓦夏答应要来的，我就先给自己编个花冠吧；割麦子还来得及。我就动手采矢车菊，可是它们在我的手指间都消失了，怎么采也没用！我给自己编不成花冠。这时候我听见有人向我走来，走到很近很近，他喊着：‘卢莎！卢莎！……’唉，我想：‘糟糕，来不及了！’管它呢，我就把月亮戴到头上代替矢车菊花冠吧。我就像戴头巾似的戴上月亮，我立刻全身闪光，把周围的整片田野照得通亮。一看，有一个人在麦穗顶上向我飞快过来，但他不是瓦夏，而是基督自身！我怎么会认出他是基督，这我说不上，人家画的他可不是这个样子的，但是我明白是他！没有蓄胡子，个子高高，年纪轻轻的，穿一身白衣服，只有腰带是金色的，他向我伸过手来，说：‘别害怕，我的打扮得好漂亮的姑娘，跟我来吧；你要在我的天国里跳轮舞，唱天堂的歌曲。’我便紧紧拉住他的手！我的狗立刻跑到我的脚边……可是我们一下腾空而起！他待在前边……他的翅膀在天空中伸得老长，像海鸥的翅膀一样，我跟着他！那只狗只得离开我了。这时候我才明白过来，这只狗就是我的病，在天国里不会有它的位置。”

卢克丽娅沉默了一会儿。

“我还做过一个梦，”她又开始说，“没准，这是我的幻觉——我搞不清楚。我觉得好像我就在这个小屋里躺着，我的已故世的父母亲来到我这儿，向我深深弯腰鞠躬，他们一句话也不说。我就问他们：“爹，娘，你们为什么向我鞠躬啊？’他们这才说：‘因为你在这个世界上受了许多苦，所以你不但解脱了自己一人的灵魂，也替我们卸下了重担。我们在那个世界里会轻松得多。你已经减轻了自己的罪孽；现在是在替我们赎罪了。’我的双亲说了这些话，又向我鞠了个躬，便消失不见了：只看见一道墙壁。后来我感到疑惑，我遇上的是怎么回事。我就对神甫讲了。可是他认为这不是幻觉，因为幻觉往往只有神职人员才会有。”

“我还做了一个这样的梦，”卢克丽娅继续说，“我梦见我好像是坐在大路旁的一棵爆竹柳下面，手里拿着一根削得光光的拐棍，肩上扛着一个背囊，头上系着头巾，真像一个女香客！我要上很远很远的地方去拜神。打我身边走过的全是香客；他们慢悠悠地走着，好像有些不乐意，人人都朝一个方向走；他们的脸都灰溜溜的，而且相互都很相像。我看见在他们中间有一个妇女在绕来绕去，前前后后地跑着，她比别的人高出一头，她的衣服很特别，不像是我们俄罗斯人的装束。那张脸也很特别，阴沉沉的，很严厉的样子。其他的人看起来在躲避她；她突然转过身，直向我走来。她停下步，张望着；她那双眼睛像老鹰的一样，又黄又大，而且亮着呢亮着呢。我就问她：‘你是谁？’她回答我说：‘我是你的死神。’照理说我该吓一跳，可是我不，我高兴得很，画了十字！那女人——我的死神——对我说：‘我很可怜你，卢克丽娅，但我不能带你走。再见了！’天哪！那时候我多么悲伤……我说：‘带我走吧，好大娘，带我走吧！’我的死神向我转过身，对我说了些话……我明白她是在指定我的死期，可是我听不懂，听不清……她好像说是在圣彼得节[3]之后……这时候我就醒了。我常常做这样奇怪的梦！”

卢克丽娅抬起眼睛……沉思起来……

“不过我最难受的是：有时我整个星期睡不着一次觉。去年有一位太太路过这儿，看见了我，给了我一小瓶治失眠的药，叫我每次服十滴。这药帮了我大忙，我吃了就睡得着了；可是现在那一小瓶药早吃完了……您知道吗，这是什么药，怎么可以搞到？”

那位过路的太太给卢克丽娅的显然是麻醉药。我答应给她搞同样一小瓶来，而我对她的那份忍耐力不能不表示惊讶。

“唉，老爷！”她不赞同地说，“您这是说的什么呀？这点忍耐力算什么呢？您看那苦行僧西梅翁的忍耐力才真叫大呢：他在柱头上站了三十年！另一位圣徒叫人把他埋在地里，直埋到胸口，蚂蚁叮他的脸……还有一位读了许多经书的人给我讲过这样的故事：从前有一个国家被阿拉伯人占领了，那里的所有居民都受到阿拉伯人的迫害和残杀；居民们不管怎样斗争，总是争取不到自由。这时候居民里出现了一位圣处女；她拿着一把宝剑，穿上两普特重的铠甲，前去跟阿拉伯人作战，把他们赶到了大海的另一边。她一赶走了他们，就对他们说：‘现在你们烧死我吧，因为我许过这样的愿：我要为我的人民死于火刑。’就这样阿拉伯人把她抓起来烧死了，从这时起人民便永远获得自由了！这才是功勋呢！而我算什么呀！”

我听了之后暗暗惊奇，关于贞德[4]的传说怎么会以这样形式传播到这里。我沉默了一会儿后，问卢克丽娅：“你有多大岁数了？”

“二十八……或者二十九……不到三十。算岁数干什么！我还要告诉你……”

卢克丽娅忽然不知怎么的轻轻咳了一声，叹了口气……

“你话说得多了，”我向她提醒说，“这对于你的身体可能有害。”

“说得对，”她非常低声地说，“我们的谈话该结束了；其实也不要紧！您走了后，我就尽量不说话了。起码我已把心事倒出来了……

我起身向她告别，把答应给她送药的事重提了一下，又再次请她好好地想一想，告诉我她还需要什么？

“我什么也不需要；一切都满足了，感谢上帝，”她费了好大劲并很动情地说了这句话，“愿上帝保佑大家身体安康！还有，老爷，请您跟您家老太太说说，这里的庄稼人穷得很哪，求她把他们的田租哪怕减轻一点点也好！他们的地很少，出产也少……他们会祈求上帝保佑您的……我什么也不需要，一切都满足了。”

我向卢克丽娅保证，一定实现她的愿望。我已走到门口……她又叫住我。

“您记得吗，老爷，”她的眼睛里和嘴唇上闪过一种奇特的表情，“从前我的辫子是什么样的？您记得吗，一直挂到膝盖头！我很久都下不定决心……这样长的头发……可是拿它怎么梳呀？在我这种情况下……所以我把它剪掉了……唉……好了，再见吧，老爷！我不能再说了……”

就在同一天，在前往打猎之前，我和田庄的一个甲长谈起了卢克丽娅。我从他那里得知，村里人都管她叫“活尸”，可是她没有给村里人添任何麻烦；也听不见她诉苦或抱怨。“她什么也不要求，相反，她对一切都表示感谢；应该说，她是个安安静静的人，真正安安静静的人。大概是因为前世作了孽受到上帝惩罚的，”甲长这样下结论说，“我们就不去管这种事了。比如说，指责她——不，我们不去指责她。由她去吧！”

几个星期以后，我听说卢克丽娅去世了。死神终于来把她召去了……时间正好是在“圣彼得节之后”。有人说，她在临终那一天老是听见钟声，虽然从阿列克谢叶夫卡到教堂一算有五俄里多地，再说那一天又不是礼拜天。不过，卢克丽娅说，钟声不是从教堂传来的，而是“从上面”传来的。也许，她不敢说是“从天上”传来的。

[1]卢莎系卢克丽娅的爱称。

[2]系瓦西利的爱称。

[3]圣彼得节是旧俄历六月二十九日。

[4]贞德（一四一二——一四三一），法国女英雄。

车轱辘响

叶尔莫莱走进小屋对我说：“我向您报告件事。”这时候我刚吃过饭，躺在行军床上。这次猎松鸡倒相当顺利，可是很累人，所以想稍稍休息一下，再说，又正是七月中旬，天气热得可怕……“我向您报告件事：咱们的霰弹全用光了。”

我从床上跳了起来。

“霰弹用光了！哪会呢！咱们从村子里出来时，不是带了大约三十来俄磅吗？整整一袋子呢！”

“那倒是；还是挺大的一袋，该够两个星期用的。可谁知道是怎么回事呢！说不准袋上有裂口，反正霰弹没有了……只剩下十来粒了。”

“那咱们现在怎么办？前面正有几处最对劲的地方——咱们本指望明天能打到六窝鸟呢……”

“那就让我到图拉跑一趟吧。离这儿不算远：只有四十五俄里地。要是您让我去，我就一口气奔去，带一普特霰弹回来。”

“那你什么时候去呢？”

“马上就去也行呀。干吗要耽误呢？不过得租两匹马才行。”

“怎么得租马！自己的马干什么呀？”

“自己的马跑不了啦。辕马的腿瘸了……瘸得厉害！”

“什么时候瘸的？”

“就在前两天——车夫牵它去钉过铁掌。铁掌倒是钉上了。大概是碰上一个二把刀的铁匠。眼下它的一只蹄子不能踩地了。是一只前蹄。它一直缩着这条腿……像狗一样。”

“那怎么办？至少把那个铁掌卸了吧？”

“没有，没有卸；应该把它立刻卸下来才是。大概钉子钉进肉里了。”

我吩咐把车夫叫来。叶尔莫莱的确没有瞎说：辕马的一只蹄子真的不能着地。我立刻嘱他把那块铁掌卸下来，让马站在湿地上。

“怎么样呀？让我租马去图拉吗？”叶尔莫莱缠着我问。

“在这个荒僻地方难道能租得到马吗？”我不禁懊恼地喊起来……

我们所逗留的这个村子很偏僻荒凉；这里的所有村民都挺穷；我们好不容易才找到这间虽谈不上干净但还算略微宽绰一点的农屋。

“能租到，”叶尔莫莱带着一向坦然的神情回答说，“您说这个村子荒僻是真的；不过这地方以前住过一个农人。人很聪明！很有钱！他有九匹马。那个人已经死了，如今是他的大儿子在当家。这个人很笨很笨，可是还没有把老子的财产糟蹋光。我们可以向他租马。您让我去找他来。听说，他有几个弟弟都挺机灵……可他还是他们的头。”

“为什么是这样呢？”

“就因为他是老大呀！当弟弟的就得听他的！”这时候他对一般当弟弟的人进行了过激的、难以形诸笔墨的评论，“我去叫他来。他是个老实巴交的人。跟他有什么不好说话的？”

当叶尔莫莱去找“老实巴交的人”的时候，我想到了，我亲自去一趟图拉不是更妥当吗？第一，我有过经验教训，我很信不过叶尔莫莱。有一回我派他上城里买东西，他答应在一天之内把我所交代的事全部办好，没料到他竟去了整整一个星期，把带去的钱全花在喝酒上了；而且他是坐竞赛马车去的，却走着回来。第二，在图拉我有一个相识的马贩子；我可以向他买一匹马来代替瘸了腿的辕马。

“就这么定了！”我心里想，“我亲自去一趟；路上还可以睡睡觉，我这马车是挺平稳的。”

“叫来了！”过了一刻钟之后叶尔莫莱一面喊着，一面闯进屋来。他后边跟着进来一个大个子庄稼人，穿着白衬衫、蓝裤子和树皮鞋；他高度近视，长着淡黄头发，棕黄色尖形胡子，又长又粗的鼻子和咧开着的嘴巴。他看起来的确像个“老实巴交的人”。

“您跟他说说吧，”叶尔莫莱说，“他有马，他愿意出租。”

“是的，是这样，我……”这个庄稼汉用稍显沙哑的嗓音嗫嚅地说，抖了抖他那稀疏的头发，用手指摆弄着拿在手上的帽子的边，“我，就是……”

“你叫什么名字？”我问。

这庄稼汉低下头，像是在思索。

“问我叫什么名字吗？”

“是呀，你叫什么名字？”

“我的名字叫——菲洛费。”

“喂，是这样，菲洛费老弟，我听说你有马。你去牵三匹马来，把它们套在我的四轮马车上——我的车子是很轻便的——由你赶车送我去一趟图拉。现在夜里有月亮，很明亮，赶起车来也凉快。你们这一带的路怎么样？”

“路吗？路倒没什么。从这儿到大路总共只二十来俄里。不过有一处地方……有点不好走，别的没什么。”

“什么地方不大好走呢？”

“有条小河，得蹚水过去。”

“怎么，您要自己到图拉去？”叶尔莫莱问。

“是的，我亲自去。”

“那好吧！”我的忠实仆人摇了摇头说。“那也好！”他又说了一声，啐了一口，就出去了。

去图拉这件事对于他来说显然已毫无吸引力了；这件事在他眼里已显得没有意思了，无所谓了。

“你熟悉路吧？”我问菲洛费。

“我们怎么会不熟悉路呢！不过，随您吧，我是说，我不能……因为这样突然……”

原来叶尔莫莱前去雇菲洛费时，曾对他声明过，要他不必顾虑，会付给他这傻瓜钱的……就光有这句话！菲洛费，虽然按叶尔莫莱的说法是个傻瓜，却不满足于这样一句话。他要我给五十卢布——这价很高；我还他十卢布的低价。我们便讨价还价起来。菲洛费起先硬坚持，后来开始让价，但仍咬得很紧。这时候叶尔莫莱进来待了一会儿，他就告诉我说：“这傻瓜（菲洛费听见了，就低声说：“瞧，他老喜欢这样损人！”）根本不懂换算钱。”他还顺便向我提起一件事：大约二十年前，我母亲曾在两条大路交叉的热闹地段开了一个旅店，就是由于被派去经管这旅店的那个老仆人的确不懂得怎么换算银币铜币，结果把那旅店搞得彻底亏损，关门了事，那个老仆人只知道数多就是好，比如，把二十五戈比的银币当作六个五戈比的铜币付给别人[1]，同时还使劲骂人。

“你呀，菲洛费，真是个菲洛费！”叶尔莫莱终于这样喊了一句，出去时还气冲冲地把门砰的一声带上。

菲洛费半句也没有顶他，似乎心里意识到，叫菲洛费这个名字确实不大得体，一个人有这样的名字该受人奚落，虽然实际上这得怪那个牧师，大概在行洗礼的时候没有好好酬谢那个牧师，所以就给取了这样的名字。

不过我最后还是跟他讲定了，给二十卢布。他便回家牵马去，过了一个小时，他牵来了五匹马供我选择。这些马都算不错，虽然鬃毛和尾巴显得乱些，肚子老大，绷得像鼓似的。菲洛费的两个弟弟也跟着他来了，他们一点也不像他。他们个子小，黑眼睛，尖鼻子，确实给人“机灵”的印象。他们话说得很多，又说得很快，正像叶尔莫莱所说的，“哇里哇啦”，可是他们都听老大的。

他们把我的四轮马车从敞棚下推出来，便动手套车，忙活了一个半钟头，一会儿把挽绳松开，一会儿又把它拉得紧紧的。两个弟弟定要让那匹“灰斑马”驾辕，理由是“它下坡走得稳”；可是菲洛费却决定：用蓬毛马！于是就把蓬毛马套上驾辕了。

他们在车子里放了不少干草，并把那匹瘸腿的辕马的马轭塞在座位底下备用，如果在图拉买到新马，可以给它配用……菲洛费还跑回家去一趟，回来时穿着他父亲的肥大的白长袍，戴着高毡帽，穿着上了油的靴子，挺得意地登上了驾车台。我坐上车，看了看表：已十点一刻了。叶尔莫莱竟没有前来跟我道声再见，而是去揍他那只叫瓦列特卡的狗；菲洛费扯了扯缰绳，朝马尖声地吆喝：“嘿，你们这些小家伙！”他的两个弟弟从两旁跑过来，朝两匹拉梢马的肚子各抽了一鞭，马车便启动了，出了大门，转到马路上；那蓬毛马本想跑回自家的院子，可是菲洛费给了它几鞭，以示教训，就这样我们的车子便跑出村子，走在密密的小榛树丛之间的十分平坦的路上了。

夜晚寂静而明朗，最适宜于驾车赶路。风儿时而在榛树丛中簌簌作响，摇动着树枝，时而完全停息下来；天上有的地方出现一些停住不动的银色的云；月亮高高地挂着，把周围照得清清楚楚。我舒展地躺在干草上，本想睡上一会儿……可是一想到那个“不大好走”的地方，便振作了一下。

“怎么样呀，菲洛费？离要蹚水的地方还远吗？”

“到要蹚水的地方吗？还有八九俄里。”

“八九俄里，”我想，“没有一小时到不了。可以睡一会儿。”

“菲洛费，这条路你很熟悉吧？”我再次问。

“这条路怎么会不熟悉呢？又不是头一回走……”

他还说了几句什么，可我已经没有去听他话……我睡着了。

有时候自己想睡一个小时，到时候往往会自动醒了，而这一回使我醒来的却是我耳边响起的虽很微弱但很奇怪的扑哧声和咕嘟声。我抬起头来……

好奇怪呀！我仍然躺在车子上，在离车边不过半俄尺的地方竟是一片洒着月光的水面，荡漾着细碎而清晰的涟漪。我往前面一瞧：菲洛费正低着头，躬着背，活像个木偶似的坐在驾车台上；再前面一点，在潺潺的流水上边，是弯弯的马轭、马头和马背。一切都呆然不动、了无声响，仿佛陷在魔法的控制中，仿佛在梦中，在神奇的梦中……多么怪呀？我掀开篷布朝后面一瞧……原来我们是停在河中央呀……河岸离我们有三十来步！

“菲洛费！”我喊了一声。

“什么事？”他回答。

“什么什么事？真有你的！咱们这是在哪儿呀？”

“在河里。”

“我知道是在河里。就这样子咱们会很快淹死的。你就这样水过河吗？啊？你睡着了，菲洛费！说话呀！”

“我搞错了一点儿，”我的这位车夫说，“定是走偏了，我搞错了一点儿，现在得等一会儿。”

“怎么个得等一会儿呀！咱们要等什么呢？”

“让这匹蓬毛马细细认一下路。它往哪儿转，咱们就该往哪儿走。”

我在干草上坐起来。辕马的头在水面上一动不动。在皎洁的月光下，看见它的一只耳朵忽前忽后地稍稍动着。

“它也睡着了，你的蓬毛马！”

“不，”菲洛费回答说，“它这会儿是在嗅着水呢。”

一切又沉寂下来了，唯有河水依然发出微弱的汩汩声。我也发呆了。

月光、夜色、河水，还有困在河水中的我们……

“是什么东西在沙沙响？”我问菲洛费。

“这声音吗？是芦苇里的小鸭子……兴许是蛇。”

骤然辕马晃动起脑袋，耳朵也竖了起来，打起响鼻，并开始转动身子。

“嘚儿——嘚儿——嘚儿——嘚儿！”菲洛费顿时放声吆喝起来，欠起身子，挥动鞭子。马车立刻离开了原来的位置，横截着水浪向前冲去，接着晃晃悠悠地走动起来……起初我觉得是在往下沉，往深处去了，然而经过两三次震撞和下陷之后，水面似乎突然下降了……水面越来越低，马车升出了水面——已经看得见车轮和马尾巴了。此时这几匹马激起了又猛又大的浪花，这些浪花在淡淡的月光下像金刚石一般，不，不是像金刚石，而是像蓝宝石一般四处飞溅——马儿们快活而齐心协力地把我们拉到了沙地的岸上，然后奋力地迈着又湿又亮的腿，沿着大路往坡上跑去。

我心里想：“菲洛费现在会不会说：‘我说的对吧！’或者诸如此类的话？”但他什么也没有说。所以我认为没有必要去责备他的疏忽大意了，于是就躺倒在干草上，又想睡觉了。

可是我睡不着——不是因为没有打猎而不觉疲累，也不是因为经历这场虚惊而驱散了我的睡意，而是因为我们来到了一处景色如画的地方。这是一片辽阔、宽广、湿润、茂盛的草地，这里有许多小草场、小湖泊、小溪、小河湾，那些小河湾里长满了柳树和灌木丛，属于地道的俄罗斯风光，是俄罗斯人最喜爱的地方，就像我们古老传说中的勇士骑着马来射白天鹅和灰鸭子的地方。被车马压平的道路像一条黄丝带似的蜿蜒着，马儿轻快地奔跑着——我不愿合上眼睛，我要欣赏一番！这一切在温情的月光下如此轻柔、如此和谐地从车旁掠过。菲洛费也为之感动了。

“我们这儿把这一带叫作圣叶戈尔草地，”他转过头对我说，“再往前去就是大公草地；像这样的草地在全俄罗斯也找不到第二处了……多么美啊！”此时辕马打了一声响鼻，颤抖了一下……“老天爷保佑你……”菲洛费庄重地小声说。“多么美啊！”他又说了一遍，叹了一口气，然后曼声地喊了一下。“很快就要开始割草了，这儿能割到多少草呀——不得了！河湾里的鱼也多着呢。多肥的鱼呀！”他像歌唱似的说着，“一句话：活着多带劲呀。”

他突然举起一只手来。

“嘿！瞧呀！那湖上……是不是停着一只苍鹭呀？难道它在夜里也捕鱼？啊哈！原来是树枝呀，不是苍鹭。看错了！月亮总是让人看错东西！”

我们的马车就这样跑着，跑着……眼看就到了草地的尽头，这儿出现了一片片小树林和一片片耕地；路旁的一个小村庄里闪烁着两三处灯光——到大路只有五六俄里地了。我睡着了。

我又不是自己醒来的。这一次是菲洛费唤醒我的。

“老爷……喂，老爷！”

我稍抬起身来。马车停在大路中央的平地上；菲洛费在驾车台上向我转过脸，眼睛睁得老大（我着实感到惊奇，没想到他的眼睛有这样大），严肃而神秘地嘟哝说：

“有车轱辘响……车轱辘响！”

“你说什么？”

“我说：有车轱辘响！您弯下身听一听。听见了吗？”

我从车子里伸出头去，屏住呼吸，确实听到后面很远很远的地方传来轻微的、断断续续的声响，像是车轮滚动的声音。

“听见了吗？”菲洛费又问一次。

“嗯，是的，”我回答说，“有辆马车在跑。”

“您还没听见……听！那是……车铃声……还有口哨声……听见吗？您把帽子脱下来……会听得清楚些。”

我没有脱下帽，而是侧过耳朵去听。

“嗯，是的……可能是。不过这有什么呢？”

菲洛费转过脸，朝着马。

“来的是辆大车……没有载着东西，轱辘是带铁皮的，”他说，一边抓起缰绳，“老爷，这是坏人来了；这里，图拉附近，拦路抢劫的……多着呢。”

“瞎说什么！你凭什么认定这一定是坏人呢？”

“我说的不会错。带着铃铛……坐的又是不装货物的大车……还能是什么人呢？”

“那怎么办，到图拉还远吗？”

“还有十五六俄里地，而且这儿没有一户人家。”

“那就赶快走，千万别耽搁。”

菲洛费挥一下鞭子，马车又跑动了。

虽然我不相信菲洛费的话，可是再也睡不着了。万一真的是这样，那怎么办？我心里出现一种很不愉快的感觉。我在车子里坐起身来（在这之前我是躺着的），开始朝四处张望。在我睡觉的时候，涌来一层薄雾——不是罩向地面，而是腾向天空；它浮在高处，月亮在雾中悬着，变成一个淡白的点，好像隐在烟气里。一切都变暗淡了、模糊了，虽然低处还较为清楚。四周尽是平坦而阴沉的地面：田野，无有尽头的田野，有些地方是灌木丛、沟谷——接着又是田野，大多是长着稀稀的杂草的休闲地，空旷……死气沉沉！连一只鹌鹑的叫声也听不到。

我们就这样走了约半个来小时。菲洛费不时地挥动鞭子，吧嗒嘴唇，可是无论他还是我都没有说一句话。此时我们爬上了一座小丘……菲洛费停住车，立刻又对我说：

“有车轱辘响……车轱辘响，老爷！”

我又从车里探出头去；不过就是在车篷里面也能听得见：那大车轮子的滚动声、人的口哨声、铃铛声，以至马蹄的嘚嘚声，虽然还很远，这会儿都听得很清楚了；我甚至听到了歌声和笑声。风的确是从那边吹过来的，但毫无疑问，那些陌生的过路人与我们已近了一俄里，也许已近了两俄里。

我和菲洛费对视了一眼，他只是把帽从脑后向前额拉了拉，立刻又俯向缰绳，挥鞭抽打马。几匹马快步跑了起来，可是没有持续多久，又换成小跑了。菲洛费继续鞭策它们。总得逃脱呀！

我自己也搞不明白，为什么起先对菲洛费的疑虑不以为然，而这一回却突然便相信跟在我们后面的准定是坏人……我没有听到什么别的声音：还是那些铃铛声，还是那辆没有载货物的大车的响声，那种口哨声，那种乱糟糟的喧闹声……可是这会儿我已经不再怀疑了。菲洛费说的不会有错！

就这样又过了二十来分钟……在这个二十分钟时间里，除了自己这辆车子的轧轧声和隆隆声外，我们已经听到另外一辆大车的轧轧声和隆隆声了……

“停车吧，菲洛费，”我说，“反正一样是完蛋！”

菲洛费怯生生地吆喝一声马。几匹马顿时便站住了，似乎很高兴能休息一下。

天哪！那铃铛简直就在我们的背后猛响着，那大车的隆隆声中还带点叮叮声，有人在吹口哨、叫喊、唱歌，马儿打着响鼻，还有嘚嘚响的马蹄声……

追上来了！

“糟——了！”菲洛费拖着腔轻轻地说，踌躇地咂下嘴，吆喝一声，又抽起马来。就在这一刹那，仿佛有什么东西猛然冲来，响起了狂喊声、轰隆声，一辆大型的摇摇晃晃的大车由三匹矫健的马拉着，如旋风似的骤然追上我们，并跑到了我们的前头，立即换成了慢步，挡住了去路。

“正是强盗的做法。”菲洛费嘀咕说。

说真的，我吓呆了……我朝着雾蒙蒙中洒着月光的半黑半亮的地方紧张地打量起来。在我们前面的大车上，不知是坐着还是躺着五六个穿着衬衫，敞开上衣的人；有两个人头上没有戴帽子；几条套着长靴的粗腿耷在车边的木杆上摇来晃去，手臂胡乱地举起来放下去……身子一颠一颠的……显而易见，这是一伙醉鬼。有几个人在乱喊乱嚷；有一个人吹着口哨，那声音很尖很脆，另一个人在谩骂；在驾车台上坐着一个穿短皮袄的大汉，他在赶车。他们让车子慢慢地走着，似乎没有注意我们。

有什么法子呢？我们也只好跟在他们后边慢慢地走着……真是无可奈何。

我们就这个样子走了四分之一俄里。这种等待真令人难堪……逃脱、自卫……哪儿行呢！他们有六个人，而我手上连一根棍子都没有！掉头往后跑呢？他们会马上追上来。我想起了茹科夫斯基[2]的一句诗（他在诗里写到了卡明斯基元帅的被害）：

强盗的斧头多卑鄙……

要不然就用脏里吧唧的绳子勒住喉咙……往阴沟里一扔……让你在沟里哼哼、挣扎，像一只落在套索中的兔子……

唉，糟透了！

而他们的车子依然慢慢吞吞地走着，他们也没有注意我们。

“菲洛费，”我悄悄地说，“试试看，往右靠，装作从旁超车的样子。”

菲洛费试着让车子靠右边走……可是他们也立刻让车子往右靠……无法超过去。

菲洛费又试着让车子靠左边走……他们还是不让他超车。他们甚至笑了起来。这表明，他们不放我们过去。

“没错，就是强盗。”菲洛费转过头小声对我说。

“那他们还等什么呢？”我也小声地问他。

“就在前面有一个洼地，小河上有一座桥……他们会在那边干掉我们！他们常常是这样的……在桥的附近。老爷，这事是明摆着的！”他叹着气接着说，“不见得会放我们活命；因为他们主要是想灭口。我只可惜一点，老爷，我这三匹马要丢了，我那两个弟弟得不到了。”

这时候我真感到惊奇，到了这个份上菲洛费还是念念不忘自己的马，老实说，我已经顾不到他的事了……“难道他们真的要杀人？”我心里反复在想，“为了什么呢？我把我的全部东西给他们就是了。”

那桥越来越近，看得越来越清楚了。我们前面的那辆马车仿佛飞腾似的奔跑起来，跑到桥边，一下子停住了，停在路上稍稍靠边的地方，像被钉住了似的。我的心猛地往下沉。

“唉，菲洛费老弟，”我说，“我和你都得死了。原谅我吧，算是我害了你。”

“哪能怨您呢，老爷！命中注定的，是逃不了的！”菲洛费又对辕马说：“喂，蓬毛马，我忠实的马儿，往前走吧，伙计！出最后一把力吧！反正是一样了……老天保佑吧！”

随之他赶着三匹马大跑起来。

我们离那座桥，离那辆停着不动的可怕的大车越来越近了……那大车上像有意安排似的一切都静了下来。一点动静也没有！梭鱼、鹞鹰、一切凶禽猛兽在猎物靠近的时候都是这样悄悄等候的。我们终于走到与那辆大车并排了……那个穿短皮袄的大汉突然跳下车，径直朝我们走过来！

他什么也没有对菲洛费说，可是菲洛费立刻自动地勒住马……车子停下了。

那大汉把两只手按在车门上，把他的毛发蓬松的头伸向前边，咧着嘴，用缓慢而平稳的声音并以行话的方式说了下面一番话：

“尊敬的先生，我们是出席一个体面的宴会、出席一个婚礼回来的；就是说，我们给一位好伙计办了婚事，把他安顿得好好的；我们这伙哥们儿都很年轻，胆子很大，我们喝了好多的酒，但是没有东西可以醒醒酒；您是否愿意赏光，给我们一点小钱，好让我的哥们儿每人再喝上半瓶酒？我们会为您的健康干杯，会记住您这位好先生的；要是不愿意——那就休得见怪了！”

“这是怎么回事？”我心里想……“是开玩笑？……是耍弄人？”

大汉低着头，仍然站着。正在这一会儿，月亮从雾里爬了出来，照亮了他的脸。这张脸在得意地微笑着——眼睛和嘴唇都在微笑。看不到那脸上有威胁的表情……不过整张脸似乎很警觉……他的牙齿是那么白，那么大……

“好的，好的……请吧……”我赶忙说，同时从口袋里掏出钱包，从中取出两个银卢布；那时候在俄国还通行银币，“请收下吧，如果不嫌少的话。”

“多谢！”那大汉像士兵似的喊了一声，他那粗大的手指一下抓走——不是整个钱包，而只是那两个银卢布，“多谢！”他抖了抖头发，便跑回那大车旁边。

“哥们儿！”他喊道，“那位过路的先生赏给咱们两个银卢布！”那车上所有的人一下哈哈大笑起来……那大汉爬上了驾车台……

“祝您好运！”

我们顷刻就看不见他们了！三匹马一鼓劲，大车便轰隆隆地跑上了山坡——那辆大车在天与地之间晦暗的交界线上再次闪现了一下，就下了坡不见了。

接着车轮子声、叫喊声、铃铛声都听不见了……

随之是死一般的沉静。

我和菲洛费没有一下子回过神来。

“唉，真会开玩笑！”他终于说了一句，一边摘下帽子，画起十字来。“真的，开玩笑，”他又说道，他朝我转过身，满是欢天喜地的样子，“这家伙准是个好人，真的。喏——喏——喏，小伙计们！快点儿跑呀！你们平安无事了！咱们都平安无事了！就是他这家伙不让我们超车过去的；是他赶的车嘛。这小子真逗。嘚儿——嘚儿——嘚儿——嘚儿！快些跑吧！”

我没有言语，可我的心情也变好了。“我们平安无事了！”我默默地反复说，并且在干草上躺了下来，“侥幸地打发了！”

我甚至有些羞愧起来，为什么我竟想起茹科夫斯基的那句诗。

我脑子里突然想起了一个问题。

“菲洛费！”

“什么事？”

“你娶老婆了吗？”

“娶了。”

“有孩子了吗？”

“有孩子了。”

“刚才你怎么没有想到他们呢？你心疼你的马，怎么没有心疼你的老婆孩子呢？”

“为什么要心疼他们呢？他们又没有落到强盗手里。可我脑子里一直在惦念他们，现在还在惦念呢……确实是这样。”菲洛费沉默了一会儿，“说不定……就是为了他们，老天爷才保佑咱们的。”

“也许那一伙人不是强盗呢？”

“那怎么知道呢？难道能钻到别人的心里去吗？俗话说，‘人心难测’嘛。信上帝总是好些的。不……我总是惦记着自己的家……嘚儿——嘚儿——嘚儿，小家伙们，快些跑呀！”

我们快到图拉时，天差不多已经大亮了。我迷迷糊糊地躺着。

“老爷，”菲洛费忽然对我说，“您瞧，他们都在酒馆里呢……那就是他们那辆大车。”

我抬头一瞧……可不，正是那伙人，还有他们的大车和马。在酒馆门口突然出现那个面熟的穿短袄的大汉。

“先生！”他喊道，一面挥动帽子，“我们正用您赏的钱喝酒呢！喂，赶车的，”他向菲洛费点点头，接着说，“刚才大概让你受惊了吧？”

“真是个蛮有趣的人。”在离开酒馆二十来俄丈的时候，菲洛费说。

我们终于到了图拉；我买了霰弹，顺便买了些茶叶和酒，还从马贩子那里买了一匹马。到中午我们便动身往回走了。菲洛费由于在图拉喝了些酒，变得特别爱说话，甚至还给我讲了些故事；当我们经过原来听见有大车响声的地方时，菲洛费忽然笑了起来。

“记得吗，老爷，我那时一直对您说：‘有车轱辘响……车轱辘响……车轱辘响！’”

他好几次使劲地挥着手……他觉得这句话挺有意思。

当天晚上我们回到了他的村子里。

我把路上所遇到的虚惊告诉了叶尔莫莱。这时候他并没有喝醉酒，可是他没有说半句同情的话，只是哼了一声——是称赞呢还是责备，我想，他自己也不清楚。然而过了两三天，他挺高兴地告诉我一个消息，就在我和菲洛费去图拉的那天晚上，也在那条路上，有一个商人被抢了，还被杀害了。我起初不相信这个消息，可是后来不得不信了：区警察局长骑着马去调查，可见确有其事。我们所遇到的那伙勇猛之徒莫非就是参加了那场“婚礼”回来？他们，用那个开玩笑的大汉话来说，所好好“安顿”的是否就是这个“好伙计”呢？我在菲洛费的村子里又逗留了五六天。我每次一遇到他，就要对他说：“怎么样？有车轱辘响吗？”

“那个人真逗。”他每次都这样回答我，自己也笑了起来。

[1]原先一个二十五戈比银币等于五个五戈比铜币。从一八四三年起，银币与铜币的比价变了：规定十戈比铜币只等于三戈比银币。所以那位老仆人把二十五戈比银币当作六个五戈比铜币付给别人，吃亏甚大。

[2]瓦·安·茹科夫斯基（一七八三——一八五二），俄国诗人。

IX Kassyan of Fair Springs

I was returning from hunting in a jolting little trap, and overcome by the stifling heat of a cloudy summer day (it is well known that the heat is often more insupportable on such days than in bright days, especially when there is no wind), I dozed and was shaken about, resigning myself with sullen fortitude to being persecuted by the fine white dust which was incessantly raised from the beaten road by the warped and creaking wheels, when suddenly my attention was aroused by the extraordinary uneasiness and agitated movements of my coachman, who had till that instant been more soundly dozing than I. He began tugging at the reins, moved uneasily on the box, and started shouting to the horses, staring all the while in one direction. I looked round. We were driving through a wide ploughed plain; low hills, also ploughed over, ran in gently sloping, swelling waves over it; the eye took in some five miles of deserted country; in the distance the round-scolloped tree-tops of some small birch-copses were the only objects to break the almost straight line of the horizon. Narrow paths ran over the fields, disappeared into the hollows, and wound round the hillocks. On one of these paths, which happened to run into our road five hundred paces ahead of us, I made out a kind of procession. At this my coachman was looking.

It was a funeral. In front, in a little cart harnessed with one horse, and advancing at a walking pace, came the priest; beside him sat the deacon driving; behind the cart four peasants, bareheaded, carried the coffin, covered with a white cloth; two women followed the coffin. The shrill wailing voice of one of them suddenly reached my ears; I listened; she was intoning a dirge. Very dismal sounded this chanted, monotonous, hopelessly-sorrowful lament among the empty fields. The coachman whipped up the horses; he wanted to get in front of this procession. To meet a corpse on the road is a bad omen. And he did succeed in galloping ahead beyond this path before the funeral had had time to turn out of it into the high-road; but we had hardly got a hundred paces beyond this point, when suddenly our trap jolted violently, heeled on one side, and all but overturned. The coachman pulled up the galloping horses, and spat with a gesture of his hand.

'What is it?' I asked.

My coachman got down without speaking or hurrying himself.

'But what is it?'

'The axle is broken…it caught fire,' he replied gloomily, and he suddenly arranged the collar on the off-side horse with such indignation that it was almost pushed over, but it stood its ground, snorted, shook itself, and tranquilly began to scratch its foreleg below the knee with its teeth.

I got out and stood for some time on the road, a prey to a vague and unpleasant feeling of helplessness. The right wheel was almost completely bent in under the trap, and it seemed to turn its centre-piece upwards in dumb despair.

'What are we to do now?' I said at last.

'That's what's the cause of it!' said my coachman, pointing with his whip to the funeral procession, which had just turned into the highroad and was approaching us. 'I have always noticed that,' he went on; 'it's a true saying —"Meet a corpse"— yes, indeed.'

And again he began worrying the off-side horse, who, seeing his ill-humour, resolved to remain perfectly quiet, and contented itself with discreetly switching its tail now and then. I walked up and down a little while, and then stopped again before the wheel.

Meanwhile the funeral had come up to us. Quietly turning off the road on to the grass, the mournful procession moved slowly past us. My coachman and I took off our caps, saluted the priest, and exchanged glances with the bearers. They moved with difficulty under their burden, their broad chests standing out under the strain. Of the two women who followed the coffin, one was very old and pale; her set face, terribly distorted as it was by grief, still kept an expression of grave and severe dignity. She walked in silence, from time to time lifting her wasted hand to her thin drawn lips. The other, a young woman of five-and-twenty, had her eyes red and moist and her whole face swollen with weeping; as she passed us she ceased wailing, and hid her face in her sleeve....But when the funeral had got round us and turned again into the road, her piteous, heart-piercing lament began again. My coachman followed the measured swaying of the coffin with his eyes in silence. Then he turned to me.

'It's Martin, the carpenter, they're burying,' he said; 'Martin of Ryaby.'

'How do you know?'

'I know by the women. The old one is his mother, and the young one's his wife.'

'Has he been ill, then?'

'Yes…fever. The day before yesterday the overseer sent for the doctor, but they did not find the doctor at home. He was a good carpenter; he drank a bit, but he was a good carpenter. See how upset his good woman is....But, there; women's tears don't cost much, we know. Women's tears are only water…yes, indeed.'

And he bent down, crept under the side-horse's trace, and seized the wooden yoke that passes over the horses' heads with both hands.

'Any way,' I observed, 'what are we going to do?'

My coachman just supported himself with his knees on the shaft-horse's shoulder, twice gave the back-strap a shake, and straightened the pad; then he crept out of the side-horse's trace again, and giving it a blow on the nose as he passed, went up to the wheel. He went up to it, and, never taking his eyes off it, slowly took out of the skirts of his coat a box, slowly pulled open its lid by a strap, slowly thrust into it his two fat fingers (which pretty well filled it up), rolled and rolled up some snuff, and creasing up his nose in anticipation, helped himself to it several times in succession, accompanying the snuff-taking every time by a prolonged sneezing. Then, his streaming eyes blinking faintly, he relapsed into profound meditation.

'Well?' I said at last.

My coachman thrust his box carefully into his pocket, brought his hat forward on to his brows without the aid of his hand by a movement of his head, and gloomily got up on the box.

'What are you doing?' I asked him, somewhat bewildered.

'Pray be seated,' he replied calmly, picking up the reins.

'But how can we go on?'

'We will go on now.'

'But the axle.'

'Pray be seated.'

'But the axle is broken.'

'It is broken; but we will get to the settlement…at a walking pace, of course. Over here, beyond the copse, on the right, is a settlement; they call it Yudino.'

'And do you think we can get there?'

My coachman did not vouchsafe me a reply.

'I had better walk,' I said.

'As you like....' And he nourished his whip. The horses started.

We did succeed in getting to the settlement, though the right front wheel was almost off, and turned in a very strange way. On one hillock it almost flew off, but my coachman shouted in a voice of exasperation, and we descended it in safety.

Yudino settlement consisted of six little low-pitched huts, the walls of which had already begun to warp out of the perpendicular, though they had certainly not been long built; the back-yards of some of the huts were not even fenced in with a hedge. As we drove into this settlement we did not meet a single living soul; there were no hens even to be seen in the street, and no dogs, but one black crop-tailed cur, which at our approach leaped hurriedly out of a perfectly dry and empty trough, to which it must have been driven by thirst, and at once, without barking, rushed headlong under a gate. I went up to the first hut, opened the door into the outer room, and called for the master of the house. No one answered me. I called once more; the hungry mewing of a cat sounded behind the other door. I pushed it open with my foot; a thin cat ran up and down near me, her green eyes glittering in the dark. I put my head into the room and looked round; it was empty, dark, and smoky. I returned to the yard, and there was no one there either....A calf lowed behind the paling; a lame grey goose waddled a little away. I passed on to the second hut. Not a soul in the second hut either. I went into the yard....

In the very middle of the yard, in the glaring sunlight, there lay, with his face on the ground and a cloak thrown over his head, a boy, as it seemed to me. In a thatched shed a few paces from him a thin little nag with broken harness was standing near a wretched little cart. The sunshine falling in streaks through the narrow cracks in the dilapidated roof, striped his shaggy, reddish-brown coat in small bands of light. Above, in the high bird-house, starlings were chattering and looking down inquisitively from their airy home. I went up to the sleeping figure and began to awaken him.

He lifted his head, saw me, and at once jumped up on to his feet.... 'What? what do you want? what is it?' he muttered, half asleep.

I did not answer him at once; I was so much impressed by his appearance.

Picture to yourself a little creature of fifty years old, with a little round wrinkled face, a sharp nose, little, scarcely visible, brown eyes, and thick curly black hair, which stood out on his tiny head like the cap on the top of a mushroom. His whole person was excessively thin and weakly, and it is absolutely impossible to translate into words the extraordinary strangeness of his expression.

'What do you want?' he asked me again. I explained to him what was the matter; he listened, slowly blinking, without taking his eyes off me.

'So cannot we get a new axle?' I said finally; 'I will gladly pay for it.'

'But who are you? Hunters, eh?' he asked, scanning me from head to foot.

'Hunters.'

'You shoot the fowls of heaven, I suppose?…the wild things of the woods?…And is it not a sin to kill God's birds, to shed the innocent blood?'

The strange old man spoke in a very drawling tone. The sound of his voice also astonished me. There was none of the weakness of age to be heard in it; it was marvellously sweet, young and almost feminine in its softness.

'I have no axle,' he added after a brief silence. 'That thing will not suit you.' He pointed to his cart. 'You have, I expect, a large trap.'

'But can I get one in the village?'

'Not much of a village here!…No one has an axle here....And there is no one at home either; they are all at work. You must go on,' he announced suddenly; and he lay down again on the ground.

I had not at all expected this conclusion.

'Listen, old man,' I said, touching him on the shoulder; 'do me a kindness, help me.'

'Go on, in God's name! I am tired; I have driven into the town,' he said, and drew his cloak over his head.

'But pray do me a kindness,' I said. 'I…I will pay for it.'

'I don't want your money.'

'But please, old man.'

He half raised himself and sat up, crossing his little legs.

'I could take you perhaps to the clearing. Some merchants have bought the forest here — God be their judge! They are cutting down the forest, and they have built a counting-house there — God be their judge! You might order an axle of them there, or buy one ready made.'

'Splendid!' I cried delighted; 'splendid! let us go.'

'An oak axle, a good one,' he continued, not getting up from his place.

'And is it far to this clearing?'

'Three miles.'

'Come, then! we can drive there in your trap.'

'Oh, no....'

'Come, let us go,' I said; 'let us go, old man! The coachman is waiting for us in the road.'

The old man rose unwillingly and followed me into the street. We found my coachman in an irritable frame of mind; he had tried to water his horses, but the water in the well, it appeared, was scanty in quantity and bad in taste, and water is the first consideration with coachmen....However, he grinned at the sight of the old man, nodded his head and cried: 'Hallo! Kassyanushka! good health to you!'

'Good health to you, Erofay, upright man!' replied Kassyan in a dejected voice.

I at once made known his suggestion to the coachman; Erofay expressed his approval of it and drove into the yard. While he was busy deliberately unharnessing the horses, the old man stood leaning with his shoulders against the gate, and looking disconsolately first at him and then at me. He seemed in some uncertainty of mind; he was not very pleased, as it seemed to me, at our sudden visit.

'So they have transported you too?' Erofay asked him suddenly, lifting the wooden arch of the harness.

'Yes.'

'Ugh!' said my coachman between his teeth. 'You know Martin the carpenter....Of course, you know Martin of Ryaby?'

'Yes.'

'Well, he is dead. We have just met his coffin.'

Kassyan shuddered.

'Dead?' he said, and his head sank dejectedly.

'Yes, he is dead. Why didn't you cure him, eh? You know they say you cure folks; you're a doctor.'

My coachman was apparently laughing and jeering at the old man.

'And is this your trap, pray?' he added, with a shrug of his shoulders in its direction.

'Yes.'

'Well, a trap…a fine trap!' he repeated, and taking it by the shafts almost turned it completely upside down. 'A trap!…But what will you drive in it to the clearing?…You can't harness our horses in these shafts; our horses are all too big.'

'I don't know,' replied Kassyan, 'what you are going to drive; that beast perhaps,' he added with a sigh.

'That?' broke in Erofay, and going up to Kassyan's nag, he tapped it disparagingly on the back with the third finger of his right hand. 'See,' he added contemptuously, 'it's asleep, the scare-crow!'

I asked Erofay to harness it as quickly as he could. I wanted to drive myself with Kassyan to the clearing; grouse are fond of such places. When the little cart was quite ready, and I, together with my dog, had been installed in the warped wicker body of it, and Kassyan huddled up into a little ball, with still the same dejected expression on his face, had taken his seat in front, Erofay came up to me and whispered with an air of mystery:

'You did well, your honour, to drive with him. He is such a queer fellow; he's cracked, you know, and his nickname is the Flea. I don't know how you managed to make him out....'

I tried to say to Erofay that so far Kassyan had seemed to me a very sensible man; but my coachman continued at once in the same voice:

'But you keep a look-out where he is driving you to. And, your honour, be pleased to choose the axle yourself; be pleased to choose a sound one....Well, Flea,' he added aloud, 'could I get a bit of bread in your house?'

'Look about; you may find some,' answered Kassyan. He pulled the reins and we rolled away.

His little horse, to my genuine astonishment, did not go badly. Kassyan preserved an obstinate silence the whole way, and made abrupt and unwilling answers to my questions. We quickly reached the clearing, and then made our way to the counting-house, a lofty cottage, standing by itself over a small gully, which had been dammed up and converted into a pool. In this counting-house I found two young merchants' clerks, with snow-white teeth, sweet and soft eyes, sweet and subtle words, and sweet and wily smiles. I bought an axle of them and returned to the clearing. I thought that Kassyan would stay with the horse and await my return; but he suddenly came up to me.

'Are you going to shoot birds, eh?' he said.

'Yes, if I come across any.'

'I will come with you....Can I?'

'Certainly, certainly.'

So we went together. The land cleared was about a mile in length. I must confess I watched Kassyan more than my dogs. He had been aptly called 'Flea.' His little black uncovered head (though his hair, indeed, was as good a covering as any cap) seemed to flash hither and thither among the bushes. He walked extraordinarily swiftly, and seemed always hopping up and down as he moved; he was for ever stooping down to pick herbs of some kind, thrusting them into his bosom, muttering to himself, and constantly looking at me and my dog with such a strange searching gaze. Among low bushes and in clearings there are often little grey birds which constantly flit from tree to tree, and which whistle as they dart away. Kassyan mimicked them, answered their calls; a young quail flew from between his feet, chirruping, and he chirruped in imitation of him; a lark began to fly down above him, moving his wings and singing melodiously: Kassyan joined in his song. He did not speak to me at all....

The weather was glorious, even more so than before; but the heat was no less. Over the clear sky the high thin clouds were hardly stirred, yellowish-white, like snow lying late in spring, flat and drawn out like rolled-up sails. Slowly but perceptibly their fringed edges, soft and fluffy as cotton-wool, changed at every moment; they were melting away, even these clouds, and no shadow fell from them. I strolled about the clearing for a long while with Kassyan. Young shoots, which had not yet had time to grow more than a yard high, surrounded the low blackened stumps with their smooth slender stems; and spongy funguses with grey edges — the same of which they make tinder — clung to these; strawberry plants flung their rosy tendrils over them; mushrooms squatted close in groups. The feet were constantly caught and entangled in the long grass, that was parched in the scorching sun; the eyes were dazzled on all sides by the glaring metallic glitter on the young reddish leaves of the trees; on all sides were the variegated blue clusters of vetch, the golden cups of bloodwort, and the half-lilac, half-yellow blossoms of the heart's-ease. In some places near the disused paths, on which the tracks of wheels were marked by streaks on the fine bright grass, rose piles of wood, blackened by wind and rain, laid in yard-lengths; there was a faint shadow cast from them in slanting oblongs; there was no other shade anywhere. A light breeze rose, then sank again; suddenly it would blow straight in the face and seem to be rising; everything would begin to rustle merrily, to nod, to shake around one; the supple tops of the ferns bow down gracefully, and one rejoices in it, but at once it dies away again, and all is at rest once more. Only the grasshoppers chirrup in chorus with frenzied energy, and wearisome is this unceasing, sharp dry sound. It is in keeping with the persistent heat of mid-day; it seems akin to it, as though evoked by it out of the glowing earth.

Without having started one single covey we at last reached another clearing. There the aspen-trees had only lately been felled, and lay stretched mournfully on the ground, crushing the grass and small undergrowth below them: on some the leaves were still green, though they were already dead, and hung limply from the motionless branches; on others they were crumpled and dried up. Fresh golden-white chips lay in heaps round the stumps that were covered with bright drops; a peculiar, very pleasant, pungent odour rose from them. Farther away, nearer the wood, sounded the dull blows of the axe, and from time to time, bowing and spreading wide its arms, a bushy tree fell slowly and majestically to the ground.

For a long time I did not come upon a single bird; at last a corncrake flew out of a thick clump of young oak across the wormwood springing up round it. I fired; it turned over in the air and fell. At the sound of the shot, Kassyan quickly covered his eyes with his hand, and he did not stir till I had reloaded the gun and picked up the bird. When I had moved farther on, he went up to the place where the wounded bird had fallen, bent down to the grass, on which some drops of blood were sprinkled, shook his head, and looked in dismay at me....I heard him afterwards whispering: 'A sin!…Ah, yes, it's a sin!'

The heat forced us at last to go into the wood. I flung myself down under a high nut-bush, over which a slender young maple gracefully stretched its light branches. Kassyan sat down on the thick trunk of a felled birch-tree. I looked at him. The leaves faintly stirred overhead, and their thin greenish shadows crept softly to and fro over his feeble body, muffled in a dark coat, and over his little face. He did not lift his head. Bored by his silence, I lay on my back and began to admire the tranquil play of the tangled foliage on the background of the bright, far away sky. A marvellously sweet occupation it is to lie on one's back in a wood and gaze upwards! You may fancy you are looking into a bottomless sea; that it stretches wide below you; that the trees are not rising out of the earth, but, like the roots of gigantic weeds, are dropping — falling straight down into those glassy, limpid depths; the leaves on the trees are at one moment transparent as emeralds, the next, they condense into golden, almost black green. Somewhere, afar off, at the end of a slender twig, a single leaf hangs motionless against the blue patch of transparent sky, and beside it another trembles with the motion of a fish on the line, as though moving of its own will, not shaken by the wind. Round white clouds float calmly across, and calmly pass away like submarine islands; and suddenly, all this ocean, this shining ether, these branches and leaves steeped in sunlight — all is rippling, quivering in fleeting brilliance, and a fresh trembling whisper awakens like the tiny, incessant plash of suddenly stirred eddies. One does not move — one looks, and no word can tell what peace, what joy, what sweetness reigns in the heart. One looks: the deep, pure blue stirs on one's lips a smile, innocent as itself; like the clouds over the sky, and, as it were, with them, happy memories pass in slow procession over the soul, and still one fancies one's gaze goes deeper and deeper, and draws one with it up into that peaceful, shining immensity, and that one cannot be brought back from that height, that depth....

'Master, master!' cried Kassyan suddenly in his musical voice.

I raised myself in surprise: up till then he had scarcely replied to my questions, and now he suddenly addressed me of himself.

'What is it?' I asked.

'What did you kill the bird for?' he began, looking me straight in the face.

'What for? Corncrake is game; one can eat it.'

'That was not what you killed it for, master, as though you were going to eat it! You killed it for amusement.'

'Well, you yourself, I suppose, eat geese or chickens?'

'Those birds are provided by God for man, but the corncrake is a wild bird of the woods: and not he alone; many they are, the wild things of the woods and the fields, and the wild things of the rivers and marshes and moors, flying on high or creeping below; and a sin it is to slay them: let them live their allotted life upon the earth. But for man another food has been provided; his food is other, and other his sustenance: bread, the good gift of God, and the water of heaven, and the tame beasts that have come down to us from our fathers of old.'

I looked in astonishment at Kassyan. His words flowed freely; he did not hesitate for a word; he spoke with quiet inspiration and gentle dignity, sometimes closing his eyes.

'So is it sinful, then, to kill fish, according to you?' I asked.

'Fishes have cold blood,' he replied with conviction. 'The fish is a dumb creature; it knows neither fear nor rejoicing. The fish is a voiceless creature. The fish does not feel; the blood in it is not living....Blood,' he continued, after a pause, 'blood is a holy thing! God's sun does not look upon blood; it is hidden away from the light…it is a great sin to bring blood into the light of day; a great sin and horror....Ah, a great sin!'

He sighed, and his head drooped forward. I looked, I confess, in absolute amazement at the strange old man. His language did not sound like the language of a peasant; the common people do not speak like that, nor those who aim at fine speaking. His speech was meditative, grave, and curious....I had never heard anything like it.

'Tell me, please, Kassyan,' I began, without taking my eyes off his slightly flushed face, 'what is your occupation?'

He did not answer my question at once. His eyes strayed uneasily for an instant.

'I live as the Lord commands,' he brought out at last; 'and as for occupation — no, I have no occupation. I've never been very clever from a child; I work when I can: I'm not much of a workman — how should I be? I have no health; my hands are awkward. In the spring I catch nightingales.'

'You catch nightingales?…But didn't you tell me that we must not touch any of the wild things of the woods and the fields, and so on?'

'We must not kill them, of a certainty; death will take its own without that. Look at Martin the carpenter; Martin lived, and his life was not long, but he died; his wife now grieves for her husband, for her little children....Neither for man nor beast is there any charm against death. Death does not hasten, nor is there any escaping it; but we must not aid death....And I do not kill nightingales — God forbid! I do not catch them to harm them, to spoil their lives, but for the pleasure of men, for their comfort and delight.'

'Do you go to Kursk to catch them?'

'Yes, I go to Kursk, and farther too, at times. I pass nights in the marshes, or at the edge of the forests; I am alone at night in the fields, in the thickets; there the curlews call and the hares squeak and the wild ducks lift up their voices....I note them at evening; at morning I give ear to them; at daybreak I cast my net over the bushes....There are nightingales that sing so pitifully sweet…yea, pitifully.'

'And do you sell them?'

'I give them to good people.'

'And what are you doing now?'

'What am I doing?'

'Yes, how are you employed?'

The old man was silent for a little.

'I am not employed at all....I am a poor workman. But I can read and write.'

'You can read?'

'Yes, I can read and write. I learnt, by the help of God and good people.'

'Have you a family?'

'No, not a family.'

'How so?…Are they dead, then?'

'No, but…I have never been lucky in life. But all that is in God's hands; we are all in God's hands; and a man should be righteous — that is all! Upright before God, that is it.'

'And you have no kindred?'

'Yes…well....'

The old man was confused.

'Tell me, please,' I began: 'I heard my coachman ask you why you did not cure Martin? You cure disease?'

'Your coachman is a righteous man,' Kassyan answered thoughtfully. 'I too am not without sin. They call me a doctor....Me a doctor, indeed! And who can heal the sick? That is all a gift from God. But there are…yes, there are herbs, and there are flowers; they are of use, of a certainty. There is plantain, for instance, a herb good for man; there is bud-marigold too; it is not sinful to speak of them: they are holy herbs of God. Then there are others not so; and they may be of use, but it's a sin; and to speak of them is a sin. Still, with prayer, may be....And doubtless there are such words....But who has faith, shall be saved,' he added, dropping his voice.

'You did not give Martin anything?' I asked.

'I heard of it too late,' replied the old man. 'But what of it! Each man's destiny is written from his birth. The carpenter Martin was not to live; he was not to live upon the earth: that was what it was. No, when a man is not to live on the earth, him the sunshine does not warm like another, and him the bread does not nourish and make strong; it is as though something is drawing him away....Yes: God rest his soul!'

'Have you been settled long amongst us?' I asked him after a short pause.

Kassyan started.

'No, not long; four years. In the old master's time we always lived in our old houses, but the trustees transported us. Our old master was a kind heart, a man of peace — the Kingdom of Heaven be his! The trustees doubtless judged righteously.'

'And where did you live before?'

'At Fair Springs.'

'Is it far from here?'

'A hundred miles.'

'Well, were you better off there?'

'Yes…yes, there there was open country, with rivers; it was our home: here we are cramped and parched up....Here we are strangers. There at home, at Fair Springs, you could get up on to a hill — and ah, my God, what a sight you could see! Streams and plains and forests, and there was a church, and then came plains beyond. You could see far, very far. Yes, how far you could look — you could look and look, ah, yes! Here, doubtless, the soil is better; it is clay — good fat clay, as the peasants say; for me the corn grows well enough everywhere.'

'Confess then, old man; you would like to visit your birth-place again?'

'Yes, I should like to see it. Still, all places are good. I am a man without kin, without neighbours. And, after all, do you gain much, pray, by staying at home? But, behold! as you walk, and as you walk,' he went on, raising his voice, 'the heart grows lighter, of a truth. And the sun shines upon you, and you are in the sight of God, and the singing comes more tunefully. Here, you look — what herb is growing; you look on it — you pick it. Here water runs, perhaps — spring water, a source of pure holy water; so you drink of it — you look on it too. The birds of heaven sing....And beyond Kursk come the steppes, that steppes-country: ah, what a marvel, what a delight for man! what freedom, what a blessing of God! And they go on, folks tell, even to the warm seas where dwells the sweet-voiced bird, the Hamayune, and from the trees the leaves fall not, neither in autumn nor in winter, and apples grow of gold, on silver branches, and every man lives in uprightness and content. And I would go even there....Have I journeyed so little already! I have been to Romyon and to Simbirsk the fair city, and even to Moscow of the golden domes; I have been to Oka the good nurse, and to Tsna the dove, and to our mother Volga, and many folks, good Christians have I seen, and noble cities I have visited....Well, I would go thither…yes…and more too…and I am not the only one, I a poor sinner…many other Christians go in bast-shoes, roaming over the world, seeking truth, yea!…For what is there at home? No righteousness in man — it's that.'

These last words Kassyan uttered quickly, almost unintelligibly; then he said something more which I could not catch at all, and such a strange expression passed over his face that I involuntarily recalled the epithet 'cracked.' He looked down, cleared his throat, and seemed to come to himself again. 'What sunshine!' he murmured in a low voice. 'It is a blessing, oh, Lord! What warmth in the woods!'

He gave a movement of the shoulders and fell into silence. With a vague look round him he began softly to sing. I could not catch all the words of his slow chant; I heard the following:

'They call me Kassyan,
But my nickname's the Flea.'

'Oh!' I thought, 'so he improvises.' Suddenly he started and ceased singing, looking intently at a thick part of the wood. I turned and saw a little peasant girl, about seven years old, in a blue frock, with a checked handkerchief over her head, and a woven bark-basket in her little bare sunburnt hand. She had certainly not expected to meet us; she had, as they say, 'stumbled upon' us, and she stood motionless in a shady recess among the thick foliage of the nut-trees, looking dismayed at me with her black eyes. I had scarcely time to catch a glimpse of her; she dived behind a tree.

'Annushka! Annushka! come here, don't be afraid!' cried the old man caressingly.

'I'm afraid,' came her shrill voice.

'Don't be afraid, don't be afraid; come to me.'

Annushka left her hiding place in silence, walked softly round — her little childish feet scarcely sounded on the thick grass — and came out of the bushes near the old man. She was not a child of seven, as I had fancied at first, from her diminutive stature, but a girl of thirteen or fourteen. Her whole person was small and thin, but very neat and graceful, and her pretty little face was strikingly like Kassyan's own, though he was certainly not handsome. There were the same thin features, and the same strange expression, shy and confiding, melancholy and shrewd, and her gestures were the same....Kassyan kept his eyes fixed on her; she took her stand at his side.

'Well, have you picked any mushrooms?' he asked.

'Yes,' she answered with a shy smile.

'Did you find many?'

'Yes.' (She stole a swift look at him and smiled again.)

'Are they white ones?'

'Yes.'

'Show me, show me....(She slipped the basket off her arm and half-lifted the big burdock leaf which covered up the mushrooms.) 'Ah!' said Kassyan, bending down over the basket; 'what splendid ones! Well done, Annushka!'

'She's your daughter, Kassyan, isn't she?' I asked. (Annushka's face flushed faintly.)

'No, well, a relative,' replied Kassyan with affected indifference. 'Come, Annushka, run along,' he added at once, 'run along, and God be with you! And take care.'

'But why should she go on foot?' I interrupted. 'We could take her with us.'

Annushka blushed like a poppy, grasped the handle of her basket with both hands, and looked in trepidation at the old man.

'No, she will get there all right,' he answered in the same languid and indifferent voice. 'Why not?…She will get there....Run along.'

Annushka went rapidly away into the forest. Kassyan looked after her, then looked down and smiled to himself. In this prolonged smile, in the few words he had spoken to Annushka, and in the very sound of his voice when he spoke to her, there was an intense, indescribable love and tenderness. He looked again in the direction she had gone, again smiled to himself, and, passing his hand across his face, he nodded his head several times.

'Why did you send her away so soon?' I asked him. 'I would have bought her mushrooms.'

'Well, you can buy them there at home just the same, sir, if you like,' he answered, for the first time using the formal 'sir' in addressing me.

'She's very pretty, your girl.'

'No…only so-so,' he answered, with seeming reluctance, and from that instant he relapsed into the same uncommunicative mood as at first.

Seeing that all my efforts to make him talk again were fruitless, I went off into the clearing. Meantime the heat had somewhat abated; but my ill-success, or, as they say among us, my 'ill-luck,' continued, and I returned to the settlement with nothing but one corncrake and the new axle. Just as we were driving into the yard, Kassyan suddenly turned to me.

'Master, master,' he began, 'do you know I have done you a wrong; it was I cast a spell to keep all the game off.'

'How so?'

'Oh, I can do that. Here you have a well-trained dog and a good one, but he could do nothing. When you think of it, what are men? what are they? Here's a beast; what have they made of him?'

It would have been useless for me to try to convince Kassyan of the impossibility of 'casting a spell' on game, and so I made him no reply. Meantime we had turned into the yard.

Annushka was not in the hut: she had had time to get there before us, and to leave her basket of mushrooms. Erofay fitted in the new axle, first exposing it to a severe and most unjust criticism; and an hour later I set off, leaving a small sum of money with Kassyan, which at first he was unwilling to accept, but afterwards, after a moment's thought, holding it in his hand, he put it in his bosom. In the course of this hour he had scarcely uttered a single word; he stood as before, leaning against the gate. He made no reply to the reproaches of my coachman, and took leave very coldly of me.

Directly I turned round, I could see that my worthy Erofay was in a gloomy frame of mind....To be sure, he had found nothing to eat in the country; the only water for his horses was bad. We drove off. With dissatisfaction expressed even in the back of his head, he sat on the box, burning to begin to talk to me. While waiting for me to begin by some question, he confined himself to a low muttering in an undertone, and some rather caustic instructions to the horses. 'A village,' he muttered; 'call that a village? You ask for a drop of kvas — not a drop of kvas even....Ah, Lord!…And the water — simply filth!' (He spat loudly.) 'Not a cucumber, nor kvas, nor nothing....Now, then!' he added aloud, turning to the right trace-horse; 'I know you, you humbug.' (And he gave him a cut with the whip.) 'That horse has learnt to shirk his work entirely, and yet he was a willing beast once. Now, then — look alive!'

'Tell me, please, Erofay,' I began, 'what sort of a man is Kassyan?'

Erofay did not answer me at once: he was, in general, a reflective and deliberate fellow; but I could see directly that my question was soothing and cheering to him.

'The Flea?' he said at last, gathering up the reins; 'he's a queer fellow; yes, a crazy chap; such a queer fellow, you wouldn't find another like him in a hurry. You know, for example, he's for all the world like our roan horse here; he gets out of everything — out of work, that's to say. But, then, what sort of workman could he be?…He's hardly body enough to keep his soul in…but still, of course....He's been like that from a child up, you know. At first he followed his uncle's business as a carrier — there were three of them in the business; but then he got tired of it, you know — he threw it up. He began to live at home, but he could not keep at home long; he's so restless — a regular flea, in fact. He happened, by good luck, to have a good master — he didn't worry him. Well, so ever since he has been wandering about like a lost sheep. And then, he's so strange; there's no understanding him. Sometimes he'll be as silent as a post, and then he'll begin talking, and God knows what he'll say! Is that good manners, pray? He's an absurd fellow, that he is. But he sings well, for all that.'

'And does he cure people, really?'

'Cure people!…Well, how should he? A fine sort of doctor! Though he did cure me of the king's evil, I must own....But how can he? He's a stupid fellow, that's what he is,' he added, after a moment's pause.

'Have you known him long?'

'A long while. I was his neighbour at Sitchovka up at Fair Springs.'

'And what of that girl — who met us in the wood, Annushka — what relation is she to him?'

Erofay looked at me over his shoulder, and grinned all over his face.

'He, he!…yes, they are relations. She is an orphan; she has no mother, and it's not even known who her mother was. But she must be a relation; she's too much like him....Anyway, she lives with him. She's a smart girl, there's no denying; a good girl; and as for the old man, she's simply the apple of his eye; she's a good girl. And, do you know, you wouldn't believe it, but do you know, he's managed to teach Annushka to read? Well, well! that's quite like him; he's such an extraordinary fellow, such a changeable fellow; there's no reckoning on him, really....Eh! eh! eh!' My coachman suddenly interrupted himself, and stopping the horses, he bent over on one side and began sniffing. 'Isn't there a smell of burning? Yes! Why, that new axle, I do declare!…I thought I'd greased it....We must get on to some water; why, here is a puddle, just right.'

And Erofay slowly got off his seat, untied the pail, went to the pool, and coming back, listened with a certain satisfaction to the hissing of the box of the wheel as the water suddenly touched it....Six times during some eight miles he had to pour water on the smouldering axle, and it was quite evening when we got home at last.

XIV Lebedyan

One of the principal advantages of hunting, my dear readers, consists in its forcing you to be constantly moving from place to place, which is highly agreeable for a man of no occupation. It is true that sometimes, especially in wet weather, it's not over pleasant to roam over by-roads, to cut 'across country,' to stop every peasant you meet with the question, 'Hey! my good man! how are we to get to Mordovka?' and at Mordovka to try to extract from a half-witted peasant woman (the working population are all in the fields) whether it is far to an inn on the high-road, and how to get to it — and then when you have gone on eight miles farther, instead of an inn, to come upon the deserted village of Hudobubnova, to the great amazement of a whole herd of pigs, who have been wallowing up to their ears in the black mud in the middle of the village street, without the slightest anticipation of ever being disturbed. There is no great joy either in having to cross planks that dance under your feet; to drop down into ravines; to wade across boggy streams: it is not over-pleasant to tramp twenty-four hours on end through the sea of green that covers the highroads or (which God forbid!) stay for hours stuck in the mud before a striped milestone with the figures 22 on one side and 23 on the other; it is not wholly pleasant to live for weeks together on eggs, milk, and the rye-bread patriots affect to be so fond of....But there is ample compensation for all these inconveniences and discomforts in pleasures and advantages of another sort. Let us come, though, to our story.

After all I have said above, there is no need to explain to the reader how I happened five years ago to be at Lebedyan just in the very thick of the horse-fair. We sportsmen may often set off on a fine morning from our more or less ancestral roof, in the full intention of returning there the following evening, and little by little, still in pursuit of snipe, may get at last to the blessed banks of Petchora. Besides, every lover of the gun and the dog is a passionate admirer of the noblest animal in the world, the horse. And so I turned up at Lebedyan, stopped at the hotel, changed my clothes, and went out to the fair. (The waiter, a thin lanky youth of twenty, had already informed me in a sweet nasal tenor that his Excellency Prince N — who purchases the chargers of the — regiment, was staying at their house; that many other gentlemen had arrived; that some gypsies were to sing in the evenings, and there was to be a performance of Pan Tvardovsky at the theatre; that the horses were fetching good prices; and that there was a fine show of them.)

In the market square there were endless rows of carts drawn up, and behind the carts, horses of every possible kind: racers, stud-horses, dray horses, cart-horses, posting-hacks, and simple peasants' nags. Some fat and sleek, assorted by colours, covered with striped horse-cloths, and tied up short to high racks, turned furtive glances backward at the too familiar whips of their owners, the horse-dealers; private owners' horses, sent by noblemen of the steppes a hundred or two hundred miles away, in charge of some decrepit old coachman and two or three headstrong stable-boys, shook their long necks, stamped with ennui, and gnawed at the fences; roan horses, from Vyatka, huddled close to one another; race-horses, dapple-grey, raven, and sorrel, with large hindquarters, flowing tails, and shaggy legs, stood in majestic immobility like lions. Connoisseurs stopped respectfully before them. The avenues formed by the rows of carts were thronged with people of every class, age, and appearance; horse-dealers in long blue coats and high caps, with sly faces, were on the look-out for purchasers; gypsies, with staring eyes and curly heads, strolled up and down, like uneasy spirits, looking into the horses' mouths, lifting up a hoof or a tail, shouting, swearing, acting as go-betweens, casting lots, or hanging about some army horse-contracter in a foraging-cap and military cloak, with beaver collar. A stalwart Cossack rode up and down on a lanky gelding with the neck of a stag, offering it for sale 'in one lot,' that is, saddle, bridle, and all. Peasants, in sheepskins torn at the arm-pits, were forcing their way despairingly through the crowd, or packing themselves by dozens into a cart harnessed to a horse, which was to be 'put to the test,' or somewhere on one side, with the aid of a wily gypsy, they were bargaining till they were exhausted, clasping each other's hands a hundred times over, each still sticking to his price, while the subject of their dispute, a wretched little jade covered with a shrunken mat, was blinking quite unmoved, as though it was no concern of hers....And, after all, what difference did it make to her who was to have the beating of her? Broad-browed landowners, with dyed moustaches and an expression of dignity on their faces, in Polish hats and cotton overcoats pulled half-on, were talking condescendingly with fat merchants in felt hats and green gloves. Officers of different regiments were crowding everywhere; an extraordinarily lanky cuirassier of German extraction was languidly inquiring of a lame horse-dealer 'what he expected to get for that chestnut.' A fair-haired young hussar, a boy of nineteen, was choosing a trace-horse to match a lean carriage-horse; a post-boy in a low-crowned hat, with a peacock's feather twisted round it, in a brown coat and long leather gloves tied round the arm with narrow, greenish bands, was looking for a shaft-horse. Coachmen were plaiting the horses' tails, wetting their manes, and giving respectful advice to their masters. Those who had completed a stroke of business were hurrying to hotel or to tavern, according to their class....And all the crowd were moving, shouting, bustling, quarrelling and making it up again, swearing and laughing, all up to their knees in the mud. I wanted to buy a set of three horses for my covered trap; mine had begun to show signs of breaking down. I had found two, but had not yet succeeded in picking up a third. After a hotel dinner, which I cannot bring myself to describe (even Aeneas had discovered how painful it is to dwell on sorrows past), I repaired to a café so-called, which was the evening resort of the purchasers of cavalry mounts, horse-breeders, and other persons. In the billiard-room, which was plunged in grey floods of tobacco smoke, there were about twenty men. Here were free-and-easy young landowners in embroidered jackets and grey trousers, with long curling hair and little waxed moustaches, staring about them with gentlemanly insolence; other noblemen in Cossack dress, with extraordinarily short necks, and eyes lost in layers of fat, were snorting with distressing distinctness; merchants sat a little apart on the qui-vive, as it is called; officers were chatting freely among themselves. At the billiard-table was Prince N—a young man of two-and-twenty, with a lively and rather contemptuous face, in a coat hanging open, a red silk shirt, and loose velvet pantaloons; he was playing with the ex-lieutenant, Viktor Hlopakov.

The ex-lieutenant, Viktor Hlopakov, a little, thinnish, dark man of thirty, with black hair, brown eyes, and a thick snub nose, is a diligent frequenter of elections and horse-fairs. He walks with a skip and a hop, waves his fat hands with a jovial swagger, cocks his cap on one side, and tucks up the sleeves of his military coat, showing the blue-black cotton lining. Mr. Hlopakov knows how to gain the favour of rich scapegraces from Petersburg; smokes, drinks, and plays cards with them; calls them by their Christian names. What they find to like in him it is rather hard to comprehend. He is not clever; he is not amusing; he is not even a buffoon. It is true they treat him with friendly casualness, as a good-natured fellow, but rather a fool; they chum with him for two or three weeks, and then all of a sudden do not recognise him in the street, and he on his side, too, does not recognise them. The chief peculiarity of Lieutenant Hlopakov consists in his continually for a year, sometimes two at a time, using in season and out of season one expression, which, though not in the least humorous, for some reason or other makes everyone laugh. Eight years ago he used on every occasion to say, 'Umble respecks and duty,' and his patrons of that date used always to fall into fits of laughter and make him repeat 'Umble respecks and duty;' then he began to adopt a more complicated expression: 'No, that's too, too k' essk' say,' and with the same brilliant success; two years later he had invented a fresh saying: 'Ne voo excite voo-self pa, man of sin, sewn in a sheepskin,' and so on. And strange to say! these, as you see, not overwhelmingly witty phrases, keep him in food and drink and clothes. (He has run through his property ages ago, and lives solely upon his friends.) There is, observe, absolutely no other attraction about him; he can, it is true, smoke a hundred pipes of Zhukov tobacco in a day, and when he plays billiards, throws his right leg higher than his head, and while taking aim shakes his cue affectedly; but, after all, not everyone has a fancy for these accomplishments. He can drink, too…but in Russia it is hard to gain distinction as a drinker. In short, his success is a complete riddle to me....There is one thing, perhaps; he is discreet; he has no taste for washing dirty linen away from home, never speaks a word against anyone.

'Well,' I thought, on seeing Hlopakov, 'I wonder what his catchword is now?'

The prince hit the white.

'Thirty love,' whined a consumptive marker, with a dark face and blue rings under his eyes.

The prince sent the yellow with a crash into the farthest pocket.

'Ah!' a stoutish merchant, sitting in the corner at a tottering little one-legged table, boomed approvingly from the depths of his chest, and immediately was overcome by confusion at his own presumption. But luckily no one noticed him. He drew a long breath, and stroked his beard.

'Thirty-six love!' the marker shouted in a nasal voice.

'Well, what do you say to that, old man?' the prince asked Hlopakov.

'What! rrrrakaliooon, of course, simply rrrrakaliooooon!'

The prince roared with laughter.

'What? what? Say it again.'

'Rrrrrakaliooon!' repeated the ex-lieutenant complacently.

'So that's the catchword!' thought I.

The prince sent the red into the pocket.

'Oh! that's not the way, prince, that's not the way,' lisped a fair-haired young officer with red eyes, a tiny nose, and a babyish, sleepy face. 'You shouldn't play like that…you ought…not that way!'

'Eh?' the prince queried over his shoulder.

'You ought to have done it…in a triplet.'

'Oh, really?' muttered the prince.

'What do you say, prince? Shall we go this evening to hear the gypsies?' the young man hurriedly went on in confusion. 'Styoshka will sing…Ilyushka....'

The prince vouchsafed no reply.

'Rrrrrakaliooon, old boy,' said Hlopakov, with a sly wink of his left eye.

And the prince exploded.

'Thirty-nine to love,' sang out the marker.

'Love…just look, I'll do the trick with that yellow.'…Hlopakov, fidgeting his cue in his hand, took aim, and missed.

'Eh, rrrakalioon,' he cried with vexation.

The prince laughed again.

'What, what, what?'

'Your honour made a miss,' observed the marker. 'Allow me to chalk the cue....Forty love.'

'Yes, gentlemen,' said the prince, addressing the whole company, and not looking at any one in particular; 'you know, Verzhembitskaya must be called before the curtain to-night.'

'To be sure, to be sure, of course,' several voices cried in rivalry, amazingly flattered at the chance of answering the prince's speech; 'Verzhembitskaya, to be sure....'

'Verzhembitskaya's an excellent actress, far superior to Sopnyakova,' whined an ugly little man in the corner with moustaches and spectacles. Luckless wretch! he was secretly sighing at Sopnyakova's feet, and the prince did not even vouchsafe him a look.

'Wai-ter, hey, a pipe!' a tall gentleman, with regular features and a most majestic manner — in fact, with all the external symptoms of a card-sharper — muttered into his cravat.

A waiter ran for a pipe, and when he came back, announced to his excellency that the groom Baklaga was asking for him.

'Ah! tell him to wait a minute and take him some vodka.'

'Yes, sir.'

Baklaga, as I was told afterwards, was the name of a youthful, handsome, and excessively depraved groom; the prince loved him, made him presents of horses, went out hunting with him, spent whole nights with him....Now you would not know this same prince, who was once a rake and a scapegrace....In what good odour he is now; how straight-laced, how supercilious! How devoted to the government — and, above all, so prudent and judicious!

However, the tobacco smoke had begun to make my eyes smart. After hearing Hlopakov's exclamation and the prince's chuckle one last time more, I went off to my room, where, on a narrow, hair-stuffed sofa pressed into hollows, with a high, curved back, my man had already made me up a bed.

The next day I went out to look at the horses in the stables, and began with the famous horsedealer Sitnikov's. I went through a gate into a yard strewn with sand. Before a wide open stable-door stood the horsedealer himself — a tall, stout man no longer young, in a hareskin coat, with a raised turnover collar. Catching sight of me, he moved slowly to meet me, held his cap in both hands above his head, and in a sing-song voice brought out:

'Ah, our respects to you. You'd like to have a look at the horses, may be?'

'Yes; I've come to look at the horses.'

'And what sort of horses, precisely, I make bold to ask?'

'Show me what you have.'

'With pleasure.'

We went into the stable. Some white pug-dogs got up from the hay and ran up to us, wagging their tails, and a long-bearded old goat walked away with an air of dissatisfaction; three stable-boys, in strong but greasy sheepskins, bowed to us without speaking. To right and to left, in horse-boxes raised above the ground, stood nearly thirty horses, groomed to perfection. Pigeons fluttered cooing about the rafters.

'What, now, do you want a horse for? for driving or for breeding?' Sitnikov inquired of me.

'Oh, I'll see both sorts.'

'To be sure, to be sure,' the horsedealer commented, dwelling on each syllable. 'Petya, show the gentleman Ermine.'

We came out into the yard.

'But won't you let them bring you a bench out of the hut?…You don't want to sit down....As you please.'

There was the thud of hoofs on the boards, the crack of a whip, and Petya, a swarthy fellow of forty, marked by small-pox, popped out of the stable with a rather well-shaped grey stallion, made it rear, ran twice round the yard with it, and adroitly pulled it up at the right place. Ermine stretched himself, snorted, raised his tail, shook his head, and looked sideways at me.

'A clever beast,' I thought.

'Give him his head, give him his head,' said Sitniker, and he stared at me.

'What may you think of him?' he inquired at last.

'The horse's not bad — the hind legs aren't quite sound.'

'His legs are first-rate!' Sitnikov rejoined, with an air of conviction;' and his hind-quarters…just look, sir…broad as an oven — you could sleep up there.' 'His pasterns are long.'

'Long! mercy on us! Start him, Petya, start him, but at a trot, a trot…don't let him gallop.'

Again Petya ran round the yard with Ermine. None of us spoke for a little.

'There, lead him back,' said Sitnikov, 'and show us Falcon.'

Falcon, a gaunt beast of Dutch extraction with sloping hind-quarters, as black as a beetle, turned out to be little better than Ermine. He was one of those beasts of whom fanciers will tell you that 'they go chopping and mincing and dancing about,' meaning thereby that they prance and throw out their fore-legs to right and to left without making much headway. Middle-aged merchants have a great fancy for such horses; their action recalls the swaggering gait of a smart waiter; they do well in single harness for an after-dinner drive; with mincing paces and curved neck they zealously draw a clumsy droshky laden with an overfed coachman, a depressed, dyspeptic merchant, and his lymphatic wife, in a blue silk mantle, with a lilac handkerchief over her head. Falcon too I declined. Sitnikov showed me several horses…One at last, a dapple-grey beast of Voyakov breed, took my fancy. I could not restrain my satisfaction, and patted him on the withers. Sitnikov at once feigned absolute indifference.

'Well, does he go well in harness?' I inquired. (They never speak of a trotting horse as 'being driven.' )

'Oh, yes,' answered the horsedealer carelessly.

'Can I see him?'

'If you like, certainly. Hi, Kuzya, put Pursuer into the droshky!'

Kuzya, the jockey, a real master of horsemanship, drove three times past us up and down the street. The horse went well, without changing its pace, nor shambling; it had a free action, held its tail high, and covered the ground well.

'And what are you asking for him?'

Sitnikov asked an impossible price. We began bargaining on the spot in the street, when suddenly a splendidly-matched team of three posting-horses flew noisily round the corner and drew up sharply at the gates before Sitnikov's house. In the smart little sportsman's trap sat Prince N—; beside him Hlopakov. Baklaga was driving…and how he drove! He could have driven them through an earring, the rascal! The bay trace-horses, little, keen, black-eyed, black-legged beasts, were all impatience; they kept rearing — a whistle, and off they would have bolted! The dark-bay shaft-horse stood firmly, its neck arched like a swan's, its breast forward, its legs like arrows, shaking its head and proudly blinking....They were splendid! No one could desire a finer turn out for an Easter procession!

'Your excellency, please to come in!' cried Sitnikov.

The prince leaped out of the trap. Hlopakov slowly descended on the other side.

'Good morning, friend…any horses.'

'You may be sure we've horses for your excellency! Pray walk in....Petya, bring out Peacock! and let them get Favourite ready too. And with you, sir,' he went on, turning to me, 'we'll settle matters another time....Fomka, a bench for his excellency.'

From a special stable which I had not at first observed they led out Peacock. A powerful dark sorrel horse seemed to fly across the yard with all its legs in the air. Sitnikov even turned away his head and winked.

'Oh, rrakalion!' piped Hlopakov; 'Zhaymsah (j'aime ça.)'

The prince laughed.

Peacock was stopped with difficulty; he dragged the stable-boy about the yard; at last he was pushed against the wall. He snorted, started and reared, while Sitnikov still teased him, brandishing a whip at him.

'What are you looking at? there! oo!' said the horsedealer with caressing menace, unable to refrain from admiring his horse himself.

'How much?' asked the prince.

'For your excellency, five thousand.'

'Three.'

'Impossible, your excellency, upon my word.'

'I tell you three, rrakalion,' put in Hlopakov.

I went away without staying to see the end of the bargaining. At the farthest corner of the street I noticed a large sheet of paper fixed on the gate of a little grey house. At the top there was a pen-and-ink sketch of a horse with a tail of the shape of a pipe and an endless neck, and below his hoofs were the following words, written in an old-fashioned hand:

'Here are for sale horses of various colours, brought to the Lebedyan fair from the celebrated steppes stud of Anastasei Ivanitch Tchornobai, landowner of Tambov. These horses are of excellent sort; broken in to perfection, and free from vice. Purchasers will kindly ask for Anastasei Ivanitch himself: should Anastasei Ivanitch be absent, then ask for Nazar Kubishkin, the coachman. Gentlemen about to purchase, kindly honour an old man.'

I stopped. 'Come,' I thought, 'let's have a look at the horses of the celebrated steppes breeder, Mr. Tchornobai.'

I was about to go in at the gate, but found that, contrary to the common usage, it was locked. I knocked.

'Who's there?…A customer?' whined a woman's voice.

'Yes.'

'Coming, sir, coming.'

The gate was opened. I beheld a peasant-woman of fifty, bareheaded, in boots, and a sheepskin worn open.

'Please to come in, kind sir, and I'll go at once, and tell Anastasei Ivanitch…Nazar, hey, Nazar!'

'What?' mumbled an old man's voice from the stable.

'Get a horse ready; here's a customer.'

The old woman ran into the house.

'A customer, a customer,' Nazar grumbled in response; 'I've not washed all their tails yet.'

'Oh, Arcadia!' thought I.

'Good day, sir, pleased to see you,' I heard a rich, pleasant voice saying behind my back. I looked round; before me, in a long-skirted blue coat, stood an old man of medium height, with white hair, a friendly smile, and fine blue eyes.

'You want a little horse? By all means, my dear sir, by all means....But won't you step in and drink just a cup of tea with me first?'

I declined and thanked him.

'Well, well, as you please. You must excuse me, my dear sir; you see I'm old-fashioned.' (Mr. Tchornobai spoke with deliberation, and in a broad Doric.) 'Everything with me is done in a plain way, you know....Nazar, hey, Nazar!' he added, not raising his voice, but prolonging each syllable. Nazar, a wrinkled old man with a little hawk nose and a wedge-shaped beard, showed himself at the stable door.

'What sort of horses is it you're wanting, my dear sir?' resumed Mr. Tchornobai.

'Not too expensive; for driving in my covered gig.'

'To be sure…we have got them to suit you, to be sure....Nazar, Nazar, show the gentleman the grey gelding, you know, that stands at the farthest corner, and the sorrel with the star, or else the other sorrel — foal of Beauty, you know.'

Nazar went back to the stable.

'And bring them out by their halters just as they are,' Mr. Tchornobai shouted after him. 'You won't find things with me, my good sir,' he went on, with a clear mild gaze into my face, 'as they are with the horse-dealers; confound their tricks! There are drugs of all sorts go in there, salt and malted grains; God forgive them! But with me, you will see, sir, everything's above-board; no underhandedness.'

The horses were led in; I did not care for them.

'Well, well, take them back, in God's name,' said Anastasei Ivanitch. 'Show us the others.'

Others were shown. At last I picked out one, rather a cheap one. We began to haggle over the price. Mr. Tchornobai did not get excited; he spoke so reasonably, with such dignity, that I could not help 'honouring' the old man; I gave him the earnest-money.

'Well, now,' observed Anastasei Ivanitch, 'allow me to give over the horse to you from hand to hand, after the old fashion....You will thank me for him…as sound as a nut, see…fresh…a true child of the steppes! Goes well in any harness.'

He crossed himself, laid the skirt of his coat over his hand, took the halter, and handed me the horse.

'You're his master now, with God's blessing....And you still won't take a cup of tea?'

'No, I thank you heartily; it's time I was going home.'

'That's as you think best....And shall my coachman lead the horse after you?'

'Yes, now, if you please.'

'By all means, my dear sir, by all means....Vassily, hey, Vassily! step along with the gentleman, lead the horse, and take the money for him. Well, good-bye, my good sir; God bless you.'

'Good-bye, Anastasei Ivanitch.'

They led the horse home for me. The next day he turned out to be broken-winded and lame. I tried having him put in harness; the horse backed, and if one gave him a flick with the whip he jibbed, kicked, and positively lay down. I set off at once to Mr. Tchornobai's. I inquired: 'At home?'

'Yes.'

'What's the meaning of this?' said I; 'here you've sold me a broken-winded horse.'

'Broken-winded?…God forbid!'

'Yes, and he's lame too, and vicious besides.'

'Lame! I know nothing about it: your coachman must have ill-treated him somehow....But before God, I—'

'Look here, Anastasei Ivanitch, as things stand, you ought to take him back.'

'No, my good sir, don't put yourself in a passion; once gone out of the yard, is done with. You should have looked before, sir.'

I understood what that meant, accepted my fate, laughed, and walked off. Luckily, I had not paid very dear for the lesson.

Two days later I left, and in a week I was again at Lebedyan on my way home again. In the café I found almost the same persons, and again I came upon Prince N— at billiards. But the usual change in the fortunes of Mr. Hlopakov had taken place in this interval: the fair-haired young officer had supplanted him in the prince's favours. The poor ex-lieutenant once more tried letting off his catchword in my presence, on the chance it might succeed as before; but, far from smiling, the prince positively scowled and shrugged his shoulders. Mr. Hlopakov looked downcast, shrank into a corner, and began furtively filling himself a pipe....

XV Tatyana Borissovna and Her Nephew

Give me your hand, gentle reader, and come along with me. It is glorious weather; there is a tender blue in the May sky; the smooth young leaves of the willows glisten as though they had been polished; the wide even road is all covered with that delicate grass with the little reddish stalk that the sheep are so fond of nibbling; to right and to left, over the long sloping hillsides, the green rye is softly waving; the shadows of small clouds glide in thin long streaks over it. In the distance is the dark mass of forests, the glitter of ponds, yellow patches of village; larks in hundreds are soaring, singing, falling headlong with outstretched necks, hopping about the clods; the crows on the highroad stand still, look at you, peck at the earth, let you drive close up, and with two hops lazily move aside. On a hill beyond a ravine a peasant is ploughing; a piebald colt, with a cropped tail and ruffled mane, is running on unsteady legs after its mother; its shrill whinnying reaches us. We drive on into the birch wood, and drink in the strong, sweet, fresh fragrance. Here we are at the boundaries. The coachman gets down; the horses snort; the trace-horses look round; the centre horse in the shafts switches his tail, and turns his head up towards the wooden yoke above it…the great gate opens creaking; the coachman seats himself....Drive on! the village is before us. Passing five homesteads, and turning off to the right, we drop down into a hollow and drive along a dyke, the farther side of a small pond; behind the round tops of the lilacs and apple-trees a wooden roof, once red, with two chimneys, comes into sight; the coachman keeps along the hedge to the left, and to the spasmodic and drowsy baying of three pug dogs he drives through the wide open gates, whisks smartly round the broad courtyard past the stable and the barn, gallantly salutes the old housekeeper, who is stepping sideways over the high lintel in the open doorway of the storehouse, and pulls up at last before the steps of a dark house with light windows....We are at Tatyana Borissovna's. And here she is herself opening the window and nodding at us.... 'Good day, ma' am!'

Tatyana Borissovna is a woman of fifty, with large, prominent grey eyes, a rather broad nose, rosy cheeks and a double chin. Her face is brimming over with friendliness and kindness. She was once married, but was soon left a widow. Tatyana Borissovna is a very remarkable woman. She lives on her little property, never leaving it, mixes very little with her neighbours, sees and likes none but young people. She was the daughter of very poor landowners, and received no education; in other words, she does not know French; she has never been in Moscow — and in spite of all these defects, she is so good and simple in her manners, so broad in her sympathies and ideas, so little infected with the ordinary prejudices of country ladies of small means, that one positively cannot help marvelling at her....Indeed, a woman who lives all the year round in the country and does not talk scandal, nor whine, nor curtsey, is never flurried, nor depressed, nor in a flutter of curiosity, is a real marvel! She usually wears a grey taffetas gown and a white cap with lilac streamers; she is fond of good cheer, but not to excess; all the preserving, pickling, and salting she leaves to her housekeeper. 'What does she do all day long?' you will ask.... 'Does she read?' No, she doesn't read, and, to tell the truth, books are not written for her....If there are no visitors with her, Tatyana Borissovna sits by herself at the window knitting a stocking in winter; in summer time she is in the garden, planting and watering her flowers, playing for hours together with her cats, or feeding her doves....She does not take much part in the management of her estate. But if a visitor pays her a call — some young neighbour whom she likes — Tatyana Borissovna is all life directly; she makes him sit down, pours him out some tea, listens to his chat, laughs, sometimes pats his cheek, but says little herself; in trouble or sorrow she comforts and gives good advice. How many people have confided their family secrets and the griefs of their hearts to her, and have wept over her hands! At times she sits opposite her visitor, leaning lightly on her elbow, and looks with such sympathy into his face, smiles so affectionately, that he cannot help feeling: 'What a dear, good woman you are, Tatyana Borissovna! Let me tell you what is in my heart.' One feels happy and warm in her small, snug rooms; in her house it is always, so to speak, fine weather. Tatyana Borissovna is a wonderful woman, but no one wonders at her; her sound good sense, her breadth and firmness, her warm sympathy in the joys and sorrows of others — in a word, all her qualities are so innate in her; they are no trouble, no effort to her....One cannot fancy her otherwise, and so one feels no need to thank her. She is particularly fond of watching the pranks and follies of young people; she folds her hands over her bosom, throws back her head, puckers up her eyes, and sits smiling at them, then all of a sudden she heaves a sigh, and says, 'Ah, my children, my children!'…Sometimes one longs to go up to her, take hold of her hands and say: 'Let me tell you, Tatyana Borissovna, you don't know your own value; for all your simplicity and lack of learning, you're an extraordinary creature!' Her very name has a sweet familiar ring; one is glad to utter it; it calls up a kindly smile at once. How often, for instance, have I chanced to ask a peasant: 'Tell me, my friend, how am I to get to Gratchevka?' let us say. 'Well, sir, you go on first to Vyazovoe, and from there to Tatyana Borissovna's, and from Tatyana Borissovna's any one will show you the way.' And at the name of Tatyana Borissovna the peasant wags his head in quite a special way. Her household is small, in accordance with her means. The house, the laundry, the stores and the kitchen, are in the charge of the housekeeper, Agafya, once her nurse, a good-natured, tearful, toothless creature; she has under her two stalwart girls with stout crimson cheeks like Antonovsky apples. The duties of valet, steward, and waiter are filled by Policarp, an extraordinary old man of seventy, a queer fellow, full of erudition, once a violinist and worshipper of Viotti, with a personal hostility to Napoleon, or, as he calls him, Bonaparty, and a passion for nightingales. He always keeps five or six of the latter in his room; in early spring he will sit for whole days together by the cage, waiting for the first trill, and when he hears it, he covers his face with his hands, and moans, 'Oh, piteous, piteous!' and sheds tears in floods. Policarp has, to help him, his grandson Vasya, a curly-headed, sharp-eyed boy of twelve; Policarp adores him, and grumbles at him from morning till night. He undertakes his education too. 'Vasya,' he says, 'say Bonaparty was a scoundrel.' 'And what'll you give me, granddad?' 'What'll I give you?…I'll give you nothing....Why, what are you? Aren't you a Russian?' 'I'm a Mtchanin, granddad; I was born in Mtchensk.' 'Oh, silly dunce! but where is Mtchensk?' 'How can I tell?' 'Mtchensk's in Russia, silly!' 'Well, what then, if it is in Russia?' 'What then? Why, his Highness the late Prince Mihalo Ilarionovitch Golenishtchev-Kutuzov-Smolensky, with God's aid, graciously drove Bonaparty out of the Russian territories. It's on that event the song was composed: "Bonaparty's in no mood to dance, He's lost the garters he brought from France."…Do you understand? he liberated your fatherland.' 'And what's that to do with me?' 'Ah! you silly boy! Why, if his Highness Prince Mihalo Ilarionovitch hadn't driven out Bonaparty, some mounseer would have been beating you about the head with a stick this minute. He'd come up to you like this, and say: "Koman voo porty voo?" and then a box on the ear!' 'But I'd give him one in the belly with my fist.' 'But he'd go on: "Bonzhur, bonzhur, veny ici," and then a cuff on the head.' 'And I'd give him one in his legs, his bandy legs.' 'You're quite right, their legs are bandy....Well, but suppose he tied your hands?' 'I wouldn't let him; I'd call Mihay the coachman to help me.' 'But, Vasya, suppose you weren't a match for the Frenchy even with Mihay?' 'Not a match for him! See how strong Mihay is!' 'Well, and what would you do with him?' 'We'd get him on his back, we would.' 'And he'd shout, "Pardon, pardon, seevooplay!"' 'We'd tell him, "None of your seevooplays, you old Frenchy!"' 'Bravo, Vasya!…Well, now then, shout, "Bonaparty's a scoundrel!"' 'But you must give me some sugar!' 'You scamp!'

Of the neighbouring ladies Tatyana Borissovna sees very little; they do not care about going to see her, and she does not know how to amuse them; the sound of their chatter sends her to sleep; she starts, tries to keep her eyes open, and drops off again. Tatyana Borissovna is not fond of women as a rule. One of her friends, a good, harmless young man, had a sister, an old maid of thirty-eight and a half, a good-natured creature, but exaggerated, affected, and enthusiastic. Her brother had often talked to her of their neighbour. One fine morning our old maid has her horse saddled, and, without a word to any one, sallies off to Tatyana Borissovna's. In her long habit, a hat on her head, a green veil and floating curls, she went into the hall, and passing by the panic-stricken Vasya, who took her for a wood-witch, ran into the drawing-room. Tatyana Borissovna, scared, tried to rise, but her legs sank under her. 'Tatyana Borissovna,' began the visitor in a supplicating voice, 'forgive my temerity; I am the sister of your friend, Alexy Nikolaevitch K— and I have heard so much about you from him that I resolved to make your acquaintance.' 'Greatly honoured,' muttered the bewildered lady. The sister flung off her hat, shook her curls, seated herself near Tatyana Borissovna; took her by the hand… 'So this is she,' she began in a pensive voice fraught with feeling: 'this is that sweet, clear, noble, holy being! This is she! that woman at once so simple and so deep! How glad I am! how glad I am! How we shall love each other! I can breathe easily at last…I always fancied her just so,' she added in a whisper, her eyes riveted on the eyes of Tatyana Borissovna. 'You won't be angry with me, will you, my dear kind friend?' 'Really, I'm delighted!…Won't you have some tea?' The lady smiled patronisingly: 'Wie wahr, wie unreflectiert,' she murmured, as it were to herself. 'Let me embrace you, my dear one!'

The old maid stayed three hours at Tatyana Borissovna's, never ceasing talking an instant. She tried to explain to her new acquaintance all her own significance. Directly after the unexpected visitor had departed, the poor lady took a bath, drank some lime-flower water, and took to her bed. But the next day the old maid came back, stayed four hours, and left, promising to come to see Tatyana Borissovna every day. Her idea, please to observe, was to develop, to complete the education of so rich a nature, to use her own expression, and she would probably have really been the death of her, if she had not, in the first place, been utterly disillusioned as regards her brother's friend within a fortnight, and secondly, fallen in love with a young student on a visit in the neighbourhood, with whom she at once rushed into a fervid and active correspondence; in her missives she consecrated him, as the manner of such is, to a noble, holy life, offered herself wholly a sacrifice, asked only for the name of sister, launched into endless descriptions of nature, made allusions to Goethe, Schiller, Bettina and German philosophy, and drove the luckless young man at last to the blackest desperation. But youth asserted itself: one fine morning he woke up with such a furious hatred for 'his sister and best of friends' that he almost killed his valet in his passion, and was snappish for a long while after at the slightest allusion to elevated and disinterested passion. But from that time forth Tatyana Borissovna began to avoid all intimacy with ladies of the neighbourhood more than ever.

Alas! nothing is lasting on this earth. All I have related as to the way of life of my kind-hearted neighbour is a thing of the past; the peace that used to reign in her house has been destroyed for ever. For more than a year now there has been living with her a nephew, an artist from Petersburg. This is how it came about.

Eight years ago, there was living with Tatyana Borissovna a boy of twelve, an orphan, the son of her brother, Andryusha. Andryusha had large, clear, humid eyes, a tiny little mouth, a regular nose, and a fine lofty brow. He spoke in a low, sweet voice, was attentive and coaxing with visitors, kissed his auntie's hand with an orphan's sensibility; and one hardly had time to show oneself before he had put a chair for one. He had no mischievous tricks; he was never noisy; he would sit by himself in a corner with a book, and with such sedateness and propriety, never even leaning back in his chair. When a visitor came in, Andryusha would get up, with a decorous smile and a flush; when the visitor went away he would sit down again, pull out of his pocket a brush and a looking-glass, and brush his hair. From his earliest years he had shown a taste for drawing. Whenever he got hold of a piece of paper, he would ask Agafya the housekeeper for a pair of scissors at once, carefully cut a square piece out of the paper, trace a border round it and set to work; he would draw an eye with an immense pupil, or a Grecian nose, or a house with a chimney and smoke coming out of it in the shape of a corkscrew, a dog, en face, looking rather like a bench, or a tree with two pigeons on it, and would sign it: 'Drawn by Andrei Byelovzorov, such a day in such a year, in the village of Maliya-Briki.' He used to toil with special industry for a fortnight before Tatyana Borissovna's birthday; he was the first to present his congratulations and offer her a roll of paper tied up with a pink ribbon. Tatyana Borissovna would kiss her nephew and undo the knot; the roll was unfolded and presented to the inquisitive gaze of the spectator, a round, boldly sketched temple in sepia, with columns and an altar in the centre; on the altar lay a burning heart and a wreath, while above, on a curling scroll, was inscribed in legible characters: 'To my aunt and benefactress, Tatyana Borissovna Bogdanov, from her dutiful and loving nephew, as a token of his deepest affection.' Tatyana Borissovna would kiss him again and give him a silver rouble. She did not, though, feel any very warm affection for him; Andryusha's fawning ways were not quite to her taste. Meanwhile, Andryusha was growing up; Tatyana Borissovna began to be anxious about his future. An unexpected incident solved the difficulty to her.

One day eight years ago she received a visit from a certain Mr. Benevolensky, Piotr Mihalitch, a college councillor with a decoration. Mr. Benevolensky had at one time held an official post in the nearest district town, and had been assiduous in his visits to Tatyana Borissovna; then he had moved to Petersburg, got into the ministry, and attained a rather important position, and on one of the numerous journeys he took in the discharge of his official duties, he remembered his old friend, and came back to see her, with the intention of taking a rest for two days from his official labours 'in the bosom of the peace of nature.' Tatyana Borissovna greeted him with her usual cordiality, and Mr. Benevolensky....But before we proceed with the rest of the story, gentle reader, let us introduce you to this new personage.

Mr. Benevolensky was a stoutish man, of middle height and mild appearance, with little short legs and little fat hands; he wore a roomy and excessively spruce frock-coat, a high broad cravat, snow-white linen, a gold chain on his silk waistcoat, a gem-ring on his forefinger, and a white wig on his head; he spoke softly and persuasively, trod noiselessly, and had an amiable smile, an amiable look in his eyes, and an amiable way of settling his chin in his cravat; he was, in fact, an amiable person altogether. God had given him a heart, too, of the softest; he was easily moved to tears and to transports; moreover, he was all aglow with disinterested passion for art: disinterested it certainly was, for Mr. Benevolensky, if the truth must be told, knew absolutely nothing about art. One is set wondering, indeed, whence, by virtue of what mysterious uncomprehended forces, this passion had come upon him. He was, to all appearance, a practical, even prosaic person…however, we have a good many people of the same sort among us in Russia.

Their devotion to art and artists produces in these people an inexpressible mawkishness; it is distressing to have to do with them and to talk to them; they are perfect logs smeared with honey. They never, for instance, call Raphael, Raphael, or Correggio, Correggio; 'the divine Sanzio, the incomparable di Allegri,' they murmur, and always with the broadest vowels. Every pretentious, conceited, home-bred mediocrity they hail as a genius: 'the blue sky of Italy,' 'the lemons of the South,' 'the balmy breezes of the banks of the Brenta,' are for ever on their lips. 'Ah, Vasya, Vasya,' or 'Oh, Sasha, Sasha,' they say to one another with deep feeling, 'we must away to the South…we are Greeks in soul — ancient Greeks.' One may observe them at exhibitions before the works of some Russian painters (these gentlemen, it should be noted, are, for the most part, passionate patriots). First they step back a couple of paces, and throw back their heads; then they go up to the picture again; their eyes are suffused with an oily moisture....'There you have it, my God!' they say at last, in voices broken with emotion; 'there's soul, soul! Ah! what feeling, what feeling! Ah, what soul he has put into it! what a mass of soul!…And how he has thought it out! thought it out like a master!' And, oh! the pictures in their own drawing-rooms! Oh, the artists that come to them in the evenings, drink tea, and listen to their conversation! And the views in perspective they make them of their own rooms, with a broom in the foreground, a little heap of dust on the polished floor, a yellow samovar on a table near the window, and the master of the house himself in skull-cap and dressing-gown, with a brilliant streak of sunlight falling on his cheek! Oh, the long-haired nurslings of the Muse, wearing spasmodic and contemptuous smiles, that cluster about them! Oh, the young ladies, with faces of greenish pallor, who squeal; over their pianos! For that is the established rule with us in Russia; a man cannot be devoted to one art alone — he must have them all. And so it is not to be wondered at that these gentlemen extend their powerful patronage to Russian literature also, especially to dramatic literature....The Jacob Sannazars are written for them; the struggle of unappreciated talent against the whole world, depicted a thousand times over, still moves them profoundly....

The day after Mr. Benevolensky's arrival, Tatyana Borissovna told her nephew at tea-time to show their guest his drawings. 'Why, does he draw?' said Mr. Benevolensky, with some surprise, and he turned with interest to Andryusha. 'Yes, he draws,' said Tatyana Borissovna; 'he's so fond of it! and he does it all alone, without a master.' 'Ah! show me, show me,' cried Mr. Benevolensky. Andryusha, blushing and smiling, brought the visitor his sketch-book. Mr. Benevolensky began turning it over with the air of a connoisseur. 'Good, young man,' he pronounced at last; 'good, very good.' And he patted Andryusha on the head. Andryusha intercepted his hand and kissed it 'Fancy, now, a talent like that!…I congratulate you, Tatyana Borissovna.' 'But what am I to do, Piotr Mihalitch? I can't get him a teacher here. To have one from the town is a great expense; our neighbours, the Artamonovs, have a drawing-master, and they say an excellent one, but his mistress forbids his giving lessons to outsiders.' 'Hm,' pronounced Mr. Benevolensky; he pondered and looked askance at Andryusha. 'Well, we will talk it over,' he added suddenly, rubbing his hands. The same day he begged Tatyana Borissovna's permission for an interview with her alone. They shut themselves up together. In half-an-hour they called Andryusha — Andryusha went in. Mr. Benevolensky was standing at the window with a slight flush on his face and a beaming expression. Tatyana Borissovna was sitting in a corner wiping her eyes. 'Come, Andryusha,' she said at last, 'you must thank Piotr Mihalitch; he will take you under his protection; he will take you to Petersburg.' Andryusha almost fainted on the spot. 'Tell me candidly,' began Mr. Benevolensky, in a voice filled with dignity and patronising indulgence; 'do you want to be an artist, young man? Do you feel yourself consecrated to the holy service of Art?' 'I want to be an artist, Piotr Mihalitch,' Andryusha declared in a trembling voice. 'I am delighted, if so it be. It will, of course,' continued Mr. Benevolensky, 'be hard for you to part from your revered aunt; you must feel the liveliest gratitude to her.' 'I adore my auntie,' Andryusha interrupted, blinking. 'Of course, of course, that's readily understood, and does you great credit; but, on the other hand, consider the pleasure that in the future…your success....' 'Kiss me, Andryusha,' muttered the kind-hearted lady. Andryusha flung himself on her neck. 'There, now, thank your benefactor.' Andryusha embraced Mr. Benevolensky's stomach, and stretching on tiptoe, reached his hand and imprinted a kiss, which his benefactor, though with some show of reluctance, accepted....He had, to be sure, to pacify the child, and, after all, might reflect that he deserved it. Two days later, Mr. Benevolensky departed, taking with him his new protégé.

During the first three years of Andryusha's absence he wrote pretty often, sometimes enclosing drawings in his letters. From time to time Mr. Benevolensky added a few words, for the most part of approbation; then the letters began to be less and less frequent, and at last ceased altogether. A whole year passed without a word from her nephew; and Tatyana Borissovna was beginning to be uneasy when suddenly she got the following note:—

'DEAREST AUNTIE — Piotr Mihalitch, my patron, died three days ago. A severe paralytic stroke has deprived me of my sole support. To be sure, I am now twenty. I have made considerable progress during the last seven years; I have the greatest confidence in my talent, and can make my living by means of it; I do not despair; but all the same send me, if you can, as soon as convenient, 250 roubles. I kiss your hand and remain…' etc.

Tatyana Borissovna sent her nephew 250 roubles. Two months later he asked for more; she got together every penny she had and sent it him. Not six weeks after the second donation he was asking a third time for help, ostensibly to buy colours for a portrait bespoken by Princess Tertereshenev. Tatyana Borissovna refused. 'Under these circumstances,' he wrote to her, 'I propose coming to you to regain my health in the country.' And in the May of the same year Andryusha did, in fact, return to Maliya-Briki.

Tatyana Borissovna did not recognise him for the first minute. From his letter she had expected to see a wasted invalid, and she beheld a stout, broad-shouldered fellow, with a big red face and greasy, curly hair. The pale, slender little Andryusha had turned into the stalwart Andrei Ivanovitch Byelovzorov. And it was not only his exterior that was transformed. The modest spruceness, the sedateness and tidiness of his earlier years, was replaced by a careless swagger and slovenliness quite insufferable; he rolled from side to side as he walked, lolled in easy-chairs, put his elbows on the table, stretched and yawned, and behaved rudely to his aunt and the servants. 'I'm an artist,' he would say; 'a free Cossack! That's our sort!' Sometimes he did not touch a brush for whole days together; then the inspiration, as he called it, would come upon him; then he would swagger about as if he were drunk, clumsy, awkward, and noisy; his cheeks were flushed with a coarse colour, his eyes dull; he would launch into discourses upon his talent, his success, his development, the advance he was making....It turned out in actual fact that he had barely talent enough to produce passable portraits. He was a perfect ignoramus, had read nothing; why should an artist read, indeed? Nature, freedom, poetry were his fitting elements; he need do nothing but shake his curls, talk, and suck away at his eternal cigarette! Russian audacity is a fine thing, but it doesn't suit every one; and Polezhaevs at second-hand, without the genius, are insufferable beings. Andrei Ivanovitch went on living at his aunt's; he did not seem to find the bread of charity bitter, notwithstanding the proverb. Visitors to the house found him a mortal nuisance. He would sit at the piano (a piano, too, had been installed at Tatyana Borissovna's) and begin strumming 'The Swift Sledge' with one finger; he would strike some chords, tap on the keys, and for hours together he would howl Varlamov's songs, 'The Solitary Pine,' or 'No, doctor, no, don't come to me,' in the most distressing manner, and his eyes seemed to disappear altogether, his cheeks were so puffed out and tense as drums....Then he would suddenly strike up: 'Be still, distracting passion's tempest!'…Tatyana Borissovna positively shuddered.

'It's a strange thing,' she observed to me one day, 'the songs they compose nowadays; there's something desperate about them; in my day they were very different. We had mournful songs, too, but it was always a pleasure to hear them....For instance:—

"'Come, come to me in the meadow,
Where I am awaiting thee;
Come, come to me in the meadow,
Where I'm shedding tears for thee…
Alas! thou'rt coming to the meadow,
But too late, dear love, for me!'"

Tatyana Borissovna smiled slyly.

'I agon-ise, I agon-ise!' yelled her nephew in the next room.

'Be quiet, Andryusha!'

'My soul's consumed apart from thee!' the indefatigable singer continued.

Tatyana Borissovna shook her head.

'Ah, these artists! these artists!'…

A year has gone by since then. Byelovzorov is still living at his aunt's, and still talking of going back to Petersburg. He has grown as broad as he is long in the country. His aunt — who could have imagined such a thing? — idolises him, and the young girls of the neighbourhood are falling in love with him…

Many of her old friends have given up going to Tatyana Borissovna's.

XVI Death

I have a neighbour, a young landowner and a young sportsman. One fine July morning I rode over to him with a proposition that we should go out grouse-shooting together. He agreed. 'Only let's go,' he said, 'to my underwoods at Zusha; I can seize the opportunity to have a look at Tchapligino; you know my oakwood; they're felling timber there.' 'By all means.' He ordered his horse to be saddled, put on a green coat with bronze buttons, stamped with a boar's head, a game-bag embroidered in crewels, and a silver flask, slung a new-fangled French gun over his shoulder, turned himself about with some satisfaction before the looking-glass, and called his dog, Hope, a gift from his cousin, an old maid with an excellent heart, but no hair on her head. We started. My neighbour took with him the village constable, Arhip, a stout, squat peasant with a square face and jaws of antediluvian proportions, and an overseer he had recently hired from the Baltic provinces, a youth of nineteen, thin, flaxen-haired, and short-sighted, with sloping shoulders and a long neck, Herr Gottlieb von der Kock. My neighbour had himself only recently come into the property. It had come to him by inheritance from an aunt, the widow of a councillor of state, Madame Kardon-Kataev, an excessively stout woman, who did nothing but lie in her bed, sighing and groaning. We reached the underwoods. 'You wait for me here at the clearing,' said Ardalion Mihalitch (my neighbour) addressing his companions. The German bowed, got off his horse, pulled a book out of his pocket — a novel of Johanna Schopenhauer's, I fancy — and sat down under a bush; Arhip remained in the sun without stirring a muscle for an hour. We beat about among the bushes, but did not come on a single covey. Ardalion Mihalitch announced his intention of going on to the wood. I myself had no faith, somehow, in our luck that day; I, too, sauntered after him. We got back to the clearing. The German noted the page, got up, put the book in his pocket, and with some difficulty mounted his bob-tailed, broken-winded mare, who neighed and kicked at the slightest touch; Arhip shook himself, gave a tug at both reins at once, swung his legs, and at last succeeded in starting his torpid and dejected nag. We set off.

I had been familiar with Ardalion Mihalitch's wood from my childhood. I had often strolled in Tchapligino with my French tutor, Monsieur Désiré Fleury, the kindest of men (who had, however, almost ruined my constitution for life by dosing me with Leroux's mixture every evening). The whole wood consisted of some two or three hundred immense oaks and ash-trees. Their stately, powerful trunks were magnificently black against the transparent golden green of the nut bushes and mountain-ashes; higher up, their wide knotted branches stood out in graceful lines against the clear blue sky, unfolding into a tent overhead; hawks, honey-buzzards and kestrels flew whizzing under the motionless tree-tops; variegated wood-peckers tapped loudly on the stout bark; the blackbird's bell-like trill was heard suddenly in the thick foliage, following on the ever-changing note of the gold-hammer; in the bushes below was the chirp and twitter of hedge-warblers, siskins, and peewits; finches ran swiftly along the paths; a hare would steal along the edge of the wood, halting cautiously as he ran; a squirrel would hop sporting from tree to tree, then suddenly sit still, with its tail over its head. In the grass among the high ant-hills under the delicate shade of the lovely, feathery, deep-indented bracken, were violets and lilies of the valley, and funguses, russet, yellow, brown, red and crimson; in the patches of grass among the spreading bushes red strawberries were to be found....And oh, the shade in the wood! In the most stifling heat, at mid-day, it was like night in the wood: such peace, such fragrance, such freshness....I had spent happy times in Tchapligino, and so, I must own, it was with melancholy feelings I entered the wood I knew so well. The ruinous, snowless winter of 1840 had not spared my old friends, the oaks and the ashes; withered, naked, covered here and there with sickly foliage, they struggled mournfully up above the young growth which 'took their place, but could never replace them.'[1]

Some trees, still covered with leaves below, fling their lifeless, ruined branches upwards, as it were, in reproach and despair; in others, stout, dead, dry branches are thrust out of the midst of foliage still thick, though with none of the luxuriant abundance of old; others have fallen altogether, and lie rotting like corpses on the ground. And — who could have dreamed of this in former days? — there was no shade — no shade to be found anywhere in Tchapligino! 'Ah,' I thought, looking at the dying trees: 'isn't it shameful and bitter for you?'…Koltsov's lines recurred to me:

'What has become
Of the mighty voices,
The haughty strength,
The royal pomp?
Where now is the
Wealth of green?…'

'How is it, Ardalion Mihalitch,' I began, 'that they didn't fell these trees the very next year? You see they won't give for them now a tenth of what they would have done before.'

He merely shrugged his shoulders.

'You should have asked my aunt that; the timber merchants came, offered money down, pressed the matter, in fact.'

'Mein Gott! mein Gott!' Von der Kock cried at every step. 'Vat a bity, vat a bity!'

'What's a bity!' observed my neighbour with a smile.

'That is; how bitiful, I meant to say.'

What particularly aroused his regrets were the oaks lying on the ground — and, indeed, many a miller would have given a good sum for them. But the constable Arhip preserved an unruffled composure, and did not indulge in any lamentations; on the contrary, he seemed even to jump over them and crack his whip on them with a certain satisfaction.

We were getting near the place where they were cutting down the trees, when suddenly a shout and hurried talk was heard, following on the crash of a falling tree, and a few instants after a young peasant, pale and dishevelled, dashed out of the thicket towards us.

'What is it? where are you running?' Ardalion Mihalitch asked him.

He stopped at once.

'Ah, Ardalion Mihalitch, sir, an accident!'

'What is it?'

'Maksim, sir, crushed by a tree.'

'How did it happen?…Maksim the foreman?'

'The foreman, sir. We'd started cutting an ash-tree, and he was standing looking on....He stood there a bit, and then off he went to the well for some water — wanted a drink, seemingly — when suddenly the ash-tree began creaking and coming straight towards him. We shout to him: 'Run, run, run!'…He should have rushed to one side, but he up and ran straight before him....He was scared, to be sure. The ash-tree covered him with its top branches. But why it fell so soon, the Lord only knows! …Perhaps it was rotten at the core.'

'And so it crushed Maksim?'

'Yes, sir.'

'To death?'

'No, sir, he's still alive — but as good as dead; his arms and legs are crushed. I was running for Seliverstitch, for the doctor.'

Ardalion Mihalitch told the constable to gallop to the village for Seliverstitch, while he himself pushed on at a quick trot to the clearing....I followed him.

We found poor Maksim on the ground. The peasants were standing about him. We got off our horses. He hardly moaned at all; from time to time he opened his eyes wide, looked round, as it were, in astonishment, and bit his lips, fast turning blue....The lower part of his face was twitching; his hair was matted on his brow; his breast heaved irregularly: he was dying. The light shade of a young lime-tree glided softly over his face.

We bent down to him. He recognised Ardalion Mihalitch.

'Please sir,' he said to him, hardly articulately, 'send…for the priest…tell…the Lord…has punished me…arms, legs, all smashed…today's…Sunday…and I…I…see…didn't let the lads off…work.'

He ceased, out of breath.

'And my money…for my wife…after deducting....Onesim here knows…whom I…what I owe.'

'We've sent for the doctor, Maksim,' said my neighbour; 'perhaps you may not die yet.'

He tried to open his eyes, and with an effort raised the lids.

'No, I'm dying. Here…here it is coming…here it....Forgive me, lads, if in any way....'

'God will forgive you, Maksim Andreitch,' said the peasants thickly with one voice, and they took off their caps; 'do you forgive us!'

He suddenly shook his head despairingly, his breast heaved with a painful effort, and he fell back again.

'We can't let him lie here and die, though,' cried Ardalion Mihalitch; 'lads, give us the mat from the cart, and carry him to the hospital.'

Two men ran to the cart.

'I bought a horse…yesterday,' faltered the dying man, 'off Efim…Sitchovsky…paid earnest money…so the horse is mine....Give it…to my wife....'

They began to move him on to the mat....He trembled all over, like a wounded bird, and stiffened....

'He is dead,' muttered the peasants.

We mounted our horses in silence and rode away.

The death of poor Maksim set me musing. How wonderfully indeed the Russian peasant dies! The temper in which he meets his end cannot be called indifference or stolidity; he dies as though he were performing a solemn rite, coolly and simply.

A few years ago a peasant belonging to another neighbour of mine in the country got burnt in the drying shed, where the corn is put. (He would have remained there, but a passing pedlar pulled him out half-dead; he plunged into a tub of water, and with a run broke down the door of the burning outhouse.) I went to his hut to see him. It was dark, smoky, stifling, in the hut. I asked, 'Where is the sick man?' 'There, sir, on the stove,' the sorrowing peasant woman answered me in a sing-song voice. I went up; the peasant was lying covered with a sheepskin, breathing heavily. 'Well, how do you feel?' The injured man stirred on the stove; all over burns, within sight of death as he was, tried to rise. 'Lie still, lie still, lie still....Well, how are you?' 'In a bad way, surely,' said he. 'Are you in pain?' No answer. 'Is there anything you want?' — No answer. 'Shouldn't I send you some tea, or anything.' 'There's no need.' I moved away from him and sat down on the bench. I sat there a quarter of an hour; I sat there half an hour — the silence of the tomb in the hut. In the corner behind the table under the holy pictures crouched a little girl of twelve years old, eating a piece of bread. Her mother threatened her every now and then. In the outer room there was coming and going, noise and talk: the brother's wife was chopping cabbage. 'Hey, Aksinya,' said the injured man at last. 'What?' 'Some kvas. 'Aksinya gave him some kvas. Silence again. I asked in a whisper, 'Have they given him the sacrament?' 'Yes.' So, then, everything was in order: he was waiting for death, that was all. I could not bear it, and went away....Again, I recall how I went one day to the hospital in the village of Krasnogorye to see the surgeon Kapiton, a friend of mine, and an enthusiastic sportsman.

This hospital consisted of what had once been the lodge of the manor-house; the lady of the manor had founded it herself; in other words, she ordered a blue board to be nailed up above the door with an inscription in white letters: 'Krasnogorye Hospital,' and had herself handed to Kapiton a red album to record the names of the patients in. On the first page of this album one of the toadying parasites of this Lady Bountiful had inscribed the following lines:

'Dans ces beaux lieux, oùrègne l'allégresse
Ce temple fut ouvert par la Beauté;
De vos seigneurs admirez la tendresse
Bons habitants de Krasnogorié!'

while another gentleman had written below:

'Et moi aussi j'aime la nature!

JEAN KOBYLIATNIKOFF.'

The surgeon bought six beds at his own expense, and had set to work in a thankful spirit to heal God's people. Besides him, the staff consisted of two persons; an engraver, Pavel, liable to attacks of insanity, and a one-armed peasant woman, Melikitrisa, who performed the duties of cook. Both of them mixed the medicines and dried and infused herbs; they, too, controlled the patients when they were delirious. The insane engraver was sullen in appearance and sparing of words; at night he would sing a song about 'lovely Venus,' and would besiege every one he met with a request for permission to marry a girl called Malanya, who had long been dead. The one-armed peasant woman used to beat him and set him to look after the turkeys. Well, one day I was at Kapiton's. We had begun talking over our last day's shooting, when suddenly a cart drove into the yard, drawn by an exceptionally stout horse, such as are only found belonging to millers. In the cart sat a thick-set peasant, in a new greatcoat, with a beard streaked with grey. 'Hullo, Vassily Dmitritch,' Kapiton shouted from the window; 'please come in....The miller of Liobovshin,' he whispered to me. The peasant climbed groaning out of the cart, came into the surgeon's room, and after looking for the holy pictures, crossed himself, bowing to them. 'Well, Vassily Dmitritch, any news?…But you must be ill; you don't look well.' 'Yes, Kapiton Timofeitch, there's something not right.' 'What's wrong with you?' 'Well, it was like this, Kapiton Timofeitch. Not long ago I bought some mill-stones in the town, so I took them home, and as I went to lift them out of the cart, I strained myself, or something; I'd a sort of rick in the loins, as though something had been torn away, and ever since I've been out of sorts. To-day I feel worse than ever.' 'Hm,' commented Kapiton, and he took a pinch of snuff; 'that's a rupture, no doubt. But is it long since this happened?' 'It's ten days now.' 'Ten days?' (The surgeon drew a long inward breath and shook his head.) 'Let me examine you.' 'Well, Vassily Dmitritch,' he pronounced at last, 'I am sorry for you, heartily sorry, but things aren't right with you at all; you're seriously ill; stay here with me; I will do everything I can, for my part, though I can't answer for anything.' 'So bad as that?' muttered the astounded peasant. 'Yes, Vassily Dmitritch, it is bad; if you'd come to me a day or two sooner, it would have been nothing much; I could have cured you in a trice; but now inflammation has set in; before we know where we are, there'll be mortification.' 'But it can't be, Kapiton Timofeitch.' 'I tell you it is so.' 'But how comes it?' (The surgeon shrugged his shoulders.) 'And I must die for a trifle like that?' 'I don't say that…only you must stop here.' The peasant pondered and pondered, his eyes fixed on the floor, then he glanced up at us, scratched his head, and picked up his cap. 'Where are you off to, Vassily Dmitritch?' 'Where? why, home to be sure, if it's so bad. I must put things to rights, if it's like that.' 'But you'll do yourself harm, Vassily Dmitritch; you will, really; I'm surprised how you managed to get here; you must stop.' 'No, brother, Kapiton Timofeitch, if I must die, I'll die at home; why die here? I've got a home, and the Lord knows how it will end.' 'No one can tell yet, Vassily Dmitritch, how it will end....Of course, there is danger, considerable danger; there's no disputing that…but for that reason you ought to stay here.' (The peasant shook his head.) 'No, Kapiton Timofeitch, I won't stay…but perhaps you will prescribe me a medicine.' 'Medicine alone will be no good.' 'I won't stay, I tell you.' 'Well, as you like....Mind you don't blame me for it afterwards.'

The surgeon tore a page out of the album, and, writing out a prescription, gave him some advice as to what he could do besides. The peasant took the sheet of paper, gave Kapiton half-a-rouble, went out of the room, and took his seat in the cart. 'Well, good-bye, Kapiton Timofeitch, don't remember evil against me, and remember my orphans, if anything....' 'Oh, do stay, Vassily!' The peasant simply shook his head, struck the horse with the reins, and drove out of the yard. The road was muddy and full of holes; the miller drove cautiously, without hurry, guiding his horse skilfully, and nodding to the acquaintances he met. Three days later he was dead.

The Russians, in general, meet death in a marvellous way. Many of the dead come back now to my memory. I recall you, my old friend, who left the university with no degree, Avenir Sorokoumov, noblest, best of men! I see once again your sickly, consumptive face, your lank brown tresses, your gentle smile, your ecstatic glance, your long limbs; I can hear your weak, caressing voice. You lived at a Great Russian landowner's, called Gur Krupyanikov, taught his children, Fofa and Zyozya, Russian grammar, geography, and history, patiently bore all the ponderous jokes of the said Gur, the coarse familiarities of the steward, the vulgar pranks of the spiteful urchins; with a bitter smile, but without repining, you complied with the caprices of their bored and exacting mother; but to make up for it all, what bliss, what peace was yours in the evening, after supper, when, free at last of all duties, you sat at the window pensively smoking a pipe, or greedily turned the pages of a greasy and mutilated number of some solid magazine, brought you from the town by the land-surveyor — just such another poor, homeless devil as yourself! How delighted you were then with any sort of poem or novel; how readily the tears started into your eyes; with what pleasure you laughed; what genuine love for others, what generous sympathy for everything good and noble, filled your pure youthful soul! One must tell the truth: you were not distinguished by excessive sharpness of wit; Nature had endowed you with neither memory nor industry; at the university you were regarded as one of the least promising students; at lectures you slumbered, at examinations you preserved a solemn silence; but who was beaming with delight and breathless with excitement at a friend's success, a friend's triumphs?…Avenir!…Who had a blind faith in the lofty destiny of his friends? who extolled them with pride? who championed them with angry vehemence? who was innocent of envy as of vanity? who was ready for the most disinterested self-sacrifice? who eagerly gave way to men who were not worthy to untie his latchet?…That was you, all you, our good Avenir! I remember how broken-heartedly you parted from your comrades, when you were going away to be a tutor in the country; you were haunted by presentiment of evil....And, indeed, your lot was a sad one in the country; you had no one there to listen to with veneration, no one to admire, no one to love....The neighbours — rude sons of the steppes, and polished gentlemen alike — treated you as a tutor: some, with rudeness and neglect, others carelessly. Besides, you were not pre-possessing in person; you were shy, given to blushing, getting hot and stammering....Even your health was no better for the country air: you wasted like a candle, poor fellow! It is true your room looked out into the garden; wild cherries, apple-trees, and limes strewed their delicate blossoms on your table, your ink-stand, your books; on the wall hung a blue silk watch-pocket, a parting present from a kind-hearted, sentimental German governess with flaxen curls and little blue eyes; and sometimes an old friend from Moscow would come out to you and throw you into ecstasies with new poetry, often even with his own. But, oh, the loneliness, the insufferable slavery of a tutor's lot! the impossibility of escape, the endless autumns and winters, the ever-advancing disease!…Poor, poor Avenir!

I paid Sorokoumov a visit not long before his death. He was then hardly able to walk. The landowner, Gur Krupyanikov, had not turned him out of the house, but had given up paying him a salary, and had taken another tutor for Zyozya....Fofa had been sent to a school of cadets. Avenir was sitting near the window in an old easy-chair. It was exquisite weather. The clear autumn sky was a bright blue above the dark-brown line of bare limes; here and there a few last leaves of lurid gold rustled and whispered about them. The earth had been covered with frost, now melting into dewdrops in the sun, whose ruddy rays fell aslant across the pale grass; there was a faint crisp resonance in the air; the voices of the labourers in the garden reached us clearly and distinctly. Avenir wore an old Bokhara dressing-gown; a green neckerchief threw a deathly hue over his terribly sunken face. He was greatly delighted to see me, held out his hand, began talking and coughing at once. I made him be quiet, and sat down by him....On Avenir's knee lay a manuscript book of Koltsov's poems, carefully copied out; he patted it with a smile. 'That's a poet,' he stammered, with an effort repressing his cough; and he fell to declaiming in a voice scarcely audible:

'Can the eagle's wings
Be chained and fettered?
Can the pathways of heaven
Be closed against him?'

I stopped him: the doctor had forbidden him to talk. I knew what would please him. Sorokoumov never, as they say, 'kept up' with the science of the day; but he was always anxious to know what results the leading intellects had reached. Sometimes he would get an old friend into a corner and begin questioning him; he would listen and wonder, take every word on trust, and even repeat it all after him. He took a special interest in German philosophy. I began discoursing to him about Hegel (this all happened long ago, as you may gather). Avenir nodded his head approvingly, raised his eyebrows, smiled, and whispered: 'I see! I see! ah, that's splendid! splendid!'…The childish curiosity of this poor, dying, homeless outcast, moved me, I confess, to tears. It must be noted that Avenir, unlike the general run of consumptives, did not deceive himself in regard to his disease....But what of that? — he did not sigh, nor grieve; he did not even once refer to his position....

Rallying his strength, he began talking of Moscow, of old friends, of Pushkin, of the drama, of Russian literature; he recalled our little suppers, the heated debates of our circle; with regret he uttered the names of two or three friends who were dead....

'Do you remember Dasha?' he went on. 'Ah, there was a heart of pure gold! What a heart! and how she loved me!…What has become of her now? Wasted and fallen away, poor dear, I daresay!'

I had not the courage to disillusion the sick man; and, indeed, why should he know that his Dasha was now broader than she was long, and that she was living under the protection of some merchants, the brothers Kondatchkov, that she used powder and paint, and was for ever swearing and scolding?

'But can't we,' I thought, looking at his wasted face, 'get him away from here? Perhaps there may still be a chance of curing him.' But Avenir cut short my suggestion.

'No, brother, thanks,' he said; 'it makes no difference where one dies. I shan't live till the winter, you see....Why give trouble for nothing? I'm used to this house. It's true the people…'

'They're unkind, eh?' I put in.

'No, not unkind! but wooden-headed creatures. However, I can't complain of them. There are neighbours: there's a Mr. Kasatkin's daughter, a cultivated, kind, charming girl…not proud…'

Sorokoumov began coughing again.

'I shouldn't mind anything,' he went on, after taking breath, 'if they'd only let me smoke my pipe....But I'll have my pipe, if I die for it!' he added, with a sly wink. 'Thank God, I have had life enough! I have known so many fine people.'

'But you should, at least, write to your relations,' I interrupted.

'Why write to them? They can't be any help; when I die they'll hear of it. But, why talk about it…I'd rather you'd tell me what you saw abroad.'

I began to tell him my experiences. He seemed positively to gloat over my story. Towards evening I left, and ten days later I received the following letter from Mr. Krupyanikov:

'I have the honour to inform you, my dear sir, that your friend, the student, living in my house, Mr. Avenir Sorokoumov, died at two o' clock in the afternoon, three days ago, and was buried to-day, at my expense, in the parish church. He asked me to forward you the books and manuscripts enclosed herewith. He was found to have twenty-two roubles and a half, which, with the rest of his belongings, pass into the possession of his relatives. Your friend died fully conscious, and, I may say, with so little sensibility that he showed no signs of regret even when the whole family of us took a last farewell of him. My wife, Kleopatra Aleksandrovna, sends you her regards. The death of your friend has, of course, affected her nerves; as regards myself, I am, thank God, in good health, and have the honour to remain, your humble servant,'

'G. KRUPYANIKOV.'

Many more examples recur to me, but one cannot relate everything. I will confine myself to one.

I was present at an old lady's death-bed; the priest had begun reading the prayers for the dying over her, but, suddenly noticing that the patient seemed to be actually dying, he made haste to give her the cross to kiss. The lady turned away with an air of displeasure. 'You're in too great a hurry, father,' she said, in a voice almost inarticulate; 'in too great a hurry.'…She kissed the cross, put her hand under the pillow and expired. Under the pillow was a silver rouble; she had meant to pay the priest for the service at her own death....

Yes, the Russians die in a wonderful way.

[1]In 1840 there were severe frosts, and no snow fell up to the very end of December; all the wintercorn was frozen, and many splendid oak-forests were destroyed by that merciless winter. It will be hard to replace them; the productive force of the land is apparently diminishing; in the 'interdicted' wastelands (visited by processions with holy images, and so not to be touched), instead of the noble trees of former days, birches and aspens grow of themselves; and, indeed, they have no idea among us of planting woods at all. —Author's Note.

XVII The Singers

The small village of Kolotovka once belonged to a lady known in the neighbourhood by the nickname of Skin-flint, in illusion to her keen business habits (her real name is lost in oblivion), but has of late years been the property of a German from Petersburg. The village lies on the slope of a barren hill, which is cut in half from top to bottom by a tremendous ravine. It is a yawning chasm, with shelving sides hollowed out by the action of rain and snow, and it winds along the very centre of the village street; it separates the two sides of the unlucky hamlet far more than a river would do, for a river could, at least, be crossed by a bridge. A few gaunt willows creep timorously down its sandy sides; at the very bottom, which is dry and yellow as copper, lie huge slabs of argillaceous rock. A cheerless position, there's no denying, yet all the surrounding inhabitants know the road to Kolotovka well; they go there often, and are always glad to go.

At the very summit of the ravine, a few paces from the point where it starts as a narrow fissure in the earth, there stands a small square hut. It stands alone, apart from all the others. It is thatched, and has a chimney; one window keeps watch like a sharp eye over the ravine, and on winter evenings when it is lighted from within, it is seen far away in the dim frosty fog, and its twinkling light is the guiding star of many a peasant on his road. A blue board is nailed up above the door; this hut is a tavern, called the 'Welcome Resort.' Spirits are sold here probably no cheaper than the usual price, but it is far more frequented than any other establishment of the same sort in the neighbourhood. The explanation of this is to be found in the tavern-keeper, Nikolai Ivanitch.

Nikolai Ivanitch — once a slender, curly-headed and rosy-cheeked young fellow, now an excessively stout, grizzled man with a fat face, sly and good-natured little eyes, and a shiny forehead, with wrinkles like lines drawn all over it — has lived for more than twenty years in Kolotovka. Nikolai Ivanitch is a shrewd, acute fellow, like the majority of tavern-keepers. Though he makes no conspicuous effort to please or to talk to people, he has the art of attracting and keeping customers, who find it particularly pleasant to sit at his bar under the placid and genial, though alert eye, of the phlegmatic host. He has a great deal of common sense; he thoroughly understands the landowner's conditions of life, the peasant's, and the tradesman's. He could give sensible advice on difficult points, but, like a cautious man and an egoist, prefers to stand aloof, and at most — and that only in the case of his favourite customers — by remote hints, dropped, as it were, unintentionally, to lead them into the true way. He is an authority on everything that is of interest or importance to a Russian; on horses and cattle, on timber, bricks, and crockery, on woollen stuffs and on leather, on songs and dances. When he has no customers he is usually sitting like a sack on the ground before the door of his hut, his thin legs tucked under him, exchanging a friendly greeting with every passer-by. He has seen a great deal in his time; many a score of petty landowners, who used to come to him for spirits, he has seen pass away before him; he knows everything that is done for eighty miles round, and never gossips, never gives a sign of knowing what is unsuspected by the most keen-sighted police-officer. He keeps his own counsel, laughs, and makes his glasses ring. His neighbours respect him; the civilian general Shtcherpetenko, the landowner highest in rank in the district, gives him a condescending nod whenever he drives past his little house. Nikolai Ivanitch is a man of influence; he made a notorious horse-stealer return a horse he had taken from the stable of one of his friends; he brought the peasants of a neighbouring village to their senses when they refused to accept a new overseer, and so on. It must not be imagined, though, that he does this from love of justice, from devotion to his neighbour — no! he simply tries to prevent anything that might, in any way, interfere with his ease and comfort. Nikolai Ivanitch is married, and has children. His wife, a smart, sharp-nosed and keen-eyed woman of the tradesman class, has grown somewhat stout of late years, like her husband. He relies on her in everything, and she keeps the key of the cash-box. Drunken brawlers are afraid of her; she does not like them; they bring little profit and make a great deal of noise: those who are taciturn and surly in their cups are more to her taste. Nikolai Ivanitch's children are still small; the first four all died, but those that are left take after their parents: it is a pleasure to look at their intelligent, healthy little faces.

It was an insufferably hot day in July when, slowly dragging my feet along, I went up alongside the Kolotovka ravine with my dog towards the Welcome Resort. The sun blazed, as it were, fiercely in the sky, baking the parched earth relentlessly; the air was thick with stifling dust. Glossy crows and ravens with gaping beaks looked plaintively at the passers-by, as though asking for sympathy; only the sparrows did not droop, but, pluming their feathers, twittered more vigorously than ever as they quarrelled among the hedges, or flew up all together from the dusty road, and hovered in grey clouds over the green hempfields. I was tormented by thirst. There was no water near: in Kolotovka, as in many other villages of the steppes, the peasants, having no spring or well, drink a sort of thin mud out of the pond....For no one could call that repulsive beverage water. I wanted to ask for a glass of beer or kvas at Nikolai Ivanitch's.

It must be confessed that at no time of the year does Kolotovka present a very cheering spectacle; but it has a particularly depressing effect when the relentless rays of a dazzling July sun pour down full upon the brown, tumble-down roofs of the houses and the deep ravine, and the parched, dusty common over which the thin, long-legged hens are straying hopelessly, and the remains of the old manor-house, now a hollow, grey framework of aspenwood, with holes instead of windows, overgrown with nettles, wormwood, and rank grass, and the pond black, as though charred and covered with goose feathers, with its edge of half-dried mud, and its broken-down dyke, near which, on the finely trodden, ash-like earth, sheep, breathless and gasping with the heat, huddle dejectedly together, their heads drooping with weary patience, as though waiting for this insufferable heat to pass at last. With weary steps I drew near Nikolai Ivanitch's dwelling, arousing in the village children the usual wonder manifested in a concentrated, meaningless stare, and in the dogs an indignation expressed in such hoarse and furious barking that it seemed as if it were tearing their very entrails, and left them breathless and choking, when suddenly in the tavern doorway there appeared a tall peasant without a cap, in a frieze cloak, girt about below his waist with a blue handkerchief. He looked like a house-serf; thick grey hair stood up in disorder above his withered and wrinkled face. He was calling to some one hurriedly, waving his arms, which obviously were not quite under his control. It could be seen that he had been drinking already.

'Come, come along!' he stammered, raising his shaggy eyebrows with an effort.' Come, Blinkard, come along! Ah, brother, how you creep along, ' pon my word! It's too bad, brother. They're waiting for you within, and here you crawl along....Come.'

'Well, I'm coming, I'm coming!' called a jarring voice, and from behind a hut a little, short, fat, lame man came into sight. He wore a rather tidy cloth coat, pulled half on, and a high pointed cap right over his brows, which gave his round plump face a sly and comic expression. His little yellow eyes moved restlessly about, his thin lips wore a continual forced smile, while his sharp, long nose peered forward saucily in front like a rudder. 'I'm coming, my dear fellow.' He went hobbling towards the tavern. 'What are you calling me for?…Who's waiting for me?'

'What am I calling you for?' repeated the man in the frieze coat reproachfully.' You're a queer fish, Blinkard: we call you to come to the tavern, and you ask what for? Here are honest folks all waiting for you: Yashka the Turk, and the Wild Master, and the booth-keeper from Zhizdry. Yashka's got a bet on with the booth-keeper: the stake's a pot of beer — for the one that does best, sings the best, I mean…do you see?'

'Is Yashka going to sing?' said the man addressed as Blinkard, with lively interest. 'But isn't it your humbug, Gabbler?'

'I'm not humbugging,' answered the Gabbler, with dignity; 'it's you are crazy. I should think he would sing since he's got a bet on it, you precious innocent, you noodle, Blinkard!'

'Well, come in, simpleton!' retorted the Blinkard.

'Then give us a kiss at least, lovey,' stammered the Gabbler, opening wide his arms.

'Get out, you great softy!' responded the Blinkard contemptuously, giving him a poke with his elbow, and both, stooping, entered the low doorway.

The conversation I had overheard roused my curiosity exceedingly. More than once rumours had reached me of Yashka the Turk as the best singer in the vicinity, and here was an opportunity all at once of hearing him in competition with another master of the art. I quickened my steps and went into the house.

Few of my readers have probably had an opportunity of getting a good view of any village taverns, but we sportsmen go everywhere. They are constructed on an exceedingly simple plan. They usually consist of a dark outer-shed, and an inner room with a chimney, divided in two by a partition, behind which none of the customers have a right to go. In this partition there is a wide opening cut above a broad oak table. At this table or bar the spirits are served. Sealed up bottles of various sizes stand on the shelves, right opposite the opening. In the front part of the room, devoted to customers, there are benches, two or three empty barrels, and a corner table. Village taverns are for the most part rather dark, and you hardly ever see on their wainscotted walls any of the glaring cheap prints which few huts are without.

When I went into the Welcome Resort, a fairly large party were already assembled there.

In his usual place behind the bar, almost filling up the entire opening in the partition, stood Nikolai Ivanitch in a striped print shirt; with a lazy smile on his full face, he poured out with his plump white hand two glasses of spirits for the Blinkard and the Gabbler as they came in; behind him, in a corner near the window, could be seen his sharp-eyed wife. In the middle of the room was standing Yashka the Turk, a thin, graceful fellow of three-and-twenty, dressed in a long skirted coat of blue nankin. He looked a smart factory hand, and could not, to judge by his appearance, boast of very good health. His hollow cheeks, his large, restless grey eyes, his straight nose, with its delicate mobile nostrils, his pale brown curls brushed back over the sloping white brow, his full but beautiful, expressive lips, and his whole face betrayed a passionate and sensitive nature. He was in a state of great excitement; he blinked, his breathing was hurried, his hands shook, as though in fever, and he was really in a fever — that sudden fever of excitement which is so well-known to all who have to speak and sing before an audience. Near him stood a man of about forty, with broad shoulders and broad jaws, with a low forehead, narrow Tartar eyes, a short flat nose, a square chin, and shining black hair coarse as bristles. The expression of his face — a swarthy face, with a sort of leaden hue in it — and especially of his pale lips, might almost have been called savage, if it had not been so still and dreamy. He hardly stirred a muscle; he only looked slowly about him like a bull under the yoke. He was dressed in a sort of surtout, not over new, with smooth brass buttons; an old black silk handkerchief was twisted round his immense neck. He was called the Wild Master. Right opposite him, on a bench under the holy pictures, was sitting Yashka's rival, the booth-keeper from Zhizdry; he was a short, stoutly-built man about thirty, pock-marked, and curly-headed, with a blunt, turn-up nose, lively brown eyes, and a scanty beard. He looked keenly about him, and, sitting with his hands under him, he kept carelessly swinging his legs and tapping with his feet, which were encased in stylish top-boots with a coloured edging. He wore a new thin coat of grey cloth, with a plush collar, in sharp contrast with the crimson shirt below, buttoned close across the chest. In the opposite corner, to the right of the door, a peasant sat at the table in a narrow, shabby smock-frock, with a huge rent on the shoulder. The sunlight fell in a narrow, yellowish streak through the dusty panes of the two small windows, but it seemed as if it struggled in vain with the habitual darkness of the room; all the objects in it were dimly, as it were, patchily lighted up. On the other hand, it was almost cool in the room, and the sense of stifling heat dropped off me like a weary load directly I crossed the threshold.

My entrance, I could see, was at first somewhat disconcerting to Nikolai Ivanitch's customers; but observing that he greeted me as a friend, they were reassured, and took no more notice of me. I asked for some beer and sat down in the corner, near the peasant in the ragged smock.

'Well, well,' piped the Gabbler, suddenly draining a glass of spirits at one gulp, and accompanying his exclamation with the strange gesticulations, without which he seemed unable to utter a single word; 'what are we waiting for? If we're going to begin, then begin. Hey, Yasha?'

'Begin, begin,' chimed in Nikolai Ivanitch approvingly.

'Let's begin, by all means,' observed the booth-keeper coolly, with a self-confident smile; 'I'm ready.'

'And I'm ready,' Yakov pronounced in a voice thrilled with excitement.

'Well, begin, lads,' whined the Blinkard. But, in spite of the unanimously expressed desire, neither began; the booth-keeper did not even get up from the bench — they all seemed to be waiting for something.

'Begin!' said the Wild Master sharply and sullenly. Yashka started. The booth-keeper pulled down his girdle and cleared his throat.

'But who's to begin?' he inquired in a slightly changed voice of the Wild Master, who still stood motionless in the middle of the room, his stalwart legs wide apart and his powerful arms thrust up to the elbow into his breeches pockets.

'You, you, booth-keeper,' stammered the Gabbler; 'you, to be sure, brother.'

The Wild Master looked at him from under his brows. The Gabbler gave a faint squeak, in confusion looked away at the ceiling, twitched his shoulder, and said no more.

'Cast lots,' the Wild Master pronounced emphatically; 'and the pot on the table.'

Nikolai Ivanitch bent down, and with a gasp picked up the pot of beer from the floor and set it on the table.

The Wild Master glanced at Yakov, and said: 'Come!'

Yakov fumbled in his pockets, took out a halfpenny, and marked it with his teeth. The booth-keeper pulled from under the skirts of his long coat a new leather purse, deliberately untied the string, and shaking out a quantity of small change into his hand, picked out a new halfpenny. The Gabbler held out his dirty cap, with its broken peak hanging loose; Yakov dropped his halfpenny in, and the booth-keeper his.

'You must pick out one,' said the Wild Master, turning to the Blinkard.

The Blinkard smiled complacently, took the cap in both hands, and began shaking it.

For an instant a profound silence reigned; the halfpennies clinked faintly, jingling against each other. I looked round attentively; every face wore an expression of intense expectation; the Wild Master himself showed signs of uneasiness; my neighbour, even, the peasant in the tattered smock, craned his neck inquisitively. The Blinkard put his hand into the cap and took out the booth-keeper's halfpenny; every one drew a long breath. Yakov flushed, and the booth-keeper passed his hand over his hair.

'There, I said you'd begin,' cried the Gabbler; 'didn't I say so?'

'There, there, don't cluck,' remarked the Wild Master contemptuously. 'Begin,' he went on, with a nod to the booth-keeper.

'What song am I to sing?' asked the booth-keeper, beginning to be nervous.

'What you choose,' answered the Blinkard; 'sing what you think best.'

'What you choose, to be sure,' Nikolai Ivanitch chimed in, slowly smoothing his hand on his breast, 'you're quite at liberty about that. Sing what you like; only sing well; and we'll give a fair decision afterwards.'

'A fair decision, of course,' put in the Gabbler, licking the edge of his empty glass.

'Let me clear my throat a bit, mates,' said the booth-keeper, fingering the collar of his coat.

'Come, come, no nonsense — begin!' protested the Wild Master, and he looked down.

The booth-keeper thought a minute, shook his head, and stepped forward. Yakov's eyes were riveted upon him.

But before I enter upon a description of the contest itself, I think it will not be amiss to say a few words about each of the personages taking part in my story. The lives of some of them were known to me already when I met them in the Welcome Resort; I collected some facts about the others later on.

Let us begin with the Gabbler. This man's real name was Evgraf Ivanovitch; but no one in the whole neighbourhood knew him as anything but the Gabbler, and he himself referred to himself by that nickname; so well did it fit him. Indeed, nothing could have been more appropriate to his insignificant, ever-restless features. He was a dissipated, unmarried house-serf, whose own masters had long ago got rid of him, and who, without any employment, without earning a halfpenny, found means to get drunk every day at other people's expense. He had a great number of acquaintances who treated him to drinks of spirits and tea, though they could not have said why they did so themselves; for, far from being entertaining in company, he bored every one with his meaningless chatter, his insufferable familiarity, his spasmodic gestures and incessant, unnatural laugh. He could neither sing nor dance; he had never said a clever, or even a sensible thing in his life; he chattered away, telling lies about everything — a regular Gabbler! And yet not a single drinking party for thirty miles around took place without his lank figure turning up among the guests; so that they were used to him by now, and put up with his presence as a necessary evil. They all, it is true, treated him with contempt; but the Wild Master was the only one who knew how to keep his foolish sallies in check.

The Blinkard was not in the least like the Gabbler. His nickname, too, suited him, though he was no more given to blinking than other people; it is a well-known fact, that the Russian peasants have a talent for finding good nicknames. In spite of my endeavours to get more detailed information about this man's past, many passages in his life have remained spots of darkness to me, and probably to many other people; episodes, buried, as the bookmen say, in the darkness of oblivion. I could only find out that he was once a coachman in the service of an old childless lady; that he had run away with three horses he was in charge of; had been lost for a whole year, and no doubt, convinced by experience of the drawbacks and hardships of a wandering life, he had gone back, a cripple, and flung himself at his mistress's feet. He succeeded in a few years in smoothing over his offence by his exemplary conduct, and, gradually getting higher in her favour, at last gained her complete confidence, was made a bailiff, and on his mistress's death, turned out — in what way was never known — to have received his freedom. He got admitted into the class of tradesmen; rented patches of market garden from the neighbours; grew rich, and now was living in ease and comfort. He was a man of experience, who knew on which side his bread was buttered; was more actuated by prudence than by either good or ill-nature; had knocked about, understood men, and knew how to turn them to his own advantage. He was cautious, and at the same time enterprising, like a fox; though he was as fond of gossip as an old woman, he never let out his own affairs, while he made everyone else talk freely of theirs. He did not affect to be a simpleton, though, as so many crafty men of his sort do; indeed it would have been difficult for him to take any one in, in that way; I have never seen a sharper, keener pair of eyes than his tiny cunning little 'peepers,' as they call them in Orel. They were never simply looking about; they were always looking one up and down and through and through. The Blinkard would sometimes ponder for weeks together over some apparently simple undertaking, and again he would suddenly decide on a desperately bold line of action, which one would fancy would bring him to ruin....But it would be sure to turn out all right; everything would go smoothly. He was lucky, and believed in his own luck, and believed in omens. He was exceedingly superstitious in general. He was not liked, because he would have nothing much to do with anyone, but he was respected. His whole family consisted of one little son, whom he idolised, and who, brought up by such a father, is likely to get on in the world. 'Little Blinkard'll be his father over again,' is said of him already, in undertones by the old men, as they sit on their mud walls gossiping on summer evenings, and every one knows what that means; there is no need to say more.

As to Yashka the Turk and the booth-keeper, there is no need to say much about them. Yakov, called the Turk because he actually was descended from a Turkish woman, a prisoner from the war, was by nature an artist in every sense of the word, and by calling, a ladler in a paper factory belonging to a merchant. As for the booth-keeper, his career, I must own, I know nothing of; he struck me as being a smart townsman of the tradesman class, ready to turn his hand to anything. But the Wild Master calls for a more detailed account.

The first impression the sight of this man produced on you was a sense of coarse, heavy, irresistible power. He was clumsily built, a 'shambler,' as they say about us, but there was an air of triumphant vigour about him, and — strange to say — his bear-like figure was not without a certain grace of its own, proceeding, perhaps, from his absolutely placid confidence in his own strength. It was hard to decide at first to what class this Hercules belonged: he did not look like a house-serf, nor a tradesman, nor an impoverished clerk out of work, nor a small ruined landowner, such as takes to being a huntsman or a fighting man; he was, in fact, quite individual. No one knew where he came from or what brought him into our district; it was said that he came of free peasant-proprietor stock, and had once been in the government service somewhere, but nothing positive was known about this; and indeed there was no one from whom one could learn — certainly not from him; he was the most silent and morose of men. So much so that no one knew for certain what he lived on; he followed no trade, visited no one, associated with scarcely anyone; yet he had money to spend; little enough, it is true, still he had some. In his behaviour he was not exactly retiring — retiring was not a word that could be applied to him: he lived as though he noticed no one about him, and cared for no one. The Wild Master (that was the nickname they had given him; his real name was Perevlyesov) enjoyed an immense influence in the whole district; he was obeyed with eager promptitude, though he had no kind of right to give orders to anyone, and did not himself evince the slightest pretension to authority over the people with whom he came into casual contact He spoke — they obeyed: strength always has an influence of its own. He scarcely drank at all, had nothing to do with women, and was passionately fond of singing. There was much that was mysterious about this man; it seemed as though vast forces sullenly reposed within him, knowing, as it were, that once roused, once bursting free, they were bound to crush him and everything they came in contact with; and I am greatly mistaken if, in this man's life, there had not been some such outbreak; if it was not owing to the lessons of experience, to a narrow escape from ruin, that he now kept himself so tightly in hand. What especially struck me in him was the combination of a sort of inborn natural ferocity, with an equally inborn generosity — a combination I have never met in any other man.

And so the booth-keeper stepped forward, and, half shutting his eyes, began singing in high falsetto. He had a fairly sweet and pleasant voice, though rather hoarse: he played with his voice like a woodlark, twisting and turning it in incessant roulades and trills up and down the scale, continually returning to the highest notes, which he held and prolonged with special care. Then he would break off, and again suddenly take up the first motive with a sort of go-ahead daring. His modulations were at times rather bold, at times rather comical; they would have given a connoisseur great satisfaction, and have made a German furiously indignant. He was a Russian tenore di grazia, ténor léger. He sang a song to a lively dance-tune, the words of which, all that I could catch through the endless maze of variations, ejaculations and repetitions, were as follows:

'A tiny patch of land, young lass,
I'll plough for thee,
And tiny crimson flowers, young lass,
I'll sow for thee.'

He sang; all listened to him with great attention. He seemed to feel that he had to do with really musical people, and therefore was exerting himself to do his best. And they really are musical in our part of the country; the village of Sergievskoe on the Orel highroad is deservedly noted throughout Russia for its harmonious chorus-singing. The booth-keeper sang for a long while without evoking much enthusiasm in his audience; he lacked the support of a chorus; but at last, after one particularly bold flourish, which set even the Wild Master smiling, the Gabbler could not refrain from a shout of delight. Everyone was roused. The Gabbler and the Blinkard began joining in in an undertone, and exclaiming: 'Bravely done!…Take it, you rogue!…Sing it out, you serpent! Hold it! That shake again, you dog you!…May Herod confound your soul!' and so on. Nikolai Ivanitch behind the bar was nodding his head from side to side approvingly. The Gabbler at last was swinging his legs, tapping with his feet and twitching his shoulder, while Yashka's eyes fairly glowed like coal, and he trembled all over like a leaf, and smiled nervously. The Wild Master alone did not change countenance, and stood motionless as before; but his eyes, fastened on the booth-keeper, looked somewhat softened, though the expression of his lips was still scornful. Emboldened by the signs of general approbation, the booth-keeper went off in a whirl of flourishes, and began to round off such trills, to turn such shakes off his tongue, and to make such furious play with his throat, that when at last, pale, exhausted, and bathed in hot perspiration, he uttered the last dying note, his whole body flung back, a general united shout greeted him in a violent outburst. The Gabbler threw himself on his neck and began strangling him in his long, bony arms; a flush came out on Nikolai Ivanitch's oily face, and he seemed to have grown younger; Yashka shouted like mad: 'Capital, capital!' — even my neighbour, the peasant in the torn smock, could not restrain himself, and with a blow of his fist on the table he cried: 'Aha! well done, damn my soul, well done!' And he spat on one side with an air of decision.

'Well, brother, you've given us a treat!' bawled the Gabbler, not releasing the exhausted booth-keeper from his embraces; 'you've given us a treat, there's no denying! You've won, brother, you've won! I congratulate you — the quart's yours! Yashka's miles behind you…I tell you: miles…take my word for it.' (And again he hugged the booth-keeper to his breast.)

'There, let him alone, let him alone; there's no being rid of you'…said the Blinkard with vexation; 'let him sit down on the bench; he's tired, see…You're a ninny, brother, a perfect ninny! What are you sticking to him like a wet leaf for…'

'Well, then, let him sit down, and I'll drink to his health,' said the Gabbler, and he went up to the bar. 'At your expense, brother,' he added, addressing the booth-keeper.

The latter nodded, sat down on the bench, pulled a piece of cloth out of his cap, and began wiping his face, while the Gabbler, with greedy haste, emptied his glass, and, with a grunt, assumed, after the manner of confirmed drinkers, an expression of careworn melancholy.

'You sing beautifully, brother, beautifully,' Nikolai Ivanitch observed caressingly. 'And now it's your turn, Yasha; mind, now, don't be afraid. We shall see who's who; we shall see. The booth-keeper sings beautifully, though; 'pon my soul, he does.'

'Very beautifully,' observed Nikolai Ivanitch's wife, and she looked with a smile at Yakov.

'Beautifully, ha!' repeated my neighbour in an undertone.

'Ah, a wild man of the woods!' the Gabbler vociferated suddenly, and going up to the peasant with the rent on his shoulder, he pointed at him with his finger, while he pranced about and went off into an insulting guffaw. 'Ha! ha! get along! wild man of the woods! Here's a ragamuffin from Woodland village! What brought you here?' he bawled amidst laughter.

The poor peasant was abashed, and was just about to get up and make off as fast as he could, when suddenly the Wild Master's iron voice was heard:

'What does the insufferable brute mean?' he articulated, grinding his teeth.

'I wasn't doing nothing,' muttered the Gabbler. 'I didn't…I only....'

'There, all right, shut up!' retorted the Wild Master. 'Yakov, begin!'

Yakov took himself by his throat:

'Well, really, brothers,…something....Hm, I don't know, on my word, what....'

'Come, that's enough; don't be timid. For shame!…why go back?…Sing the best you can, by God's gift.'

And the Wild Master looked down expectant. Yakov was silent for a minute; he glanced round, and covered his face with his hand. All had their eyes simply fastened upon him, especially the booth-keeper, on whose face a faint, involuntary uneasiness could be seen through his habitual expression of self-confidence and the triumph of his success. He leant back against the wall, and again put both hands under him, but did not swing his legs as before. When at last Yakov uncovered his face it was pale as a dead man's; his eyes gleamed faintly under their drooping lashes. He gave a deep sigh, and began to sing....The first sound of his voice was faint and unequal, and seemed not to come from his chest, but to be wafted from somewhere afar off, as though it had floated by chance into the room. A strange effect was produced on all of us by this trembling, resonant note; we glanced at one another, and Nikolai Ivanitch's wife seemed to draw herself up. This first note was followed by another, bolder and prolonged, but still obviously quivering, like a harpstring when suddenly struck by a stray finger it throbs in a last, swiftly-dying tremble; the second was followed by a third, and, gradually gaining fire and breadth, the strains swelled into a pathetic melody. 'Not one little path ran into the field,' he sang, and sweet and mournful it was in our ears. I have seldom, I must confess, heard a voice like it; it was slightly hoarse, and not perfectly true; there was even something morbid about it at first; but it had genuine depth of passion, and youth and sweetness and a sort of fascinating, careless, pathetic melancholy. A spirit of truth and fire, a Russian spirit, was sounding and breathing in that voice, and it seemed to go straight to your heart, to go straight to all that was Russian in it. The song swelled and flowed. Yakov was clearly carried away by enthusiasm; he was not timid now; he surrendered himself wholly to the rapture of his art; his voice no longer trembled; it quivered, but with the scarce perceptible inward quiver of passion, which pierces like an arrow to the very soul of the listeners; and he steadily gained strength and firmness and breadth. I remember I once saw at sunset on a flat sandy shore, when the tide was low and the sea's roar came weighty and menacing from the distance, a great white sea-gull; it sat motionless, its silky bosom facing the crimson glow of the setting sun, and only now and then opening wide its great wings to greet the well-known sea, to greet the sinking lurid sun: I recalled it, as I heard Yakov. He sang, utterly forgetful of his rival and all of us; he seemed supported, as a bold swimmer by the waves, by our silent, passionate sympathy. He sang, and in every sound of his voice one seemed to feel something dear and akin to us, something of breadth and space, as though the familiar steppes were unfolding before our eyes and stretching away into endless distance. I felt the tears gathering in my bosom and rising to my eyes; suddenly I was struck by dull, smothered sobs....I looked round — the innkeeper's wife was weeping, her bosom pressed close to the window. Yakov threw a quick glance at her, and he sang more sweetly, more melodiously than ever; Nikolai Ivanitch looked down; the Blinkard turned away; the Gabbler, quite touched, stood, his gaping mouth stupidly open; the humble peasant was sobbing softly in the corner, and shaking his head with a plaintive murmur; and on the iron visage of the Wild Master, from under his overhanging brows there slowly rolled a heavy tear; the booth-keeper raised his clenched fist to his brow, and did not stir…I don't know how the general emotion would have ended, if Yakov had not suddenly come to a full stop on a high, exceptionally shrill note — as though his voice had broken. No one called out, or even stirred; every one seemed to be waiting to see whether he was not going to sing more; but he opened his eyes as though wondering at our silence, looked round at all of us with a face of inquiry, and saw that the victory was his....

'Yasha,' said the Wild Master, laying his hand on his shoulder, and he could say no more.

We all stood, as it were, petrified. The booth-keeper softly rose and went up to Yakov.

'You…yours…you've won,' he articulated at last with an effort, and rushed out of the room. His rapid, decided action, as it were, broke the spell; we all suddenly fell into noisy, delighted talk. The Gabbler bounded up and down, stammered and brandished his arms like mill-sails; the Blinkard limped up to Yakov and began kissing him; Nikolai Ivanitch got up and solemnly announced that he would add a second pot of beer from himself. The Wild Master laughed a sort of kind, simple laugh, which I should never have expected to see on his face; the humble peasant as he wiped his eyes, cheeks, nose, and beard on his sleeves, kept repeating in his corner: 'Ah, beautiful it was, by God! blast me for the son of a dog, but it was fine!' while Nikolai Ivanitch's wife, her face red with weeping, got up quickly and went away, Yakov was enjoying his triumph like a child; his whole face was tranformed, his eyes especially fairly glowed with happiness. They dragged him to the bar; he beckoned the weeping peasant up to it, and sent the innkeeper's little son to look after the booth-keeper, who was not found, however; and the festivities began. 'You'll sing to us again; you're going to sing to us till evening,' the Gabbler declared, flourishing his hands in the air.

I took one more look at Yakov and went out. I did not want to stay — I was afraid of spoiling the impression I had received. But the heat was as insupportable as before. It seemed hanging in a thick, heavy layer right over the earth; over the dark blue sky, tiny bright fires seemed whisking through the finest, almost black dust. Everything was still; and there was something hopeless and oppressive in this profound hush of exhausted nature. I made my way to a hay-loft, and lay down on the fresh-cut, but already almost dry grass. For a long while I could not go to sleep; for a long while Yakov's irresistible voice was ringing in my ears....At last the heat and fatigue regained their sway, however, and I fell into a dead sleep. When I waked up, everything was in darkness; the hay scattered around smelt strong and was slightly damp; through the slender rafters of the half-open roof pale stars were faintly twinkling. I went out. The glow of sunset had long died away, and its last trace showed in a faint light on the horizon; but above the freshness of the night there was still a feeling of heat in the atmosphere, lately baked through by the sun, and the breast still craved for a draught of cool air. There was no wind, nor were there any clouds; the sky all round was clear, and transparently dark, softly glimmering with innumerable, but scarcely visible stars. There were lights twinkling about the village; from the flaring tavern close by rose a confused, discordant din, amid which I fancied I recognised the voice of Yakov. Violent laughter came from there in an outburst at times. I went up to the little window and pressed my face against the pane. I saw a cheerless, though varied and animated scene; all were drunk — all from Yakov upwards. With breast bared, he sat on a bench, and singing in a thick voice a street song to a dance-tune, he lazily fingered and strummed on the strings of a guitar. His moist hair hung in tufts over his fearfully pale face. In the middle of the room, the Gabbler, completely 'screwed' and without his coat, was hopping about in a dance before the peasant in the grey smock; the peasant, on his side, was with difficulty stamping and scraping with his feet, and grinning meaninglessly over his dishevelled beard; he waved one hand from time to time, as much as to say, 'Here goes!' Nothing could be more ludicrous than his face; however much he twitched up his eyebrows, his heavy lids would hardly rise, but seemed lying upon his scarcely visible, dim, and mawkish eyes. He was in that amiable frame of mind of a perfectly intoxicated man, when every passer-by, directly he looks him in the face, is sure to say, 'Bless you, brother, bless you!' The Blinkard, as red as a lobster, and his nostrils dilated wide, was laughing malignantly in a corner; only Nikolai Ivanitch, as befits a good tavern-keeper, preserved his composure unchanged. The room was thronged with many new faces; but the Wild Master I did not see in it.

I turned away with rapid steps and began descending the hill on which Kolotovka lies. At the foot of this hill stretches a wide plain; plunged in the misty waves of the evening haze, it seemed more immense, and was, as it were, merged in the darkening sky. I walked with long strides along the road by the ravine, when all at once from somewhere far away in the plain came a boy's clear voice: 'Antropka! Antropka-a-a!…' He shouted in obstinate and tearful desperation, with long, long drawing out of the last syllable.

He was silent for a few instants, and started shouting again. His voice rang out clear in the still, lightly slumbering air. Thirty times at least he had called the name, Antropka. When suddenly, from the farthest end of the plain, as though from another world, there floated a scarcely audible reply:

'Wha-a-t?'

The boy's voice shouted back at once with gleeful exasperation:

'Come here, devil! woo-od imp!'

'What fo-or?' replied the other, after a long interval.

'Because dad wants to thrash you!' the first voice shouted back hurriedly.

The second voice did not call back again, and the boy fell to shouting Antropka once more. His cries, fainter and less and less frequent, still floated up to my ears, when it had grown completely dark, and I had turned the corner of the wood which skirts my village and lies over three miles from Kolotovka....'Antropka-a-a!' was still audible in the air, filled with the shadows of night.

XVIII Piotr Petrovitch Karataev

One autumn five years ago, I chanced, when on the road from Moscow to Tula, to spend almost a whole day at a posting station for want of horses. I was on the way back from a shooting expedition, and had been so incautious as to send my three horses on in front of me. The man in charge of the station, a surly, elderly man, with hair hanging over his brows to his very nose, with little sleepy eyes, answered all my complaints and requests with disconnected grumbling, slammed the door angrily, as though he were cursing his calling in life, and going out on the steps abused the postilions who were sauntering in a leisurely way through the mud with the weighty wooden yokes on their arms, or sat yawning and scratching themselves on a bench, and paid no special attention to the wrathful exclamations of their superior. I had already sat myself down three times to tea, had several times tried in vain to sleep, and had read all the inscriptions on the walls and windows; I was overpowered by fearful boredom. In chill and helpless despair I was staring at the upturned shafts of my carriage, when suddenly I heard the tinkling of a bell, and a small trap, drawn by three jaded horses, drew up at the steps. The new arrival leaped out of the trap, and shouting 'Horses! and look sharp!' he went into the room. While he was listening with the strange wonder customary in such cases to the overseer's answer that there were no horses, I had time to scan my new companion from top to toe with all the greedy curiosity of a man bored to death. He appeared to be nearly thirty. Small-pox had left indelible traces on his face, which was dry and yellowish, with an unpleasant coppery tinge; his long blue-black hair fell in ringlets on his collar behind, and was twisted into jaunty curls in front; his small swollen eyes were quite expressionless; a few hairs sprouted on his upper lip. He was dressed like a dissipated country gentleman, given to frequenting horse-fairs, in a rather greasy striped Caucasian jacket, a faded lilac silk-tie, a waistcoat with copper buttons, and grey trousers shaped like huge funnels, from under which the toes of unbrushed shoes could just be discerned. He smelt strongly of tobacco and spirits; on his fat, red hands, almost hidden in his sleeves, could be seen silver and Tula rings. Such figures are met in Russia not by dozens, but by hundreds; an acquaintance with them is not, to tell the truth, productive of any particular pleasure; but in spite of the prejudice with which I looked at the new-comer, I could not fail to notice the recklessly good-natured and passionate expression of his face.

'This gentleman's been waiting more than an hour here too,' observed the overseer indicating me.

More than an hour! The rascal was making fun of me.

'But perhaps he doesn't need them as I do,' answered the new comer.

'I know nothing about that,' said the overseer sulkily.

'Then is it really impossible? Are there positively no horses?'

'Impossible. There's not a single horse.'

'Well, tell them to bring me a samovar. I'll wait a little; there's nothing else to be done.'

The new comer sat down on the bench, flung his cap on the table, and passed his hand over his hair.

'Have you had tea already?' he inquired of me.

'Yes.'

'But won't you have a little more for company.'

I consented. The stout red samovar made its appearance for the fourth time on the table. I brought out a bottle of rum. I was not wrong in taking my new acquaintance for a country gentleman of small property. His name was Piotr Petrovitch Karataev.

We got into conversation. In less than half-an-hour after his arrival, he was telling me his whole life with the most simple-hearted openness.

'I'm on my way to Moscow now,' he told me as he sipped his fourth glass; 'there's nothing for me to do now in the country.'

'How so?'

'Well, it's come to that. My property's in disorder; I've ruined my peasants, I must confess; there have been bad years: bad harvests, and all sorts of ill-luck, you know....Though, indeed,' he added, looking away dejectedly; 'how could I manage an estate!'

'Why's that?'

'But, no,' he interrupted me? 'there are people like me who make good managers! You see,' he went on, screwing his head on one side and sucking his pipe assiduously, 'looking at me, I dare say you think I'm not much…but you, see, I must confess, I've had a very middling education; I wasn't well off. I beg your pardon; I'm an open man, and if you come to that....'

He did not complete his sentence, but broke off with a wave of the hand. I began to assure him that he was mistaken, that I was highly delighted to meet him, and so on, and then observed that I should have thought a very thorough education was not indispensable for the good management of property.

'Agreed,' he responded; 'I agree with you. But still, a special sort of disposition's essential! There are some may do anything they like, and it's all right! but I....Allow me to ask, are you from Petersburg or from Moscow?'

'I'm from Petersburg.'

He blew a long coil of smoke from his nostrils.

'And I'm going in to Moscow to be an official.'

'What department do you mean to enter?'

'I don't know; that's as it happens. I'll own to you, I'm afraid of official life; one's under responsibility at once. I've always lived in the country; I'm used to it, you know…but now, there's no help for it…it's through poverty! Oh, poverty, how I hate it!'

'But then you will be living in the capital.'

'In the capital....Well, I don't know what there is that's pleasant in the capital. We shall see; may be, it's pleasant too....Though nothing, I fancy, could be better than the country.'

'Then is it really impossible for you to live at your country place?'

He gave a sigh.

'Quite impossible. It's, so to say, not my own now.'

'Why, how so?'

'Well, a good fellow there — a neighbour — is in possession…a bill of exchange.'

Poor Piotr Petrovitch passed his hand over his face, thought a minute, and shook his head.

'Well?'…I must own, though,' he added after a brief silence, 'I can't blame anybody; it's my own fault. I was fond of cutting a dash, I am fond of cutting a dash, damn my soul!'

'You had a jolly life in the country?' I asked him.

'I had, sir,' he responded emphatically, looking me straight in the face, 'twelve harriers — harriers, I can tell you, such as you don't very often see.' (The last words he uttered in a drawl with great significance.) 'A grey hare they'd double upon in no time. After the red fox — they were devils, regular serpents. And I could boast of my greyhounds too. It's all a thing of the past now, I've no reason to lie. I used to go out shooting too. I had a dog called the Countess, a wonderful setter, with a first-rate scent — she took everything. Sometimes I'd go to a marsh and call "Seek." If she refused, you might go with a dozen dogs, and you'd find nothing. But when she was after anything, it was a sight to see her. And in the house so well-bred. If you gave her bread with your left hand and said, "A Jew's tasted it," she wouldn't touch it; but give it with your right and say, "The young lady's had some," and she'd take it and eat it at once. I had a pup of hers — capital pup he was, and I meant to bring him with me to Moscow, but a friend asked me for him, together with a gun; he said, "In Moscow you'll have other things to think of." I gave him the pup and the gun; and so, you know, it stayed there.'

'But you might go shooting in Moscow.'

'No, what would be the use? I didn't know when to pull myself up, so now I must grin and bear it.

But there, kindly tell me rather about the living in Moscow — is it dear?'

'No, not very.'

'Not very....And tell me, please, are there any gypsies in Moscow?'

'What sort of gypsies?'

'Why, such as hang about fairs?'

'Yes, there are in Moscow....'

'Well, that's good news. I like gypsies, damn my soul! I like ' em....'

And there was a gleam of reckless merriment in Piotr Petrovitch's eyes. But suddenly he turned round on the bench, then seemed to ponder, dropped his eyes, and held out his empty glass to me.

'Give me some of your rum,' he said.'

'But the tea's all finished.'

'Never mind, as it is, without tea…Ah — h!' Karataev laid his head in his hands and leaned his elbows on the table. I looked at him without speaking, and although I was expecting the sentimental exclamations, possibly even the tears of which the inebriate are so lavish, yet when he raised his head, I was, I must own, impressed by the profoundly mournful expression of his face.

'What's wrong with you?'

'Nothing....I was thinking of old times. An anecdote that…I would tell it you, but I am ashamed to trouble you....'

'What nonsense!'

'Yes,' he went on with a sigh:— 'there are cases…like mine, for instance. Well, if you like, I will tell you. Though really I don't know....'

'Do tell me, dear Piotr Petrovitch.'

'Very well, though it's a…Well, do you see,' he began; 'but, upon my word, I don't know.'

'Come, that's enough, dear Piotr Petrovitch.'

'All right. This, then, was what befel me, so to say. I used to live in the country…All of a sudden, I took a fancy to a girl. Ah, what a girl she was!…handsome, clever, and so good and sweet! Her name was Matrona. But she wasn't a lady — that is, you understand, she was a serf, simply a serf-girl. And not my girl; she belonged to someone else — that was the trouble. Well, so I loved her — it's really an incident that one can hardly…well, and she loved me, too. And so Matrona began begging me to buy her off from her mistress; and, indeed, the thought had crossed my mind too....But her mistress was a rich, dreadful old body; she lived about twelve miles from me. Well, so one fine day, as the saying is, I ordered my team of three horses to be harnessed abreast to the droshky — in the centre I'd a first-rate goer, an extraordinary Asiatic horse, for that reason called Lampurdos — I dressed myself in my best, and went off to Matrona's mistress. I arrived; it was a big house with wings and a garden....Matrona was waiting for me at the bend of the road; she tried to say a word to me, but she could only kiss her hand and turn away. Well, so I went into the hall and asked if the mistress were at home?…And a tall footman says to me: "What name shall I say?" I answered, "Say, brother, Squire Karataev has called on a matter of business." The footman walked away; I waited by myself and thought, "I wonder how it'll be? I daresay the old beast'll screw out a fearful price, for all she's so rich. Five hundred roubles she'll ask, I shouldn't be surprised." Well, at last the footman returned, saying, "If you please, walk up." I followed him into the drawing-room. A little yellowish old woman sat in an armchair blinking. "What do you want?" To begin with, you know, I thought it necessary to say how glad I was to make her acquaintance...."You are making a mistake; I am not the mistress here; I'm a relation of hers....What do you want?" I remarked upon that, "I had to speak to the mistress herself." "Marya Ilyinishna is not receiving to-day; she is unwell....What do you want?" There's nothing for it, I thought to myself; so I explained my position to her. The old lady heard me out. "Matrona! what Matrona?"

'"Matrona Fedorovna, Kulik's daughter."

'"Fedor Kulik's daughter…But how did you come to know her?""By chance." "And is she aware of your intention?" "Yes." The old lady was silent for a minute. Then, "Ah, I'll let her know it, the worthless hussy!" she said. I was astounded, I must confess. "What ever for? upon my word!…I'm ready to pay a good sum, if you will be so good as to name it."'

'The old hag positively hissed at me. "A surprising idea you've concocted there; as though we needed your money!…I'll teach her, I'll show her!…I'll beat the folly out of her!" The old lady choked with spitefulness. "Wasn't she well off with us, pray?…Ah, she's a little devil! God forgive my transgressions!" I fired up, I'll confess. "What are you threatening the poor girl for? How is she to blame?" The old lady crossed herself. "Ah, Lord have mercy on me, do you suppose I'd…" "But she's not yours, you know!" "Well, Marya Ilyinishna knows best about that; it's not your business, my good sir; but I'll show that chit of a Matrona whose serf she is." I'll confess, I almost fell on the damned old woman, but I thought of Matrona, and my hands dropped. I was more frightened than I can tell you; I began entreating the old lady. "Take what you like," I said. "But what use is she to you?" "I like her, good ma' am; put yourself in my position....Allow me to kiss your little hand." And I positively kissed the wretch's hand! "Well," mumbled the old witch, "I'll tell Marya Ilyinishna — it's for her to decide; you come back in a couple of days." I went home in great uneasiness. I began to suspect that I'd managed the thing badly; that I'd been wrong in letting her notice my state of mind, but I thought of that too late. Two days after, I went to see the mistress. I was shown into a boudoir. There were heaps of flowers and splendid furniture; the lady herself was sitting in a wonderful easy-chair, with her head lolling back on a cushion; and the same relation was sitting there too, and some young lady, with white eyebrows and a mouth all awry, in a green gown — a companion, most likely. The old lady said through her nose, "Please be seated." I sat down. She began questioning me as to how old I was, and where I'd been in the service, and what I meant to do, and all that very condescendingly and solemnly. I answered minutely. The old lady took a handkerchief off the table, flourished it, fanning herself...."Katerina Karpovna informed me," says she, "of your scheme; she informed me of it; but I make it my rule," says she, "not to allow my people to leave my service. It is improper, and quite unsuitable in a well-ordered house; it is not good order. I have already given my orders," says she. "There will be no need for you to trouble yourself further," says she. "Oh, no trouble, really....But can it be, Matrona Fedorovna is so necessary to you?" "No," says she, "she is not necessary." "Then why won't you part with her to me?" "Because I don't choose to; I don't choose — and that's all about it. I've already," says she, "given my orders: she is being sent to a village in the steppes." I was thunderstruck. The old lady said a couple of words in French to the young lady in green; she went out. "I am," says she, "a woman of strict principles, and my health is delicate; I can't stand being worried. You are still young, and I'm an old woman, and entitled to give you advice. Wouldn't it be better for you to settle down, get married; to look out a good match; wealthy brides are few, but a poor girl, of the highest moral character, could be found." I stared, do you know, at the old lady, and didn't understand what she was driving at; I could hear she was talking about marriage, but the village in the steppes was ringing in my ears all the while. Get married!…what the devil!…'

Here he suddenly stopped in his story and looked at me.

'You're not married, I suppose?'

'No.'

'There, of course, I could see it. I couldn't stand it. "But, upon my word, ma'am, what on earth are you talking about? How does marriage come in? I simply want to know from you whether you will part with your serf-girl Matrona or not?" The old lady began sighing and groaning. "Ah, he's worrying me! ah, send him away! ah!" The relation flew to her, and began scolding me, while the lady kept on moaning: "What have I done to deserve it?…I suppose I'm not mistress in my own house? Ah! ah!" I snatched my hat, and ran out of the house like a madman.

'Perhaps,' he continued, 'you will blame me for being so warmly attached to a girl of low position; I don't mean to justify myself exactly, either…but so it came to pass!…Would you believe it, I had no rest by day or by night....I was in torment! Besides, I thought, "I have ruined the poor girl!" At times I thought that she was herding geese in a smock, and being ill-treated by her mistress's orders, and the bailiff, a peasant in tarred boots, reviling her with foul abuse. I positively fell into a cold sweat. Well, I could not stand it. I found out what village she had been sent to, mounted my horse, and set off. I only got there the evening of the next day. Evidently they hadn't expected such a proceeding on my part, and had given no order in regard to me. I went straight to the bailiff as though I were a neighbour; I go into the yard and look around; there was Matrona sitting on the steps leaning on her elbow. She was on the point of crying out, but I held up my finger and pointed outside, towards the open country. I went into the hut; I chatted away a bit to the bailiff, told him ten thousand lies, seized the right moment, and went out to Matrona. She, poor girl, fairly hung round my neck. She was pale and thin, my poor darling! I kept saying to her, do you know: "There, it's all right, Matrona; it's all right, don't cry," and my own tears simply flowed and flowed....Well, at last though, I was ashamed, I said to her: "Matrona, tears are no help in trouble, but we must act, as they say, resolutely; you must run away with me; that's how we must act." Matrona fairly swooned away...."How can it be! I shall be ruined; they will be the death of me altogether." "You silly! who will find you?" "They will find me; they will be sure to find me. Thank you, Piotr Petrovitch — I shall never forget your kindness; but now you must leave me; such is my fate, it seems." "Ah, Matrona, Matrona, I thought you were a girl of character!" And, indeed, she had a great deal of character....She had a heart, a heart of gold! "Why should you be left here? It makes no difference; things can't be worse. Come, tell me — you've felt the bailiff's fists, eh?" Matrona fairly crimsoned, and her lips trembled. "But there'll be no living for my family on my account." "Why, your family now — will they send them for soldiers?" "Yes; they'll send my brother for a soldier." "And your father?" "Oh, they won't send father; he's the only good tailor among us."

'"There, you see; and it won't kill your brother." Would you believe it, I'd hard work to persuade her; she even brought forward a notion that I might have to answer for it. "But that's not your affair," said I....However, I did carry her off…not that time, but another; one night I came with a light cart, and carried her off.'

'You carried her off?'

'Yes....Well, so she lived in my house. It was a little house, and I'd few servants. My people, I will tell you frankly, respected me; they wouldn't have betrayed me for any reward. I began to be as happy as a prince. Matrona rested and recovered, and I grew devoted to her....And what a girl she was! It seemed to come by nature! She could sing, and dance, and play the guitar!…I didn't show her to my neighbours; I was afraid they'd gossip! But there was one fellow, my bosom friend, Gornostaev, Panteley — you don't know him? He was simply crazy about her; he'd kiss her hand as though she were a lady; he would, really. And I must tell you, Gornostaev was not like me; he was a cultivated man, had read all Pushkin; sometimes, he'd talk to Matrona and me so that we pricked up our ears to listen. He taught her to write; such a queer chap he was! And how I dressed her — better than the governor's wife, really; I had a pelisse made her of crimson velvet, edged with fur…Ah! how that pelisse suited her! It was made by a Moscow madame in a new fashion, with a waist. And what a wonderful creature Matrona was! Sometimes she'd fall to musing, and sit for hours together looking at the ground, without stirring a muscle; and I'd sit too, and look at her, and could never gaze enough, just as if I were seeing her for the first time....Then she would smile, and my heart would give a jump as though someone were tickling me. Or else she'd suddenly fall to laughing, joking, dancing; she would embrace me so warmly, so passionately, that my head went round. From morning to evening I thought of nothing but how I could please her. And would you believe it? I gave her presents simply to see how pleased she would be, the darling! all blushing with delight! How she would try on my present; how she would come back with her new possession on, and kiss me! Her father, Kulik, got wind of it, somehow; the old man came to see us, and how he wept....In that way we lived for five months, and I should have been glad to live with her for ever, but for my cursed ill-luck!'

Piotr Petrovitch stopped.

'What was it happened?' I asked him sympathetically. He waved his hand.

'Everything went to the devil. I was the ruin of her too. My little Matrona was passionately fond of driving in sledges, and she used to drive herself; she used to put on her pelisse and her embroidered Torzhok gloves, and cry out with delight all the way. We used to go out sledging always in the evening, so as not to meet any one, you know. So, once it was such a splendid day, you know, frosty and clear, and no wind…we drove out. Matrona had the reins. I looked where she was driving. Could it be to Kukuyevka, her mistress's village? Yes, it was to Kukuyevka. I said to her, "You mad girl, where are you going?" She gave me a look over her shoulder and laughed. "Let me," she said, "for a lark." "Well," thought I, "come what may!…" To drive past her mistress's house was nice, wasn't it? Tell me yourself — wasn't it nice? So we drove on. The shaft-horse seemed to float through the air, and the trace-horses went, I can tell you, like a regular whirlwind. We were already in sight of Kukuyevka; when suddenly I see an old green coach crawling along with a groom on the footboard up behind…It was the mistress — the mistress driving towards us! My heart failed me; but Matrona — how she lashed the horses with the reins, and flew straight towards the coach! The coachman, he, you understand, sees us flying to meet him, meant, you know, to move on one side, turned too sharp, and upset the coach in a snowdrift. The window was broken; the mistress shrieked, "Ai! ai! ai! ai! ai! ai!" The companion wailed, "Help! help!" while we flew by at the best speed we might. We galloped on, but I thought, "Evil will come of it. I did wrong to let her drive to Kukuyevka." And what do you think? Why, the mistress had recognised Matrona, and me too, the old wretch, and made a complaint against me. "My runaway serf-girl," said she, "is living at Mr. Karataev's"; and thereupon she made a suitable present. Lo and behold! the captain of police comes to me; and he was a man I knew, Stepan Sergyeitch Kuzovkin, a good fellow; that's to say, really a regular bad lot. So he came up and said this and that, and "How could you do so, Piotr Petrovitch?…The liability is serious, and the laws very distinct on the subject." I tell him, "Well, we'll have a talk about that, of course; but come, you'll take a little something after your drive." He agreed to take something, but he said, "Justice has claims, Piotr Petrovitch; think for yourself." "Justice, to be sure," said I, "of course…but, I have heard say you've a little black horse. Would you be willing to exchange it for my Lampurdos?…But there's no girl called Matrona Fedorovna in my keeping." "Come," says he, "Piotr Petrovitch, the girl's with you, we're not living in Switzerland, you know…though my little horse might be exchanged for Lampurdos; I might, to be sure, accept it in that way." However, I managed to get rid of him somehow that time. But the old lady made a greater fuss than ever; ten thousand roubles, she said, she wouldn't grudge over the business. You see, when she saw me, she suddenly took an idea into her head to marry me to her young lady companion in green; that I found out later; that was why she was so spiteful. What ideas won't these great ladies take into their heads!…It comes through being dull, I suppose. Things went badly with me: I didn't spare money, and I kept Matrona in hiding. No, they harassed me, and turned me this way and that: I got into debt; I lost my health....So one night, as I lay in my bed, thinking, "My God, why should I suffer so? What am I to do, since I can't get over loving her?…There, I can't, and that's all about it!" into the room walked Matrona. I had hidden her for the time at a farmhouse a mile and a half from my house. I was frightened. "What? have they discovered you even there?" "No, Piotr Petrovitch," said she, "no one disturbs me at Bubnova; but will that last long? My heart," she said, "is torn, Piotr Petrovitch; I am sorry for you, my dear one; never shall I forget your goodness, Piotr Petrovitch, but now I've come to say good-bye to you." "What do you mean, what do you mean, you mad girl?…Good-bye, how good-bye?"…"Yes…I am going to give myself up." "But I'll lock you up in a garret, mad girl!…Do you mean to destroy me? Do you want to kill me, or what?" The girl was silent; she looked on the floor. "Come, speak, speak!" "I can't bear to cause you any more trouble, Piotr Petrovitch." Well, one might talk to her as one pleased…"But do you know, little fool, do you know, mad…"'

And Piotr Petrovitch sobbed bitterly.

'Well, what do you think?' he went on, striking the table with his fist and trying to frown, while the tears still coursed down his flushed cheeks; 'the girl gave herself up…She went and gave herself up…'

'The horses are ready,' the overseer cried triumphantly, entering the room.

We both stood up.

'What became of Matrona?' I asked.

Karataev waved his hand.

A year after my meeting with Karataev, I happened to go to Moscow. One day, before dinner, for some reason or other I went into a café in the Ohotny row — an original Moscow café. In the billiard-room, across clouds of smoke, I caught glimpses of flushed faces, whiskers, old-fashioned Hungarian coats, and new-fangled Slavonic costumes.

Thin little old men in sober surtouts were reading the Russian papers. The waiters flitted airily about with trays, treading softly on the green carpets. Merchants, with painful concentration, were drinking tea. Suddenly a man came out of the billiard-room, rather dishevelled, and not quite steady on his legs. He put his hands in his pockets, bent his head, and looked aimlessly about.

'Ba, ba, ba! Piotr Petrovitch!…How are you?'

Piotr Petrovitch almost fell on my neck, and, slightly staggering, drew me into a small private room.

'Come here,' he said, carefully seating me in an easy-chair; 'here you will be comfortable. Waiter, beer! No, I mean champagne! There, I'll confess, I didn't expect; I didn't expect…Have you been here long? Are you staying much longer? Well, God has brought us, as they say, together.'

'Yes, do you remember…'

'To be sure, I remember; to be sure, I remember!' he interrupted me hurriedly; 'it's a thing of the past…'

'Well, what are you doing here, my dear Piotr Petrovitch?'

'I'm living, as you can see. Life's first-rate here; they're a merry lot here. Here I've found peace.'

And he sighed, and raised his eyes towards heaven.

'Are you in the service?'

'No, I'm not in the service yet, but I think I shall enter. But what's the service?…People are the chief thing. What people I have got to know here!…'

A boy came in with a bottle of champagne on a black tray.

'There, and this is a good fellow....Isn't that true, Vasya, that you're a good fellow? To your health!'

The boy stood a minute, shook his head, decorously smiled, and went out.

'Yes, there are capital people here,' pursued Piotr Petrovitch; 'people of soul, of feeling....Would you like me to introduce you? — such jolly chaps....They'll all be glad to know you. I say…Bobrov is dead; that's a sad thing.'

'What Bobrov?'

'Sergay Bobrov; he was a capital fellow; he took me under his wing as an ignoramus from the wilds. And Panteley Gornostaev is dead. All dead, all!'

'Have you been living all the time in Moscow? You haven't been away to the country?'

'To the country!…My country place is sold.'

'Sold?'

'By auction....There! what a pity you didn't buy it.'

'What are you going to live on, Piotr Petrovitch?'

'I shan't die of hunger; God will provide when I've no money. I shall have friends. And what is money....Dust and ashes! Gold is dust!'

He shut his eyes, felt in his pocket, and held out to me in the palm of his hand two sixpences and a penny.

'What's that? Isn't it dust and ashes' (and the money flew on the floor). 'But you had better tell me, have you read Polezhaev?'

'Yes.'

'Have you seen Motchalov in Hamlet?'

'No, I haven't.'

'You've not seen him, not seen him!…' (And Karataev's face turned pale; his eyes strayed uneasily; he turned away; a faint spasm passed over his lips.) 'Ah, Motchalov, Motchalov! "To die — to sleep!"' he said in a thick voice:

'No more; and by a sleep to say we end
The heart-ache and the thousand natural shocks
That flesh is heir to; ' tis a consummation
Devoutly to be wished. To die — to sleep!'

'To sleep — to sleep,' he muttered several times.

'Tell me, please,' I began; but he went on with fire:

'Who would bear the whips and scorns of time,
The oppressor's wrong, the proud man's contumely,
The insolence of office and the spurns
That patient merit of the unworthy takes
When he himself might his quietus make
With a bare bodkin? Nymph in thy orisons
Be all my sins remembered.'

And he dropped his head on the table. He began stammering and talking at random. 'Within a month'! he delivered with fresh fire:

'A little month, or ere those shoes were old,
With which she followed my poor father's body,
Like Niobe — all tears; why she, even she —
O God! a beast, that wants discourse of reason,
Would have mourned longer!'

He raised a glass of champagne to his lips, but did not drink off the wine, and went on:

'For Hecuba!
What's Hecuba to him, or he to Hecuba,
That he should weep for her?…
But I'm a dull and muddy mettled-rascal,
Who calls me coward? gives me the lie i' the throat?
…Why I should take it; for it cannot be,
But I am pigeon-livered and lack gall
To make oppression bitter.'

Karataev put down the glass and grabbed at his head. I fancied I understood him.

'Well, well,' he said at last, 'one must not rake up the past. Isn't that so?' (and he laughed). 'To your health!'

'Shall you stay in Moscow?' I asked him.

'I shall die in Moscow!'

'Karataev!' called a voice in the next room; 'Karataev, where are you? Come here, my dear fellow!'

'They're calling me,' he said, getting up heavily from his seat. 'Good-bye; come and see me if you can; I live in....'

But next day, through unforeseen circumstances, I was obliged to leave Moscow, and I never saw Piotr Petrovitch Karataev again.

XIX The Tryst

I was sitting in a birchwood in autumn, about the middle of September. From early morning a fine rain had been falling, with intervals from time to time of warm sunshine; the weather was unsettled. The sky was at one time overcast with soft white clouds, at another it suddenly cleared in parts for an instant, and then behind the parting clouds could be seen a blue, bright and tender as a beautiful eye. I sat looking about and listening. The leaves faintly rustled over my head; from the sound of them alone one could tell what time of year it was. It was not the gay laughing tremor of the spring, nor the subdued whispering, the prolonged gossip of the summer, nor the chill and timid faltering of late autumn, but a scarcely audible, drowsy chatter. A slight breeze was faintly humming in the tree-tops. Wet with the rain, the copse in its inmost recesses was for ever changing as the sun shone or hid behind a cloud; at one moment it was all a radiance, as though suddenly everything were smiling in it; the slender stems of the thinly-growing birch-trees took all at once the soft lustre of white silk, the tiny leaves lying on the earth were on a sudden flecked and flaring with purplish gold, and the graceful stalks of the high, curly bracken, decked already in their autumn colour, the hue of an over-ripe grape, seemed interlacing in endless tangling crisscross before one's eyes; then suddenly again everything around was faintly bluish; the glaring tints died away instantaneously, the birch-trees stood all white and lustreless, white as fresh-fallen snow, before the cold rays of the winter sun have caressed it; and slily, stealthily there began drizzling and whispering through the wood the finest rain. The leaves on the birches were still almost all green, though perceptibly paler; only here and there stood one young leaf, all red or golden, and it was a sight to see how it flamed in the sunshine when the sunbeams suddenly pierced with tangled flecks of light through the thick network of delicate twigs, freshly washed by the sparkling rain. Not one bird could be heard; all were in hiding and silent, except that at times there rang out the metallic, bell-like sound of the jeering tomtit. Before halting in this birch copse I had been through a wood of tall aspen-trees with my dog. I confess I have no great liking for that tree, the aspen, with its pale-lilac trunk and the greyish-green metallic leaves which it flings high as it can, and unfolds in a quivering fan in the air; I do not care for the eternal shaking of its round, slovenly leaves, awkwardly hooked on to long stalks. It is only fine on some summer evenings when, rising singly above low undergrowth, it faces the reddening beams of the setting sun, and shines and quivers, bathed from root to top in one unbroken yellow glow, or when, on a clear windy day, it is all rippling, rustling, and whispering to the blue sky, and every leaf is, as it were, taken by a longing to break away, to fly off and soar into the distance. But, as a rule, I don't care for the tree, and so, not stopping to rest in the aspen wood, I made my way to the birch-copse, nestled down under one tree whose branches started low down near the ground, and were consequently capable of shielding me from the rain, and after admiring the surrounding view a little, I fell into that sweet untroubled sleep only known to sportsmen.

I cannot say how long I was asleep, but when I opened my eyes, all the depths of the wood were filled with sunlight, and in all directions across the joyously rustling leaves there were glimpses and, as it were, flashes of intense blue sky; the clouds had vanished, driven away by the blustering wind; the weather had changed to fair, and there was that feeling of peculiar dry freshness in the air which fills the heart with a sense of boldness, and is almost always a sure sign of a still bright evening after a rainy day. I was just about to get up and try my luck again when suddenly my eyes fell on a motionless human figure. I looked attentively; it was a young peasant girl. She was sitting twenty paces off, her head bent in thought, and her hands lying in her lap; one of them, half-open, held a big nosegay of wild flowers, which softly stirred on her checked petticoat with every breath. Her clean white smock, buttoned up at the throat and wrists, lay in short soft folds about her figure; two rows of big yellow beads fell from her neck to her bosom. She was very pretty. Her thick fair hair of a lovely, almost ashen hue, was parted into two carefully combed semicircles, under the narrow crimson fillet, which was brought down almost on to her forehead, white as ivory; the rest of her face was faintly tanned that golden hue which is only taken by a delicate skin. I could not see her eyes — she did not raise them; but I saw her delicate high eye-brows, her long lashes; they were wet, and on one of her cheeks there shone in the sun the traces of quickly drying tears, reaching right down to her rather pale lips. Her little head was very charming altogether; even her rather thick and snub nose did not spoil her. I was especially taken with the expression of her face; it was so simple and gentle, so sad and so full of childish wonder at its own sadness. She was obviously waiting for some one; something made a faint crackling in the wood; she raised her head at once, and looked round; in the transparent shade I caught a rapid glimpse of her eyes, large, clear, and timorous, like a fawn's. For a few instants she listened, not moving her wide open eyes from the spot whence the faint sound had come; she sighed, turned her head slowly, bent still lower, and began sorting her flowers. Her eyelids turned red, her lips twitched faintly, and a fresh tear rolled from under her thick eyelashes, and stood brightly shining on her cheek. Rather a long while passed thus; the poor girl did not stir, except for a despairing movement of her hands now and then — and she kept listening, listening....Again there was a crackling sound in the wood: she started. The sound did not cease, grew more distinct, and came closer; at last one could hear quick resolute footsteps. She drew herself up and seemed frightened; her intent gaze was all aquiver, all aglow with expectation. Through the thicket quickly appeared the figure of a man. She gazed at it, suddenly flushed, gave a radiant, blissful smile, tried to rise, and sank back again at once, turned white and confused, and only raised her quivering, almost supplicating eyes to the man approaching, when the latter stood still beside her.

I looked at him with curiosity from my ambush. I confess he did not make an agreeable impression on me. He was, to judge by external signs, the pampered valet of some rich young gentleman. His attire betrayed pretensions to style and fashionable carelessness; he wore a shortish coat of a bronze colour, doubtless from his master's wardrobe, buttoned up to the top, a pink cravat with lilac ends, and a black velvet cap with a gold ribbon, pulled forward right on to his eyebrows. The round collar of his white shirt mercilessly propped up his ears and cut his cheeks, and his starched cuffs hid his whole hand to the red crooked fingers, adorned by gold and silver rings, with turquoise forget-me-nots. His red, fresh, impudent-looking face belonged to the order of faces which, as far as I have observed, are almost always repulsive to men, and unfortunately are very often attractive to women. He was obviously trying to give a scornful and bored expression to his coarse features; he was incessantly screwing up his milky grey eyes — small enough at all times; he scowled, dropped the corners of his mouth, affected to yawn, and with careless, though not perfectly natural nonchalance, pushed back his modishly curled red locks, or pinched the yellow hairs sprouting on his thick upper lip — in fact, he gave himself insufferable airs. He began his antics directly he caught sight of the young peasant girl waiting for him; slowly, with a swaggering step, he went up to her, stood a moment shrugging his shoulders, stuffed both hands in his coat pockets, and barely vouchsafing the poor girl a cursory and indifferent glance, he dropped on to the ground.

'Well,' he began, still gazing away, swinging his leg and yawning, 'have you been here long?'

The girl could not at once answer.

'Yes, a long while, Viktor Alexandritch,' she said at last, in a voice hardly audible.

'Ah!' (He took off his cap, majestically passed his hand over his thick, stiffly curled hair, which grew almost down to his eyebrows, and looking round him with dignity, he carelessly covered his precious head again.) 'And I quite forgot all about it. Besides, it rained!' (He yawned again.) 'Lots to do; there's no looking after everything; and he's always scolding. We set off to-morrow....'

'To-morrow?' uttered the young girl. And she fastened her startled eyes upon him.

'Yes, to-morrow....Come, come, come, please!' he added, in a tone of vexation, seeing she was shaking all over and softly bending her head; 'please, Akulina, don't cry. You know, I can't stand that.' (And he wrinkled up his snub nose.) 'Else I'll go away at once....What silliness — snivelling!'

'There, I won't, I won't!' cried Akulina, hurriedly gulping down her tears with an effort. 'You are starting to-morrow?' she added, after a brief silence: 'when will God grant that we see each other again, Viktor Alexandritch?'

'We shall see each other, we shall see each other. If not next year — then later. The master wants to enter the service in Petersburg, I fancy,' he went on, pronouncing his words with careless condescension through his nose; 'and perhaps we shall go abroad too.'

'You will forget me, Viktor Alexandritch,' said Akulina mournfully.

'No, why so? I won't forget you; only you be sensible, don't be a fool; obey your father....And I won't forget you — no-o.' (And he placidly stretched and yawned again.)

'Don't forget me, Viktor Alexandritch,' she went on in a supplicating voice. 'I think none could, love you as I do. I have given you everything....You tell me to obey my father, Viktor Alexandritch....But how can I obey my father?…'

'Why not?' (He uttered these words, as it were, from his stomach, lying on his back with his hands behind his head.)

'But how can I, Viktor Alexandritch? — you know yourself…'

She broke off. Viktor played with his steel watch-chain.

'You're not a fool, Akulina,' he said at last, 'so don't talk nonsense. I desire your good — do you understand me? To be sure, you're not a fool — not altogether a mere rustic, so to say; and your mother, too, wasn't always a peasant. Still you've no education — so you ought to do what you're told.'

'But it's fearful, Viktor Alexandritch.'

'O-oh! that's nonsense, my dear; a queer thing to be afraid of! What have you got there?' he added, moving closer to her; 'flowers?'

'Yes,' Akulina responded dejectedly. 'That's some wild tansy I picked,' she went on, brightening up a little; 'it's good for calves. And this is bud-marigold — against the king's evil. Look, what an exquisite flower! I've never seen such a lovely flower before. These are forget-me-nots, and that's mother-darling....And these I picked for you,' she added, taking from under a yellow tansy a small bunch of blue corn-flowers, tied up with a thin blade of grass.' Do you like them?'

Viktor languidly held out his hand, took the flowers, carelessly sniffed at them, and began twirling them in his fingers, looking upwards. Akulina watched him....In her mournful eyes there was such tender devotion, adoring submission and love. She was afraid of him, and did not dare to cry, and was saying good-bye to him and admiring him for the last time; while he lay, lolling like a sultan, and with magnanimous patience and condescension put up with her adoration. I must own, I glared indignantly at his red face, on which, under the affectation of scornful indifference, one could discern vanity soothed and satisfied. Akulina was so sweet at that instant; her whole soul was confidingly and passionately laid bare before him, full of longing and caressing tenderness, while he…he dropped the corn-flowers on the grass, pulled out of the side pocket of his coat a round eye-glass set in a brass rim, and began sticking it in his eye; but however much he tried to hold it with his frowning eyebrow, his pursed-up cheek and nose, the eye-glass kept tumbling out and falling into his hand.

'What is it?' Akulina asked at last in wonder.

'An eye-glass,' he answered with dignity.

'What for?'

'Why, to see better.'

'Show me.'

Viktor scowled, but gave her the glass.

'Don't break it; look out.'

'No fear, I won't break it.' (She put it to her eye.) 'I see nothing,' she said innocently.

'But you must shut your eye,' he retorted in the tones of a displeased teacher. (She shut the eye before which she held the glass.)

'Not that one, not that one, you fool! the other!' cried Viktor, and he took away his eye-glass, without allowing her to correct her mistake.

Akulina flushed a little, gave a faint laugh, and turned away.

'It's clear it's not for the likes of us,' she said.

'I should think not, indeed!'

The poor girl was silent and gave a deep sigh.

'Ah, Viktor Alexandritch, what it will be like for me to be without you!' she said suddenly.

Victor rubbed the glass on the lappet of his coat and put it back in his pocket.

'Yes, yes,' he said at last, 'at first it will be hard for you, certainly.'(He patted her condescendingly on the shoulder; she softly took his hand from her shoulder and timidly kissed it.) 'There, there, you're a good girl, certainly,' he went on, with a complacent smile; 'but what's to be done? You can see for yourself! me and the master could never stay on here; it will soon be winter now, and winter in the country — you know yourself — is simply disgusting. It's quite another thing in Petersburg! There there are simply such wonders as a silly girl like you could never fancy in your dreams! Such horses and streets, and society, and civilisation — simply marvellous!…' (Akulina listened with devouring attention, her lips slightly parted, like a child.) 'But what's the use,' he added, turning over on the ground, 'of my telling you all this? Of course, you can't understand it!'

'Why so, Viktor Alexandritch! I understand; I understood everything.'

'My eye, what a girl it is!'

Akulina looked down.

'You used not to talk to me like that once, Viktor Alexandritch,' she said, not lifting her eyes.

'Once?…once!…My goodness!' he remarked, as though in indignation.

They both were silent.

'It's time I was going,' said Viktor, and he was already rising on to his elbow.

'Wait a little longer,' Akulina besought him in a supplicating voice.

'What for?…Why, I've said good-bye to you.'

'Wait a little,' repeated Akulina.

Viktor lay down again and began whistling. Akulina never took her eyes off him. I could see that she was gradually being overcome by emotion; her lips twitched, her pale cheeks faintly glowed.

'Viktor Alexandritch,' she began at last in a broken voice, 'it's too bad of you…it is too bad of you, Viktor Alexandritch, indeed it is!'

'What's too bad?' he asked frowning, and he slightly raised his head and turned it towards her.

'It's too bad, Viktor Alexandritch. You might at least say one kind word to me at parting; you might have said one little word to me, a poor luckless forlorn.'…

'But what am I to say to you?'

'I don't know; you know that best, Viktor Alexandritch. Here you are going away, and one little word....What have I done to deserve it?'

'You're such a queer creature! What can I do?'

'One word at least.'

'There, she keeps on at the same thing,' he commented with annoyance, and he got up.

'Don't be angry, Viktor Alexandritch,' she added hurriedly, with difficulty suppressing her tears.

I'm not angry, only you're silly....What do you want? You know I can't marry you, can I? I can't, can I? What is it you want then, eh?' (He thrust his face forward as though expecting an answer, and spread his fingers out.)

'I want nothing…nothing,' she answered falteringly, and she ventured to hold out her trembling hands to him; 'but only a word at parting.'

And her tears fell in a torrent.

'There, that means she's gone off into crying,' said Viktor coolly, pushing down his cap on to his eyes.

'I want nothing,' she went on, sobbing and covering her face with her hands; 'but what is there before me in my family? what is there before me? what will happen to me? what will become of me, poor wretch? They will marry me to a hateful…poor forsaken…Poor me!'

'Sing away, sing away,' muttered Viktor in an undertone, fidgeting with impatience as he stood.

'And he might say one word, one word....He might say, "Akulina…I…"'

Sudden heart-breaking sobs prevented her from finishing; she lay with her face in the grass and bitterly, bitterly she wept....Her whole body shook convulsively, her neck fairly heaved....Her long-suppressed grief broke out in a torrent at last. Viktor stood over her, stood a moment, shrugged his shoulders, turned away and strode off.

A few instants passed…she grew calmer, raised her head, jumped up, looked round and wrung her hands; she tried to run after him, but her legs gave way under her — she fell on her knees....I could not refrain from rushing up to her; but, almost before she had time to look at me, making a superhuman effort she got up with a faint shriek and vanished behind the trees, leaving her flowers scattered on the ground.

I stood a minute, picked up the bunch of cornflowers, and went out of the wood into the open country. The sun had sunk low in the pale clear sky; its rays too seemed to have grown pale and chill; they did not shine; they were diffused in an unbroken, watery light. It was within half-an-hour of sunset, but there was scarcely any of the glow of evening. A gusty wind scurried to meet me across the yellow parched stubble; little curled-up leaves, scudding hurriedly before it, flew by across the road, along the edge of the copse; the side of the copse facing the fields like a wall, was all shaking and lighted up by tiny gleams, distinct, but not glowing; on the reddish plants, the blades of grass, the straws on all sides, were sparkling and stirring innumerable threads of autumn spider-webs. I stopped…I felt sad at heart: under the bright but chill smile of fading nature, the dismal dread of coming winter seemed to steal upon me. High overhead flew a cautious crow, heavily and sharply cleaving the air with his wings; he turned his head, looked sideways at me, flapped his wings and, cawing abruptly, vanished behind the wood; a great flock of pigeons flew up playfully from a threshing floor, and suddenly eddying round in a column, scattered busily about the country. Sure sign of autumn! Some one came driving over the bare hillside, his empty cart rattling loudly....

I turned homewards; but it was long before the figure of poor Akulina faded out of my mind, and her cornflowers, long since withered, are still in my keeping.

XX The Hamlet of the Shtchigri District

On one of my excursions I received an invitation to dine at the house of a rich landowner and sportsman, Alexandr Mihalitch G—. His property was four miles from the small village where I was staying at the time. I put on a frock-coat, an article without which I advise no one to travel, even on a hunting expedition, and betook myself to Alexandr Mihalitch's. The dinner was fixed for six o' clock; I arrived at five, and found already a great number of gentlemen in uniforms, in civilian dress, and other nondescript garments. My host met me cordially, but soon hurried away to the butler's pantry. He was expecting a great dignitary, and was in a state of agitation not quite in keeping with his independent position in society and his wealth. Alexandr Mihalitch had never married, and did not care for women; his house was the centre of a bachelor society. He lived in grand style; he had enlarged and sumptuously redecorated his ancestral mansion, spent fifteen thousand roubles on wine from Moscow every year, and enjoyed the highest public consideration. Alexandr Mihalitch had retired from the service ages ago, and had no ambition to gain official honours of any kind. What could have induced him to go out of his way to procure a guest of high official position, and to be in a state of excitement from early morning on the day of the grand dinner? That remains buried in the obscurity of the unknown, as a friend of mine, an attorney, is in the habit of saying when he is asked whether he takes bribes when kindly-disposed persons offer them.

On parting from my host, I began walking through the rooms. Almost all the guests were utterly unknown to me: about twenty persons were already seated at the card-tables. Among these devotees of preference were two warriors, with aristocratic but rather battered countenances, a few civilian officials, with tight high cravats and drooping dyed moustaches, such as are only to be found in persons of resolute character and strict conservative opinions: these conservative persons picked up their cards with dignity, and, without turning their heads, glared sideways at everyone who approached; and five or six local petty officials, with fair round bellies, fat, moist little hands, and staid, immovable little legs. These worthies spoke in a subdued voice, smiled benignly in all directions, held their cards close up to their very shirt-fronts, and when they trumped did not flap their cards on the table, but, on the contrary, shed them with an undulatory motion on the green cloth, and packed their tricks together with a slight, unassuming, and decorous swish. The rest of the company were sitting on sofas, or hanging in groups about the doors or at the windows; one gentleman, no longer young, though of feminine appearance, stood in a corner, fidgeting, blushing, and twisting the seal of his watch over his stomach in his embarrassment, though no one was paying any attention to him; some others in swallow-tail coats and checked trousers, the handiwork of the tailor and Perpetual Master of the Tailors Corporation, Firs Klyuhin, were talking together with extraordinary ease and liveliness, turning their bald, greasy heads from side to side unconstrainedly as they talked; a young man of twenty, short-sighted and fair-haired, dressed from head to foot in black, obviously shy, smiled sarcastically....

I was beginning, however, to feel bored, when suddenly I was joined by a young man, one Voinitsin by name, a student without a degree, who resided in the house of Alexandr Mihalitch in the capacity of…it would be hard to say precisely, of what. He was a first-rate shot, and could train dogs. I had known him before in Moscow. He was one of those young men who at every examination 'played at dumb-show,' that is to say, did not answer a single word to the professor's questions. Such persons were also designated 'the bearded students.' (You will gather that this was in long past days.) This was how it used to be: they would call Voinitsin, for example. Voinitsin, who had sat upright and motionless in his place, bathed in a hot perspiration from head to foot, slowly and aimlessly looked about him, got up, hurriedly buttoned up his undergraduate's uniform, and edged up to the examiner's table. 'Take a paper, please,' the professor would say to him pleasantly. Voinitsin would stretch out his hand, and with trembling fingers fumble at the pile of papers. 'No selecting, if you please,' observed, in a jarring voice, an assistant-examiner, an irritable old gentleman, a professor in some other faculty, conceiving a sudden hatred for the unlucky bearded one. Voinitsin resigned himself to his fate, took a paper, showed the number on it, and went and sat down by the window, while his predecessor was answering his question. At the window Voinitsin never took his eyes off his paper, except that at times he looked slowly round as before, though he did not move a muscle. But his predecessor would finish at last, and would be dismissed with, 'Good! you can go,' or even 'Good indeed, very good!' according to his abilities. Then they call Voinitsin: Voinitsin gets up, and with resolute step approaches the table. 'Read your question,' they tell him. Voinitsin raises the paper in both hands up to his very nose, slowly reads it, and slowly drops his hands. 'Well, now, your answer, please,' the same professor remarks languidly, throwing himself backwards, and crossing his arms over his breast.

There reigns the silence of the tomb. 'Why are you silent?' Voinitsin is mute. The assistant-examiner begins to be restive. 'Well, say something!' Voinitsin is as still as if he were dead. All his companions gaze inquisitively at the back of his thick, close-cropped, motionless head. The assistant-examiner's eyes are almost starting out of his head; he positively hates Voinitsin. 'Well, this is strange, really,' observes the other examiner. 'Why do you stand as if you were dumb? Come, don't you know it? if so, say so.' 'Let me take another question,' the luckless youth articulates thickly. The professors look at one another. 'Well, take one,' the head-examiner answers, with a wave of the hand. Voinitsin again takes a paper, again goes to the window, again returns to the table, and again is silent as the grave. The assistant-examiner is capable of devouring him alive. At last they send him away and mark him a nought. You would think, 'Now, at least, he will go.' Not a bit of it! He goes back to his place, sits just as immovably to the end of the examination, and, as he goes out, exclaims: 'I've been on the rack! what ill-luck!' and the whole of that day he wanders about Moscow, clutching every now and then at his head, and bitterly cursing his luckless fate. He never, of course, touched a book, and the next day the same story was repeated.

So this was the Voinitsin who joined me. We talked about Moscow, about sport.

'Would you like me,' he whispered to me suddenly, 'to introduce you to the first wit of these parts?'

'If you will be so kind.'

Voinitsin led me up to a little man, with a high tuft of hair on his forehead and moustaches, in a cinnamon-coloured frock-coat and striped cravat. His yellow, mobile features were certainly full of cleverness and sarcasm. His lips were perpetually curved in a flitting ironical smile; little black eyes, screwed up with an impudent expression, looked out from under uneven lashes. Beside him stood a country gentleman, broad, soft, and sweet — a veritable sugar-and-honey mixture — with one eye. He laughed in anticipation at the witticisms of the little man, and seemed positively melting with delight. Voinitsin presented me to the wit, whose name was Piotr Petrovitch Lupihin. We were introduced and exchanged the preliminary civilities.

'Allow me to present to you my best friend,' said Lupihin suddenly in a strident voice, seizing the sugary gentleman by the arm.

'Come, don't resist, Kirila Selifanitch,' he added; 'we're not going to bite you. I commend him to you,' he went on, while the embarrassed Kirila Selifanitch bowed with about as much grace as if he were undergoing a surgical operation; 'he's a most superior gentleman. He enjoyed excellent health up to the age of fifty, then suddenly conceived the idea of doctoring his eyes, in consequence of which he has lost one. Since then he doctors his peasants with similar success....They, to be sure, repay with similar devotion…'

'What a fellow it is!' muttered Kirila Selifanitch. And he laughed.

'Speak out, my friend; eh, speak out!' Lupihin rejoined. 'Why, they may elect you a judge; I shouldn't wonder, and they will, too, you see. Well, to be sure, the secretaries will do the thinking for you, we may assume; but you know you'll have to be able to speak, anyhow, even if only to express the ideas of others. Suppose the governor comes and asks, "Why is it the judge stammers?" And they'd say, let's assume, "It's a paralytic stroke." "Then bleed him," he'd say. And it would be highly indecorous, in your position, you'll admit.'

The sugary gentleman was positively rolling with mirth.

'You see he laughs,' Lupihin pursued with a malignant glance at Kirila Selifanitch's heaving stomach. 'And why shouldn't he laugh?' he added, turning to me: 'he has enough to eat, good health, and no children; his peasants aren't mortgaged — to be sure, he doctors them — and his wife is cracked.' (Kirila Selifanitch turned a little away as though he were not listening, but he still continued to chuckle.) 'I laugh too, while my wife has eloped with a land-surveyor.' (He grinned.) 'Didn't you know that? What! Why, one fine day she ran away with him and left me a letter.

'"Dear Piotr Petrovitch," she said, "forgive me: carried away by passion, I am leaving with the friend of my heart."…And the land-surveyor only took her fancy through not cutting his nails and wearing tight trousers. You're surprised at that? "Why, this," she said, "is a man with no dissimulation about him."…But mercy on us! Rustic fellows like us speak the truth too plainly. But let us move away a bit....It's not for us to stand beside a future judge.'…

He took me by the arm, and we moved away to a window.

'I've the reputation of a wit here,' he said to me, in the course of conversation. 'You need not believe that. I'm simply an embittered man, and I do my railing aloud: that's how it is I'm so free and easy in my speech. And why should I mince matters, if you come to that; I don't care a straw for anyone's opinion, and I've nothing to gain; I'm spiteful — what of that? A spiteful man, at least, needs no wit. And, however enlightening it may be, you won't believe it....I say, now, I say, look at our host! There! what is he running to and fro like that for? Upon my word, he keeps looking at his watch, smiling, perspiring, putting on a solemn face, keeping us all starving for our dinner! Such a prodigy! a real court grandee! Look, look, he's running again — bounding, positively, look!'

And Lupihin laughed shrilly.

'The only pity is, there are no ladies,' he resumed with a deep sigh; 'it's a bachelor party, else that's when your humble servant gets on. Look, look,' he cried suddenly: 'Prince Kozelsky's come — that tall man there, with a beard, in yellow gloves. You can see at once he's been abroad…and he always arrives as late. He's as heavy, I tell you, by himself, as a pair of merchant's horses, and you should see how condescendingly he talks with your humble servant, how graciously he deigns to smile at the civilities of our starving mothers and daughters!…And he sometimes sets up for a wit, but he is only here for a little time; and oh, his witticisms! It's for all the world like hacking at a ship's cable with a blunt knife. He can't bear me....I'm going to bow to him.'

And Lupihin ran off to meet the prince.

'And here comes my special enemy,' he observed, turning all at once to me. 'Do you see that fat man with the brown face and the bristles on his head, over there, that's got his cap clutched in his hand, and is creeping along by the wall and glaring in all directions like a wolf? I sold him for 400 roubles a horse worth 1000, and that stupid animal has a perfect right now to despise me; though all the while he is so destitute of all faculty of imagination, especially in the morning before his tea, or after dinner, that if you say "Good morning!" to him, he'll answer, "Is it?" And here comes the general,' pursued Lupihin, 'the civilian general, a retired, destitute general. He has a daughter of beetroot-sugar, and a manufactory with scrofula....Beg pardon, I've got it wrong…but there, you understand. Ah! and the architect's turned up here! A German, and wears moustaches, and does not understand his business — a natural phenomenon!…though what need for him to understand his business so long as he takes bribes and sticks in pillars everywhere to suit the tastes of our pillars of society!'

Lupihin chuckled again....But suddenly a wave of excitement passed over the whole house. The grandee had arrived. The host positively rushed into the hall. After him ran a few devoted members of the household and eager guests....The noisy talk was transformed into a subdued pleasant chat, like the buzzing of bees in spring within their hives. Only the turbulent wasp, Lupihin, and the splendid drone, Kozelsky, did not subdue their voices....And behold, at last, the queen! — the great dignitary entered. Hearts bounded to meet him, sitting bodies rose; even the gentleman who had bought a horse from Lupihin poked his chin into his chest. The great personage kept up his dignity in an inimitable manner; throwing his head back, as though he were bowing, he uttered a few words of approbation, of which each was prefaced by the syllable er, drawled through his nose; with a sort of devouring indignation he looked at Prince Kozelsky's democratic beard, and gave the destitute general with the factory and the daughter the forefinger of his right hand. After a few minutes, in the course of which the dignitary had had time to observe twice that he was very glad he was not late for dinner, the whole company trooped into the dining-room, the swells first.

There is no need to describe to the reader how they put the great man in the most important place, between the civilian general and the marshal of the province, a man of an independent and dignified expression of face, in perfect keeping with his starched shirt-front, his expanse of waistcoat, and his round snuff-box full of French snuff; how our host bustled about, and ran up and down, fussing and pressing the guests to eat, smiling at the great man's back in passing, and hurriedly snatching a plate of soup or a bit of bread in a corner like a schoolboy; how the butler brought in a fish more than a yard long, with a nosegay in its mouth; how the surly-looking foot-men in livery sullenly plied every gentleman, now with Malaga, now dry Madeira; and how almost all the gentlemen, particularly the more elderly ones, drank off glass after glass with an air of reluctantly resigning themselves to a sense of duty; and finally, how they began popping champagne bottles and proposing toasts: all that is probably only too well known to the reader. But what struck me as especially noteworthy was the anecdote told us by the great man himself amid a general delighted silence. Someone — I fancy it was the destitute general, a man familiar with modern literature — referred to the influence of women in general, and especially on young men. 'Yes, yes,' chimed in the great man, 'that's true; but young men ought to be kept in strict subjection, or else, very likely, they'll go out of their senses over every petticoat.' (A smile of child-like delight flitted over the faces of all the guests; positive gratitude could be seen in one gentleman's eyes.) 'For young men are idiots.' (The great man, I suppose for the sake of greater impressiveness, sometimes changed the accepted accentuation of words.)

'My son, Ivan, for instance,' he went on; 'the fool's only just twenty — and all at once he comes to me and says: "Let me be married, father." I told him he was a fool; told him he must go into the service first....Well, there was despair — tears…but with me…no nonsense.' (The words 'no nonsense' the great man seemed to enunciate more with his stomach than his lips; he paused and glanced majestically at his neighbour, the general, while he raised his eyebrows higher than any one could have expected. The civilian general nodded agreeably a little on one side, and with extraordinary rapidity winked with the eye turned to the great man.) 'And what do you think?' the great man began again: 'now he writes to me himself, and thanks me for looking after him when he was a fool....So that's the way to act.' All the guests, of course, were in complete agreement with the speaker, and seemed quite cheered up by the pleasure and instruction they derived from him....After dinner, the whole party rose and moved into the drawing-room with a great deal of noise — decorous, however; and, as it were, licensed for the occasion....They sat down to cards.

I got through the evening somehow, and charging my coachman to have my carriage ready at five o' clock next morning, I went to my room. But I was destined, in the course of that same day, to make the acquaintance of a remarkable man.

In consequence of the great number of guests staying in the house, no one had a bedroom to himself. In the small, greenish, damp room to which I was conducted by Alexandr Mihalitch's butler, there was already another guest, quite undressed. On seeing me, he quickly ducked under the bed-clothes, covered himself up to the nose, turned a little on the soft feather-bed, and lay quiet, keeping a sharp look-out from under the round frill of his cotton night-cap. I went up to the other bed (there were only two in the room), undressed, and lay down in the damp sheets. My neighbour turned over in bed....I wished him good-night.

Half-an-hour went by. In spite of all my efforts, I could not get to sleep: aimless and vague thoughts kept persistently and monotonously dragging one after another on an endless chain, like the buckets of a hydraulic machine.

'You're not asleep, I fancy?' observed my neighbour.

'No, as you see,' I answered. 'And you're not sleepy either, are you?'

'I'm never sleepy.'

'How's that?'

'Oh! I go to sleep — I don't know what for. I lie in bed, and lie in bed, and so get to sleep.'

'Why do you go to bed before you feel sleepy?'

'Why, what would you have me do?'

I made no answer to my neighbour's question.

'I wonder,' he went on, after a brief silence, 'how it is there are no fleas here? Where should there be fleas if not here, one wonders?'

'You seem to regret them,' I remarked.

'No, I don't regret them; but I like everything to be consecutive.'

'O-ho!' thought I; 'what words he uses.'

My neighbour was silent again.

'Would you like to make a bet with me?' he said again, rather loudly.

'What about?'

I began to be amused by him.

'Hm…what about? Why, about this: I'm certain you take me for a fool.'

'Really,' I muttered, astounded.

'For an ignoramus, for a rustic of the steppes....Confess....'

'I haven't the pleasure of knowing you,' I responded. 'What can make you infer?…'

'Why, the sound of your voice is enough; you answer me so carelessly....But I'm not at all what you suppose....'

'Allow me....'

'No, you allow me. In the first place, I speak French as well as you, and German even better; secondly, I have spent three years abroad — in Berlin alone I lived eight months. I've studied Hegel, honoured sir; I know Goethe by heart: add to that, I was a long while in love with a German professor's daughter, and was married at home to a consumptive lady, who was bald, but a remarkable personality. So I'm a bird of your feather; I'm not a barbarian of the steppes, as you imagine....I too have been bitten by reflection, and there's nothing obvious about me.'

I raised my head and looked with redoubled attention at the queer fellow. By the dim light of the night-lamp I could hardly distinguish his features.

'There, you're looking at me now,' he went on, setting his nightcap straight, 'and probably you're asking yourself, "How is it I didn't notice him to-day?" I'll tell you why you didn't notice me: because I didn't raise my voice; because I get behind other people, hang about doorways, and talk to no one; because, when the butler passes me with a tray, he raises his elbow to the level of my shoulder....And how is it all that comes about? From two causes: first, I'm poor; and secondly, I've grown humble....Tell the truth, you didn't notice me, did you?'

'Certainly, I've not had the pleasure....'

'There, there,' he interrupted me, 'I knew that.'

He raised himself and folded his arms; the long shadow of his cap was bent from the wall to the ceiling.

'And confess, now,' he added, with a sudden sideway glance at me; 'I must strike you as a queer fellow, an original, as they say, or possibly as something worse: perhaps you think I affect to be original!'

'I must repeat again that I don't know you....'

He looked down an instant.

'Why have I begun talking so unexpectedly to you, a man utterly a stranger? — the Lord, the Lord only knows!' (He sighed.) 'Not through the natural affinity of our souls! Both you and I are respectable people, that's to say, egoists: neither of us has the least concern with the other; isn't it so? But we are neither of us sleepy…so why not chat? I'm in the mood, and that's rare with me. I'm shy, do you see? and not shy because I'm a provincial, of no rank and poor, but because I'm a fearfully vain person. But at times, under favourable circumstances, occasions which I could not, however, particularise nor foresee, my shyness vanishes completely, as at this moment, for instance. At this moment you might set me face to face with the Grand Lama, and I'd ask him for a pinch of snuff. But perhaps you want to go to sleep?'

'Quite the contrary,' I hastened to respond; 'it is a pleasure for me to talk to you.'

'That is, I amuse you, you mean to say....All the better....And so, I tell you, they call me here an original; that's what they call me when my name is casually mentioned, among other gossip. No one is much concerned about my fate....They think it wounds me....Oh, good Lord! if they only knew…it's just what's my ruin, that there is absolutely nothing original in me — nothing, except such freaks as, for instance, my conversation at this moment with you; but such freaks are not worth a brass farthing. That's the cheapest and lowest sort of originality.'

He turned facing me, and waved his hands.

'Honoured sir!' he cried, 'I am of the opinion that life on earth's only worth living, as a rule, for original people; it's only they who have a right to live. Man verre n'est pas grand, maisje bois dans mon verre, said someone. Do you see,' he added in an undertone, 'how well I pronounce French? What is it to one if one's a capacious brain, and understands everything, and knows a lot, and keeps pace with the age, if one's nothing of one's own, of oneself! One more storehouse for hackneyed commonplaces in the world; and what good does that do to anyone? No, better be stupid even, but in one's own way! One should have a flavour of one's own, one's individual flavour; that's the thing! And don't suppose that I am very exacting as to that flavour....God forbid! There are no end of original people of the sort I mean: look where you will — there's an original: every live man is an original; but I am not to be reckoned among them!'

'And yet,' he went on, after a brief silence, 'in my youth what expectations I aroused! What a high opinion I cherished of my own individuality before I went abroad, and even, at first, after my return! Well, abroad I kept my ears open, held aloof from everyone, as befits a man like me, who is always seeing through things by himself, and at the end has not understood the A B C!'

'An original, an original!' he hurried on, shaking his head reproachfully....' They call me an original....In reality, it turns out that there's not a man in the world less original than your humble servant. I must have been born even in imitation of someone else....Oh, dear! It seems I am living, too, in imitation of the various authors studied by me; in the sweat of my brow I live: and I've studied, and fallen in love, and married, in fact, as it were, not through my own will — as it were, fulfilling some sort of duty, or sort of fate — who's to make it out?'

He tore the nightcap off his head and flung it on the bed.

'Would you like me to tell you the story of my life?' he asked me in an abrupt voice; 'or, rather, a few incidents of my life?'

'Please do me the favour.'

'Or, no, I'd better tell you how I got married. You see marriage is an important thing, the touchstone that tests the whole man: in it, as in a glass, is reflected....But that sounds too hackneyed....If you'll allow me, I'll take a pinch of snuff.'

He pulled a snuff-box from under his pillow, opened it, and began again, waving the open snuff-box about.

'Put yourself, honoured sir, in my place....Judge for yourself, what, now what, tell me as a favour: what benefit could I derive from the encyclopaedia of Hegel? What is there in common, tell me, between that encyclopaedia and Russian life? and how would you advise me to apply it to our life, and not it, the encyclopaedia only, but German philosophy in general....I will say more — science itself?'

He gave a bound on the bed and muttered to himself, gnashing his teeth angrily.

'Ah, that's it, that's it!…Then why did you go trailing off abroad? Why didn't you stay at home and study the life surrounding you on the spot? You might have found out its needs and its future, and have come to a clear comprehension of your vocation, so to say....But, upon my word,' he went on, changing his tone again as though timidly justifying himself, 'where is one to study what no sage has yet inscribed in any book? I should have been glad indeed to take lessons of her — of Russian life, I mean — but she's dumb, the poor dear. You must take her as she is; but that's beyond my power: you must give me the inference; you must present me with a conclusion. Here you have a conclusion too: listen to our wise men of Moscow — they're a set of nightingales worth listening to, aren't they? Yes, that's the pity of it, that they pipe away like Kursk nightingales, instead of talking as the people talk....Well, I thought, and thought —"Science, to be sure," I thought, "is everywhere the same, and truth is the same"— so I was up and off, in God's name, to foreign parts, to the heathen....What would you have? I was infatuated with youth and conceit; I didn't want, you know, to get fat before my time, though they say it's healthy. Though, indeed, if nature doesn't put the flesh on your bones, you won't see much fat on your body!'

'But I fancy,' he added, after a moment's thought, 'I promised to tell you how I got married — listen. First, I must tell you that my wife is no longer living; secondly…secondly, I see I must give you some account of my youth, or else you won't be able to make anything out of it....But don't you want to go to sleep?'

'No, I'm not sleepy.'

'That's good news. Hark!…how vulgarly Mr. Kantagryuhin is snoring in the next room! I was the son of parents of small property — I say parents, because, according to tradition, I had once had a father as well as a mother, I don't remember him: he was a narrow-minded man, I've been told, with a big nose, freckles, and red hair; he used to take snuff on one side of his nose only; his portrait used to hang in my mother's bedroom, and very hideous he was in a red uniform with a black collar up to his ears. They used to take me to be whipped before him, and my mother used always on such occasions to point to him, saying, "He would give it to you much more if he were here." You can imagine what an encouraging effect that had on me. I had no brother nor sister — that's to say, speaking accurately, I had once had a brother knocking about, with the English disease in his neck, but he soon died....And why ever, one wonders, should the English disease make its way to the Shtchigri district of the province of Kursk? But that's neither here nor there. My mother undertook my education with all the vigorous zeal of a country lady of the steppes: she undertook it from the solemn day of my birth till the time when my sixteenth year had come....You are following my story?'

'Yes, please go on.'

'All right. Well, when I was sixteen, my mother promptly dismissed my teacher of French, a German, Filipóvitch, from the Greek settlement of Nyezhin. She conducted me to Moscow, put down my name for the university, and gave up her soul to the Almighty, leaving me in the hands of my uncle, the attorney Koltun-Babur, one of a sort well-known not only in the Shtchigri district. My uncle, the attorney Koltun-Babur, plundered me to the last half-penny, after the custom of guardians....But again that's neither here nor there. I entered the university — I must do so much justice to my mother — rather well grounded; but my lack of originality was even then apparent. My childhood was in no way distinguished from the childhood of other boys; I grew up just as languidly and dully — much as if I were under a feather-bed — just as early I began repeating poetry by heart and moping under the pretence of a dreamy inclination…for what? — why, for the beautiful…and so on. In the university I went on in the same way; I promptly got into a "circle." Times were different then....But you don't know, perhaps, what sort of thing a student's "circle" is? I remember Schiller said somewhere:

Gefährlich ist's den Leu zu wecken
Und schrecklich ist des Tigers Zahn,
Doch das schrecklichste der Schrecken
Das ist der Mensch in seinem Wahn!

He didn't mean that, I can assure you; he meant to say: Das ist ein circle in der Stadt Moskau!'

'But what do you find so awful in the circle?' I asked.

My neighbour snatched his cap and pulled it down on to his nose.

'What do I find so awful?' he shouted. 'Why, this: the circle is the destruction of all independent development; the circle is a hideous substitute for society, woman, life; the circle…oh, wait a bit, I'll tell you what a circle is! A circle is a slothful, dull living side by side in common, to which is attached a serious significance and a show of rational activity; the circle replaces conversation by debate, trains you in fruitless discussion, draws you away from solitary, useful labour, develops in you the itch for authorship — deprives you, in fact, of all freshness and virgin vigour of soul. The circle — why, it's vulgarity and boredom under the name of brotherhood and friendship! a concatenation of misunderstandings and cavillings under the pretence of openness and sympathy: in the circle — thanks to the right of every friend, at all hours and seasons, to poke his unwashed fingers into the very inmost soul of his comrade — no one has a single spot in his soul pure and undefiled; in the circle they fall down before the shallow, vain, smart talker and the premature wise-acre, and worship the rhymester with no poetic gift, but full of "subtle" ideas; in the circle young lads of seventeen talk glibly and learnedly of women and of love, while in the presence of women they are dumb or talk to them like a book — and what do they talk about? The circle is the hot-bed of glib fluency; in the circle they spy on one another like so many police officials....Oh, circle! thou'rt not a circle, but an enchanted ring, which has been the ruin of many a decent fellow!'

'Come, you're exaggerating, allow me to observe,' I broke in.

My neighbour looked at me in silence.

'Perhaps, God knows, perhaps. But, you see, there's only one pleasure left your humble servant, and that's exaggeration — well, that was the way I spent four years in Moscow. I can't tell you, my dear sir, how quickly, how fearfully quickly, that time passed; it's positively painful and vexatious to remember. Some mornings one gets up, and it's like sliding downhill on little sledges....Before one can look round, one's flown to the bottom; it's evening already, and already the sleepy servant is pulling on one's coat; one dresses, and trails off to a friend, and may be smokes a pipe, drinks weak tea in glasses, and discusses German philosophy, love, the eternal sunshine of the spirit, and other far-fetched topics. But even there I met original, independent people: however some men stultify themselves and warp themselves out of shape, still nature asserts itself; I alone, poor wretch, moulded myself like soft wax, and my pitiful little nature never made the faintest resistance! Meantime I had reached my twenty-first year. I came into possession of my inheritance, or, more correctly speaking, that part of my inheritance which my guardian had thought fit to leave me, gave a freed house-serf Vassily Kudryashev a warranty to superintend all my patrimony, and set off abroad to Berlin. I was abroad, as I have already had the pleasure of telling you, three years. Well. There too, abroad too, I remained the same unoriginal creature. In the first place, I need not say that of Europe, of European life, I really learnt nothing. I listened to German professors and read German books on their birthplace: that was all the difference. I led as solitary a life as any monk; I got on good terms with a retired lieutenant, weighed down, like myself, by a thirst for knowledge but always dull of comprehension, and not gifted with a flow of words; I made friends with slow-witted families from Penza and other agricultural provinces, hung about cafés, read the papers, in the evening went to the theatre. With the natives I associated very little; I talked to them with constraint, and never had one of them to see me at my own place, except two or three intrusive fellows of Jewish extraction, who were constantly running in upon me and borrowing money — thanks to der Russe's gullibility. A strange freak of chance brought me at last to the house of one of my professors. It was like this: I came to him to enter my name for a course of lectures, and he, all of a sudden, invited me to an evening party at his house. This professor had two daughters, of twenty-seven, such stumpy little things — God bless them! — with such majestic noses, frizzed curls and pale-blue eyes, and red hands with white nails. One was called Linchen and the other Minchen. I began to go to the professor's. I ought to tell you that the professor was not exactly stupid, but seemed, as it were, dazed: in his professorial desk he spoke fairly consecutively, but at home he lisped, and always had his spectacles on his forehead — he was a very learned man, though. Well, suddenly it seemed to me that I was in love with Linchen, and for six whole months this impression remained. I talked to her, it's true, very little — it was more that I looked at her; but I used to read various touching passages aloud to her, to press her hand on the sly, and to dream beside her in the evenings, gazing persistently at the moon, or else simply up aloft. Besides, she made such delicious coffee! One asks oneself — what more could one desire? Only one thing troubled me: at the very moments of ineffable bliss, as it's called, I always had a sort of sinking in the pit of the stomach, and a cold shudder ran down my back. At last I could not stand such happiness, and ran away. Two whole years after that I was abroad: I went to Italy, stood before the Transfiguration in Rome, and before the Venus in Florence, and suddenly fell into exaggerated raptures, as though an attack of delirium had come upon me; in the evenings I wrote verses, began a diary; in fact, there too I behaved just like everyone else. And just mark how easy it is to be original! I take no interest, for instance, in painting and sculpture....But simply saying so aloud…no, it was impossible! I must needs take a cicerone, and run to gaze at the frescoes.'…

He looked down again, and again pulled off his nightcap.

'Well, I came back to my own country at last,' he went on in a weary voice. 'I went to Moscow. In Moscow a marvellous transformation took place in me. Abroad I was mostly silent, but now suddenly I began to talk with unexpected smartness, and at the same time I began to conceive all sorts of ideas of myself. There were kindly disposed persons to be found, to whom I seemed all but a genius; ladies listened sympathetically to my diatribes; but I was not able to keep on the summit of my glory. One fine morning a slander sprang up about me (who had originated it, I don't know; it must have been some old maid of the male sex — there are any number of such old maids in Moscow); it sprang up and began to throw off outshoots and tendrils like a strawberry plant. I was abashed, tried to get out of it, to break through its clinging toils — that was no good....I went away. Well, in that too I showed that I was an absurd person; I ought to have calmly waited for the storm to blow over, just as one waits for the end of nettle-rash, and the same kindly-disposed persons would have opened their arms to me again, the same ladies would have smiled approvingly again at my remarks....But what's wrong is just that I'm not an original person. Conscientious scruples, please to observe, had been stirred up in me; I was somehow ashamed of talk, talk without ceasing, nothing but talk — yesterday in Arbat, to-day in Truba, to-morrow in Sivtsevy-Vrazhky, and all about the same thing....But if that is what people want of me? Look at the really successful men in that line: they don't ask its use; on the contrary, it's all they need; some will keep their tongues wagging twenty years together, and always in one direction....That's what comes of self-confidence and conceit! I had that too, conceit — indeed, even now it's not altogether stifled....But what was wrong was that — I say again, I'm not an original person — I stopped midway: nature ought to have given me far more conceit or none at all. But at first I felt the change a very hard one; moreover, my stay abroad too had utterly drained my resources, while I was not disposed to marry a merchant's daughter, young, but flabby as a jelly, so I retired to my country place. I fancy,' added my neighbour, with another glance sideways at me, 'I may pass over in silence the first impressions of country life, references to the beauty of nature, the gentle charm of solitude, etc.'

'You can, indeed,' I put in.

'All the more,' he continued, 'as all that's nonsense; at least, as far as I'm concerned. I was as bored in the country as a puppy locked up, though I will own that on my journey home, when I passed through the familiar birchwood in spring for the first time, my head was in a whirl and my heart beat with a vague, sweet expectation. But these vague expectations, as you're well aware, never come to pass; on the other hand, very different things do come to pass, which you don't at all expect, such as cattle disease, arrears, sales by auction, and so on, and so on. I managed to make a shift from day to day with the aid of my agent, Yakov, who replaced the former superintendent, and turned out in the course of time to be as great, if not a greater robber, and over and above that poisoned my existence by the smell of his tarred boots; suddenly one day I remembered a family I knew in the neighbourhood, consisting of the widow of a retired colonel and her two daughters, ordered out my droshky, and set off to see them. That day must always be a memorable one for me; six months later I was married to the retired colonel's second daughter!…'

The speaker dropped his head, and lifted his hands to heaven.

'And now,' he went on warmly, 'I couldn't bear to give you an unfavourable opinion of my late wife. Heaven forbid! She was the most generous, sweetest creature, a loving nature capable of any sacrifice, though I must between ourselves confess that if I had not had the misfortune to lose her, I should probably not be in a position to be talking to you to-day; since the beam is still there in my barn, to which I repeatedly made up my mind to hang myself!'

'Some pears,' he began again, after a brief pause, 'need to lie in an underground cellar for a time, to come, as they say, to their real flavour; my wife, it seems, belonged to a similar order of nature's works. It's only now that I do her complete justice. It's only now, for instance, that memories of some evenings I spent with her before marriage no longer awaken the slightest bitterness, but move me almost to tears. They were not rich people; their house was very old-fashioned and built of wood, but comfortable; it stood on a hill between an overgrown courtyard and a garden run wild. At the bottom of the hill ran a river, which could just be seen through the thick leaves. A wide terrace led from the house to the garden; before the terrace flaunted a long flower-bed, covered with roses; at each end of the flower-bed grew two acacias, which had been trained to grow into the shape of a screw by its late owner. A little farther, in the very midst of a thicket of neglected and overgrown raspberries, stood an arbour, smartly painted within, but so old and tumble-down outside that it was depressing to look at it. A glass door led from the terrace into the drawing-room; in the drawing-room this was what met the eye of the inquisitive spectator: in the various corners stoves of Dutch tiles, a squeaky piano to the right, piled with manuscript music, a sofa, covered with faded blue material with a whitish pattern, a round table, two what-nots of china and glass, knicknacks of the Catherine period; on the wall the well-known picture of a flaxen-haired girl with a dove on her breast and eyes turned upwards; on the table a vase of fresh roses. You see how minutely I describe it. In that drawing-room, on that terrace, was rehearsed all the tragi-comedy of my love. The colonel's wife herself was an ill-natured old dame, whose voice was always hoarse with spite — a petty, snappish creature. Of the daughters, one, Vera, did not differ in any respect from the common run of young ladies of the provinces; the other, Sofya, I fell in love with. The two sisters had another little room too, their common bedroom, with two innocent little wooden bedsteads, yellowish albums, mignonette, portraits of friends sketched in pencil rather badly (among them was one gentleman with an exceptionally vigorous expression of face and a still more vigorous signature, who had in his youth raised disproportionate expectations, but had come, like all of us, to nothing), with busts of Goethe and Schiller, German books, dried wreaths, and other objects, kept as souvenirs. But that room I rarely and reluctantly entered; I felt stifled there somehow. And, too, strange to say, I liked Sofya best of all when I was sitting with my back to her, or still more, perhaps, when I was thinking or dreaming about her in the evening on the terrace. At such times I used to gaze at the sunset, at the trees, at the tiny leaves, already in darkness, but standing out sharply against the rosy sky; in the drawing-room Sofya sat at the piano continually playing over and over again some favourite, passionately pathetic phrase from Beethoven; the ill-natured old lady snored peacefully, sitting on the sofa; in the dining-room, which was flooded by a glow of lurid light, Vera was bustling about getting tea; the samovar hissed merrily as though it were pleased at something; the cracknels snapped with a pleasant crispness, and the spoons tinkled against the cups; the canary, which trilled mercilessly all day, was suddenly still, and only chirruped from time to time, as though asking for something; from a light transparent cloud there fell a few passing drops of rain....And I would sit and sit, listen, listen, and look, my heart would expand, and again it seemed to me that I was in love. Well, under the influence of such an evening, I one day asked the old lady for her daughter's hand, and two months later I was married. It seemed to me that I loved her....By now, indeed, it's time I should know, but, by God, even now I don't know whether I loved Sofya. She was a sweet creature, clever, silent, and warm-hearted, but God only knows from what cause, whether from living too long in the country, or for some other reason, there was at the bottom of her heart (if only there is a bottom to the heart) a secret wound, or, to put it better, a little open sore which nothing could heal, to which neither she nor I could give a name. Of the existence of this sore, of course, I only guessed after marriage. The struggles I had over it…nothing availed! When I was a child I had a little bird, which had once been caught by the cat in its claws; it was saved and tended, but the poor bird never got right; it moped, it pined, it ceased to sing....It ended by a cat getting into its open cage one night and biting off its beak, after which it made up its mind at last to die. I don't know what cat had caught my wife in its claws, but she too moped and pined just like my unlucky bird. Sometimes she obviously made an effort to shake herself, to rejoice in the open air, in the sunshine and freedom; she would try, and shrink up into herself again. And, you know she loved me; how many times has she assured me that she had nothing left to wish for? — oof! damn my soul! and the light was fading out of her eyes all the while. I wondered whether there hadn't been something in her past. I made investigations: there was nothing forthcoming. Well, you may form your own judgment; an original man would have shrugged his shoulders and heaved a sigh or two, perhaps, and would have proceeded to live his own life; but I, not being an original creature, began to contemplate a beam and halter. My wife was so thoroughly permeated by all the habits of an old maid — Beethoven, evening walks, mignonette, corresponding with her friends, albums, et cetera — that she never could accustom herself to any other mode of life, especially to the life of the mistress of a house; and yet it seemed absurd for a married woman to be pining in vague melancholy and singing in the evening: "Waken her not at the dawn!"

'Well, we were blissful after that fashion for three years; in the fourth, Sofya died in her first confinement, and, strange to say, I had felt, as it were, beforehand that she would not be capable of giving me a daughter or a son — of giving the earth a new inhabitant. I remember how they buried her. It was in the spring. Our parish church was small and old, the screen was blackened, the walls bare, the brick floor worn into hollows in parts; there was a big, old-fashioned holy picture in each half of the choir. They brought in the coffin, placed it in the middle before the holy gates, covered it with a faded pall, set three candlesticks about it. The service commenced. A decrepit deacon, with a little shock of hair behind, belted low down with a green kerchief, was mournfully mumbling before a reading-desk; a priest, also an old man, with a kindly, purblind face, in a lilac cassock with yellow flowers on it, served the mass for himself and the deacon. At all the open windows the fresh young leaves were stirring and whispering, and the smell of the grass rose from the churchyard outside; the red flame of the waxcandles paled in the bright light of the spring day; the sparrows were twittering all over the church, and every now and then there came the ringing cry of a swallow flying in under the cupola. In the golden motes of the sunbeams the brown heads of the few peasants kept rising and dropping down again as they prayed earnestly for the dead; in a thin bluish stream the smoke issued from the holes of the censer. I looked at the dead face of my wife....My God! even death — death itself — had not set her free, had not healed her wound: the same sickly, timid, dumb look, as though, even in her coffin, she were ill at ease....My heart was filled with bitterness. A sweet, sweet creature she was, and she did well for herself to die!'

The speaker's cheeks flushed, and his eyes grew dim.

'When at last,' he began again, 'I emerged from the deep depression which overwhelmed me after my wife's death, I resolved to devote myself, as it is called, to work. I went into a government office in the capital of the province; but in the great apartments of the government institution my head ached, and my eyesight too began to fail: other incidental causes came in....I retired. I had thought of going on a visit to Moscow, but, in the first place, I hadn't the money, and secondly…I've told you already: I'm resigned. This resignation came upon me both suddenly and not suddenly. In spirit I had long ago resigned myself, but my brain was still unwilling to accept the yoke. I ascribed my humble temper and ideas to the influence of country life and happiness!…On the other side, I had long observed that all my neighbours, young and old alike, who had been frightened at first by my learning, my residence abroad, and my other advantages of education, had not only had time to get completely used to me, but had even begun to treat me half-rudely, half-contemptuously, did not listen to my observations, and, in talking to me, no longer made use of superfluous signs of respect. I forgot to tell you, too, that during the first year after my marriage, I had tried to launch into literature, and even sent a thing to a journal — a story, if I'm not mistaken; but in a little time I received a polite letter from the editor, in which, among other things, I was told that he could not deny I had intelligence, but he was obliged to say I had no talent, and talent alone was what was needed in literature. To add to this, it came to my knowledge that a young man, on a visit from Moscow — a most good-natured youth too — had referred to me at an evening party at the governor's as a shallow person, antiquated and behind the times. But my half-wilful blindness still persisted: I was unwilling to give myself a slap in the face, you know; at last, one fine morning, my eyes were opened. This was how it happened. The district captain of police came to see me, with the object of calling my attention to a tumble-down bridge on my property, which I had absolutely no money to repair. After consuming a glass of vodka and a snack of dried fish, this condescending guardian of order reproached me in a paternal way for my heedlessness, sympathising, however, with my position, and only advising me to order my peasants to patch up the bridge with some rubbish; he lighted a pipe, and began talking of the coming elections. A candidate for the honourable post of marshal of the province was at that time one Orbassanov, a noisy, shallow fellow, who took bribes into the bargain. Besides, he was not distinguished either for wealth or for family. I expressed my opinion with regard to him, and rather casually too: I regarded Mr. Orbassanov, I must own, as beneath my level. The police-captain looked at me, patted me amicably on the shoulder, and said good-naturedly: "Come, come, Vassily Vassilyevitch, it's not for you and me to criticise men like that — how are we qualified to? Let the shoemaker stick to his last.""But, upon my word," I retorted with annoyance, "whatever difference is there between me and Mr. Orbassanov?" The police-captain took his pipe out of his mouth, opened his eyes wide, and fairly roared. "Well, you're an amusing chap," he observed at last, while the tears ran down his cheeks: "what a joke to make!…Ah! you are a funny fellow!" And till his departure he never ceased jeering at me, now and then giving me a poke in the ribs with his elbow, and addressing me by my Christian name. He went away at last. This was enough: it was the last drop, and my cup was overflowing. I paced several times up and down the room, stood still before the looking-glass and gazed a long, long while at my embarrassed countenance, and deliberately putting out my tongue, I shook my head with a bitter smile. The scales fell from my eyes: I saw clearly, more clearly than I saw my face in the glass, what a shallow, insignificant, worthless, unoriginal person I was!'

He paused.

'In one of Voltaire's tragedies,' he went on wearily, 'there is some worthy who rejoices that he has reached the furthest limit of unhappiness. Though there is nothing tragic in my fate, I will admit I have experienced something of that sort. I have known the bitter transports of cold despair; I have felt how sweet it is, lying in bed, to curse deliberately for a whole morning together the hour and day of my birth. I could not resign myself all at once. And indeed, think of it yourself: I was kept by impecuniosity in the country, which I hated; I was not fitted for managing my land, nor for the public service, nor for literature, nor anything; my neighbours I didn't care for, and books I loathed; as for the mawkish and morbidly sentimental young ladies who shake their curls and feverishly harp on the word "life," I had ceased to have any attraction for them ever since I gave up ranting and gushing; complete solitude I could not face....I began — what do you suppose? — I began hanging about, visiting my neighbours. As though drunk with self-contempt, I purposely exposed myself to all sorts of petty slights. I was missed over in serving at table; I was met with supercilious coldness, and at last was not noticed at all; I was not even allowed to take part in general conversation, and from my corner I myself used purposely to back up some stupid talker who in those days at Moscow would have ecstatically licked the dust off my feet, and kissed the hem of my cloak....I did not even allow myself to believe that I was enjoying the bitter satisfaction of irony....What sort of irony, indeed, can a man enjoy in solitude? Well, so I have behaved for some years on end, and so I behave now.'

'Really, this is beyond everything,' grumbled the sleepy voice of Mr. Kantagryuhin from the next room: 'what fool is it that has taken a fancy to talk all night?'

The speaker promptly ducked under the clothes and peeping out timidly, held up his finger to me warningly.

'Sh — sh —!' he whispered; and, as it were, bowing apologetically in the direction of Kantagryuhin's voice, he said respectfully: 'I obey, sir, I obey; I beg your pardon....It's permissible for him to sleep; he ought to sleep,' he went on again in a whisper: 'he must recruit his energies — well, if only to eat his dinner with the same relish to-morrow. We have no right to disturb him. Besides, I think I've told you all I wanted to; probably you're sleepy too. I wish you good-night.'

He turned away with feverish rapidity and buried his head in the pillow.

'Let me at least know,' I asked, 'with whom I have had the pleasure....'

He raised his head quickly.

'No, for mercy's sake!' he cut me short, 'don't inquire my name either of me or of others. Let me remain to you an unknown being, crushed by fate, Vassily Vassilyevitch. Besides, as an unoriginal person, I don't deserve an individual name....But if you really want to give me some title, call me…call me the Hamlet of the Shtchigri district. There are many such Hamlets in every district, but perhaps you haven't come across others....After which, good-bye.'

He buried himself again in his feather-bed, and the next morning, when they came to wake me, he was no longer in the room. He had left before daylight.

XXI Tchertop-Hanov and Nedopyuskin

One hot summer day I was coming home from hunting in a light cart; Yermolaï sat beside me dozing and scratching his nose. The sleeping dogs were jolted up and down like lifeless bodies under our feet. The coachman kept flicking gadflies off the horses with his whip. The white dust rose in a light cloud behind the cart. We drove in between bushes. The road here was full of ruts, and the wheels began catching in the twigs. Yermolaï started up and looked round.... 'Hullo!' he said; 'there ought to be grouse here. Let's get out.' We stopped and went into the thicket. My dog hit upon a covey. I took a shot and was beginning to reload, when suddenly there was a loud crackling behind me, and a man on horseback came towards me, pushing the bushes apart with his hands. 'Sir…pe-ermit me to ask,' he began in a haughty voice, 'by what right you are — er — shooting here, sir?' The stranger spoke extraordinarily quickly, jerkily and condescendingly. I looked at his face; never in my life have I seen anything like it. Picture to yourselves, gentle readers, a little flaxen-haired man, with a little turnup red nose and long red moustaches. A pointed Persian cap with a crimson cloth crown covered his forehead right down to his eyebrows. He was dressed in a shabby yellow Caucasian overcoat, with black velveteen cartridge pockets on the breast, and tarnish silver braid on all the seams; over his shoulder was slung a horn; in his sash was sticking a dagger. A raw-boned, hook-nosed chestnut horse shambled unsteadily under his weight; two lean, crook-pawed greyhounds kept turning round just under the horse's legs. The face, the glance, the voice, every action, the whole being of the stranger, was expressive of a wild daring and an unbounded, incredible pride; his pale-blue glassy eyes strayed about with a sideway squint like a drunkard's; he flung back his head, puffed out his cheeks, snorted and quivered all over, as though bursting with dignity — for all the world like a turkey-cock. He repeated his question.

'I didn't know it was forbidden to shoot here,' I replied.

'You are here, sir,' he continued, 'on my land.'

'With your permission, I will go off it.'

'But pe-ermit me to ask,' he rejoined, 'is it a nobleman I have the honour of addressing?'

I mentioned my name.

'In that case, oblige me by hunting here. I am a nobleman myself, and am very pleased to do any service to a nobleman....And my name is Panteley Tchertop-hanov.' He bowed, hallooed, gave his horse a lash on the neck; the horse shook its head, reared, shied, and trampled on a dog's paws. The dog gave a piercing squeal. Tchertop-hanov boiled over with rage; foaming at the mouth, he struck the horse with his fist on the head between the ears, leaped to the ground quicker than lightning, looked at the dog's paw, spat on the wound, gave it a kick in the ribs to stop its whining, caught on to the horse's forelock, and put his foot in the stirrup. The horse flung up its head, and with its tail in the air edged away into the bushes; he followed it, hopping on one leg; he got into the saddle at last, however, flourished his whip in a sort of frenzy, blew his horn, and galloped off. I had not time to recover from the unexpected appearance of Tchertop-hanov, when suddenly, almost without any noise, there came out of the bushes a stoutish man of forty on a little black nag. He stopped, took off his green leather cap, and in a thin, subdued voice he asked me whether I hadn't seen a horseman riding a chestnut? I answered that I had.

'Which way did the gentleman go?' he went on in the same tone, without putting on his cap.

'Over there.'

'I humbly thank you, sir.'

He made a kissing sound with his lips, swung his legs against his horse's sides, and fell into a jog-trot in the direction indicated. I looked after him till his peaked cap was hidden behind the branches. This second stranger was not in the least like his predecessor in exterior. His face, plump and round as a ball, expressed bashfulness, good-nature, and humble meekness; his nose, also plump and round and streaked with blue veins, betokened a sensualist. On the front of his head there was not a single hair left, some thin brown tufts stuck out behind; there was an ingratiating twinkle in his little eyes, set in long slits, and a sweet smile on his red, juicy lips. He had on a coat with a stand-up collar and brass buttons, very worn but clean; his cloth trousers were hitched up high, his fat calves were visible above the yellow tops of his boots.

'Who's that?' I inquired of Yermolaï.

'That? Nedopyuskin, Tihon Ivanitch. He lives at Tchertop-hanov's.'

'What is he, a poor man?'

'He's not rich; but, to be sure, Tchertop-hanov's not got a brass farthing either.'

'Then why does he live with him?'

'Oh, they made friends. One's never seen without the other....It's a fact, indeed — where the horse puts its hoof, there the crab sticks its claw.'

We got out of the bushes; suddenly two hounds 'gave tongue' close to us, and a big hare bounded through the oats, which were fairly high by now. The dogs, hounds and harriers, leaped out of the thicket after him, and after the dogs flew out Tchertop-hanov himself. He did not shout, nor urge the dogs on, nor halloo; he was breathless and gasping; broken, senseless sounds were jerked out of his gaping mouth now and then; he dashed on, his eyes starting out of his head, and furiously lashed at his luckless horse with the whip. The harriers were gaining on the hare…it squatted for a moment, doubled sharply back, and darted past Yermolaï into the bushes....The harriers rushed in pursuit. 'Lo-ok out! lo-ok out!' the exhausted horseman articulated with effort, in a sort of stutter: 'lo-ok out, friend!' Yermolaï shot…the wounded hare rolled head over heels on the smooth dry grass, leaped into the air, and squealed piteously in the teeth of a worrying dog. The hounds crowded about her. Like an arrow, Tchertop-hanov flew off his horse, clutched his dagger, ran straddling among the dogs with furious imprecations, snatched the mangled hare from them, and, creasing up his whole face, he buried the dagger in its throat up to the very hilt…buried it, and began hallooing. Tihon Ivanitch made his appearance on the edge of the thicket 'Ho-ho-ho-ho-ho-ho-ho-ho!' vociferated Tchertop-hanov a second time. 'Ho-ho-ho-ho,' his companion repeated placidly.

'But really, you know, one ought not to hunt in summer, 'I observed to Tchertop-hanov, pointing to the trampled-down oats.

'It's my field,' answered Tchertop-hanov, gasping.

He pulled the hare into shape, hung it on to his saddle, and flung the paws among the dogs.

'I owe you a charge, my friend, by the rules of hunting,' he said, addressing Yermolaï. 'And you, dear sir,' he added in the same jerky, abrupt voice, 'my thanks.'

He mounted his horse.

'Pe-ermit me to ask…I've forgotten your name and your father's.'

Again I told him my name.

'Delighted to make your acquaintance. When you have an opportunity, hope you'll come and see me....But where is that Fomka, Tihon Ivanitch?' he went on with heat; 'the hare was run down without him.'

'His horse fell down under him,' replied Tihon Ivanitch with a smile.

'Fell down! Orbassan fell down? Pugh! tut!…Where is he?'

'Over there, behind the copse.'

Tchertop-hanov struck his horse on the muzzle with his whip, and galloped off at a breakneck pace. Tihon Ivanitch bowed to me twice, once for himself and once for his companion, and again set off at a trot into the bushes.

These two gentlemen aroused my curiosity keenly. What could unite two creatures so different in the bonds of an inseparable friendship? I began to make inquiries. This was what I learned.

Panteley Eremyitch Tchertop-hanov had the reputation in the whole surrounding vicinity of a dangerous, crack-brained fellow, haughty and quarrelsome in the extreme. He had served a very short time in the army, and had retired from the service through 'difficulties' with his superiors, with that rank which is generally regarded as equivalent to no rank at all. He came of an old family, once rich; his forefathers lived sumptuously, after the manner of the steppes — that is, they welcomed all, invited or uninvited, fed them to exhaustion, gave out oats by the quarter to their guests' coachmen for their teams, kept musicians, singers, jesters, and dogs; on festive days regaled their people with spirits and beer, drove to Moscow in the winter with their own horses, in heavy old coaches, and sometimes were for whole months without a farthing, living on home-grown produce. The estate came into Panteley Eremyitch's father's hands in a crippled condition; he, in his turn, 'played ducks and drakes' with it, and when he died, left his sole heir, Panteley, the small mortgaged village of Bezsonovo, with thirty-five souls of the male, and seventy-six of the female sex, and twenty-eight acres and a half of useless land on the waste of Kolobrodova, no record of serfs for which could be found among the deceased's deeds. The deceased had, it must be confessed, ruined himself in a very strange way: 'provident management' had been his destruction. According to his notions, a nobleman ought not to depend on merchants, townsmen, and 'brigands' of that sort, as he called them; he set up all possible trades and crafts on his estate; 'it's both seemlier and cheaper,' he used to say: 'it's provident management'! He never relinquished this fatal idea to the end of his days; indeed, it was his ruin. But, then, what entertainment it gave him! He never denied himself the satisfaction of a single whim. Among other freaks, he once began building, after his own fancy, so immense a family coach that, in spite of the united efforts of the peasants' horses, drawn together from the whole village, as well as their owners, it came to grief and fell to pieces on the first hillside. Eremey Lukitch (the name of Panteley's father was Eremey Lukitch), ordered a memorial to be put up on the hillside, but was not, however, at all abashed over the affair. He conceived the happy thought, too, of building a church — by himself, of course — without the assistance of an architect. He burnt a whole forest in making the bricks, laid an immense foundation, as though for a provincial hall, raised the walls, and began putting on the cupola; the cupola fell down. He tried again — the cupola again broke down; he tried the third time —-the cupola fell to pieces a third time. Good Eremey Lukitch grew thoughtful; there was something uncanny about it, he reflected…some accursed witchcraft must have a hand in it…and at once he gave orders to flog all the old women in the village. They flogged the old women; but they didn't get the cupola on, for all that. He began reconstructing the peasants' huts on a new plan, and all on a system of 'provident management'; he set them three homesteads together in a triangle, and in the middle stuck up a post with a painted bird-cage and flag. Every day he invented some new freak; at one time he was making soup of burdocks, at another cutting his horses' tails off to make caps for his servants; at another, proposing to substitute nettles for flax, to feed pigs on mushrooms....He had once read in the Moscow Gazette an article by a Harkov landowner, Hryak-Hrupyorsky, on the importance of morality to the well-being of the peasant, and the next day he gave forth a decree to all his peasants to learn off the Harkov landowner's article by heart at once. The peasants learnt the article; the master asked them whether they understood what was said in it? The bailiff replied — that to be sure they understood it! About the same time he ordered all his subjects, with a view to the maintenance of order and provident management, to be numbered, and each to have his number sewn on his collar. On meeting the master, each was to shout, 'Number so-and-so is here!' and the master would answer affably: 'Go on, in God's name!'

In spite, however, of order and provident management, Eremey Lukitch got by degrees into a very difficult position; he began at first by mortgaging his villages, and then was brought to the sale of them; the last ancestral home, the village with the unfinished church, was sold at last for arrears to the Crown, luckily not in the lifetime of Eremey Lukitch — he could never have supported such a blow — but a fortnight after his death. He succeeded in dying at home in his own bed, surrounded by his own people, and under the care of his own doctor; but nothing was left to poor Panteley but Bezsonovo.

Panteley heard of his father's illness while he was still in the service, in the very heat of the 'difficulties' mentioned above. He was only just nineteen. From his earliest childhood he had not left his father's house, and under the guidance of his mother, a very good-natured but perfectly stupid woman, Vassilissa Vassilyevna, he grew up spoilt and conceited. She undertook his education alone; Eremey Lukitch, buried in his economical fancies, had no thoughts to spare for it. It is true, he once punished his son with his own hand for mispronouncing a letter of the alphabet; but Eremey Lukitch had received a cruel and secret blow that day: his best dog had been crushed by a tree. Vassilissa Vassilyevna's efforts in regard Panteley's education did not, however, get beyond one terrific exertion; in the sweat of her brow she engaged him a tutor, one Birkopf, a retired Alsatian soldier, and to the day of her death she trembled like a leaf before him. 'Oh,' she thought, 'if he throws us up — I'm lost! Where could I turn? Where could I find another teacher? Why, with what pains, what pains I enticed this one away from our neighbours!' And Birkopf, like a shrewd man, promptly took advantage of his unique position; he drank like a fish, and slept from morning till night. On the completion of his 'course of science,' Panteley entered the army. Vassilissa Vassilyevna was no more; she had died six months before that important event, of fright. She had had a dream of a white figure riding on a bear. Eremey Lukitch soon followed his better half.

At the first news of his illness, Panteley galloped home at breakneck speed, but he did not find his father alive. What was the amazement of the dutiful son when he found himself, utterly unexpectedly, transformed from a rich heir to a poor man! Few men are capable of bearing so sharp a reverse well. Panteley was embittered, made misanthropical by it. From an honest, generous, good-natured fellow, though spoilt and hot-tempered, he became haughty and quarrelsome; he gave up associating with the neighbours — he was too proud to visit the rich, and he disdained the poor — and behaved with unheard of arrogance to everyone, even to the established authorities. 'I am of the ancient hereditary nobility,' he would say. Once he had been on the point of shooting the police-commissioner for coming into the room with his cap on his head. Of course the authorities, on their side, had their revenge, and took every opportunity to make him feel their power; but still, they were rather afraid of him, because he had a desperate temper, and would propose a duel with knives at the second word. At the slightest retort Tchertop-hanov's eyes blazed, his voice broke....Ah, er — er — er,' he stammered, 'damn my soul!'…and nothing could stop him. And, moreover, he was a man of stainless character, who had never had a hand in anything the least shady. No one, of course, visited him…and with all this he was a good-hearted, even a great-hearted man in his own way; acts of injustice, of oppression, he would not brook even against strangers; he stood up for his own peasants like a rock. 'What?' he would say, with a violent blow on his own head: 'touch my people, mine? My name's not Tchertop-hanov, if I…'

Tihon Ivanitch Nedopyuskin could not, like Panteley Eremyitch, pride himself on his origin. His father came of the peasant proprietor class, and only after forty years of service attained the rank of a noble. Mr. Nedopyuskin, the father, belonged to the number of those people who are pursued by misfortune with an obduracy akin to personal hatred. For sixty whole years, from his very birth to his very death, the poor man was struggling with all the hardships, calamities, and privations, incidental to people of small means; he struggled like a fish under the ice, never having enough food and sleep — cringing, worrying, wearing himself to exhaustion, fretting over every farthing, with genuine 'innocence' suffering in the service, and dying at last in either a garret or a cellar, in the unsuccessful struggle to gain for himself or his children a crust of dry bread. Fate had hunted him down like a hare.

He was a good-natured and honest man, though he did take bribes — from a threepenny bit up to a crown piece inclusive. Nedopyuskin had a wife, thin and consumptive; he had children too; luckily they all died young except Tihon and a daughter, Mitrodora, nicknamed 'the merchants' belle,' who, after many painful and ludicrous adventures, was married to a retired attorney. Mr. Nedopyuskin had succeeded before his death in getting Tihon a place as supernumerary clerk in some office; but directly after his father's death Tihon resigned his situation. Their perpetual anxieties, their heartrending struggle with cold and hunger, his mother's careworn depression, his father's toiling despair, the coarse aggressiveness of landladies and shopkeepers — all the unending daily suffering of their life had developed an exaggerated timidity in Tihon: at the mere sight of his chief he was faint and trembling like a captured bird. He threw up his office. Nature, in her indifference, or perhaps her irony, implants in people all sorts of faculties and tendencies utterly inconsistent with their means and their position in society; with her characteristic care and love she had moulded of Tihon, the son of a poor clerk, a sensuous, indolent, soft, impressionable creature — a creature fitted exclusively for enjoyment, gifted with an excessively delicate sense of smell and of taste…she had moulded him, finished him off most carefully, and set her creation to struggle up on sour cabbage and putrid fish! And, behold! the creation did struggle up somehow, and began what is called 'life.' Then the fun began. Fate, which had so ruthlessly tormented Nedopyuskin the father, took to the son too; she had a taste for them, one must suppose. But she treated Tihon on a different plan: she did not torture him; she played with him. She did not once drive him to desperation, she did not set him to suffer the degrading agonies of hunger, but she led him a dance through the whole of Russia from one end to the other, from one degrading and ludicrous position to another; at one time Fate made him 'majordomo' to a snappish, choleric Lady Bountiful, at another a humble parasite on a wealthy skinflint merchant, then a private secretary to a goggle-eyed gentleman, with his hair cut in the English style, then she promoted him to the post of something between butler and buffoon to a dog-fancier....In short, Fate drove poor Tihon to drink drop by drop to the dregs the bitter poisoned cup of a dependent existence. He had been, in his time, the sport of the dull malignity and the boorish pranks of slothful masters. How often, alone in his room, released at last 'to go in peace,' after a mob of visitors had glutted their taste for horseplay at his expense, he had vowed, blushing with shame, chill tears of despair in his eyes, that he would run away in secret, would try his luck in the town, would find himself some little place as clerk, or die once for all of hunger in the street! But, in the first place, God had not given him strength of character; secondly, his timidity unhinged him; and thirdly, how could he get himself a place? whom could he ask? 'They'll never give it me,' the luckless wretch would murmur, tossing wearily in his bed, 'they'll never give it me!' And the next day he would take up the same degrading life again. His position was the more painful that, with all her care, nature had not troubled to give him the smallest share of the gifts and qualifications without which the trade of a buffoon is almost impossible. He was not equal, for instance, to dancing till he dropped, in a bearskin coat turned inside out, nor making jokes and cutting capers in the immediate vicinity of cracking whips; if he was turned out in a state of nature into a temperature of twenty degrees below freezing, as often as not, he caught cold; his stomach could not digest brandy mixed with ink and other filth, nor minced funguses and toadstools in vinegar. There is no knowing what would have become of Tihon if the last of his patrons, a contractor who had made his fortune, had not taken it into his head in a merry hour to inscribe in his will: 'And to Zyozo (Tihon, to wit) Nedopyuskin, I leave in perpetual possession, to him and his heirs, the village of Bezselendyevka, lawfully acquired by me, with all its appurtenances.' A few days later this patron was taken with a fit of apoplexy after gorging on sturgeon soup. A great commotion followed; the officials came and put seals on the property.

The relations arrived; the will was opened and read; and they called for Nedopyuskin: Nedopyuskin made his appearance. The greater number of the party knew the nature of Tihon Ivanitch's duties in his patron's household; he was greeted with deafening shouts and ironical congratulations. 'The landowner; here is the new owner!' shouted the other heirs. 'Well, really this,' put in one, a noted wit and humourist; 'well, really this, one may say…this positively is…really what one may call…an heir-apparent!' and they all went off into shrieks. For a long while Nedopyuskin could not believe in his good fortune. They showed him the will: he flushed, shut his eyes, and with a despairing gesture he burst into tears. The chuckles of the party passed into a deep unanimous roar. The village of Bezselendyevka consisted of only twenty-two serfs, no one regretted its loss keenly; so why not get some fun out of it? One of the heirs from Petersburg, an important man, with a Greek nose and a majestic expression of face, Rostislav Adamitch Shtoppel, went so far as to go up to Nedopyuskin and look haughtily at him over his shoulder. 'So far as I can gather, honoured sir,' he observed with contemptuous carelessness, 'you enjoyed your position in the household of our respected Fedor Fedoritch, owing to your obliging readiness to wait on his diversions?' The gentleman from Petersburg expressed himself in a style insufferably refined, smart, and correct. Nedopyuskin, in his agitation and confusion, had not taken in the unknown gentleman's words, but the others were all quiet at once; the wit smiled condescendingly. Mr. Shtoppel rubbed his hands and repeated his question. Nedopyuskin raised his eyes in bewilderment and opened his mouth. Rostislav Adamitch puckered his face up sarcastically.

'I congratulate you, my dear sir, I congratulate you,' he went on: 'it's true, one may say, not everyone would have consented to gain his daily bread in such a fashion; but de guslibus non est disputandum, that is, everyone to his taste....Eh?'

Someone at the back uttered a rapid, decorous shriek of admiration and delight.

'Tell us,' pursued Mr. Shtoppel, much encouraged by the smiles of the whole party, 'to what special talent are you indebted for your good-fortune? No, don't be bashful, tell us; we're all here, so to speak, en famille. Aren't we, gentlemen, all here en famille?'

The relation to whom Rostislav Adamitch chanced to turn with this question did not, unfortunately, know French, and so he confined himself to a faint grunt of approbation. But another relation, a young man, with patches of a yellow colour on his forehead, hastened to chime in, 'Wee, wee, to be sure.'

'Perhaps,' Mr. Shtoppel began again, 'you can walk on your hands, your legs raised, so to say, in the air?'

Nedopyuskin looked round in agony: every face wore a taunting smile, every eye was moist with delight.

'Or perhaps you can crow like a cock?'

A loud guffaw broke out on all sides, and was hushed at once, stifled by expectation.

'Or perhaps on your nose you can....'

'Stop that!' a loud harsh voice suddenly interrupted Rostislav Adamitch; 'I wonder you're not ashamed to torment the poor man!'

Everyone looked round. In the doorway stood Tchertop-hanov. As a cousin four times removed of the deceased contractor, he too had received a note of invitation to the meeting of the relations. During the whole time of reading the will he had kept, as he always did, haughtily apart from the others.

'Stop that!' he repeated, throwing his head back proudly.

Mr. Shtoppel turned round quickly, and seeing a poorly dressed, unattractive-looking man, he inquired of his neighbour in an undertone (caution's always a good thing):

'Who's that?'

'Tchertop-hanov — he's no great shakes,' the latter whispered in his ear.

Rostislav Adamitch assumed a haughty air.

'And who are you to give orders?' he said through his nose, drooping his eyelids scornfully; 'who may you be, allow me to inquire? — a queer fish, upon my word!'

Tchertop-hanov exploded like gunpowder at a spark. He was choked with fury.

'Ss — ss — ss!' he hissed like one possessed, and all at once he thundered: 'Who am I? Who am I? I'm Panteley Tchertop-hanov, of the ancient hereditary nobility; my forefathers served the Tsar: and who may you be?'

Rostislav Adamitch turned pale and stepped back. He had not expected such resistance.

'I— I— a fish indeed!'

Tchertop-hanov darted forward; Shtoppel bounded away in great perturbation, the others rushed to meet the exasperated nobleman.

'A duel, a duel, a duel, at once, across a handkerchief!' shouted the enraged Panteley, 'or beg my pardon — yes, and his too....'

'Pray beg his pardon!' the agitated relations muttered all round Shtoppel; 'he's such a madman, he'd cut your throat in a minute!'

'I beg your pardon, I beg your pardon, I didn't know,' stammered Shtoppel; 'I didn't know....'

'And beg his too!' vociferated the implacable Panteley.

'I beg your pardon too,' added Rostislav Adamitch, addressing Nedopyuskin, who was shaking as if he were in an ague.

Tchertop-hanov calmed down; he went up to Tihon Ivanitch, took him by the hand, looked fiercely round, and, as not one pair of eyes ventured to meet his, he walked triumphantly amid profound silence out of the room, with the new owner of the lawfully acquired village of Bezselendyevka.

From that day they never parted again. (The village of Bezselendyevka was only seven miles from Bezsonovo.) The boundless gratitude of Nedopyuskin soon passed into the most adoring veneration. The weak, soft, and not perfectly stainless Tihon bowed down in the dust before the fearless and irreproachable Panteley. 'It's no slight thing,' he thought to himself sometimes, 'to talk to the governor, look him straight in the face....Christ have mercy on us, doesn't he look at him!'

He marvelled at him, he exhausted all the force of his soul in his admiration of him, he regarded him as an extraordinary man, as clever, as learned. And there's no denying that, bad as Tchertop-hanov's education might be, still, in comparison with Tihon's education, it might pass for brilliant. Tchertop-hanov, it is true, had read little Russian, and knew French very badly — so badly that once, in reply to the question of a Swiss tutor: 'Vous parlez français, monsieur?' he answered: 'Je ne comprehend,' and after a moment's thought, he added pa; but any way he was aware that Voltaire had once existed, and was a very witty writer, and that Frederick the Great, king of Prussia, had been distinguished as a great military commander. Of Russian writers he respected Derzhavin, but liked Marlinsky, and called Ammalat-Bek the best of the pack....

A few days after my first meeting with the two friends, I set off for the village of Bezsonovo to see Panteley Eremyitch. His little house could be seen a long way off; it stood out on a bare place, half a mile from the village, on the 'bluff,' as it is called, like a hawk on a ploughed field. Tchertop-hanov's homestead consisted of nothing more than four old tumble-down buildings of different sizes — that is, a lodge, a stable, a barn, and a bath-house. Each building stood apart by itself; there was neither a fence round nor a gate to be seen. My coachman stopped in perplexity at a well which was choked up and had almost disappeared. Near the barn some thin and unkempt puppies were mangling a dead horse, probably Orbassan; one of them lifted up the bleeding nose, barked hurriedly, and again fell to devouring the bare ribs. Near the horse stood a boy of seventeen, with a puffy, yellow face, dressed like a Cossack, and barelegged; he looked with a responsible air at the dogs committed to his charge, and now and then gave the greediest a lash with his whip.

'Is your master at home?' I inquired.

'The Lord knows!' answered the lad; 'you'd better knock.'

I jumped out of the droshky, and went up to the steps of the lodge.

Mr. Tchertop-hanov's dwelling presented a very cheerless aspect; the beams were blackened and bulging forward, the chimney had fallen off, the corners of the house were stained with damp, and sunk out of the perpendicular, the small, dusty, bluish windows peeped out from under the shaggy overhanging roof with an indescribably morose expression: some old vagrants have eyes that look like that. I knocked; no one responded. I could hear, however, through the door some sharply uttered words:

'A, B, C; there now, idiot!' a hoarse voice was saying: 'A, B, C, D…no! D, E, E, E!…Now then, idiot!'

I knocked a second time.

The same voice shouted: 'Come in; who's there?'…

I went into the small empty hall, and through the open door I saw Tchertop-hanov himself. In a greasy oriental dressing-gown, loose trousers, and a red skull-cap, he was sitting on a chair; in one hand he gripped the face of a young poodle, while in the other he was holding a piece of bread just above his nose.

'Ah!' he pronounced with dignity, not stirring from his seat: 'delighted to see you. Please sit down. I am busy here with Venzor....Tihon Ivanitch,' he added, raising his voice, 'come here, will you? Here's a visitor.'

'I'm coming, I'm coming,' Tihon Ivanitch responded from the other room. 'Masha, give me my cravat.'

Tchertop-hanov turned to Venzor again and laid the piece of bread on his nose. I looked round. Except an extending table much warped with thirteen legs of unequal length, and four rush chairs worn into hollows, there was no furniture of any kind in the room; the walls, which had been washed white, ages ago, with blue, star-shaped spots, were peeling off in many places; between the windows hung a broken tarnished looking-glass in a huge frame of red wood. In the corners stood pipestands and guns; from the ceiling hung fat black cobwebs.

'A, B, C, D,' Tchertop-hanov repeated slowly, and suddenly he cried furiously: 'E! E! E! E!…What a stupid brute!…'

But the luckless poodle only shivered, and could not make up his mind to open his mouth; he still sat wagging his tail uneasily and wrinkling up his face, blinked dejectedly, and frowned as though saying to himself: 'Of course, it's just as you please!'

'There, eat! come! take it!' repeated the indefatigable master.

'You've frightened him,' I remarked.

'Well, he can get along, then!'

He gave him a kick. The poor dog got up softly, dropped the bread off his nose, and walked, as it were, on tiptoe to the hall, deeply wounded. And with good reason: a stranger calling for the first time, and to treat him like that!

The door from the next room gave a subdued creak, and Mr. Nedopyuskin came in, affably bowing and smiling.

I got up and bowed.

'Don't disturb yourself, don't disturb yourself,' he lisped.

We sat down. Tchertop-hanov went into the next room.

'You have been for some time in our neighbourhood,' began Nedopyuskin in a subdued voice, coughing discreetly into his hand, and holding his fingers before his lips from a feeling of propriety.

'I came last month.'

'Indeed.'

We were silent for a little.

'Lovely weather we are having just now,' resumed Nedopyuskin, and he looked gratefully at me as though I were in some way responsible for the weather: 'the corn, one may say, is doing wonderfully.'

I nodded in token of assent. We were silent again.

'Panteley Eremyitch was pleased to hunt two hares yesterday,' Nedopyuskin began again with an effort, obviously wishing to enliven the conversation; 'yes, indeed, very big hares they were, sir.'

'Has Mr. Tchertop-hanov good hounds?'

'The most wonderful hounds, sir!' Nedopyuskin replied, delighted; 'one may say, the best in the province, indeed.' (He drew nearer to me.) 'But, then, Panteley Eremyitch is such a wonderful man! He has only to wish for anything — he has only to take an idea into his head — and before you can look round, it's done; everything, you may say, goes like clockwork. Panteley Eremyitch, I assure you....'

Tchertop-hanov came into the room. Nedopyuskin smiled, ceased speaking, and indicated him to me with a glance which seemed to say, 'There, you will see for yourself.' We fell to talking about hunting.

'Would you like me to show you my leash?' Tchertop-hanov asked me; and, not waiting for a reply, he called Karp.

A sturdy lad came in, in a green nankin long coat, with a blue collar and livery buttons.

'Tell Fomka,' said Tchertop-hanov abruptly, 'to bring in Ammalat and Saiga, and in good order, do you understand?'

Karp gave a broad grin, uttered an indefinite sound, and went away. Fomka made his appearance, well combed and tightly buttoned up, in boots, and with the hounds. From politeness, I admired the stupid beasts (harriers are all exceedingly stupid). Tchertop-hanov spat right into Ammalat's nostrils, which did not, however, apparently afford that dog the slightest satisfaction. Nedopyuskin, too, stroked Ammalat from behind. We began chatting again. By degrees Tchertop-hanov unbent completely, and no longer stood on his dignity nor snorted defiantly; the expression of his face changed. He glanced at me and at Nedopyuskin....

'Hey!' he cried suddenly; 'why should she sit in there alone? Masha! hi, Masha! come in here!'

Some one stirred in the next room, but there was no answer.

'Ma-a-sha!' Tchertop-hanov repeated caressingly; 'come in here. It's all right, don't be afraid.'

The door was softly opened, and I caught sight of a tall and slender girl of twenty, with a dark gypsy face, golden-brown eyes, and hair black as pitch; her large white teeth gleamed between full red lips. She had on a white dress; a blue shawl, pinned close round her throat with a gold brooch, half hid her slender, beautiful arms, in which one could see the fineness of her race. She took two steps with the bashful awkwardness of some wild creature, stood still, and looked down.

'Come, let me introduce,' said Panteley Eremyitch; 'wife she is not, but she's to be respected as a wife.'

Masha flushed slightly, and smiled in confusion. I made her a low bow. I thought her very charming. The delicate falcon nose, with distended, half-transparent nostrils; the bold sweep of her high eyebrows, the pale, almost sunken cheeks — every feature of her face denoted wilful passion and reckless devilry. From under the coil of her hair two rows of little shining hairs ran down her broad neck — a sign of race and vigour.

She went to the window and sat down. I did not want to increase her embarrassment, and began talking with Tchertop-hanov. Masha turned her head slyly, and began peeping from under her eyelids at me stealthily, shyly, and swiftly. Her glance seemed to flash out like a snake's sting. Nedopyuskin sat beside her, and whispered something in her ear. She smiled again. When she smiled, her nose slightly puckered up, and her upper lip was raised, which gave her face something of the expression of a cat or a lion....

'Oh, but you're one of the "hands off!" sort,' I thought, in my turn stealing a look at her supple frame, her hollow breast, and her quick, angular movements.

'Masha,' Tchertop-hanov asked, 'don't you think we ought to give our visitor some entertainment, eh?'

'We've got some jam,' she replied.

'Well, bring the jam here, and some vodka, too, while you're about it. And, I say, Masha,' he shouted after her, 'bring the guitar in too.'

'What's the guitar for? I'm not going to sing.'

'Why?'

'I don't want to.'

'Oh, nonsense; you'll want to when....'

'What?' asked Masha, rapidly knitting her brows.

'When you're asked,' Tchertop-hanov went on, with some embarrassment.

'Oh!'

She went out, soon came back with jam and vodka, and again sat by the window. There was still a line to be seen on her forehead; the two eyebrows rose and drooped like a wasp's antennae....Have you ever noticed, reader, what a wicked face the wasp has? 'Well,' I thought, 'I'm in for a storm.' The conversation flagged. Nedopyuskin shut up completely, and wore a forced smile; Tchertop-hanov panted, turned red, and opened his eyes wide; I was on the point of taking leave....Suddenly Masha got up, flung open the window, thrust out her head, and shouted lustily to a passing peasant woman, 'Aksinya!' The woman started, and tried to turn round, but slipped down and flopped heavily on to a dung-heap. Masha threw herself back and laughed merrily; Tchertop-hanov laughed too; Nedopyuskin shrieked with delight. We all revived. The storm had passed off in one flash of lightning…the air was clear again.

Half-an-hour later, no one would have recognised us; we were chatting and frolicking like children. Masha was the merriest of all; Tchertop-hanov simply could not take his eyes off her. Her face grew paler, her nostrils dilated, her eyes glowed and darkened at the same time. It was a wild creature at play. Nedopyuskin limped after her on his short, fat little legs, like a drake after a duck. Even Venzor crawled out of his hiding-place in the hall, stood a moment in the doorway, glanced at us, and suddenly fell to jumping up into the air and barking. Masha flitted into the other room, fetched the guitar, flung off the shawl from her shoulders, seated herself quickly, and, raising her head, began singing a gypsy song. Her voice rang out, vibrating like a glass bell when it is struck; it flamed up and died away....It filled the heart with sweetness and pain....Tchertop-hanov fell to dancing. Nedopyuskin stamped and swung his legs in tune. Masha was all a-quiver, like birch-bark in the fire; her delicate fingers flew playfully over the guitar, her dark-skinned throat slowly heaved under the two rows of amber. All at once she would cease singing, sink into exhaustion, and twang the guitar, as it were involuntarily, and Tchertop-hanov stood still, merely working his shoulders and turning round in one place, while Nedopyuskin nodded his head like a Chinese figure; then she would break out into song like a mad thing, drawing herself up and holding up her head, and Tchertop-hanov again curtsied down to the ground, leaped up to the ceiling, spun round like a top, crying 'Quicker!…'

'Quicker, quicker, quicker!' Nedopyuskin chimed in, speaking very fast.

It was late in the evening when I left Bezsonovo....

XXII The End of Tchertop-Hanov

1

It was two years after my visit that Panteley Eremyitch's troubles began — his real troubles. Disappointments, disasters, even misfortunes he had had before that time, but he had paid no attention to them, and had risen superior to them in former days. The first blow that fell upon him was the most heartrending for him. Masha left him.

What induced her to forsake his roof, where she seemed to be so thoroughly at home, it is hard to say. Tchertop-hanov to the end of his days clung to the conviction that a certain young neighbour, a retired captain of Uhlans, named Yaff, was at the root of Masha's desertion. He had taken her fancy, according to Panteley Eremyitch, simply by constantly curling his moustaches, pomading himself to excess, and sniggering significantly; but one must suppose that the vagrant gypsy blood in Masha's veins had more to do with it. However that may have been, one fine summer evening Masha tied up a few odds and ends in a small bundle, and walked out of Tchertop-hanov's house.

For three days before this she had sat crouched up in a corner, huddled against the wall, like a wounded fox, and had not spoken a word to any one; she had only turned her eyes about, and twitched her eyebrows, and faintly gnashed her teeth, and moved her arms as though she were wrapping herself up. This mood had come upon her before, but had never lasted long: Tchertop-hanov knew that, and so he neither worried himself nor worried her. But when, on coming in from the kennels, where, in his huntsman's words, the last two hounds 'had departed,' he met a servant girl who, in a trembling voice, informed him that Marya Akinfyevna sent him her greetings, and left word that she wished him every happiness, but she was not coming back to him any more; Tchertop-hanov, after reeling round where he stood and uttering a hoarse yell, rushed at once after the runaway, snatching up his pistol as he went.

He overtook her a mile and a half from his house, near a birch wood, on the high-road to the district town. The sun was sinking on the horizon, and everything was suddenly suffused with purple glow — trees, plants, and earth alike.

'To Yaff! to Yaff!' groaned Tchertop-hanov directly he caught sight of Masha. 'Going to Yaff!' he repeated, running up to her, and almost stumbling at every step.

Masha stood still, and turned round facing him.

She stood with her back to the light, and looked all black, as though she had been carved out of dark wood; only the whites of her eyes stood out like silvery almonds, but the eyes themselves — the pupils — were darker than ever.

She flung her bundle aside, and folded her arms. 'You are going to Yaff, wretched girl!' repeated Tchertop-hanov, and he was on the point of seizing her by the shoulder, but, meeting her eyes, he was abashed, and stood uneasily where he was.

'I am not going to Mr. Yaff, Panteley Eremyitch,' replied Masha in soft, even tones; 'it's only I can't live with you any longer.'

'Can't live with me? Why not? Have I offended you in some way?'

Masha shook her head. 'You've not offended me in any way, Panteley Eremyitch, only my heart is heavy in your house....Thanks for the past, but I can't stay — no!'

Tchertop-hanov was amazed; he positively slapped his thighs, and bounced up and down in his astonishment.

'How is that? Here she's gone on living with me, and known nothing but peace and happiness, and all of a sudden — her heart's heavy! and she flings me over! She goes and puts a kerchief on her head, and is gone. She received every respect, like any lady.'

'I don't care for that in the least,' Masha interrupted.

'Don't care for it? From a wandering gypsy to turn into a lady, and she doesn't care for it! How don't you care for it, you low-born slave? Do you expect me to believe that? There's treachery hidden in it — treachery!'

He began frowning again.

'There's no treachery in my thoughts, and never has been,' said Masha in her distinct, resonant voice; 'I've told you already, my heart was heavy.'

'Masha!' cried Tchertop-hanov, striking himself a blow on the chest with his fist; 'there, stop it; hush, you have tortured me…now, it's enough! O my God! think only what Tisha will say; you might have pity on him, at least!'

'Remember me to Tihon Ivanitch, and tell him…'

Tchertop-hanov wrung his hands. 'No, you are talking nonsense — you are not going! Your Yaff may wait for you in vain!'

'Mr. Yaff,' Masha was beginning....

'A fine Mister Yaff!' Tchertop-hanov mimicked her. 'He's an underhand rascal, a low cur — that's what he is — and a phiz like an ape's!'

For fully half-an-hour Tchertop-hanov was struggling with Masha. He came close to her, he fell back, he shook his fists at her, he bowed down before her, he wept, he scolded.

… 'I can't,' repeated Masha; 'I am so sad at heart…devoured by weariness.'

Little by little her face assumed such an indifferent, almost drowsy expression, that Tchertop-hanov asked her if they had not drugged her with laudanum.

'It's weariness,' she said for the tenth time.

'Then what if I kill you?' he cried suddenly, and he pulled the pistol out of his pocket.

Masha smiled; her face brightened.

'Well, kill me, Panteley Eremyitch; as you will; but go back, I won't.'

'You won't come back?' Tchertop-hanov cocked the pistol.

'I won't go back, my dearie. Never in my life will I go back. My word is steadfast.'

Tchertop-hanov suddenly thrust the pistol into her hand, and sat down on the ground.

'Then, you kill me! Without you I don't care to live. I have grown loathsome to you — and everything's loathsome for me!'

Masha bent down, took up her bundle, laid the pistol on the grass, its mouth away from Tchertop-hanov, and went up to him.

'Ah, my dearie, why torture yourself? Don't you know what we gypsy girls are? It's our nature; you must make up your mind to it. When there comes weariness the divider, and calls the soul away to strange, distant parts, how is one to stay here? Don't forget your Masha; you won't find such another sweetheart, and I won't forget you, my dearie; but our life together's over!'

'I loved you, Masha,' Tchertop-hanov muttered into the fingers in which he had buried his face....

'And I loved you, little friend Panteley Eremyitch.'

'I love you, I love you madly, senselessly — and when I think now that you, in your right senses, without rhyme or reason, are leaving me like this, and going to wander over the face of the earth — well, it strikes me that if I weren't a poor penniless devil, you wouldn't be throwing me over!'

At these words Masha only laughed.

'And he used to say I didn't care for money,' she commented, and she gave Tchertop-hanov a vigorous thump on the shoulder.

He jumped up on to his feet.

'Come, at least you must let me give you some money — how can you go like this without a halfpenny? But best of all: kill me! I tell you plainly: kill me once for all!'

Masha shook her head again. 'Kill you? Why get sent to Siberia, my dearie?'

Tchertop-hanov shuddered. 'Then it's only from that — from fear of penal servitude.'

He rolled on the grass again.

Masha stood over him in silence. 'I'm sorry for you, dear,' she said with a sigh: 'you're a good fellow…but there's no help for it: good-bye!'

She turned away and took two steps. The night had come on by now, and dim shadows were closing in on all sides. Tchertop-hanov jumped up swiftly and seized Masha from behind by her two elbows.

'You are going away like this, serpent, to Yaff!'

'Good-bye!' Masha repeated sharply and significantly; she tore herself away and walked off.

Tchertop-hanov looked after her, ran to the place where the pistol was lying, snatched it up, took aim, fired....But before he touched the trigger, his arm twitched upwards; the ball whistled over Masha's head. She looked at him over her shoulder without stopping, and went on, swinging as she walked, as though in defiance of him.

He hid his face — and fell to running.

But before he had run fifty paces he suddenly stood still as though turned to stone. A well-known, too well-known voice came floating to him. Masha was singing. 'It was in the sweet days of youth,' she sang: every note seemed to linger plaintive and ardent in the evening air. Tchertop-hanov listened intently. The voice retreated and retreated; at one moment it died away, at the next it floated across, hardly audible, but still with the same passionate glow.

'She does it to spite me,' thought Tchertop-hanov; but at once he moaned, 'oh, no! it's her last farewell to me for ever,'— and he burst into floods of tears.

The next day he appeared at the lodgings of Mr. Yaff, who, as a true man of the world, not liking the solitude of the country, resided in the district town, 'to be nearer the young ladies,' as he expressed it. Tchertop-hanov did not find Yaff; he had, in the words of his valet, set off for Moscow the evening before.

'Then it is so!' cried Tchertop-hanov furiously; 'there was an arrangement between them; she has run away with him…but wait a bit!'

He broke into the young cavalry captain's room in spite of the resistance of the valet. In the room there was hanging over the sofa a portrait in oils of the master, in the Uhlan uniform. 'Ah, here you are, you tailless ape!' thundered Tchertop-hanov; he jumped on to the sofa, and with a blow of his fist burst a big hole in the taut canvas.

'Tell your worthless master,' he turned to the valet, 'that, in the absence of his own filthy phiz, the nobleman Tchertop-hanov put a hole through the painted one; and if he cares for satisfaction from me, he knows where to find the nobleman Tchertop-hanov! or else I'll find him out myself! I'll fetch the rascally ape from the bottom of the sea!'

Saying these words, Tchertop-hanov jumped off the sofa and majestically withdrew.

But the cavalry captain Yaff did not demand satisfaction from him — indeed, he never met him anywhere — and Tchertop-hanov did not think of seeking his enemy out, and no scandal followed. Masha herself soon after this disappeared beyond all trace. Tchertop-hanov took to drink; however, he 'reformed' later. But then a second blow fell upon him.

2

This was the death of his bosom friend Tihon Ivanovitch Nedopyuskin. His health had begun to fail two years before his death: he began to suffer from asthma, and was constantly dropping asleep, and on waking up could not at once come to himself; the district doctor maintained that this was the result of 'something rather like fits.' During the three days which preceded Masha's departure, those three days when 'her heart was heavy,' Nedopyuskin had been away at his own place at Bezselendyevka: he had been laid up with a severe cold. Masha's conduct was consequently even more unexpected for him; it made almost a deeper impression on him than on Tchertop-hanov himself. With his natural sweetness and diffidence, he gave utterance to nothing but the tenderest sympathy with his friend, and the most painful perplexity…but it crushed and made havoc of everything in him. 'She has torn the heart out of me,' he would murmur to himself, as he sat on his favourite checked sofa and twisted his fingers. Even when Tchertop-hanov had got over it, he, Nedopyuskin, did not recover, and still felt that 'there was a void within him.' 'Here,' he would say, pointing to the middle of his breast above his stomach. In that way he lingered on till the winter. When the frosts came, his asthma got better, but he was visited by, not 'something rather like a fit' this time, but a real unmistakable fit. He did not lose his memory at once; he still knew Tchertop-hanov and his friend's cry of despair, 'How can you desert me, Tisha, without my consent, just as Masha did?' He even responded with faltering, uncertain tongue, 'O— P— a — ey — E— e — yitch, I will o — bey you.'

This did not, however, prevent him from dying the same day, without waiting for the district doctor, who (on seeing the hardly cold body) found nothing left for him to do, but with a melancholy recognition of the instability of all things mortal, to ask for 'a drop of vodka and a snack of fish.' As might have been anticipated, Tihon Ivanitch had bequeathed his property to his revered patron and generous protector, Panteley Eremyitch Tchertop-hanov; but it was of no great benefit to the revered patron, as it was shortly after sold by public auction, partly in order to cover the expense of a sepulchral monument, a statue, which Tchertop-hanov (and one can see his father's craze coming out in him here) had thought fit to put up over the ashes of his friend. This statue, which was to have represented an angel praying, was ordered by him from Moscow; but the agent recommended to him, conceiving that connoisseurs in sculpture were not often to be met with in the provinces, sent him, instead of an angel, a goddess Flora, which had for many years adorned one of those neglected gardens near Moscow, laid out in the days of Catherine. He had an excellent reason for doing so, since this statue, though highly artistic, in the rococo style, with plump little arms, tossing curls, a wreath of roses round the bare bosom, and a serpentine figure, was obtained by him, the agent, for nothing. And so to this day the mythological goddess stands, with one foot elegantly lifted, above the tomb of Tihon Ivanovitch, and with a genuinely Pompadour simper, gazes at the calves and sheep, those invariable visitors of our village graveyards, as they stray about her.

3

On the loss of his faithful friend, Tchertop-hanov again took to drink, and this time far more seriously. Everything went utterly to the bad with him. He had no money left for sport; the last of his meagre fortune was spent; the last of his few servants ran away. Panteley Eremyitch's isolation became complete: he had no one to speak a word to even, far less to open his heart to. His pride alone had suffered no diminution. On the contrary, the worse his surroundings became, the more haughty and lofty and inaccessible he was himself. He became a complete misanthrope in the end. One distraction, one delight, was left him: a superb grey horse, of the Don breed, named by him Malek-Adel, a really wonderful animal.

This horse came into his possession in this fashion.

As he was riding one day through a neighbouring village, Tchertop-hanov heard a crowd of peasants shouting and hooting before a tavern. In the middle of the crowd stalwart arms were continually rising and falling in exactly the same place.

'What is happening there?' he asked, in the peremptory tone peculiar to him, of an old peasant woman who was standing on the threshold of her hut. Leaning against the doorpost as though dozing, the old woman stared in the direction of the tavern. A white-headed urchin in a print smock, with a cypress-wood cross on his little bare breast, was sitting with little outstretched legs, and little clenched fists between her bast slippers; a chicken close by was chipping at a stale crust of rye-bread.

'The Lord knows, your honour,' answered the old woman. Bending forward, she laid her wrinkled brown hand on the child's head. 'They say our lads are beating a Jew.'

'A Jew? What Jew?'

'The Lord knows, your honour. A Jew came among us; and where he's come from — who knows? Vassya, come to your mammy, sir; sh, sh, nasty brute!'

The old woman drove away the chicken, while Vassya clung to her petticoat.

'So, you see, they're beating him, sir.'

'Why beating him? What for?'

'I don't know, your honour. No doubt, he deserves it. And, indeed, why not beat him? You know, your honour, he crucified Christ!'

Tchertop-hanov uttered a whoop, gave his horse a lash on the neck with the riding-whip, flew straight towards the crowd, and plunging into it, began with the same riding-whip thrashing the peasants to left and to right indiscriminately, shouting in broken tones: 'Lawless brutes! lawless brutes! It's for the law to punish, and not pri-vate per-sons! The law! the law! the law!'

Before two minutes had passed the crowd had beaten a retreat in various directions; and on the ground before the tavern door could be seen a small, thin, swarthy creature, in a nankin long coat, dishevelled and mangled…a pale face, rolling eyes, open mouth....What was it?…deadly terror, or death itself?

'Why have you killed this Jew?' Tchertop-hanov shouted at the top of his voice, brandishing his riding-whip menacingly.

The crowd faintly roared in response. One peasant was rubbing his shoulder, another his side, a third his nose.

'You're pretty free with your whip!' was heard in the back rows.

'Why have you killed the Jew, you christened Pagans?' repeated Tchertop-hanov.

But, at this point, the creature lying on the ground hurriedly jumped on to its feet, and, running up to Tchertop-hanov, convulsively seized hold of the edge of the saddle.

'Alive!' was heard in the background.

'He's a regular cat!'

'Your ex-shelency, defend me, save me!' the unhappy Jew was faltering meanwhile, his whole body squeezed up against Tchertop-hanov's foot; 'or they will murder me, they will murder me, your ex-shelency!'

'What have they against you?' asked Tchertop-hanov.

'I can't tell, so help me God! Some cow hereabouts died…so they suspect me…but I…' 'Well, that we'll go into later!' Tchertop-hanov interrupted; 'but now, you hold on to the saddle and follow me. And you!' he added, turning to the crowd,' do you know me? — I'm the landowner Panteley Tchertop-hanov. I live at Bezsonovo — and so you can take proceedings against me, when you think fit — and against the Jew too, while you're about it!'

'Why take proceedings?' said a grey-bearded, decent-looking peasant, bowing low, the very picture of an ancient patriarch. (He had been no whit behind the others in belabouring the Jew, however). 'We know your honour, Panteley Eremyitch, well; we thank your honour humbly for teaching us better!'

'Why take proceedings?' chimed in the others.

'As to the Jew, we'll take it out of him another day! He won't escape us! We shall be on the look-out for him.'

Tchertop-hanov pulled his moustaches, snorted, and went home at a walking pace, accompanied by the Jew, whom he had delivered from his persecutors just as he had once delivered Tihon Nedopyuskin.

4

A few days later the one groom who was left to Tchertop-hanov announced that someone had come on horseback and wanted to speak to him. Tchertop-hanov went out on to the steps and recognised the Jew, riding a splendid horse of the Don breed, which stood proud and motionless in the middle of the courtyard. The Jew was bareheaded; he held his cap under his arm, and had thrust his feet into the stirrup-straps, not into the stirrups themselves; the ragged skirts of his long coat hung down on both sides of the saddle. On seeing Tchertop-hanov, he gave a smack with his lips, and ducked down with a twitch of the elbows and a bend of the legs. Tchertop-hanov, however, not only failed to respond to his greeting, but was even enraged by it; he was all on fire in a minute: a scurvy Jew dare to ride a magnificent horse like that!…It was positively indecent!

'Hi, you Ethiopian fright!' he shouted; 'get off at once, if you don't want to be flung off into the mud!'

The Jew promptly obeyed, rolled off the horse like a sack, and keeping hold of the rein with one hand, he approached Tchertop-hanov, smiling and bowing.

'What do you want?' Panteley Eremyitch inquired with dignity.

'Your ex-shelency, deign to look what a horse!' said the Jew, never ceasing to bow for an instant.

'Er…well…the horse is all right. Where did you get it from? Stole it, I suppose?'

'How can you say that, your ex-shelency! I'm an honest Jew. I didn't steal it, but I obtained it for your ex-shelency — really! And the trouble, the trouble I had to get it? But, then, see what a horse it is! There's not another horse like it to be found in all the Don country! Look, your ex-shelency, what a horse it is! Here, kindly step this way! Wo!…wo!…turn round, stand sideways! And we'll take off the saddle. What do you think of him, your ex-shelency?'

'The horse is all right,' repeated Tchertop-hanov with affected indifference, though his heart was beating like a sledge-hammer in his breast. He was a passionate lover of 'horse-flesh,' and knew a good thing when he saw it.

'Only take a look at him, your ex-shelency! Pat him on the neck! yes, yes, he-he-he-he! like this, like this!'

Tchertop-hanov, with apparent reluctance, laid his hand on the horse's neck, gave it a pat or two, then passed his fingers from the forelock along the spine, and when he had reached a certain spot above the kidneys, like a connoisseur, he lightly pressed that spot. The horse instantly arched its spine, and looking round suspiciously at Tchertop-hanov with its haughty black eye, snorted and moved its hind legs.

The Jew laughed and faintly clapped his hands. 'He knows his master, your ex-shelency, his master!'

'Don't talk nonsense,' Tchertop-hanov interrupted with vexation. 'To buy this horse from you…I haven't the means, and as for presents, I not only wouldn't take them from a Jew; I wouldn't take a present from Almighty God Himself!'

'As though I would presume to offer you a present, mercy upon me!' cried the Jew: 'you buy it, your ex-shelency…and as to the little sum — I can wait for it.'

Tchertop-hanov sank into thought.

'What will you take for it?' he muttered at last between his teeth.

The Jew shrugged his shoulders.

'What I paid for it myself. Two hundred roubles.'

The horse was well worth twice —perhaps even three times that sum.

Tchertop-hanov turned away and yawned feverishly.

'And the money…when?' he asked, scowling furiously and not looking at the Jew.

'When your ex-shelency thinks fit.'

Tchertop-hanov flung his head back, but did not raise his eyes. 'That's no answer. Speak plainly, son of Herod! Am I to be under an obligation to you, hey?'

'Well, let's say, then,' the Jew hastened to add, 'in six months' time…Do you agree?'

Tchertop-hanov made no reply.

The Jew tried to get a look at his face. 'Do you agree? You permit him to be led to your stable?'

'The saddle I don't want,' Tchertop-hanov blurted out abruptly. 'Take the saddle — do you hear?'

'To be sure, to be sure, I will take it,' faltered the delighted Jew, shouldering the saddle.

'And the money,' Tchertop-hanov pursued… 'in six months. And not two hundred, but two hundred and fifty. Not a word! Two hundred and fifty, I tell you! to my account.'

Tchertop-hanov still could not bring himself to raise his eyes. Never had his pride been so cruelly wounded.

'It's plain, it's a present,' was the thought in his mind; 'he's brought it out of gratitude, the devil!' And he would have liked to kiss the Jew, and he would have liked to beat him.

'Your ex-shelency,' began the Jew, gaining a little courage, and grinning all over his face, 'should, after the Russian fashion, take from hand to hand....'

'What next? what an idea! A Hebrew…and Russian customs! Hey! you there! Take the horse; lead him to the stable. And give him some oats. I'll come myself and look after him. And his name is to be — Malek-Adel!'

Tchertop-hanov turned to go up the steps, but turning sharply back, and running up to the Jew, he pressed his hand warmly. The latter was bending down to kiss his hand, but Tchertop-hanov bounded back again, and murmuring, 'Tell no one!' he vanished through the door.

5

From that very day the chief interest, the chief occupation, the chief pleasure in the life of Tchertop-hanov, was Malek-Adel. He loved him as he had not loved even Masha; he became more attached to him than even to Nedopyuskin. And what a horse it was! All fire — simply explosive as gunpowder — and stately as a boyar! Untiring, enduring, obedient, whatever you might put him to; and costing nothing for his keep; he'd be ready to nibble at the ground under his feet if there was nothing else. When he stepped at a walking pace, it was like being lulled to sleep in a nurse's arms; when he trotted, it was like rocking at sea; when he galloped, he outstripped the wind! Never out of breath, perfectly sound in his wind. Sinews of steel: for him to stumble was a thing never recorded! To take a ditch or a fence was nothing to him — and what a clever beast! At his master's voice he would run with his head in the air; if you told him to stand still and walked away from him, he would not stir; directly you turned back, a faint neigh to say, 'Here I am.' And afraid of nothing: in the pitch-dark, in a snow-storm he would find his way; and he would not let a stranger come near him for anything; he would have had his teeth in him! And a dog dare never approach him; he would have his fore-leg on his head in a minute! and that was the end of the beast. A horse of proper pride, you might flourish a switch over him as an ornament — but God forbid you touched him! But why say more? — a perfect treasure, not a horse!

If Tchertop-hanov set to describing his Malek-Adel, he could not find words to express himself. And how he petted and pampered him! His coat shone like silver — not old, but new silver — with a dark polish on it; if one passed one's hand over it, it was like velvet! His saddle, his cloth, his bridle — all his trappings, in fact, were so well-fitted, in such good order, so bright — a perfect picture! Tchertop-hanov himself — what more can we say? — with his own hands plaited his favourite's forelocks and mane, and washed his tail with beer, and even, more than once, rubbed his hoofs with polish. Sometimes he would mount Malek-Adel and ride out, not to see his neighbours — he avoided them, as of old — but across their lands, past their homesteads…for them, poor fools, to admire him from a distance! Or he would hear that there was to be a hunt somewhere, that a rich landowner had arranged a meet in some outlying part of his land: he would be off there at once, and would canter in the distance, on the horizon, astounding all spectators by the swiftness and beauty of his horse, and not letting any one come close to him. Once some hunting landowner even gave chase to him with all his suite; he saw Tchertop-hanov was getting away, and he began shouting after him with all his might, as he galloped at full speed: 'Hey, you! Here! Take what you like for your horse! I wouldn't grudge a thousand! I'd give my wife, my children! Take my last farthing!'

Tchertop-hanov suddenly reined in Malek-Adel. The hunting gentleman flew up to him. 'My dear sir!' he shouted, 'tell me what you want? My dear friend!'

'If you were the Tsar,' said Tchertop-hanov emphatically (and he had never heard of Shakespeare), 'you might give me all your kingdom for my horse; I wouldn't take it!' He uttered these words, chuckled, drew Malek-Adel up on to his haunches, turned him in the air on his hind legs like a top or teetotum, and off! He went like a flash over the stubble. And the hunting man (a rich prince, they said he was) flung his cap on the ground, threw himself down with his face in his cap, and lay so for half an hour.

And how could Tchertop-hanov fail to prize his horse? Was it not thanks to him, he had again an unmistakable superiority, a last superiority over all his neighbours?

6

Meanwhile time went by, the day fixed for payment was approaching; while, far from having two hundred and fifty roubles, Tchertop-hanov had not even fifty. What was to be done? how could it be met? 'Well,' he decided at last, 'if the Jew is relentless, if he won't wait any longer, I'll give him my house and my land, and I'll set off on my horse, no matter where! I'll starve before I'll give up Malek-Adel!' He was greatly perturbed and even downcast; but at this juncture Fate, for the first and last time, was pitiful and smiled upon him; some distant kinswoman, whose very name was unknown to Tchertop-hanov, left him in her will a sum immense in his eyes — no less than two thousand roubles! And he received this sum in the very nick, as they say, of time; the day before the Jew was to come. Tchertop-hanov almost went out of his mind with joy, but he never even thought of vodka; from the very day Malek-Adel came into his hands he had not touched a drop.

He ran into the stable and kissed his favourite on both sides of his face above the nostrils, where the horse's skin is always so soft. 'Now we shall not be parted!' he cried, patting Malek-Adel on the neck, under his well-combed mane. When he went back into the house, he counted out and sealed up in a packet two hundred and fifty roubles. Then, as he lay on his back and smoked a pipe, he mused on how he would lay out the rest of the money — what dogs he would procure, real Kostroma hounds, spot and tan, and no mistake! He even had a little talk with Perfishka, to whom he promised a new Cossack coat, with yellow braid on all the seams, and went to bed in a blissful frame of mind.

He had a bad dream: he dreamt he was riding out, hunting, not on Malek-Adel, but on some strange beast of the nature of a unicorn; a white fox, white as snow, ran to meet him....He tried to crack his whip, tried to set the dogs on her — but instead of his riding-whip, he found he had a wisp of bast in his hand, and the fox ran in front of him, putting her tongue out at him. He jumped off, his unicorn stumbled, he fell…and fell straight into the arms of a police-constable, who was taking him before the Governor-General, and whom he recognised as Yaff....

Tchertop-hanov waked up. The room was dark; the cocks were just crowing for the second time....Somewhere in the far, far distance a horse neighed. Tchertop-hanov lifted up his head....Once more a faint, faint neigh was heard.

'That's Malek-Adel neighing!' was his thought.... 'It's his neigh. But why so far away? Bless us and save us!…It can't be…'

Tchertop-hanov suddenly turned chill all over; he instantly leaped out of bed, fumbled after his boots and his clothes, dressed himself, and, snatching up the stable-door key from under his pillow, he dashed out into the courtyard.

7

The stable was at the very end of the courtyard; one wall faced the open country. Tchertop-hanov could not at once fit the key into the lock — his hands were shaking — and he did not immediately turn the key....He stood motionless, holding his breath; if only something would stir inside! 'Malek! Malek!' he cried, in a low voice: the silence of death! Tchertop-hanov unconsciously jogged the key; the door creaked and opened....So, it was not locked. He stepped over the threshold, and again called his horse; this time by his full name, Malek-Adel! But no response came from his faithful companion; only a mouse rustled in the straw. Then Tchertop-hanov rushed into one of the three horse-boxes in the stable in which Malek-Adel was put. He went straight to the horse-box, though it was pitch-dark around....Empty! Tchertop-hanov's head went round; it seemed as though a bell was booming in his brain. He tried to say something, but only brought out a sort of hiss; and fumbling with his hands above, below, on all sides, breathless, with shaking knees, he made his way from one horse-box to another…to a third, full almost to the top with hay; stumbled against one wall, and then the other; fell down, rolled over on his head, got up, and suddenly ran headlong through the half-open door into the courtyard....

'Stolen! Perfishka! Perfishka! Stolen!' he yelled at the top of his voice.

The groom Perfishka flew head-over-heels out of the loft where he slept, with only his shirt on....

Like drunk men they ran against one another, the master and his solitary servant, in the middle of the courtyard; like madmen they turned round each other. The master could not explain what was the matter; nor could the servant make out what was wanted of him. 'Woe! woe!' wailed Tchertop-hanov. 'Woe! woe!' the groom repeated after him. 'A lantern! here! light a lantern! Light! light!' broke at last from Tchertop-hanov's fainting lips. Perfishka rushed into the house.

But to light the lantern, to get fire, was not easy; lucifer matches were regarded as a rarity in those days in Russia; the last embers had long ago gone out in the kitchen; flint and steel were not quickly found, and they did not work well. Gnashing his teeth, Tchertop-hanov snatched them out of the hands of the flustered Perfishka, and began striking a light himself; the sparks fell in abundance, in still greater abundance fell curses, and even groans; but the tinder either did not catch or went out again, in spite of the united efforts of four swollen cheeks and lips to blow it into a flame! At last, in five minutes, not sooner, a bit of tallow candle was alight at the bottom of a battered lantern; and Tchertop-hanov, accompanied by Perfishka, dashed into the stable, lifted the lantern above his head, looked round....

All empty!

He bounded out into the courtyard, ran up and down it in all directions — no horse anywhere! The hurdle-fence, enclosing Panteley Eremyitch's yard, had long been dilapidated, and in many places was bent and lying on the ground....Beside the stable, it had been completely levelled for a good yard's width. Perfishka pointed this spot out to Tchertop-hanov.

'Master! look here; this wasn't like this to-day. And see the ends of the uprights sticking out of the ground; that means someone has pulled them out.'

Tchertop-hanov ran up with the lantern, moved it about over the ground....

'Hoofs, hoofs, prints of horse-shoes, fresh prints!' he muttered, speaking hurriedly. 'They took him through here, through here!'

He instantly leaped over the fence, and with a shout, 'Malek-Adel! Malek-Adel!' he ran straight into the open country.

Perfishka remained standing bewildered at the fence. The ring of light from the lantern was soon lost to his eyes, swallowed up in the dense darkness of a starless, moonless night.

Fainter and fainter came the sound of the despairing cries of Tchertop-hanov....

8

It was daylight when he came home again. He hardly looked like a human being. His clothes were covered with mud, his face had a wild and ferocious expression, his eyes looked dull and sullen. In a hoarse whisper he drove Perfishka away, and locked himself in his room. He could hardly stand with fatigue, but he did not lie on his bed, but sat down on a chair by the door and clutched at his head.

'Stolen!…stolen!…'

But in what way had the thief contrived by night, when the stable was locked, to steal Malek-Adel? Malek-Adel, who would never let a stranger come near him even by day — steal him, too, without noise, without a sound? And how explain that not a yard-dog had barked? It was true there were only two left — two young puppies — and those two probably burrowing in rubbish from cold and hunger — but still!

'And what am I to do now without Malek-Adel?' Tchertop-hanov brooded. 'I've lost my last pleasure now; it's time to die. Buy another horse, seeing the money has come? But where find another horse like that?'

'Panteley Eremyitch! Panteley Eremyitch!' he heard a timid call at the door.

Tchertop-hanov jumped on to his feet.

'Who is it?' he shouted in a voice not his own.

'It's I, your groom, Perfishka.'

'What do you want? Is he found? has he run home?'

'No, Panteley Eremyitch; but that Jew chap who sold him.'…

'Well?'

'He's come.'

'Ho-ho-ho-ho-ho!' yelled Tchertop-hanov, and he at once flung open the door. 'Drag him here! drag him along!'

On seeing the sudden apparition of his 'benefactor's' dishevelled, wild-looking figure, the Jew, who was standing behind Perfishka's back, tried to give them the slip; but Tchertop-hanov, in two bounds, was upon him, and like a tiger flew at his throat.

'Ah! he's come for the money! for the money!' he cried as hoarsely as though he were being strangled himself instead of strangling the Jew; 'you stole him by night, and are come by day for the money, eh? Eh? Eh?'

'Mercy on us, your ex-shelency,' the Jew tried to groan out.

'Tell me, where's my horse? What have you done with him? Whom have you sold him to? Tell me, tell me, tell me!'

The Jew by now could not even groan; his face was rapidly turning livid, and even the expression of fear had vanished from it. His hands dropped and hung lifeless, his whole body, furiously shaken by Tchertop-hanov, waved backwards and forwards like a reed.

'I'll pay you your money, I'll pay it you in full to the last farthing,' roared Tchertop-hanov, 'but I'll strangle you like any chicken if you don't tell me at once!'…

'But you have strangled him already, master,' observed the groom Perfishka humbly.

Then only Tchertop-hanov came to his senses.

He let go of the Jew's neck; the latter fell heavily to the ground. Tchertop-hanov picked him up, sat him on a bench, poured a glass of vodka down his throat, and restored him to consciousness. And having restored him to consciousness, he began to talk to him.

It turned out that the Jew had not the slightest idea that Malek-Adel had been stolen. And, indeed, what motive could he have to steal the horse which he had himself procured for his 'revered Panteley Eremyitch.'

Then Tchertop-hanov led him into the stable.

Together they scrutinised the horse-boxes, the manger, and the lock on the door, turned over the hay and the straw, and then went into the courtyard. Tchertop-hanov showed the Jew the hoofprints at the fence, and all at once he slapped his thighs.

'Stay!' he cried. 'Where did you buy the horse?'

'In the district of Maloarchangel, at Verhosensky Fair,' answered the Jew.

'Of whom?'

'A Cossack.'

'Stay! This Cossack; was he a young man or old?'

'Middle-aged — a steady man.'

'And what was he like? What did he look like? A cunning rascal, I expect?'

'Sure to have been a rascal, your ex-shelency.'

'And, I say, what did he say, this rascal? — had he had the horse long?'

'I recollect he said he'd had it a long while.'

'Well, then, no one could have stolen him but he! Consider it yourself, listen, stand here!…What's your name?'

The Jew started and turned his little black eyes upon Tchertop-hanov.

'What's my name?'

'Yes, yes; what are you called?'

'Moshel Leyba.'

'Well, judge then, Moshel Leyba, my friend — you're a man of sense — whom would Malek-Adel have allowed to touch him except his old master? You see he must have saddled him and bridled him and taken off his cloth — there it is lying on the hay!…and made all his arrangements simply as if he were at home! Why, anyone except his master, Malek-Adel would have trampled under foot! He'd have raised such a din, he'd have roused the whole village? Do you agree with me?'

'I agree, I agree, your ex-shelency.'…

'Well, then, it follows that first of all we must find this Cossack!'

'But how are we to find him, your ex-shelency? I have only seen him one little time in my life, and where is he now, and what's his name? Alack, alack!' added the Jew, shaking the long curls over his ears sorrowfully.

'Leyba!' shouted Tchertop-hanov suddenly; 'Leyba, look at me! You see I've lost my senses; I'm not myself!…I shall lay hands on myself if you don't come to my aid!'

'But how can I?'…

'Come with me, and let us find the thief.'

'But where shall we go?'

'We'll go to the fairs, the highways and by-ways, to the horse-stealers, to towns and villages and hamlets — everywhere, everywhere! And don't trouble about money; I've come into a fortune, brother! I'll spend my last farthing, but I'll get my darling back! And he shan't escape us, our enemy, the Cossack! Where he goes we'll go! If he's hidden in the earth we'll follow him! If he's gone to the devil, we'll follow him to Satan himself!'

'Oh, why to Satan?' observed the Jew; 'we can do without him.'

'Leyba!' Tchertop-hanov went on; 'Leyba, though you're a Jew, and your creed's an accursed one, you've a soul better than many a Christian soul! Have pity on me! I can't go alone; alone I can never carry the thing through. I'm a hot-headed fellow, but you've a brain — a brain worth its weight in gold! Your race are like that; you succeed in everything without being taught! You're wondering, perhaps, where I could have got the money? Come into my room — I'll show you all the money. You may take it, you may take the cross off my neck, only give me back Malek-Adel; give him me back again!'

Tchertop-hanov was shivering as if he were in a fever; the sweat rolled down his face in drops, and, mingling with his tears, was lost in his moustaches. He pressed Leyba's hands, he besought him, he almost kissed him....He was in a sort of delirium. The Jew tried to object, to declare that it was utterly impossible for him to get away; that he had business....It was useless! Tchertop-hanov would not even hear anything. There was no help for it; the poor Jew consented.

The next day Tchertop-hanov set out from Bezsonovo in a peasant cart, with Leyba. The Jew wore a somewhat troubled aspect; he held on to the rail with one hand, while all his withered figure bounded up and down on the jolting seat; the other hand he held pressed to his bosom, where lay a packet of notes wrapped up in newspaper. Tchertop-hanov sat like a statue, only moving his eyes about him, and drawing in deep breaths; in his sash there was stuck a dagger.

'There, the miscreant who has parted us must look out for himself now!' he muttered, as they drove out on the high-road.

His house he left in the charge of Perfishka and an old cook, a deaf old peasant woman, whom he took care of out of compassion.

'I shall come back to you on Malek-Adel,' he shouted to them at parting, 'or never come back at all!'

'You might as well be married to me at once!' jested Perfishka, giving the cook a dig in the ribs with his elbow. 'No fear! the master'll never come back to us; and here I shall be bored to death all alone!'

9

A year passed…a whole year: no news had come of Panteley Eremyitch. The cook was dead, Perfishka himself made up his mind to abandon the house and go off to town, where he was constantly being persuaded to come by his cousin, apprenticed to a barber; when suddenly a rumour was set afloat that his master was coming back. The parish deacon got a letter from Panteley Eremyitch himself, in which he informed him of his intention of arriving at Bezsonovo, and asked him to prepare his servant to be ready for his immediate return. These words Perfishka understood to mean that he was to sweep up the place a bit. He did not, however, put much confidence in the news; he was convinced, though, that the deacon had spoken the truth, when a few days later Panteley Eremyitch in person appeared in the courtyard, riding on Malek-Adel.

Perfishka rushed up to his master, and, holding the stirrup, would have helped him to dismount, but the latter got off alone, and with a triumphant glance about him, cried in a loud voice: 'I said I would find Malek-Adel, and I have found him in spite of my enemies, and of Fate itself!' Perfishka went up to kiss his hand, but Tchertop-hanov paid no attention to his servant's devotion. Leading Malek-Adel after him by the rein, he went with long strides towards the stable. Perfishka looked more intently at his master, and his heart sank. 'Oh, how thin and old he's grown in a year; and what a stern, grim face!' One would have thought Panteley Eremyitch would have been rejoicing, that he had gained his end; and he was rejoicing, certainly…and yet Perfishka's heart sank: he even felt a sort of dread. Tchertop-hanov put the horse in its old place, gave him a light pat on the back, and said, 'There! now you're at home again; and mind what you're about.' The same day he hired a freedman out of work as watchman, established himself again in his rooms, and began living as before....

Not altogether as before, however…but of that later…

The day after his return, Panteley Eremyitch called Perfishka in to him, and for want of anyone else to talk to, began telling him — keeping up, of course, his sense of his own dignity and his bass voice — how he had succeeded in finding Malek-Adel. Tchertop-hanov sat facing the window while he told his story, and smoked a pipe with a long tube while Perfishka stood in the doorway, his hands behind his back, and, respectfully contemplating the back of his master's head, heard him relate how, after many fruitless efforts and idle expeditions, Panteley Eremyitch had at last come to the fair at Romyon by himself, without the Jew Leyba, who, through weakness of character, had not persevered, but had deserted him; how, on the fifth day, when he was on the point of leaving, he walked for the last time along the rows of carts, and all at once he saw between three other horses fastened to the railings — he saw Malek-Adel! How he knew him at once, and how Malek-Adel knew him too, and began neighing, and dragging at his tether, and scraping the earth with his hoof.

'And he was not with the Cossack,' Tchertop-hanov went on, still not turning his head, and in the same bass voice, 'but with a gypsy horse-dealer; I, of course, at once took hold of my horse and tried to get him away by force, but the brute of a gypsy started yelling as if he'd been scalded, all over the market, and began swearing he'd bought the horse off another gypsy — and wanted to bring witnesses to prove it....I spat, and paid him the money: damn the fellow! All I cared for was that I had found my favourite, and had got back my peace of mind. Moreover, in the Karatchevsky district, I took a man for the Cossack — I took the Jew Leyba's word for it that he was my thief — and smashed his face for him; but the Cossack turned out to be a priest's son, and got damages out of me — a hundred and twenty roubles. Well, money's a thing one may get again, but the great thing is, I've Malek-Adel back again! I'm happy now — I'm going to enjoy myself in peace. And I've one instruction to give you, Perfishka: if ever you, which God forbid, catch sight of the Cossack in this neighbourhood, run the very minute without saying a word, and bring me my gun, and I shall know what to do!'

This was what Panteley Eremyitch said to Perfishka: this was how his tongue spoke; but at heart he was not so completely at peace as he declared.

Alas! in his heart of hearts he was not perfectly convinced that the horse he had brought back was really Malek-Adel!

10

Troubled times followed for Panteley Eremyitch. Peace was just the last thing he enjoyed. He had some happy days, it is true; the doubt stirring within him would seem to him all nonsense; he would drive away the ridiculous idea, like a persistent fly, and even laugh at himself; but he had bad days too: the importunate thought began again stealthily gnawing and tearing at his heart, like a mouse under the floor, and he existed in secret torture. On the memorable day when he found Malek-Adel, Tchertop-hanov had felt nothing but rapturous bliss…but the next morning, when, in a low-pitched shed of the inn, he began saddling his recovered joy, beside whom he had spent the whole night, he felt for the first time a certain secret pang....He only shook his head, but the seed was sown. During the homeward journey (it lasted a whole week) doubts seldom arose in him; they grew stronger and more distinct directly he was back at Bezsonovo, directly he was home again in the place where the old authentic Malek-Adel had lived....On the road home he had ridden at a quiet, swinging pace, looking in all directions, smoking a short pipe, and not reflecting at all, except at times the thought struck him: 'When the Tchertop-hanovs want a thing, they get it, you bet!' and he smiled to himself; but on his return home it was a very different state of things. All this, however, he kept to himself; vanity alone would have prevented him from giving utterance to his inner dread. He would have torn anyone to pieces who had dropped the most distant hint that the new Malek-Adel was possibly not the old one; he accepted congratulations on his 'successful recovery of his horse,' from the few persons whom he happened to meet; but he did not seek such congratulations; he avoided all contact with people more than ever — a bad sign! He was almost always putting Malek-Adel through examinations, if one may use the expression; he would ride him out to some point at a little distance in the open country, and put him to the proof, or would go stealthily into the stable, lock the door after him, and standing right before the horse's head, look into his eyes, and ask him in a whisper, 'Is it you? Is it you? You?'…or else stare at him silently and intently for hours together, and then mutter, brightening up: 'Yes! it's he! Of course it's he!' or else go out with a puzzled, even confused look on his face. Tchertop-hanov was not so much confused by the physical differences between this Malek-Adel and that one…though there were a few such differences: that one's tail and mane were a little thinner, and his ears more pointed, and his pasterns shorter, and his eyes brighter — but all that might be only fancy; what confounded Tchertop-hanov most were, so to say, the moral differences. The habits of that one had been different: all his ways were not the same. For instance, that Malek-Adel had looked round and given a faint neigh every time Tchertop-hanov went into the stable; while this one went on munching hay as though nothing had happened, or dozed with his head bent. Both of them stood still when their master leaped out of the saddle; but that one came at once at his voice when he was called, while this one stood stock still. That one galloped as fast, but with higher and longer bounds; this one went with a freer step and at a more jolting trot, and at times 'wriggled' with his shoes — that is, knocked the back one against the front one; that one had never done anything so disgraceful — God forbid! This one, it struck Tchertop-hanov, kept twitching his ears in such a stupid way, while with that one it was quite the contrary; he used to lay one ear back, and hold it so, as though on the alert for his master! That one, directly he saw that it was dirty about him, would at once knock on the partition of his box with his hind-leg, but this one did not care if the dung was heaped up to his belly. That one if, for instance, he were set facing the wind, would take deep breaths and shake himself, this one simply snorted; that one was put out by the rain, this one cared nothing for it....This was a coarser beast — coarser! And there wasn't the gentleness in it, and hard in the mouth it was — no denying it! That horse was a darling, but this....

This was what Tchertop-hanov sometimes thought, and very bitter were such thoughts to him. At other times he would set his horse at full gallop over some newly ploughed field, or would make him leap down to the very bottom of a hollow ravine, and leap out again at the very steepest point, and his heart would throb with rapture, a loud whoop would break from his lips, and he would know, would know for certain, that it was the real, authentic Malek-Adel he had under him; for what other horse could do what this one was doing?

However, there were sometimes shortcomings and misfortunes even here. The prolonged search for Malek-Adel had cost Tchertop-hanov a great deal of money; he did not even dream of Kostroma hounds now, and rode about the neighbourhood in solitude as before. So one morning, four miles from Bezsonovo, Tchertop-hanov chanced to come upon the same prince's hunting party before whom he had cut such a triumphant figure a year and a half before. And, as fate would have it, just as on that day a hare must go leaping out from the hedge before the dogs, down the hillside! Tally-ho! Tally-ho! All the hunt fairly flew after it, and Tchertop-hanov flew along too, but not with the rest of the party, but two hundred paces to one side of it, just as he had done the time before. A huge watercourse ran zigzagging across the hillside, and as it rose higher and higher got gradually narrower, cutting off Tchertop-hanov's path. At the point where he had to jump it, and where, eighteen months before, he actually had jumped it, it was eight feet wide and fourteen feet deep. In anticipation of a triumph — a triumph repeated in such a delightful way — Tchertop-hanov chuckled exultantly, cracked his riding-whip; the hunting party were galloping too, their eyes fixed on the daring rider; his horse whizzed along like a bullet, and now the watercourse was just under his nose — now, now, at one leap, as then!…But Malek-Adel pulled up sharply, wheeled to the left, and in spite of Tchertop-hanov's tugging him to the edge, to the watercourse, he galloped along beside the ravine.

He was afraid, then; did not trust himself!

Then Tchertop-hanov, burning with shame and wrath, almost in tears, dropped the reins, and set the horse going straight forward, down the hill, away, away from the hunting party, if only not to hear them jeering at him, to escape as soon as might be from their damnable eyes!

Covered with foam, his sides lashed unmercifully, Malek-Adel galloped home, and Tchertop-hanov at once locked himself into his room.

'No, it's not he; it's not my darling! He would have broken his neck before he would have betrayed me!'

11

What finally 'did for,' as they say, Tchertop-hanov was the following circumstance. One day he sauntered, riding on Malek-Adel, about the back-yards of the priest's quarters round about the church of the parish in which is Bezsonovo. Huddled up, with his Cossack fur cap pulled down over his eyes, and his hands hanging loose on the saddle-bow, he jogged slowly on, a vague discontent in his heart. Suddenly someone called him.

He stopped his horse, raised his head, and saw his correspondent, the deacon. With a brown, three-cornered hat on his brown hair, which was plaited in a pig-tail, attired in a yellowish nankin long coat, girt much below the waist by a strip of blue stuff, the servant of the altar had come out into his back-garden, and, catching sight of Panteley Eremyitch, he thought it his duty to pay his respects to him, and to take the opportunity of doing so to ask him a question about something. Without some such hidden motive, as we know, ecclesiastical persons do not venture to address temporal ones.

But Tchertop-hanov was in no mood for the deacon; he barely responded to his bow, and, muttering something between his teeth, he was already cracking his whip, when....

'What a magnificent horse you have!' the deacon made haste to add: 'and really you can take credit to yourself for it. Truly you're a man of amazing cleverness, simply a lion indeed!'

His reverence the deacon prided himself on his fluency, which was a great source of vexation to his reverence the priest, to whom the gift of words had not been vouchsafed; even vodka did not loosen his tongue.

'After losing one animal by the cunning of evil men,' continued the deacon, 'you did not lose courage in repining; but, on the other hand, trusting the more confidently in Divine Providence, procured yourself another, in no wise inferior, but even, one may say, superior, since....'

'What nonsense are you talking?' Tchertop-hanov interrupted gloomily; 'what other horse do you mean? This is the same one; this is Malek-Adel…I found him. The fellow's raving!'…

'Ay! ay! ay!' responded the deacon emphatically with a sort of drawl, drumming with his fingers in his beard, and eyeing Tchertop-hanov with his bright eager eyes: 'How's that, sir? Your horse, God help my memory, was stolen a fortnight before Intercession last year, and now we're near the end of November.'

'Well, what of that?'

The deacon still fingered his beard.

'Why, it follows that more than a year's gone by since then, and your horse was a dapple grey then, just as it is now; in fact, it seems even darker. How's that? Grey horses get a great deal lighter in colour in a year.'

Tchertop-hanov started…as though someone had driven a dagger into his heart. It was true: the grey colour did change! How was it such a simple reflection had never occurred to him?

'You damned pigtail! get out!' he yelled suddenly, his eyes flashing with fury, and instantaneously he disappeared out of the sight of the amazed deacon.

Well, everything was over!

Now, at last, everything was really over, everything was shattered, the last card trumped. Everything crumbled away at once before that word 'lighter!'

Grey horses get lighter in colour!

'Gallop, gallop on, accursed brute! You can never gallop away from that word!'

Tchertop-hanov flew home, and again locked himself up.

12

That this worthless jade was not Malek-Adel; that between him and Malek-Adel there was not the smallest resemblance; that any man of the slightest sense would have seen this from the first minute; that he, Tchertop-hanov, had been taken in in the vulgarest way — no! that he purposely, of set intent, tricked himself, blinded his own eyes — of all this he had not now the faintest doubt!

Tchertop-hanov walked up and down in his room, turning monotonously on his heels at each wall, like a beast in a cage. His vanity suffered intolerably; but he was not only tortured by the sting of wounded vanity; he was overwhelmed by despair, stifled by rage, and burning with the thirst for revenge. But rage against whom? On whom was he to be revenged? On the Jew, Yaff, Masha, the deacon, the Cossack-thief, all his neighbours, the whole world, himself? His brain was giving way. The last card was trumped! (That simile gratified him.) And he was again the most worthless, the most contemptible of men, a common laughing-stock, a motley fool, a damned idiot, an object for jibes — to a deacon!…He fancied, he pictured vividly how that loathsome pig-tailed priest would tell the story of the grey horse and the foolish gentleman....O damn!! In vain Tchertop-hanov tried to check his rising passion, in vain he tried to assure himself that this…horse, though not Malek-Adel, was still…a good horse, and might be of service to him for many years to come; he put this thought away from him on the spot with fury, as though there were contained in it a new insult to that Malek-Adel whom he considered he had wronged so already....Yes, indeed! this jade, this carrion he, like a blind idiot, had put on a level with him, Malek-Adel! And as to the service the jade could be to him!…as though he would ever deign to get astride of him? Never! on no consideration!!…He would sell him to a Tartar for dog's meat — it deserved no better end....Yes, that would be best!

For more than two hours Tchertop-hanov wandered up and down his room.

'Perfishka!' he called peremptorily all of a sudden, 'run this minute to the tavern; fetch a gallon of vodka! Do you hear? A gallon, and look sharp! I want the vodka here this very second on the table!'

The vodka was not long in making its appearance on Panteley Eremyitch's table, and he began drinking.

13

If anyone had looked at Tchertop-hanov then; if anyone could have been a witness of the sullen exasperation with which he drained glass after glass — he would inevitably have felt an involuntary shudder of fear. The night came on, the tallow candle burnt dimly on the table. Tchertop-hanov ceased wandering from corner to corner; he sat all flushed, with dull eyes, which he dropped at one time on the floor, at another fixed obstinately on the dark window; he got up, poured out some vodka, drank it off, sat down again, again fixed his eyes on one point, and did not stir — only his breathing grew quicker and his face still more flushed. It seemed as though some resolution were ripening within him, which he was himself ashamed of, but which he was gradually getting used to; one single thought kept obstinately and undeviatingly moving up closer and closer, one single image stood out more and more distinctly, and under the burning weight of heavy drunkenness the angry irritation was replaced by a feeling of ferocity in his heart, and a vindictive smile appeared on his lips.

'Yes, the time has come!' he declared in a matter-of-fact, almost weary tone. 'I must get to work.'

He drank off the last glass of vodka, took from over his bed the pistol — the very pistol from which he had shot at Masha — loaded it, put some cartridges in his pocket — to be ready for anything — and went round to the stables.

The watchman ran up to him when he began to open the door, but he shouted to him: 'It's I! Are you blind? Get out!' The watchman moved a little aside. 'Get out and go to bed!' Tchertop-hanov shouted at him again: 'there's nothing for you to guard here! A mighty wonder, a treasure indeed to watch over!' He went into the stable. Malek-Adel…the spurious Malek-Adel, was lying on his litter. Tchertop-hanov gave him a kick, saying, 'Get up, you brute!' Then he unhooked a halter from a nail, took off the horsecloth and flung it on the ground, and roughly turning the submissive horse round in the box, led it out into the courtyard, and from the yard into the open country, to the great amazement of the watchman, who could not make out at all where the master was going off to by night, leading an unharnessed horse. He was, of course, afraid to question him, and only followed him with his eyes till he disappeared at the bend in the road leading to a neighbouring wood.

14

Tchertop-hanov walked with long strides, not stopping nor looking round. Malek-Adel — we will call him by that name to the end — followed him meekly. It was a rather clear night; Tchertop-hanov could make out the jagged outline of the forest, which formed a black mass in front of him. When he got into the chill night air, he would certainly have thrown off the intoxication of the vodka he had drunk, if it had not been for another, stronger intoxication, which completely over-mastered him. His head was heavy, his blood pulsed in thuds in his throat and ears, but he went on steadily, and knew where he was going.

He had made up his mind to kill Malek-Adel; he had thought of nothing else the whole day....Now he had made up his mind!

He went out to do this thing not only calmly, but confidently, unhesitatingly, as a man going about something from a sense of duty. This 'job' seemed a very 'simple' thing to him; in making an end of the impostor, he was quits with 'everyone' at once — he punished himself for his stupidity, and made expiation to his real darling, and showed the whole world (Tchertop-hanov worried himself a great deal about the 'whole world' ) that he was not to be trifled with....And, above all, he was making an end of himself too with the impostor — for what had he to live for now? How all this took shape in his brain, and why, it seemed to him so simple — it is not easy to explain, though not altogether impossible; stung to the quick, solitary, without a human soul near to him, without a halfpenny, and with his blood on fire with vodka, he was in a state bordering on madness, and there is no doubt that even in the absurdest freaks of mad people there is, to their eyes, a sort of logic, and even justice. Of his justice Tchertop-hanov was, at any rate, fully persuaded; he did not hesitate, he made haste to carry out sentence on the guilty without giving himself any clear definition of whom he meant by that term....To tell the truth, he reflected very little on what he was about to do. 'I must, I must make an end,' was what he kept stupidly and severely repeating to himself; 'I must make an end!'

And the guiltless guilty one followed in a submissive trot behind his back....But there was no pity for him in Tchertop-hanov's heart.

15

Not far from the forest to which he was leading his horse there stretched a small ravine, half overgrown with young oak bushes. Tchertop-hanov went down into it....Malek-Adel stumbled and almost fell on him.

'So you would crush me, would you, you damned brute!' shouted Tchertop-hanov, and, as though in self-defence, he pulled the pistol out of his pocket. He no longer felt furious exasperation, but that special numbness of the senses which they say comes over a man before the perpetration of a crime. But his own voice terrified him — it sounded so wild and strange under the cover of dark branches in the close, decaying dampness of the forest ravine! Moreover, in response to his exclamation, some great bird suddenly fluttered in a tree-top above his head…Tchertop-hanov shuddered. He had, as it were, roused a witness to his act — and where? In that silent place where he should not have met a living creature....

'Away with you, devil, to the four winds of heaven!' he muttered, and letting go Malek-Adel's rein, he gave him a violent blow on the shoulder with the butt end of the pistol. Malek-Adel promptly turned back, clambered out of the ravine…and ran away. But the thud of his hoofs was not long audible. The rising wind confused and blended all sounds together.

Tchertop-hanov too slowly clambered out of the ravine, reached the forest, and made his way along the road homewards. He was ill at ease with himself; the weight he had felt in his head and his heart had spread over all his limbs; he walked angry, gloomy, dissatisfied, hungry, as though some one had insulted him, snatched his prey, his food from him....

The suicide, baffled in his intent, must know such sensations.

Suddenly something poked him behind between his shoulder blades. He looked round....Malek-Adel was standing in the middle of the road. He had walked after his master; he touched him with his nose to announce himself.

'Ah!' shouted Tchertop-hanov, 'of yourself, of yourself you have come to your death! So, there!'

In the twinkling of an eye he had snatched out his pistol, drawn the trigger, turned the muzzle on Malek-Adel's brow, fired....

The poor horse sprung aside, rose on its haunches, bounded ten paces away, and suddenly fell heavily, and gasped as it writhed upon the ground....

Tchertop-hanov put his two hands over his ears and ran away. His knees were shaking under him. His drunkenness and revenge and blind self-confidence — all had flown at once. There was left nothing but a sense of shame and loathing — and the consciousness, unmistakeable, that this time he had put an end to himself too.

16

Six weeks later, the groom Perfishka thought it his duty to stop the commissioner of police as he happened to be passing Bezsonovo.

'What do you want?' inquired the guardian of order.

'If you please, your excellency, come into our house,' answered the groom with a low bow.

'Panteley Eremyitch, I fancy, is about to die; so that I'm afraid of getting into trouble.'

'What? die?' queried the commissioner.

'Yes, sir. First, his honour drank vodka every day, and now he's taken to his bed and got very thin. I fancy his honour does not understand anything now. He's lost his tongue completely.'

The commissioner got out of his trap.

'Have you sent for the priest, at least? Has your master been confessed? Taken the sacrament?'

'No, sir!'

The commissioner frowned. 'How is that, my boy? How can that be — hey? Don't you know that for that…you're liable to have to answer heavily — hey?'

'Indeed, and I did ask him the day before yesterday, and yesterday again,' protested the intimidated groom. "Wouldn't you, Panteley Eremyitch," says I, "let me run for the priest, sir?" "You hold your tongue, idiot," says he; "mind your own business." But to-day, when I began to address him, his honour only looked at me, and twitched his moustache.'

'And has he been drinking a great deal of vodka?' inquired the commissioner.

'Rather! But if you would be so good, your honour, come into his room.'

'Well, lead the way!' grumbled the commissioner, and he followed Perfishka.

An astounding sight was in store for him. In a damp, dark back-room, on a wretched bedstead covered with a horsecloth, with a rough felt cloak for a pillow, lay Tchertop-hanov. He was not pale now, but yellowish green, like a corpse, with sunken eyes under leaden lids and a sharp, pinched nose — still reddish — above his dishevelled whiskers. He lay dressed in his invariable Caucasian coat, with the cartridge pockets on the breast, and blue Circassian trousers. A Cossack cap with a crimson crown covered his forehead to his very eyebrows. In one hand Tchertop-hanov held his hunting whip, in the other an embroidered tobacco pouch — Masha's last gift to him. On a table near the bed stood an empty spirit bottle, and at the head of the bed were two water-colour sketches pinned to the wall; one represented, as far as could be made out, a fat man with a guitar in his hand — probably Nedopyuskin; the other portrayed a horseman galloping at full speed....The horse was like those fabulous animals which are sketched by children on walls and fences; but the carefully washed-in dappling of the horse's grey coat, and the cartridge pocket on the rider's breast, the pointed toes of his boots, and the immense moustaches, left no room for doubt — this sketch was meant to represent Panteley Eremyitch riding on Malek-Adel.

The astonished commissioner of police did not know how to proceed. The silence of death reigned in the room. 'Why, he's dead already!' he thought, and raising his voice, he said, 'Panteley Eremyitch! Eh, Panteley Eremyitch!'

Then something extraordinary occurred. Tchertop-hanov's eyelids slowly opened, the eyes, fast growing dim, moved first from right to left, then from left to right, rested on the commissioner — saw him....Something gleamed in their dull whites, the semblance of a flash came back to them, the blue lips were gradually unglued, and a hoarse, almost sepulchral, voice was heard.

'Panteley Eremyitch of the ancient hereditary nobility is dying: who can hinder him? He owes no man anything, asks nothing from any one....Leave him, people! Go!'

The hand holding the whip tried to lift it…In vain! The lips cleaved together again, the eyes closed, and as before Tchertop-hanov lay on his comfortless bed, flat as an empty sack, and his feet close together.

'Let me know when he dies,' the commissioner whispered to Perfishka as he went out of the room; 'and I suppose you can send for the priest now. You must observe due order; give him extreme unction.'

Perfishka went that same day for the priest, and the following morning he had to let the commissioner know: Panteley Eremyitch had died in the night.

When they buried him, two men followed his coffin; the groom Perfishka and Moshel Leyba. The news of Tchertop-hanov's death had somehow reached the Jew, and he did not fail to pay this last act of respect to his benefactor.